<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Annika Sörenstam</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>229557</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744404314</id>
      <parentid>739332195</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-15T00:35:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot (v1.2.5)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23638">{{Vital article|level=4|topic=People|class=A}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|blp=yes|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=yes|class=A|A-Class=pass|sports-work-group=yes|sports-priority=top|old-peer-review=yes|listas=Sorenstam, Annika}}
{{WikiProject Golf|class=A|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Women's sport|class=A|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Sweden|class=A|importance=mid}}
}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=2 April 2007
|action1result=listed
|action1link=Talk:Annika Sörenstam#GA review
|action1oldid=119842601

|action2=WPR
|action2date=9 May 2007
|action2link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Biography/Peer review/Annika Sörenstam
|action2result=reviewed
|action2oldid=129315998

|action3=WAR
|action3date=26 March 2008
|action3link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Biography/A-class review/Annika Sörenstam
|action3result=pass
|action3oldid=199935261

|action4=GAR
|action4date=16 January 2009
|action4link=Talk:Annika Sörenstam/GA1
|action4result=Kept
|action4oldid=264366362

|currentstatus=GA
|topic=Everydaylife
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2011-05-22|oldid1=430391172|date2=2013-05-22|oldid2=556292477}}

== Sörenstam ==
If her name is Sörenstam (and it is) then don't spell it Sorenstam in the article.

The change in the categories from Sorenstam to Sörenstam was not an attempt at &quot;deliberate missorting&quot; but an attempt at consistency. This being the English version of Wikipedia, we ought to have some sort of agreement on use of ö or not in this article. [[User:Mudforce|Mudforce]] 22:06, 20 February 2007 (UTC)

Not everyone knows how to create the ö character on their keyboard. It might be an honest mistake. [[User:Crunch|Crunch]] 23:54, 20 February 2007 (UTC)

== Vijay ==

About Vijay's comments: it is tough to find out what he really said, and I didn't see his comments on TV.  The media apparently twisted it around somewhat, and quoted him on some things, but left out other parts, which didn't lead to a complete quoting of what he really said.  [[User:Dgrant|dave]] 01:24 19 May 2003 (UTC)

:Well done.  Assuming those are from televised comments, or from newsprint and he was quoted correctly.  Thanks.  [[User:Dgrant|dave]] 19:54 19 May 2003 (UTC)

----

Some discussion on how to reference the fact that Sorenstam was born in Sweden has taken place recently (given the edits in the past few hours).  I'd be interested in comments from others on [[User talk:Cafemusique|my talk page]] on the subject. - [[User:Cafemusique|Cafemusique]] 22:03 23 May 2003 (UTC)

----

I've swapped the redirect and the article, so the article is now titled with the correct spelling, and the accentless version is a redirect. --[[User:Brion VIBBER|Brion]] 18:22 24 May 2003 (UTC)

== Swedish atheists? ==

Someone added this article to the category Swedish Atheists. Is there a reference for this? Did you perhaps mean Swedish '''athletes'''? Without a reference, I propose deleting the link. Otherwise, add a reference. [[User:Crunch|Crunch]] 17:00, 17 June 2006 (UTC)
:This is so ridiculous it's not funny. Don't you understand we have better things to do? Not everyone belongs to the Church of George Bush and thank goodness most people on this planet don't have the idiotic ideas you have. Personal beliefs are PERSONAL and have no place in this Wiki. Whether you 'over there' grasp this or not. Leave the poor girl alone! And get on with your lives! And let her (and us) get on with ours! &amp;mdash;''[[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|Please sign your posts on talk pages]]. The preceding comment was added by [[User: 62.1.131.242|62.1.131.242]] at 15:58, 5 August 2006.
:No reply, it's been removed. [[User:Crunch|Crunch]] 19:40, 25 June 2006 (UTC)
::Take a look at [http://www.celebatheists.com/index.php?title=Annika_S%C3%B6renstam]. I actually remember reading this article. --[[User:Bomkia|Bomkia]] 14:06, 26 July 2006 (UTC)
::I think there is a leap from saying you don't believe there is someone &quot;in the clouds running the show&quot; to proclaiming yourself an atheist.  [[User:Crunch|Crunch]] 10:39, 27 July 2006 (UTC)

This topic has been included in this article before and decided as non-encyclopedic and therefoe non wikipedian. We can reopen the debate here before adding to the article. &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Mudforce|Mudforce]] ([[User talk:Mudforce|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Mudforce|contribs]]) 16:07, 5 October 2009&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

== Point of View Flag ==

[[User:John Cho]] has flagged this article as having point of view issues but without any note on the discussion page as to what the point of view issues might be.  Until the issues are addressed here, I have removed the POV flag. [[User:Crunch|Crunch]] 02:23, 24 July 2006 (UTC)

== Photo in middle of results section ==

I think the addition of photos is generally a good idea, but I'm not sure the photo of Annika on the practice putting green at the 2006 British Open is helping, at least not where it's placed. It's in the middle of the LPGA wins section, which causes that section to shift off to the side.  Can we find a better location for that photo? Or maybe we can do without it.  [[User:Crunch|Crunch]] 13:12, 6 March 2007 (UTC)


I've re-arranged the pictures. I think it looks better than before [[User:Mudforce|Mudforce]] 18:45, 6 March 2007 (UTC)

Much better. Nice photos, too. [[User:Crunch|Crunch]] 19:35, 6 March 2007 (UTC)

Did you change this again? There is a photo now obscuring the Results in LPGA Majors sections. Maybe just reduce the size of the photos if you still want to have all of these in the article.[[User:Crunch|Crunch]] 20:15, 16 March 2007 (UTC)

:I changed the picture layout when the references went to a 2 column structure. This should be better. [[User:Mudforce|Mudforce]] 20:33, 16 March 2007 (UTC)

:It's better, at least you can see all the text, but still not right. Can you see how &quot;Kraft Nabisco Championship&quot; wraps in the top table?  Plus, when we add 2008, we'll run into more problems.  I really recommend not putting a photo in that section.  It's distracting and the photo isn't very informative anyway. How useful is another photo of Annika on the practice putting green where all you can see if the top of her head?  [[User:Crunch|Crunch]] 22:50, 16 March 2007 (UTC)

:At my default screen resolution it's not a problem but I can see your point. I've resized the photos and re-arranged them, losing the one mentioned above. [[User:Mudforce|Mudforce]] 08:20, 17 March 2007 (UTC)

==GA tip==
I have not done a formal review, but if you want to get GA, fix the ref formatting, it's highly inconsistent.[[User:Rlevse|Rlevse]] 18:17, 16 March 2007 (UTC)
:Ref formating fixed. Thanks for the tip [[User:Mudforce|Mudforce]] 19:15, 16 March 2007 (UTC)

==GA review==
This article is very well written and well organized. The references look good (although as a minor point, some of the references could use a bit more information regarding who published them ... e.g. 'LET' isn't very descriptive, should those links go away. Where possible, try and include author information (who wrote the article) in the reference as well. But they are in a consistent format, so these issues are not being considered against GA status (should be fixed prior to FA, though).

I like the article's use of GFDL, amateur images. Some of them look very good. The use of the one copyrighted image at the top is fine, since it's a promotional photo (fair use).

Overall, the article is very good and very broad. Some additional details could be added in the future on personal life and off-the-course stuff. But overall, I think this meets the [[WP:WIAGA|good article criteria]]. Cheers! [[User:Derek.cashman|Dr. Cash]] 17:41, 3 April 2007 (UTC)

== Merge Annika Sörenstam at the Colonial into this Article? ==

I'm proposing that [[Annika Sörenstam at the Colonial]] be merged into this article.  The topic is already covered in this article and it seems neither necessary nor logical to have two pages.  Please vote below by stating '''merge''' or '''no merge'''.  We'll run this poll for at least 5 days in accordance with the [[Merging_and_moving_pages#Proposing_a_merger|Wikipedia policy]]. --[[User:Crunch|Crunch]] 20:58, 10 May 2007 (UTC)
*'''Merge'''. For reasons stated above. --[[User:Crunch|Crunch]] 20:58, 10 May 2007 (UTC)
*'''Merge'''. Agree with above comments. Main article now expands on the controversy as suggested in Peer Review so separate page is superfluous. [[User:Mudforce|Mudforce]] 21:13, 10 May 2007 (UTC)
*The result was '''Merge''' [[Annika Sörenstam at the Colonial]]  into this article. --[[User:Crunch|Crunch]] 01:12, 22 May 2007 (UTC)

== Main image isn't fair use ==

[[:Image:Sorenstam15.jpg]] has been tagged as ''not'' fair use - it is not unrepeatable. Anyone have a free image that can be uploaded? [[User:Not a dog|Not a dog]] 14:29, 25 May 2007 (UTC)

:GFDL image added - [[User:Mudforce|Mudforce]] 18:21, 25 May 2007 (UTC)

Know what would be nice?  A free photo that clearly shows her face.  All of the images of her that we have now are not terribly clear or obscured.  --[[User:Edward Morgan Blake|Edward Morgan Blake]] ([[User talk:Edward Morgan Blake|talk]]) 11:20, 10 December 2007 (UTC)

:Does an image from the cover of a book count as fair use? --[[User:Crunch|Crunch]] ([[User talk:Crunch|talk]]) 23:07, 10 December 2007 (UTC)

::Is that better? [[User:Mudforce|Mudforce]] ([[User talk:Mudforce|talk]]) 14:14, 11 December 2007 (UTC)

== Not retired yet ==

There have been a lot of edits on this, so it's probably worth mentioning these points:
#She is not retired yet. She only mentioned her plans to retire at the end of the year, and only then just from competitive golf not from all other aspects of golf she's involved in, so to say she is &quot;retired&quot; or &quot;retired in 2008&quot; is inaccurate.
#Even after she retires from competition she will still be a professional golfer. To say she is a &quot;former professional golfer&quot; is certainly now, and will be in the future, inaccurate. Is Jack Nicklaus a former professional golfer? Anyone who teaches golf for money as she does and will continue to do is a professional golfer. --[[User:Crunch|Crunch]] ([[User talk:Crunch|talk]]) 11:15, 15 May 2008 (UTC)

== USSA Athlete of the Year ==

The link for Annika winning the 2004 United States Sports Academy Female Athlete of the Year award was dead, so I searched for a replacement. During my search, I found the following page from the Academy, which states that gymnast [[Carly Patterson]] won the award.[http://web.archive.org/web/20051030153758/http://www.ussa.edu/aoy/index.asp] [http://www.asama.org/awards/Athletes/femaleAward.html This page] indicates that Annika was a past winner, but I can't find a yearly list, and all of the individual year pages are down. If someone could find out when she won this honor, that would be great, but for now I've removed it. [[User:Giants2008|Giants2008]] ([[User talk:Giants2008|talk]]) 15:57, 21 May 2008 (UTC)

{{Talk:Annika Sörenstam/GA1}}

== Personal life ==

Hi, this is a warning that the personal life information in this article is much too short. Any biography that is of GA standard must have at least one well organised paragraph describing the persons life outside of their field for which they are famous or otherwise incorporate that information elsewhere in the text. This article does not provide enough information on the person in question and does not give enough context for the incidents and information that is mentioned. For an example of how such a section might look, see [[Brian Urlacher]] and for pointers on how to expand and improve the section, see [[User:Jackyd101/review templates#Personal life guide|this guide]]. If this information is not improved then this article  would be unlikely to survive a Good Article Reassessment and may well be delisted in the future. Thanks --[[User:Jackyd101|Jackyd101]] ([[User talk:Jackyd101|talk]]) 10:41, 30 January 2009 (UTC)

: Copy edit changes made [[User:Mudforce|Mudforce]] ([[User talk:Mudforce|talk]]) 16:42, 31 January 2009 (UTC)

The sentence re: 2nd marriage starts by saying she married in august of 2007 and ends saying they married in Orlando in January 2009.  Must confirm which. [[Special:Contributions/99.251.237.133|99.251.237.133]] ([[User talk:99.251.237.133|talk]]) 22:54, 10 July 2016 (UTC)mailyn4882

==Inacuracy in Colonial==

It says she was the first woman to compete in the PGA since Babe Zaharias did in the LA open. I don't this this is true, Babe Zaharias made the cut in 3 PGA tournaments that year, and I believe the LA open was her first cut, here most recent cut made was at the Tuscon Open. Isn't the Tuscon open after the LA open? or am I wrong here? [[User:MATThematical|MATThematical]] ([[User talk:MATThematical|talk]])  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|undated]] comment added 01:22, 1 June 2009 (UTC).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!--Template:Undated--&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Nationality ==

Is it really correct to have United States too as a &quot;nationality&quot; just because she have US citizenship? She's 100% Swedish after all. -- ''[[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|Please sign your posts on talk pages]]. The preceding comment was added by [[User: 62.20.211.21|62.20.211.21]] at 18:39:00, 24 August 2009.]]''

You might want to post something to [[Template_talk:Infobox_Golfer]] to determine how the Nationality field is intended to be used and specifically in the case of individuals holding dual citizenship. --[[User:Crunch|Crunch]] ([[User talk:Crunch|talk]]) 01:23, 26 August 2009 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:9|one external link|9 external links}} on [[Annika Sörenstam]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=707271378 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20081008134054/http://www.gogirlworld.org:80/cgi-bin/iowa/about/media/press.html?record=116 to http://www.gogirlworld.org/cgi-bin/iowa/about/media/press.html?record=116
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20070929115019/http://www.lpga.com/content_1.aspx?mid=4&amp;pid=231 to http://www.lpga.com/content_1.aspx?mid=4&amp;pid=231
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20061027003059/http://www.lpga.com/content_1.aspx?pid=2500&amp;mid=2 to http://www.lpga.com/content_1.aspx?pid=2500&amp;mid=2
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20100815050412/http://www.lpga.com:80/content_1.aspx?mid=2&amp;pid=24021 to http://www.lpga.com/content_1.aspx?mid=2&amp;pid=24021
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20080203200946/http://www.lpga.com:80/content_1.aspx?pid=10405&amp;mid=2 to http://www.lpga.com/content_1.aspx?pid=10405&amp;mid=2
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20070921015320/http://www.lpga.com:80/content_1.aspx?pid=11124&amp;mid=1 to http://www.lpga.com/content_1.aspx?pid=11124&amp;mid=1#annika
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20070929120720/http://www.lpga.com/content_1.aspx?pid=5531&amp;mid=4 to http://www.lpga.com/content_1.aspx?pid=5531&amp;mid=4
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20090212104336/http://www.lpga.com:80/content_1.aspx?mid=2&amp;pid=7840 to http://www.lpga.com/content_1.aspx?mid=2&amp;pid=7840
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20121026075800/http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20090111/ap_on_sp_go_ne/glf_sorenstam_wedding;_ylt=AnN9pBnOlepN7B2iN61qBy4LMxIF to http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20090111/ap_on_sp_go_ne/glf_sorenstam_wedding;_ylt=AnN9pBnOlepN7B2iN61qBy4LMxIF

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 21:40, 27 February 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:16|one external link|16 external links}} on [[Annika Sörenstam]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=739332189 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.lpga.com/player_results.aspx?id=553
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.lpga.com/content_1.aspx?pid=13517&amp;amp;mid=2
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.ladieseuropeantour.info/profiles/010792.htm
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070326091037/http://www.sr.se/cgi-bin/radiosporten/nyheter/amnessida.asp?programID=179&amp;Nyheter=&amp;grupp=3602&amp;artikel=1041550 to http://www.sr.se/cgi-bin/radiosporten/nyheter/amnessida.asp?programID=179&amp;Nyheter=&amp;grupp=3602&amp;artikel=1041550
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.ecs.net/golf/tour/women/1996/220896.html
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.lpga.com/content_1.aspx?mid=1&amp;amp;pid=307
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.lpga.com/Content_1.aspx?pid=5784&amp;amp;mid=4
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.lpga.com/content_1.aspx?pid=15338&amp;amp;mid=2
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.lpga.com/content_1.aspx?mid=2&amp;amp;pid=18304
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.lpga.com/content_1.aspx?pid=11818&amp;amp;mid=2
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.lpga.com/content_1.aspx?pid=13365&amp;amp;mid=2
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.linksmagazine.com/best_of_golf/personalities/annika_sorenstam_women_golf_course_designers_print.html
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.wish.org/news/news_releases/annika_ambassador
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.lpga.com/content_1.aspx?pid=2822&amp;amp;mid=2
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.lpga.com/content_1.aspx?pid=7726&amp;amp;mid=2
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20090212113622/http://www.pgatour.com/2007/r/08/25/ANNIKA.ENGAGED/ to http://www.pgatour.com/2007/r/08/25/ANNIKA.ENGAGED/

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 02:38, 14 September 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:18|one external link|18 external links}} on [[Annika Sörenstam]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=744404311 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20081201145425/http://www.sportsline.com:80/golf/story/10042794/2 to http://www.sportsline.com/golf/story/10042794/2
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20110629135436/http://www.lpga.com/content/2010PlayerBiosPDF/Sorenstam,Annika-10.pdf to http://www.lpga.com/content/2010PlayerBiosPDF/Sorenstam,Annika-10.pdf
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070930201249/http://www.ladieseuropeantour.com/content/let_content_news.php?Id=4628&amp;page=133 to http://www.ladieseuropeantour.com/content/let_content_news.php?Id=4628&amp;page=133
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070930185249/http://www.ladieseuropeantour.com/content/let_content_news.php?Id=4214&amp;page=104 to http://www.ladieseuropeantour.com/content/let_content_news.php?Id=4214&amp;page=104
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20110904152246/http://www.athletesforhope.org/annika-sorenstam-allstar.html to http://www.athletesforhope.org/annika-sorenstam-allstar.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20061025123552/http://www.ladieseuropeantour.com/content/let_content_news.php?Id=4355 to http://www.ladieseuropeantour.com/content/let_content_news.php?Id=4355
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070415045540/http://www.lpga.com/content/Alltimerecords.pdf to http://www.lpga.com/content/Alltimerecords.pdf
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070930184530/http://www.ladieseuropeantour.com/content/let_content_news.php?Id=3816&amp;page=50 to http://www.ladieseuropeantour.com/content/let_content_news.php?Id=3816&amp;page=50
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070930201309/http://www.ladieseuropeantour.com/content/let_content_news.php?Id=3875&amp;page=44 to http://www.ladieseuropeantour.com/content/let_content_news.php?Id=3875&amp;page=44
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20121024163130/http://www.ladieseuropeantour.com/main_article.php?id=3898&amp;pid=1001 to http://www.ladieseuropeantour.com/main_article.php?id=3898&amp;pid=1001
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070930201542/http://www.ladieseuropeantour.com/content/let_content_news.php?Id=4016&amp;page=32 to http://www.ladieseuropeantour.com/content/let_content_news.php?Id=4016&amp;page=32
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070927235921/http://www.ladieseuropeantour.com/content/let_content_news.php?Id=4882&amp;page=30 to http://www.ladieseuropeantour.com/content/let_content_news.php?Id=4882&amp;page=30
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070927235928/http://www.ladieseuropeantour.com/content/let_content_news.php?Id=8004&amp;page=7 to http://www.ladieseuropeantour.com/content/let_content_news.php?Id=8004&amp;page=7
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070927235804/http://www.ladieseuropeantour.com/content/let_content_news.php?Id=6998&amp;page=14 to http://www.ladieseuropeantour.com/content/let_content_news.php?Id=6998&amp;page=14
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070929121558/http://dailyjournalonline.com/articles/2007/04/14/sports/doc461f8764d847d777663225.txt to http://dailyjournalonline.com/articles/2007/04/14/sports/doc461f8764d847d777663225.txt
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20080820231332/http://www.golf.com:80/golf/tours_news/article/0,28136,1827713,00.html to http://www.golf.com/golf/tours_news/article/0,28136,1827713,00.html
*Added {{tlx|dead link}} tag to http://www.ladieseuropeantour.com/content/let_content_news.php?Id=18788
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20090213054840/http://www.golf.com:80/golf/tours_news/article/0,28136,1578469-0,00.html to http://www.golf.com/golf/tours_news/article/0,28136,1578469-0,00.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20080518005413/http://www.ladieseuropeantour.com:80/content/let_content_interview.php?Id=4579 to http://www.ladieseuropeantour.com/content/let_content_interview.php?Id=4579

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 00:35, 15 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>hur7mzmlh4qh6qs4p5qkdr8phcmy2th</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
