<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.28.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2600" case="first-letter">Topic</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Barnaby Rudge</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>817035</id>
    <revision>
      <id>736022794</id>
      <parentid>734810788</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-24T16:57:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Heavenlyblue</username>
        <id>6604420</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14829">{{EngvarB|date=September 2013}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2013}}
{{Infobox book  | &lt;!-- See Wikipedia:WikiProject_Novels or Wikipedia:WikiProject_Books --&gt;
|name        =Barnaby Rudge
|title_orig  =Barnaby Rudge: A Tale of the Riots of Eighty
|image       =Masterclock serial cover.jpg
|caption=Cover of the magazine ''[[Master Humphrey's Clock]]'' where the novel was [[Serial (literature)|serialized]]
|author      =[[Charles Dickens]] (&quot;Boz&quot;)
|illustrator =[[George Cattermole]]&lt;br&gt;[[Hablot Knight Browne]] ([[Phiz]])
|cover_artist=
|country     =England
|language    =English
|genre       =[[Novel]]
|published  = [[Serial (literature)|Serialized]]: February–November 1841;&lt;ref&gt;[http://charlesdickenspage.com/rudge.html David Perdue's. Charles Dickens Page; Barnaby Rudge]&lt;/ref&gt; as a book 1841
|publisher   =[[Chapman &amp; Hall]]
|media_type  =Print ([[Serial (literature)|serial]], hardback, and paperback)
|pages       =
|isbn        =
|preceded_by =
|followed_by =}}
'''''Barnaby Rudge: A Tale of the Riots of Eighty''''' (commonly known as '''''Barnaby Rudge''''') is a historical novel by British novelist [[Charles Dickens]]. ''Barnaby Rudge'' was one of two novels (the other was ''[[The Old Curiosity Shop]]'') that Dickens published in his short-lived (1840–1841) weekly serial ''[[Master Humphrey's Clock]]''. '''Barnaby Rudge''' is largely set during the [[Gordon Riots]] of 1780.

''Barnaby Rudge'' was the fifth of Dickens' novels to be published. It had originally been planned to appear as his first, but changes of publisher led to many delays, and it first appeared in serial form in the ''Clock'' from February to November 1841.

It was Dickens' first historical novel.  His only other is the much later ''[[A Tale of Two Cities]]'', also set in revolutionary times.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.online-literature.com/dickens/barnabyrudge/ Online Literature website; Barnaby Rudge]&lt;/ref&gt; It is one of his less popular novels&lt;ref&gt;''[[Peter Ackroyd]]'' has called it &quot;one of Dickens's most neglected, but most rewarding, novels&quot;
&lt;/ref&gt; and has rarely been adapted for film or television.  The last production was [[Barnaby Rudge (TV series)|a 1960 BBC production]]; prior to that, silent films [[Barnaby Rudge (film)|were made in 1911 and 1915]].

==Plot summary==
[[File:Dolly Varden by William Powell Frith.jpg|thumb|left|150px|Dolly Varden as painted by [[William Powell Frith]], 1842]]
Gathered round the fire at the Maypole Inn, in the village of [[Chigwell]], on an evening of foul weather in the year 1775, are John Willet, proprietor of the Maypole, and his three cronies. One of the three, Solomon Daisy, tells an ill-kempt stranger at the inn a well-known local tale of the murder of Reuben Haredale which had occurred 22 years ago that very day. Reuben had been the owner of the Warren, a local estate which is now the residence of Geoffrey, the deceased Reuben's brother, and Geoffrey's niece, Reuben's daughter Emma Haredale. After the murder, Reuben's gardener and steward went missing and were suspects in the crime. A body was later found and identified as that of the steward, so the gardener was assumed to be the murderer.

Joe Willet, son of the Maypole proprietor, quarrels with his father because John treats 20-year-old Joe as a child. Finally having had enough of this ill treatment, Joe leaves the Maypole and goes for a soldier, stopping to say goodbye to the woman he loves, Dolly Varden, daughter of London locksmith Gabriel Varden.

Meanwhile, Edward Chester is in love with Emma Haredale. Both Edward's father, John Chester, and Emma's uncle, the Catholic Geoffrey Haredale – these two are sworn enemies – oppose the union after Sir John untruthfully convinces Geoffrey that Edward's intentions are dishonourable. Sir John intends to marry Edward to a woman with a rich inheritance, to support John's expensive lifestyle and to pay off his debtors. Edward quarrels with his father and leaves home for the West Indies.

Barnaby Rudge, a simpleton,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.naxosaudiobooks.com/90912.htm Barnaby Rudge]&lt;/ref&gt; wanders in and out of the story with his pet raven, Grip. Barnaby's mother begins to receive visits from the ill-kempt stranger, whom she feels compelled to protect. She later gives up the annuity she had been receiving from Geoffrey Haredale and, without explanation, takes Barnaby and leaves the city hoping to escape the unwanted visitor.

The story advances five years to a wintry evening in early 1780. On the 27th anniversary of Reuben Haredale's murder, Soloman Daisy, winding the bell tower clock, sees a ghost in the churchyard. He reports this hair-raising event to his friends at the Maypole, and John Willet decides that Geoffrey Haredale should hear the story. He departs in a winter storm taking Hugh, [[wiktionary:hostler|hostler]] of the Maypole, as a guide. On the way back to the Maypole, John and Hugh are met by three men seeking the way to London. Finding that London is still 13 miles off, the men seek refuge for the night. Beds are prepared for them at the Maypole.

[[Image:LordGeorgeGordon.jpg|thumb|left|150px|[[Lord George Gordon]] head of the [[Protestant Association]]]] These visitors prove to be Lord George Gordon; his secretary, Gashford; and a servant, John Grueby. Lord George makes an impassioned speech full of anti-papist sentiment, arguing (among other things) that Catholics in the military would, given a chance, join forces with their co-religionists on the Continent and attack Britain. Next day the three depart for London, inciting anti-Catholic sentiment along the way and recruiting Protestant volunteers, from whom Ned Dennis, hangman of Tyburn, and Simon Tappertit, former apprentice to Gabriel Varden, are chosen as leaders. Hugh, finding a handbill left at the Maypole, joins the Protestant throng which Dickens describes as &quot;sprinkled doubtless here and there with honest zealots, but composed for the most part of the very scum and refuse of London, whose growth was fostered by bad criminal laws, bad prison regulations, and the worst conceivable police.&quot;

Barnaby and his mother have been living quietly in a country village, their whereabouts unknown despite Geoffrey Haredale's attempts to find them. The mysterious stranger finds them and sends Stagg, the blind man, to attempt to get money from them. Barnaby and his mother then flee to London, hoping to again lose their pursuer.

When Barnaby and his mother arrive at Westminster Bridge they see an unruly crowd heading for a meeting on the [[Surrey]] side of the river. Barnaby is duped into joining them, despite his mother's pleas. The rioters then march on Parliament, and burn several Catholic churches and the homes of Catholic families.

A detachment led by Hugh and Dennis head for Chigwell, intent on exacting revenge on Geoffrey Haredale, leaving Barnaby to guard [[Cromer Street#Pubs|The Boot]], the tavern they use as their headquarters. The mob loots the Maypole on their way to the Warren, which they burn to the ground. Emma Haredale and Dolly Varden (now Emma's companion) are taken captive by the rioters. Barnaby is taken prisoner by soldiers and held in Newgate, which the mob plans to storm.

The mysterious stranger haunting Mrs. Rudge is captured by Haredale at the smoldering ruins of the Warren. He turns out to be Barnaby Rudge Sr., the steward who had murdered Reuben Haredale and his gardener years earlier. It is revealed that he had switched clothes with the dead gardener to divert suspicion from himself.

The rioters capture Gabriel Varden, with the help of his wife's maid Miggs, and attempt to have the locksmith help them break into Newgate to release prisoners. He refuses and is rescued by two men, one of whom has only one arm. The rioters then burn Newgate where Barnaby and his father are being held. All of the prisoners escape, but Barnaby, his father, and Hugh are betrayed by Dennis the hangman and captured by soldiers. Dennis has changed sides, believing he will obtain the bounty offered for them as well as numerous clients needing his special talents. With the military patrolling the streets, the rioters scatter and many are killed.

The one-armed man turns out to be Joe Willet, who has returned from fighting against the American revolutionaries. Joe and Edward Chester turn out to be the rescuers of Gabriel Varden. The pair then rescue Dolly and Emma.

[[File:Illustrirte Zeitung (1843) 16 256 3 Hugh und Dennis fünf Minuten vor der Hinrichtung.PNG|thumb|''Hugh and Dennis five minutes before execution'' (Book illustration)]]
Dennis is arrested and sentenced to die with Hugh and Barnaby. Hugh and Dennis are hanged. Barnaby, through the efforts of Gabriel Varden, is pardoned.

Joe and Dolly are married and become proprietors of the rebuilt Maypole. Edward Chester and Emma are married and go to the West Indies. Miggs tries to get her position back at the Varden household, is rejected, and becomes a jailer at a women's prison. Simon Tappertit, his legs crushed in the riots, becomes a shoe-black. Gashford later commits suicide. Lord George Gordon is held in the Tower and is later judged to be innocent of inciting the riots. Sir John Chester, now a member of parliament, turns out to be the father of Hugh and is killed in a duel by Geoffrey Haredale. Haredale escapes to the continent where he ends his days in a monastery. Barnaby and his mother live out their years tending a farm at the Maypole Inn where Barnaby can work effectively due to his physical strength.

==Characters==
*The Rudges – '''Barnaby''', a [[developmentally disabled|simple]] man, his loving mother '''Mary''', and his companion '''Grip''', the loquacious raven
*The Willets – '''Old John''', the keeper of the Maypole Inn, and his kindly son '''Joe'''
*The Vardens – '''Gabriel''', the locksmith, his manipulative wife '''Martha''', and his beautiful daughter '''Dolly Varden'''
*The Chesters – the villainous '''Sir John, Esquire, M.P.''' (Member of Parliament) and his innocent son '''Edward'''
*The Haredales – '''Mr Geoffrey Haredale''', younger brother of the murdered '''Reuben''', and his niece (Reuben's daughter) '''Emma'''
*'''Hugh''' – the sinister hostler of the Maypole Inn
*'''[[Lord George Gordon]]''' (a fictionalisation of the historical personality), his loyal servant '''John Grueby''', and his obsequious and duplicitous secretary '''Mr Gashford'''
*'''Simon Tappertit''' – Gabriel Varden's apprentice, and '''Miggs''', Mrs Varden's shrewish housemaid
*'''Ned Dennis''' – the hangman of Tyburn
*The mysterious '''stranger''', ultimately revealed to be '''Barnaby Rudge, Sr''', the steward and murderer of Reuben Haredale
*'''Stagg''' – the crafty blind man
*'''Solomon Daisy''', ''''Long' Phil Parkes''', and '''Tom Cobb''', Old John's three cronies
*'''Mr Langdale''' – the purple-faced old vintner

==Allusions and references in other works==
Grip the raven inspired [[Edgar Allan Poe]] to write his most famous poem, &quot;[[The Raven]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Kopley, Richard and Kevin J. Hayes. &quot;Two verse masterworks: 'The Raven' and 'Ulalume',&quot; collected in ''The Cambridge Companion to Edgar Allan Poe'', edited by Kevin J. Hayes. New York: [[Cambridge University Press]], 2002. p. 192. ISBN 0-521-79727-6&lt;/ref&gt; Poe had written a review of ''Barnaby Rudge'' for ''[[Graham's Magazine]]'' saying, among other things, that the raven should have served a more symbolic prophetic purpose.

==Adaptations==
Thomas Higgie adapted it into a three-act play in 1854. [[Charles Selby]] and Charles Melville did the same in 1875.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Marzials|first1=Frank Thomas|title=Life of Charles Dickens|date=1908|pages=262|url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=hFzKOSya-2sC&amp;dq=Charles+Melville+dickens&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s|accessdate=13 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The latter was produced at the [[Lyceum Theatre, London|English Opera House]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=itle-page of &quot;Barnaby Rudge. A Domestic Drama, In Three Acts&quot;|url=http://www.victorianweb.org/mt/adaptations/16.html|website=The Victorian Web|accessdate=13 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1915 [[Thomas Bentley]] directed ''Barnaby Rudge'', &quot;the biggest-budget British film of its day&quot;, but it is now lost.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Eaton|first1=Michael|title=Dickens on Film|url=http://www.screenonline.org.uk/film/id/473285/|website=British Film Institute|accessdate=13 May 2016|quote=Bentley made six silent Dickens adaptations, the most sumptuous of which must surely have been 1915's Barnaby Rudge, the biggest-budget British film of its day, now sadly missing. The surviving pressbook shows spectacular sets of 18th century London built at Walton-on-Thames}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The BBC made [[Barnaby Rudge (TV series)|a 13 episode TV series in 1960]]. 

''Barnaby Rudge'' was re-invented as a stage play, ''The Locksmith of London'', by Eileen Norris. It was staged in 2012 at the [[Kings Theatre, Southsea]] by Alchemy Theatre, where the [[Dickens Fellowship]] attended a performance during their annual conference.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Barnaby Rudge Website|url=http://www.dickensfellowship.org/content/barnaby-rudge-website|website=Dickens Fellowship|accessdate=13 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[BBC Radio 4]] chose it for their ''[[Classic Serial]]'' in 2014, and cast an actor with [[Down's Syndrome]], Daniel Laurie, in the title role.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Rose|first1=Damon|title=The actor with Down's syndrome tackling Dickens|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/blogs-ouch-27543429|date=24 May 2014|accessdate=5 August 2016|agency=BBC|quote=He plays Barnaby Rudge in a new radio adaptation of one of Charles Dickens's lesser-known works. Rudge is an &quot;idiot&quot; as the language of the time would have it. Today we might say he has a learning disability.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{portal|Novels|Literature|Charles Dickens}}

*[[Political fiction]]
*[[Dolly Varden trout#Origin of common name &quot;Dolly Varden&quot;|Dolly Varden trout]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Sisterlinks|v=no|b=no|wikt=no|n=no|commons=Category:Barnaby Rudge}}
'''Online editions'''
*[https://archive.org/stream/scmasterhumphrey02dickrich#page/n7/mode/2up''Barnaby Rudge''] at [[Internet Archive]]. Master Humphrey's Clock edition
*{{gutenberg|no=917|name=Barnaby Rudge}}
* {{librivox book | title=Barnaby Rudge | author=Charles Dickens}}

'''Commentary'''
*[http://books.guardian.co.uk/departments/classics/story/0,,1587304,00.html Guardian.co.uk], an essay on ''Barnaby Rudge'' by [[Peter Ackroyd]] in ''[[The Guardian]]''

{{Charles Dickens}}
{{The Raven}}

[[Category:1780 in fiction]]
[[Category:1841 novels]]
[[Category:Chapman &amp; Hall books]]
[[Category:Edgar Allan Poe]]
[[Category:English historical novels]]
[[Category:Novels by Charles Dickens]]
[[Category:Novels set in Essex]]
[[Category:Victorian novels]]
[[Category:Works originally published in Master Humphrey's Clock]]</text>
      <sha1>n5hty3hwqihg4btqg15bdodxmz37hoq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
