<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Gay bar</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>501560</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746743144</id>
      <parentid>746741070</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-29T07:52:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DRAGON BOOSTER</username>
        <id>11104969</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* List of gay bars */ Copyedit (minor)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="38430">{{about|the type of bar|the song by Electric Six|Gay Bar (song)}}
{{pp-pc1}}
[[File:Stonewall Inn 1969.jpg|thumb|250px|The [[Stonewall Inn]] in [[New York City]] was the site of the [[Stonewall riots]] of 1969, which have come to symbolize the beginning of the modern [[gay liberation]] movement in the United States. Shown here in 1969, it has since been remodeled.]]

A '''gay bar''' is a [[Bar (establishment)|drinking establishment]] that caters to an exclusively or predominantly [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexual]], and [[transgender]] ([[LGBT]]) clientele; the term ''gay'' is used as a broadly inclusive concept for LGBT and [[queer]] communities.

Gay bars once served as the centre of gay culture and were one of the few places people with [[homosexuality|same-sex]] orientations and [[gender-variant]] identities could openly socialize. Other names used to describe these establishments include ''boy bar'', ''girl bar'', ''gay club'', ''gay [[Public house|pub]]'', ''queer bar'', ''lesbian bar'', ''drag bar'', and ''[[Dyke (slang)|dyke]] bar'', depending on the niche communities that they served.

With the advent of the Internet and an increasing acceptance of LGBT people across the Western world, the relevance of gay bars in the [[LGBT community]] has somewhat diminished.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author=Geoff Williams | title=10 Businesses Facing Extinction in 10 Years | url=http://www.entrepreneur.com//startingabusiness/article184288.html | work=Entrepreneur | date=19 September 2007 | accessdate=2008-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; In areas without a gay bar, certain establishments may hold a [[gay night]].

==History==

Gathering places favoured by homosexuals have operated for centuries. Reports from as early as the 17th century record the existence of bars and clubs that catered to, or at least tolerated, openly gay clientele in several major European cities.&lt;ref&gt;Tim Blanning. ''The Pursuit of Glory: Europe 1648-1815''. p 80. ISBN 978-0-670-06320-8.&lt;/ref&gt; The White Swan (created by James Cook and Yardley, full name unknown), on [[Vere Street, Westminster|Vere Street]], in London, England, was raided in 1810 during the so-called [[Vere Street Coterie]]. The raid led to the executions of John Hepburn and Thomas White for [[sodomy]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.capitalpunishmentuk.org/new1800.html capitalpunishment.org Newgate executions 1800 - 1836]&lt;/ref&gt; The site was the scene of alleged [[gay marriage]]s carried out by the [[Reverend John Church]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author=Caryn E. Neumann | title=The Vere Street Coterie | url=http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/vere_street_coterie.html | work= | date=17 June 2007 | accessdate=2008-11-26}}http://wayback.archive.org/web/20150925093526/http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/vere_street_coterie.html&lt;/ref&gt;

It's not clear which place is the first gay bar in the modern sense. In Cannes, France, such a bar had already opened in 1885, and there were many more in Berlin around 1900. In the United Kingdom and the Netherlands gay bars were established throughout the first quarter of the 20th century.

=== France ===
The very first gay bar in Europe and probably in the world was the Zanzibar in [[Cannes]] on the French Riviera. The place was opened in 1885 and existed for 125 years, before it was closed in December 2010. Among its visitors were many artists, like actor [[Jean Marais]] and comedians [[Thierry Le Luron]] and Coluche.&lt;ref&gt;RTBF.be: [http://www.rtbf.be/info/societe/detail_france-fermeture-du-plus-vieux-bar-gay-d-europe-a-cannes?id=5559303 France: fermeture du &quot;plus vieux bar gay d'Europe&quot; à Cannes], January 7, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Main article|LGBT culture in Paris}}
[[Paris]] became known as a centre for gay culture in the 19th century, making the city a queer capital during the early 20th century, when the [[Montmartre]] and [[Quartier Pigalle|Pigalle]] districts were meeting places of the LGBT community. Although [[Amsterdam]], [[Berlin]], and [[London]] had more meeting places and organizations than Paris, the latter was known for the &quot;flamboyance&quot; of LGBT quarters and &quot;visibility&quot; of LGBT celebrities.&lt;ref name=Tamagnep240&gt;Florence Tamagne, ''Paris: 'Resting on its Laurels'?'', in: Queer Cities, Queer Cultures: Europe since 1945, p. [https://books.google.com/books?id=r6zDAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA240 240].&lt;/ref&gt;

Paris retained the LGBT capital image after the end of [[World War II]], but the center of the meeting place shifted to [[Saint-Germain-des-Prés]]. In the 1950s and 1960s the police and authorities tolerated homosexuals as long as the conduct was private and out of view, but gay bar raids occurred and there were occasions when the owners of the bars were involved in facilitating the raids. Lesbians rarely visited gay bars and instead socialized in circles of friends. Lesbians who did go to bars often originated from the working class.&lt;ref name=Tamagnep242243&gt;Tamagne, p. [https://books.google.com/books?id=r6zDAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA242 242]- [https://books.google.com/books?id=r6zDAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA243 243].&lt;/ref&gt; Chez Moune, opened in 1936,  and New Moon were 20th century lesbian cabarets located in [[Place Pigalle]], which converted to mixed music clubs in the 21st century.&lt;ref&gt;Laurent Jézéquel, &quot;[http://www.telerama.fr/sortir/new-moon-comment-un-cabaret-de-pigalle-est-devenu-le-qg-du-rock-alternatif,132223.php New Moon : comment un cabaret de Pigalle est devenu le QG du rock alternatif&quot;, ''Telerama]''   Publié le 05/10/2015. Mis à jour le 07/10/2015 à 18h59.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://lostwomynsspace.blogspot.com/2011_07_01_archive.html&lt;/ref&gt;

Since the 1980s, the [[Le Marais]] district is the center of the gay scene in Paris.

=== Germany ===
{{Main article|LGBT culture in Berlin}}
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-1983-0121-500, Berlin, Bar &quot;Eldorado&quot;.jpg|thumb|right|The gay club Eldorado in Berlin, 1932]]
In [[Berlin]], there was gay and lesbian night life already around the year 1900, which throughout the 1920s became very open and vibrant, especially when compared to other capitals. Especially in the [[Schöneberg]] district around [[Nollendorfplatz]] there were many cafes, bars and clubs, which also attracted gay people who had to flee their own country in fear of prosecution, like for example [[Christopher Isherwood]]. The gay club Eldorado in the [[Motzstraße]] was internationally known for its [[transvestite]] shows. There was also a relatively very high number of places for lesbians. Within a few weeks after the Nazis took over government in 1933, fourteen of the best known gay establishments were closed. After homosexuality was decriminalized in 1969, many gay bars opened in [[West Berlin]], resulting in a lively gay scene.

=== United Kingdom ===
{{Main article|LGBT culture in London}}

In the 18th Century, [[Molly house|Molly Houses]] were clandestine clubs where gay men could meet, drink, dance and have sex with each other.  One of the most famous was Mother Clap's Molly House.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cabinetmagazine.org/issues/8/bailey.php Amanda Bailey, Cabinet Magazine, Issue 8 Pharmacopia , Fall 2002, Welcome to the Molly-House: An Interview with Randolph Trumbach]&lt;/ref&gt;

The first gay bar in Britain in the modern sense was [[The Cave of the Golden Calf]], established as a [[night club]] in [[London]]. It opened in an underground location at 9 Heddon Street, just off [[Regent Street]], in 1912 and became a haunt for the wealthy, aristocratic and bohemian.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=London and the Culture of Homosexuality, 1885-1914 (Cambridge Studies in Nineteenth-Century Literature and Culture)|author=Matt Cook|isbn=0521089808}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its creator [[Frida Uhl|Frida Strindberg née Uhl]] set it up as an [[avant-garde]] and artistic venture.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.20thcenturylondon.org.uk/server.php?show=conObject.4983|title=The programme and menu from the Cave of the Golden Calf, Cabaret and Theatre Club|author=|date=|work=20thcenturylondon.org.uk|accessdate=8 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The club provided a solid model for future nightclubs.

After homosexuality was decriminalized in the UK in 1967, gay bar culture became more visible and gradually [[Soho]] became the centre of the London LGBT community, which was &quot;firmly established&quot; by the early 1990s.&lt;ref name=Turnerp50&gt;Turner, p. [https://books.google.com/books?id=5VdsY1LF_gMC&amp;pg=PA50 50].&lt;/ref&gt; Gay bars, cafes, restaurants and clubs are centred on [[Old Compton Street]].

Other cities in the UK also have districts or streets with a concentration of gay bars, like for example [[Stanley Street Quarter]] in Liverpool, [[Canal Street (Manchester)|Canal Street]] in Manchester and the [[Birmingham Gay Village]].

=== The Netherlands ===
{{see also|LGBT history in the Netherlands}}
[[File:Café ‘t Mandje.jpg|thumb|Café 't Mandje at Zeedijk in Amsterdam]]
In [[Amsterdam]], there were already a few gay bars in the first quarter of the 20th century. The best known was The Empire, which was first mentioned in 1911 and existed until the late 1930s.&lt;ref&gt;Pieter Koenders, ''Tussen christelijk réveil en seksuele revolutie - Bestrijding van zedeloosheid in Nederland'', Amsterdam 1996, p. 704-706&lt;/ref&gt; The oldest place that still exists is [[Café ‘t Mandje]], which was opened in 1927 by lesbian Bet van Beeren.&lt;ref name=gaybarnl&gt;Gert Hekma (Gay Studies University of Amsterdam), [http://web.archive.org/web/20050306020448/http://www2.fmg.uva.nl/gl/gaybar.html The Amsterdam Bar Culture And Changing Gay/Lesbian Identities]&lt;/ref&gt; It closed in 1982, but was reopened in 2008.

After [[World War II]], the Amsterdam city government acted rather pragmatic and tolerated the existence of gay bars. In the 1960s their number grew rapidly and they clustered in and around a number of streets, although this was limited to bars, clubs and shops and they never became residential areas for gays, like the [[gay village]]s in the US.

Since the late 1950s the main Amsterdam gay street was [[Kerkstraat]], which was succeeded by [[Reguliersdwarsstraat]] in the early 1980s, when the first openly gay places opened here, like the famous cafe April in 1981, followed by dancing Havana in 1989.&lt;ref&gt;Reguliers.net: [http://www.reguliers.net/history.php History of Reguliersdwarsstraat]&lt;/ref&gt; Other streets where there are still concentrations of gay bars are [[Zeedijk]], Amstel and [[Warmoesstraat]], the latter being the center of the Amsterdam [[leather scene]], where the first leather bar already opened around 1955.&lt;ref name=gaybarnl /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;About the history of the Amsterdam [http://www.leatherhistory.eu/ Leather Scene]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Denmark ===

{{See also|LGBT rights in Denmark}}

The bar Centralhjørnet in [[Copenhagen]] opened in 1917 and became a gay bar in the 1950s. It now claims to be one of the oldest gay bars in Europe.&lt;ref&gt;See: [http://www.visitcopenhagen.com/gaycopenhagen LGBT Copenhagen]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.patroc.com/copenhagen/|title=Copenhagen Gay Travel Guide 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Russia===

{{See also|LGBT culture in Russia}}

Because of the high prevalence of [[homophobia]] in Russia,  patrons of gay bars there often have had to be on the alert for bullying and attacks.  In 2013, Moscow's largest gay bar, Central Station, had its walls sprayed with gunfire, had harmful gas released into a crowd of 500 patrons, and had its ceiling nearly brought down by a gang who wanted to crush the people inside.  Nonetheless, gay nightlife is increasing in Moscow and St. Petersburg,  offering drag shows and Russian music, with some bars also offering discreet gay only taxi services.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vice.com/read/this-is-what-a-gay-night-out-in-moscow-is-like Jessica Kirk, Secrecy, Dark Rooms, and Patriotic Drag Queens: A Gay Night Out in Moscow,  Vice,   March 26, 2015]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Spain===

{{See also|LGBT history in Spain}}

Under the dictatorship of [[General Francisco Franco]] from 1939-1977,  homosexuality was illegal.  However,  in 1962, Spain's first gay bar, Tony's, opened in [[Torremolinos]] and a clandestine gay bar scene also emerged in the 60's and early 70's in [[Barcelona]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theolivepress.es/spain-news/2015/07/27/how-la-nogalera-came-to-be-torremolinos-gay-hot-spot/ Rob Horgan , How La Nogalera came to be Torremolinos’ gay hot-spot, The Olive Press,   27 Jul, 2015]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== United States ===

There are many institutions in the United States that claim to be the oldest gay bar. Since [[Prohibition]] ended in 1933, there are a number of places open and continuously operating since that date:
* The [[Atlantic House]] in [[Provincetown, Massachusetts]] was constructed in 1798 and was a tavern and stagecoach stop before becoming a ''de facto'' gay bar after artists and actors, including [[Tennessee Williams]] began spending summers in P-town in the 1920s.&lt;ref name=&quot;A-House&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.ahouse.com/history.html | title=History | accessdate=November 28, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Black Cat Bar]], founded in 1906 and operated again after Prohibition was ended in 1933, was located in [[San Francisco]]'s [[North Beach, San Francisco|North Beach]] neighborhood and was the focus of one of the earliest victories of the [[homophile]] movement. In 1951, the [[California Supreme Court]] affirmed the right of homosexuals to assemble in a case brought by the heterosexual owner of the bar.
*[[Black Cat Tavern|The Black Cat Tavern]] opened in November 1966 and was one of many LGBT bars to be raided, which happened on New Year's Day in 1967. It is now considered a Los Angeles Historic-Cultural Monument.
* The [[Double Header]] in [[Seattle|Seattle's]] Pioneer Square is claimed to be the oldest gay bar on the North American West Coast, operating since 1933.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author=Kery Murakami | title=No longer at the center of Seattle's gay scene, bar still serving outsiders | url=http://www.seattlepi.com/local/320946_doubleheader23.html | work=The Seattle PI | date=June 23, 2007 | accessdate=1 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Esta Noche (gay bar)|Esta Noche]] was the first gay Latino bar that opened in 1979. It was located on Mission Street and 16th Street. Closed down in 1997 as one of the last gay Latino bar in the [[Mission District, San Francisco|Mission District]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://works.bepress.com/horacio_roqueramirez/4/|title=&quot;&quot;'Mira, Yo Soy Boricua y Estoy Aquí': Rafa Negrón's Pan Dulce and the Queer Sonic Latinaje of San Francisco&quot;&quot; by Horacio N Roque Ramirez|last=Press|first=Berkeley Electronic|website=works.bepress.com|access-date=2016-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* [[Maud's (bar)|Maud's Study]] (961 Cole Street San Francisco), featured in the film &quot;[[Last Call at Maud's (1993 film)|Last Call At Maud's]]&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[http://variety.com/1993/film/reviews/last-call-at-maud-s-1200431389/ Elley, Derek.  &quot;Review: Last Call At Maud's&quot;, ''Variety'', February 25, 1993]&lt;/ref&gt;  was a lesbian bar which was founded by [[Rikki Streicher]] in 1966 and closed in September 1989. At closing, it claimed to be the oldest continuously operating lesbian bar.&lt;ref&gt;Bajko, Matthew, &quot;[http://ebar.com/news/article.php?sec=news&amp;article=71691 For Many, Shuttered SF Lesbian Bar Maud's Was Home,&quot;''The Bay Area Reporter''], June 30, 2016&lt;/ref&gt; It closed during the AIDS crisis when a &quot;clean and sober&quot; mentality drove down a lot of bars.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Girls in the Back Room: Looking at the Lesbian Bar|last=Hankin|first=Kelly|publisher=University of Minnesota Press|year=2002|isbn=|location=|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In [[New York City]], the modern gay bar dates to [[Julius (New York City)|Julius Bar]], founded by local socialite Matthew Nicol, where the [[Mattachine Society]] staged a &quot;Sip-In&quot; on 21 April 1966 challenging a New York State Liquor Authority rule prohibited serving [[alcoholic beverage]]s to gays on the basis that they were considered disorderly. The court ruling in the case that gays could peacefully assemble at bars would lead to the opening of the [[Stonewall Inn]] a block southwest in 1967, which in turn led to the 1969 [[Stonewall Riots]]. Julius is New York City's oldest continuously operating gay bar.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author=Scott Simon | title=Remembering a 1966 'Sip-In' for Gay Rights | url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=91993823 | publisher=National Public Radio | date=28 June 2008 | accessdate=2008-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Cafe Lafitte in Exile]] in [[New Orleans]], dating back to 1933 and the end of Prohibition, claims to be the oldest continuously operating gay bar in the United States.
* The White Horse Inn in [[Oakland, California]], also operating legally since Prohibition, but likely during the period where sales of alcohol were banned in the U.S., also claims to be the oldest gay bar in operation.&lt;ref name=&quot;White Horse Bar&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/05/21/americas-oldest-gay-bar_n_3314338.html | title=America's Oldest Gay Bar, WhiteHorse, Turns 80 | publisher=Huffington Post | date=May 21, 2013 | accessdate=November 28, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mexico===

{{Main article|LGBT history in Mexico}}

Because of a raid on a Mexico City drag ball in 1901, when 41 men were arrested,  the number 41 has come to symbolize male homosexuality in [[Culture of Mexico|Mexican popular culture]], figuring frequently in [[joke]]s and in casual [[teasing]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Coerver, Pasztor and Buffington, p. 202&quot;&gt;Coerver, Pasztor and Buffington, p. 202.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dynes, Johansson, Percy and Donaldson, p. 806&quot;&gt;Dynes, Johansson, Percy and Donaldson, p. 806&lt;ref name=&quot;Dynes, Johansson, Percy and Donaldson, p. 806&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The raid on the ''Dance of the 41'' was followed by a less-publicized raid of a [[lesbian bar]] on 4 December 1901 in Santa Maria. Despite the [[Great Depression|international depression of the 1930s]] and along with the social revolution overseen by [[President of Mexico|President]] [[Lázaro Cárdenas]] (1934–40), the growth of Mexico City was accompanied by the opening of gay bars and [[gay bathhouse]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dynes, Johansson, Percy and Donaldson, p. 806&quot;/&gt; During the [[Second World War]], ten to fifteen gay bars operated in Mexico City, with dancing permitted in at least two, ''El África'' and ''El Triunfo''. Relative freedom from official [[harassment]] continued until 1959 when [[Head of Government of the Federal District|Mayor]] Ernesto Uruchurtu closed every gay bar following a grisly triple murder. But by the late 1960s several Mexican cities had gay bars and, later, [[United States|U.S.-style]] [[dance club]]s. These places, however, were sometimes clandestine but tolerated by local authorities,which often meant that they were allowed to exist so long as the owners paid [[Bribery|bribes]]. A fairly visible presence was developed in large cities such as Guadalajara, [[Acapulco, Guerrero|Acapulco]], [[Veracruz, Veracruz|Veracruz]] and Mexico City.&lt;ref name=&quot;Herrick and Stuart, p. 141&quot;&gt;Herrick and Stuart, p. 141.&lt;/ref&gt; Today, Mexico City is home to numerous gay bars, many of them located in the [[Zona Rosa (Mexico City)|Zona Rosa]].

=== Singapore ===

{{See also|LGBT history in Singapore}}

The first recorded use of the term 'gay bar' is in the diaries of homosexual British comedian [[Kenneth Williams]]: &quot;16 January 1947.  Went round to the gay bar which wasn't in the least gay.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''The Kenneth Williams Diaries'' edited by [[Russell Davies]], 1993, 8.&lt;/ref&gt; At the time Williams was serving in the British Army in [[Singapore]]. In the 1970s, straight nightclubs began to open their doors to gay clients on designated nights of the week.  In the 1980s, a lesbian bar named Crocodile Rock opened in Far East Plaza, which remains to this day the oldest lesbian bar in Singapore. Today, many gay bars are located on the Neil Road stretch,  from Taboo and Tantric, to Backstage Bar, May Wong’s Café, DYMK and Play.  Mega-clubs like Zouk and Avalon are also a big draw for the gay crowd.&lt;ref&gt;[https://sg.style.yahoo.com/blogs/singapore-showbiz/behind-doors-singapore-gay-night-club-scene-031521386.html jeffoon , Behind the doors of Singapore’s gay night club scene,  Singapore Showbiz, 29 December 2012]&lt;/ref&gt;

===China===

{{See also|LGBT history in China}}

The oldest gay bar in [[Beijing]] is the Half-and-Half, which in 2004 had been open over ten years.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=Jm2NAgAAQBAJ&amp;dq=china+oldest+gay+bar&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s Loretta Wing Wah Ho, Gay and Lesbian Subculture in Urban China, Routledge, Sep 10, 2009, p. 43]&lt;/ref&gt;  The first lesbian bar was Maple Bar, opened in 2000 by pop singer [[Qiao Qiao]].  Qiao Qiao also opened another popular lesbian bar, Feng bar, also known as Pipes,which was closed by the police in 2009.  The On/Off was a popular bar for both gay men and lesbians.&lt;ref&gt;http://newurbanquestion.ifou.org/proceedings/3%20The%20Urbanized%20Society/poster%20papers/B034_Teng_Jingru_Lesbian%20Spaces%20in%20Beijing.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; The increase in China's gay and lesbian bars in recent years is linked to China's opening up to global capitalism and its  consequent economic and social restructuring.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=Jm2NAgAAQBAJ&amp;dq=china+oldest+gay+bar&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s Loretta Wing Wah Ho, Gay and Lesbian Subculture in Urban China, Routledge, Sep 10, 2009, pps 41-43]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Japan ===

''See also:'' ''[[LGBT in Tokyo]]''

The oldest continuously operating Japanese gay bar, New Sazae, opened in Tokyo in 1966.&lt;ref name = &quot;new sazae&quot;&gt;In 1966 (昭和41), There is the continuously operating gay bar &quot;New Sazae&quot; which opened in Tokyo, [[Shinjuku Ni-chōme]]. 8 December 2007 [[:ja:出没!アド街ック天国]] Shinjuku Ni-chōme.[http://www.tv-tokyo.co.jp/adomachi/backnumber/20071208/31164.html]&lt;/ref&gt; Most gay bars in Tokyo are located in the [[Shinjuku Ni-chōme]] district, which is home to about 300 bars.&lt;ref&gt;''Independent''. February 7, 2010. Retrieved on March 16, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; Each bar may only have room to seat about a dozen people; as a result, many bars are specialized according to interest.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.utopia-asia.com/tipsjapn.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

===Jordan===

{{See also|LGBT rights in Jordan}}

Jordan's most famous and oldest gay-friendly establishment is a combination bar/cafe/restaurant and bookshop in [[Amman]] called Books@cafe, opened in 1997.  When the bar was first opened, it was infiltrated by government undercover agents who were concerned about its effect on public morality and outed the owner as homosexual to his family and friends.  Now, however, the owner claims to have no problem with the government and has since opened a second establishment.&lt;ref&gt;https://twothousandfourhundredmiles.wordpress.com/2015/02/25/the-rebels-of-amman-being-gay-in-jordans-capital/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dailyxtra.com/canada/news-and-ideas/news/exploring-ammans-gay-spaces-52160&lt;/ref&gt;

===South Africa===

{{See also|LGBT rights in South Africa}}

The history of gay and lesbian bars in South Africa reflects the racial divisions that began in the [[Apartheid]] era and continue, to some extent, in the 21st century.&lt;ref&gt;Ken Cage, Moyra Evans, Gayle: The Language of Kinks and Queens : a History and Dictionary of Gay Language in South Africa Jacana Media, 2003, p. 15&lt;/ref&gt;

The first white gay bar opened in the Carlton Hotel in downtown [[Johannesburg]] in the late 1940s, catering exclusiely to men of wealth. In the 1960s, other urban bars began to open that drew more middle and working class white men; lesbians were excluded.  The language of [[Gayle language|Gayle]] had its roots in the [[Cape Coloured]] and [[Afrikaans]] -speaking underground gay bar culture.  In 1968, when the government threatened to pass repressive anti-gay legislation,  queer culture went even further underground, which meant clubs and bars were often the only places to meet.  These bars were often the targets of police raids.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=WSn7026sq_cC&amp;pg=PA11&amp;dq=history+gay+bars+south+africa&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjXuJbuwsfOAhUX02MKHSI_CakQ6AEIHDAA#v=onepage&amp;q=history%20gay%20bars%20south%20africa&amp;f=false Ken Cage, Moyra Evans, Gayle: The Language of Kinks and Queens : a History and Dictionary of Gay Language in South Africa Jacana Media, 2003, p. 15]&lt;/ref&gt; The decade of the 1970s was when urban gay clubs took root. The most popular gay club of Johannesburg was The Dungeon, which attracted females as well as males, and lasted until the 1990s.  The 1979 police assault on the New Mandy's Club, in which patrons fought back, has been referred to as South Africa's [[Stonewall riots|Stonewall]].&lt;ref&gt;Philip Harrison, Gay and Lesbian, New Africa Books, 2005, p. 13&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1980s, police raids on white gay clubs lessened as the apartheid government forces found itself dealing with more and more resistance from the black population. In the black townships, some of the [[shebeens]], unlicensed bars established in people's homes and garages, catered to LGBTQ clients.  During the struggle against apartheid, some of these shebeens were important meeting places for black gay and lesbian resistance fighters. Lee’s, a shebeen in [[Soweto]], for example, was used as a meeting place for black gay men who were part of the Gay Association of South Africa (GASA) but did not feel welcome in the GASA offices&lt;ref name=&quot;citation.allacademic.com&quot;&gt;[http://citation.allacademic.com/meta/p_mla_apa_research_citation/2/4/2/8/9/pages242891/p242891-4.php Williams, Jill.Spatial Transversals: Gender, Race, Class, and Tourism in Cape Town, South Africa]&lt;/ref&gt;

With the establishment of the post-apartheid 1996 constitution that outlawed discrimination based on sexual orientation as well as race, South Africa's gay night life exploded, though many bars continued to be segregated by race, and fewer blacks than whites go to the urban bars. The 2005 inaugural gay shebeen tour was advertised as a gay pub crawl that would provide an opportunity for South Africans and foreigners to “experience true African gay Shebeen culture”&lt;ref name=&quot;citation.allacademic.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/4329017.stm Alastair Leithead.  Taking Gay Pride to SA's townships BBC News, Cape Town,Tuesday, 8 March, 2005,]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Today ==

A number of commentators have suggested that gay bars are facing decline in the contemporary age. [[Andrew Sullivan]] argued in his essay &quot;The End of Gay Culture&quot; that gay bars are declining because &quot;the Internet dealt them a body blow. If you are merely looking for sex or a date, the Web is now the first stop for most gay men&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.tnr.com/article/politics/the-end-gay-culture|title=The End of Gay Culture|first=Andrew|last=Sullivan|publisher=The New Republic|date=4 October 2005|accessdate=22 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

June Thomas explained the decline by noting that there is less need for gay-specific venues like bars because gay people are less likely to encounter discrimination or be made unwelcome in wider society.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.slate.com/articles/life/the_gay_bar/2011/06/the_gay_bar_6.html|title=The Gay Bar: is it dying|first=June|last=Thomas|publisher=Slate|date=27 June 2011|accessdate=22 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Entrepreneur'' magazine in 2007 included them on a list of ten types of business that would be extinct by 2017 along with record stores, used bookstores and newspapers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.entrepreneur.com/article/184288|title=10 Businesses Facing Extinction in 10 Years|first=Geoff|last=Williams|publisher=Entrepreneur|date=19 September 2007|accessdate=22 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==

[[File:Barzilay Venue in Tel Aviv Israel.jpg|thumb|right|250px|The interior of a gay bar in [[Tel Aviv]], [[Israel]], which contains a dance floor and music.]]

[[File:De Waterkant 7.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Hub of men-only gay bars in [[Cape Town]], South Africa]]

Like most bars and pubs, gay bars range in size from the small, five-seat bars of [[Tokyo]] to large, multi-story clubs with several distinct areas and more than one dance floor. A large venue may be referred to as a [[nightclub]], [[Club (organization)|club]], or bar, while smaller venues are typically called bars and sometimes [[pubs]]. The only defining characteristic of a gay bar is the nature of its clientele. While many gay bars target the gay and/or lesbian communities, some (usually older and firmly established) gay bars have become gay, as it were, through custom, over a long period of time.

The serving of alcohol is the primary business of gay bars and pubs. Like non-gay establishments they serve as a meeting place and [[Gay community|LGBT community]] focal point, in which conversation, relaxation, and meeting potential romantic and sexual partners is the primary focus of the clientele. Historically and continuing in many communities, gay bars have been valued by patrons as the only place closeted gay men and lesbians can be open and demonstrative about their sexuality without fear of discovery. [[Gerard Koskovich]] of the [[GLBT Historical Society|Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual, Transgender Historical Society]] explains that &quot;[Gay bars] were a public place where gay people could meet and start to have a conversation, where they didn't feel like sexual freaks or somehow not part of the larger social fabric; from that came culture, politics, demands for equal rights.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;San Francisco Chronicle&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.sfchronicle.com/lgbt/article/Oakland-s-White-Horse-gay-bar-turns-80-4503994.php?t=17c55728e38cb1714c | title=Oakland's White Horse gay bar turns 80 | work=San Francisco Chronicle | date=May 9, 2013 | accessdate=November 28, 2015 | author=Jones, Carolyn}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Gay bars traditionally preferred to remain discreet and virtually unidentifiable outside the gay community, relying exclusively on word of mouth promotion. More recently, gay clubs and events are often advertised by handing out eye-catching [[flyer (pamphlet)|flyers]] on the street, in gay or gay-friendly shops and venues, and at other clubs and events. Similar to flyers for predominantly heterosexual venues, these flyers frequently feature provocative images and theme party announcements.

While traditional gay pub-like bars are nearly identical to bars catering to the general public, gay dance venues often feature elaborate lighting design and video projection, fog machines and raised dancing platforms. Hired dancers (called [[go-go dancing|go-go girls]] or [[go-go dancing|go-go boys]]) may also feature in decorative cages or on podiums. Gay sports bars are relatively unusual, but it is not unusual for gay bars to sponsor teams in local sports/game leagues, and many otherwise traditional gay pubs are well known for hosting post-game parties—often filling with local gay athletes and their fans on specific nights or when major professional sporting events are broadcast on TV. Some of the longest established gay bars are unofficial hosts of elaborate local 'Royal Court' drag pageants and drag-related social groups.

Gay bars and nightclubs are sometimes segregated by sex. In some establishments, people who are perceived to be of the &quot;wrong&quot; sex (for example, a man attempting to enter a women's club) may be unwelcome or even barred from entry. This may be more common in specialty bars, such as gay male [[leather fetish]] or [[BDSM]] bars, or bars or clubs which have a strict [[dress code]]. It is also common in bars and clubs where sex on the premises is a primary focus of the establishment. On the other hand, gay bars are usually welcoming of [[transgender]] and cross-dressed people, and [[Drag queen|drag]] shows are a common feature in many gay bars, even men-only spaces. Some gay bars and clubs which have a predominantly male clientele, as well as some [[gay bathhouse]]s and other [[sex club]]s, may offer occasional women-only nights.

A few gay bars attempt to restrict entry to only gay or lesbian people, but in practice this is difficult to enforce. Most famously, [[Melbourne]]'s Peel Hotel was granted an exemption from [[Australia|Australia's]] [[Equal Opportunities Act]] by a state tribunal, on the grounds that the exemption was needed to prevent &quot;sexually-based insults and violence&quot; aimed at the pub's patrons. As a result of the decision, the pub is legally able to advertise as a &quot;gay only&quot; establishment, and [[Bouncer (doorman)|door staff]] can ask people whether they are gay before allowing them inside, and can turn away non-gay people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | agency=Associated Press | title=Australian gay bar can ban straights | url=http://www.advocate.com/news_detail_ektid45504.asp | work=The Advocate | date=30 May 2007 | accessdate=2008-11-26}}http://www.advocate.com/news/2007/05/30/australian-gay-bar-can-ban-straights&lt;/ref&gt;

Already categorized as gay or lesbian, many gay bars in larger cities/urban areas take this sub-categorization a step further by appealing to distinct subcultures within the gay community. Some of these sub-cultures are defined by costume and performance. These bars often forge a like-minded community in dozens of cities with leather gay bars, line-dancing gay bars, and drag revues. Other subcultures cater to men who fit a certain type, one that is often defined by age, body type, personality, and musical preference. There are some bars and clubs that cater more to a [[working class]]/[[blue collar]] crowd and some that cater to a more upscale clientele. There are gay bars that cater to &quot;[[twink (gay slang)|twinks]]&quot; (young, smooth-bodied [[wikt:pretty boy|pretty boys]]) and others that cater to [[bear (gay culture)|bears]] (older, larger, hairier alternatives to the well-manicured and fey [[LGBT stereotypes|gay stereotype]]). There are also gay bars that cater to certain races, such as ones for Asian men &quot;and their admirers&quot;, Latin men, or black men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |title=Night. Life. |url=http://www.gaybarculture.com |work=Gay Bar Culture |year=2008 |accessdate=2008-11-26 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080912160258/http://www.gaybarculture.com/ |archivedate=September 12, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Music==

[[Music]], either live or, more commonly, mixed by a [[Disc jockey]] (DJ), is often a prominent feature of gay bars. Typically, the music in gay bars include [[Pop music|pop]], [[Dance music|dance]], [[contemporary R&amp;B]], [[House music|house]], [[Trance music|trance]], and [[Techno music|techno]]. In larger North American cities and in Australia, one or more gay bars with a country music theme and line dancing are also common, as are bars known for retro 1960s pop and &quot;Motown Sound.&quot;

== List of gay bars ==
&lt;!-- PLEASE: Only list bars that have articles, if the bar has no article you have to create it first then add it. see [[Wikipedia:Write the article first]] Please keep list alphabetical by country. --&gt;

'''Canada'''
* [[Woody's (Toronto)|Woody's]], [[Toronto]]

'''Denmark'''
* [[Pan Club Copenhagen]] (closed 2007)

'''Ireland'''
* [[The George, Dublin]]
* [[Panti|Panti Bar, Dublin]]

'''The Netherlands'''
* [[Café ‘t Mandje]]

'''Thailand'''
* [[Sunee Plaza]], a close collection of gay bars

'''United Kingdom'''
{|
|
* [[Royal Vauxhall Tavern]], [[London]]
* [[G-A-Y]], [[London]] Inc G-A-Y Bar and G-A-Y Late
* [[The Black Cap]], [[London]]
* [[Coleherne pub|The Coleherne]], [[London]] Now closed down
* [[London Astoria]], now closed
|
* [[Heaven (nightclub)|Heaven]], [[London]]
* [[Cruz 101]], [[Manchester]]
* [[Planet Out]], [[Edinburgh]]
* [[The New Penny]], [[Leeds]]
* [[The Joiners Arms, Hackney]], [[London]]
|}

'''United States'''
{|
|
* [[The Abbey (club)|The Abbey]], [[West Hollywood, California]]
* [[Black Cat Bar]], [[San Francisco]] (closed)
* [[Black Cat Tavern]], [[Silverlake, Los Angeles, California]] (closed)
* [[CC Slaughters]], Portland, Oregon
* [[Club Universe]], [[San Francisco]] (closed)
* [[Down the Street]], [[Asbury Park, New Jersey]] (closed)
* [[Embers Avenue]], Portland, Oregon
* [[Hobo's]], Portland, Oregon
* [[Jewel's Catch One]], Los Angeles (closed)
* [[Julius (New York City)|Julius]], [[New York City]]
* [[Neon Boots Dancehall &amp; Saloon]], [[Houston, Texas]]
* [[Paddock Club]], [[Greenville, North Carolina]] (closed)
* [[Phase 1 (bar)|Phase 1]], [[Washington, DC]]
* [[Pulse (nightclub)|Pulse]], [[Orlando, Florida|Orlando, FL]] (destroyed by fire)
* [[Rawhide 2010]], [[New Orleans, LA]]
* [[Red Cap Garage]], Portland, Oregon (closed)
* [[Silverado (gay bar)|Silverado]], Portland, Oregon
* [[South Beach (nightclub)|South Beach]], [[Houston, Texas]]
* [[Stag PDX]], Portland, Oregon
* [[Stonewall Inn]], [[New York City]]
* [[This is It! (Gay Bar)|This is It!]], [[Milwaukee|Milwaukee, WI]]
* [[Three Sisters Tavern]], [[Portland, Oregon]] (closed)
* [[Velvet Nation]] at [[Nation (nightclub)|Nation]], [[Washington, DC]] (closed)
* [[Ziegfeld's]], [[Washington, DC]]
|}

== List of lesbian bars ==

While some gay bars open their doors to all LGBTQ people, other bars cater specifically to lesbians. In recent years many lesbian bars have closed down. In 2015, [[JD Samson]] made a documentary exploring the remaining lesbian bars in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.afterellen.com/people/448465-broadly-goes-last-lesbian-bars |title=Broadly goes to &quot;The Last Lesbian Bars&quot; |last=Bendix |first=Trish |date=17 August 2015 |website=AfterEllen |access-date=22 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''United States'''
* [[Maud's (bar)|Maud's]], San Francisco (closed)
* [[The Lexington Club]], [[San Francisco]] (closed)
* [[Peg's Place (bar)|Peg's Place]], San Francisco (closed)
* [[Phase 1 (bar)|Phase 1]], [[Washington, DC]]
* [[Chances Bar]], [[Houston]] (closed)

'''United Kingdom'''
* [[Candy Bar (London)]] (closed)
* [[Gateways club|Gateways Club]] (London) (closed)

==See also==

* [[Lloyd G. Davies]], Los Angeles City Council member, 1943–51, fought against &quot;undesirable&quot; bars in Hollywood, California
* [[List of public house topics]]

==References==

{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==

* {{cite book | last=Cante | first=Richard C. | title=Gay Men and the Forms of Contemporary US Culture | location=London | publisher=Ashgate Publishing | year=2009 | oclc=173218594}}
* [http://www.glbtqarchive.com/ssh/gay_lesbian_bars_S.pdf Matthew D. Johnson, Claude J. Summers, &quot;Gay and Lesbian Bars&quot;,  GLBTQ Encyclopedia,  2005]

{{Portal bar|LGBT|Liquor|Sexuality}}
{{LGBT|culture=expanded}}
{{authority control}}
{{LGBTcultureworldwide}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gay Bar}}
[[Category:LGBT nightclubs| ]]
[[Category:Types of drinking establishment]]</text>
      <sha1>qutnpyrn2md0skmh6whh0nkccmovap1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
