<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Aye-aye</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>61697</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750238029</id>
      <parentid>750237978</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-18T15:11:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Philroc</username>
        <id>19549021</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 750237978 by [[Special:Contributions/Philroc|Philroc]] ([[User talk:Philroc|talk]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23206">{{about|the lemur species|the nautical phrase|Aye aye, sir}}
{{Speciesbox
| name = Aye-aye
| taxon = Daubentonia madagascariensis
| grandparent_authority = [[John Edward Gray|Gray]], 1863
| parent_authority = [[Étienne Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire|É. Geoffroy]], 1795
| authority = [[Johann Friedrich Gmelin|Gmelin]], 1788
| display_parents = 3
| image = Wild aye aye.jpg
| status = EN
| status_system = IUCN3.1
| status_ref = {{r|IUCN}}
| status2 = CITES_A1
| status2_system = CITES
| status2_ref = &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://checklist.cites.org/#/en/search/scientific_name=Daubentonia | title = Checklist of CITES Species | website = CITES | publisher = UNEP-WCMC | accessdate = 18 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| subdivision_ranks = Species
| subdivision = {{species list
|'''D. madagascariensis'''|
|†[[Giant aye-aye|D. robusta]]}}
| synonyms =
Family:
*Cheiromyidae &lt;small&gt;I. Geoffroy St. Hilaire, 1851&lt;/small&gt;
*Chiromyidae &lt;small&gt;Bonaparte, 1850&lt;/small&gt;
Genus:
*''Aye-aye'' &lt;small&gt;Lacépède, 1799&lt;/small&gt;
*''Cheiromys'' &lt;small&gt;G. Cuvier, 1817&lt;/small&gt;
*''Cheyromys'' &lt;small&gt;É. Geoffroy, 1803&lt;/small&gt;
*''Chiromys'' &lt;small&gt;Illiger, 1811&lt;/small&gt;
*''Myslemur'' &lt;small&gt;Anon. [?de Blainville], 1846&lt;/small&gt;
*''Myspithecus'' &lt;small&gt;de Blainville, 1839&lt;/small&gt;
*''Psilodactylus'' &lt;small&gt;Oken, 1816&lt;/small&gt;
*''Scolecophagus'' &lt;small&gt;É. Geoffroy, 1795&lt;/small&gt;
Species:
*''daubentonii'' &lt;small&gt;Shaw, 1800&lt;/small&gt;
*''laniger'' &lt;small&gt;G. Grandidier, 1930&lt;/small&gt;
*''psilodactylus'' &lt;small&gt;Schreber, 1800&lt;/small&gt;
| range_map = Daubentonia madagascariensis range map.svg
| range_map_caption = Distribution of{{Clear}}''Daubentonia madagascariensis''{{r|IUCN}}
}}
[[File:Aye-Aye Daubentonia madagascariensis in Stockholm.jpg|thumb|right|220px|Skeleton]]

The '''aye-aye''' (''Daubentonia madagascariensis'') is a [[lemur]], a [[Strepsirrhini|strepsirrhine]] [[primate]] native to [[Madagascar]] that combines [[rodent]]-like teeth that perpetually grow&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = |title = Primates Prosimiens|last = Petter|first = J|date = 1977|journal = ORSTOM|doi = |pmid = |access-date = |last2 = Albignac|first2 = R|last3 = Rumpler|first3 = Y}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a special thin middle finger.

It is the world's largest [[Nocturnality|nocturnal]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://animals.nationalgeographic.com/animals/mammals/aye-aye/|title=Aye-Aye Daubentonia madagascariensis|work=National Geographic|accessdate=18 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; primate, and is characterized by its unusual method of finding food; it taps on trees to find [[Larva|grubs]], then gnaws holes in the wood using its forward slanting incisors to create a small hole in which it inserts its narrow middle finger to pull the grubs out. This foraging method is called ''percussive foraging'' which takes up 5-41% of foraging time.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Erickson|first=C J|author2=S. Nowicki |author3=L. Dollar |author4=N. Goehring |title=Percussive Foraging:stimuli for prey location by aye-ayes (Daubentonia madagascariensis)|journal=International Journal of Primatology|year=1998|volume=19|issue=1|page=111|doi=10.1023/A:1020363128240}}&lt;!--|accessdate=6 May 2013--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = |title = Adaptations in the ayeaye: A review|last = Sterling|first = E. J.|date = 2006|journal = Lemurs: Ecology and adaptaions|doi = |pmid = |access-date = |last2 = McCreless|first2 = E. E.|publisher = Gould L, Sauther ML}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The only other animal species known to find food in this way is the [[striped possum]].{{Sfn|Sterling|2003|p=1348}} From an ecological point of view the aye-aye fills the niche of a [[woodpecker]], as it is capable of penetrating wood to extract the invertebrates within.{{r|2007Piper}}{{Sfn|Beck|2009|p=??}}

The aye-aye is the only [[Extant taxon|extant]] member of the [[genus]] ''Daubentonia'' and [[family (biology)|family]] Daubentoniidae.  It is currently classified as [[Endangered species|Endangered]] by the [[IUCN]]; and a second species, ''[[Giant aye-aye|Daubentonia robusta]]'', appears to have become [[extinct]] at some point within the last 1000 years.{{Sfn|Nowak|1999|pp=533–534}}

== Etymology ==
The genus ''Daubentonia'' was named after the French naturalist [[Louis-Jean-Marie Daubenton]] by his student, [[Étienne Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire]], in 1795.  Initially Geoffroy considering using the Greek name, ''Scolecophagus'' (&quot;worm-eater&quot;) in reference to its eating habits, but he decided against it because he was uncertain about the aye-aye's habits and whether other related species might eventually be discovered.{{R|2012Dunkel_et_al}}  In 1863, British zoologist [[John Edward Gray]] coined the family name Daubentoniidae.{{Sfn|Groves|2005}}

The French naturalist, [[Pierre Sonnerat]] was the first to use the vernacular name, &quot;aye-aye&quot;, in 1782 when he described and illustrated the lemur, though it was also called the &quot;long-fingered lemur&quot; by English zoologist [[George Shaw]] in 1800—a name that did not stick.  According to Sonnerat, the name &quot;aye-aye&quot; was a &quot;''cri d'exclamation &amp; d'étonnement''&quot; (cry of exclamation and astonishment).  However, American paleoanthropologist [[Ian Tattersall]] noted in 1982 that the name resembles the [[Malagasy language|Malagasy]] name &quot;hai hai&quot; or &quot;hay hay&quot;, which is used around the island.  According to Dunkel ''et al.'' in 2012, the widespread use of the Malagasy name indicates that the name could not have come from Sonnerat.  Another hypothesis proposed by Simons and Meyers in 2001 is that it derives from &quot;''heh heh''&quot;, which is Malagasy for &quot;I don't know&quot;. If correct, then the name might have originated from Malagasy people saying &quot;''heh heh''&quot; to [[avoidance speech|avoid saying the name]] of a feared, magical animal.{{R|2012Dunkel_et_al}}

==Evolutionary history and taxonomy==
Due to its [[Cladistics|derived]] [[morphology (biology)|morphological]] features, the classification of the aye-aye has been debated since its discovery.  The possession of continually growing [[incisor]]s (front teeth) parallels those of [[rodent]]s, leading early naturalists to mistakenly classify the aye-aye within the mammalian order [[Rodent]]ia{{Sfn|Ankel-Simons|2007|p=257}} and as a squirrel, due to its toes, hair coloring, and tail. However, the aye-aye is also similar to felines in its head shape, eyes, ears and nostrils.&lt;ref name=Science&gt;{{cite journal|title=The Aye-Ayes or Cheiromys of Madagascar|journal=Science|date=3 November 1881|volume=2|issue=75|pages=574–576|doi=10.1126/science.os-2.76.574 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The aye-aye's classification with the order Primates has been just as uncertain.  It has been considered a highly derived member of the family [[Indridae]], a basal branch of the [[strepsirrhine]] suborder, and of indeterminate relation to all living primates.{{Sfn|Yoder|Vilgalys|Ruvolo|1996|pp=??}}  In 1931, Anthony and Coupin classified the aye-aye under infraorder '''Chiromyiformes''', a sister group to the other strepsirrhines. [[Colin Groves]] upheld this classification in 2005 because he was not entirely convinced the aye-aye formed a [[clade]] with the rest of the Malagasy lemurs,{{Sfn|Groves|2005|p=121}} despite molecular tests that had shown Daubentoniidae was basal to all Lemuriformes,{{Sfn|Yoder|Vilgalys|Ruvolo|1996|pp=??}} deriving from the same lemur ancestor that [[Oceanic dispersal|rafted]] to Madagascar during the [[Paleocene]] or [[Eocene]].  In 2008, [[Russell Mittermeier]], Colin Groves, and others ignored addressing higher-level taxonomy by defining lemurs as monophyletic and containing five living families, including Daubentoniidae. {{Sfn|Mittermeier|Ganzhorn|Konstant|Glander|2008|pp=??}}

Further evidence indicating that the aye-aye belongs in the superfamily [[Lemuroidea]] can be inferred from the presence of [[Petrous part of the temporal bone|petrosal]] bullae encasing the [[ossicles]] of the ear. However, interestingly, the bones themselves may have some resemblance to those of rodents.{{Sfn|Ankel-Simons|2007|p=257}} The aye-ayes are also similar to lemurs in their shorter back legs.&lt;ref name=Science/&gt;

==Anatomy and morphology==
Young aye-ayes typically are silver colored on their front and have a stripe down their back. However, as the aye-ayes begin to reach maturity, their bodies will be completely covered in thick fur and are typically not one solid color. On the head and back, the ends of the hair are typically tipped with white while the rest of the body will ordinarily be a yellow and/or brown color.

In length, a full-grown aye-aye is typically about three feet long with a tail as long as its body. Among the aye-aye's signature traits are its fingers. The third finger, which is thinner than the others, is used for tapping and grooming, while the fourth finger, the longest, is used for pulling bugs out of trees.&lt;ref name=Science/&gt; The middle finger is unique in that it possesses a ball-and-socket metacarpophalangeal joint.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = |title = Anatomy of the hand and arm in Daubentonia madagascariensis: a functional and phylogenetic outlook|last = Soligo|first = C.|date = 2005|journal = Folia Primatol|doi = |pmid = |access-date = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The complex geometry of ridges on the inner surface of aye-aye ears helps to sharply focus not only echolocation signals from the tapping of its finger, but also to passively listen for any other sound produced by the prey. These ridges can be regarded as the acoustic equivalent of a [[Fresnel lens]], and may be seen in a large variety of unrelated animals, such as [[lesser galago]], [[bat-eared fox]], [[mouse lemur]], and others.

Females have two nipples located in the region of the groin.

==Behaviour and lifestyle==
[[File:Ayeaye, Daubentonia madagascariensis, Joseph Wolf.jpg|thumb|220px|An aye-aye foraging, c.1863, [[Joseph Wolf]]]]
[[File:Aye-Aye Daubentonia madagascariensis in Copenhagen (Left Hand).jpg|thumb|220px|right|Closeup of the hand showing the elongated digits and the thinner third digit]]
The aye-aye is a nocturnal and arboreal animal meaning that it spends most of its life high in the trees. Although they are known to come down to the ground on occasion, aye-ayes sleep, eat, travel and mate in the trees and are most commonly found close to the canopy where there is plenty of cover from the dense foliage. During the day, aye-ayes sleep in spherical nests in the forks of tree branches that are constructed out of leaves, branches and vines before emerging after dark to begin their hunt for food. Aye-aye are solitary animals that mark their large home range with scent.  The smaller territories of females often overlap those of at least a couple of males. Male aye-ayes tend to share their territories with other males and are even known to share the same nests (although not at the same time), and can seemingly tolerate each other until they hear the call of a female that is looking for a mate.

===Diet and foraging===
The aye-aye commonly eats seeds, fruits, nectar and fungi, but also insect larvae classifying it as an [[omnivore]].{{LoM3 Sfn|p=606}}
Aye-ayes tap on the trunks and branches of trees at a rate of up to eight times per second, and listen to the echo produced to find hollow chambers. Studies have suggested that the acoustic properties associated with the foraging cavity have no effect on excavation behavior.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; Once a chamber is found, they chew a hole into the wood and get grubs out of that hole with their highly adapted narrow and bony middle fingers.&lt;ref name=Haring&gt;{{cite journal|last=Haring|first=David|title=Eep! It's an Aye-Aye.|journal=Wildlife Conservation|date=March 1996|pages=28–35|accessdate=July 24, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The aye-aye begins [[foraging]] between 30 minutes before and three hours after sunset. Up to 80% of the night is spent foraging in the canopy, separated by occasional rest periods. It climbs trees by making successive vertical leaps, much like a squirrel. Horizontal movement is more difficult, but the aye-aye rarely descends to jump to another tree, and can often travel up to {{convert|4|km|mi|abbr=on}} a night.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}}

Though foraging is usually solitary, they occasionally forage in groups. Individual movements within the group are coordinated using both vocalisations and scent signals.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}}

===Social systems===
The aye-aye is classically considered 'solitary' as they have not been observed to groom each other.{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}} However, recent research suggests it is more social than once thought. It usually sticks to foraging in its own personal home range, or territory. The home ranges of males often overlap, and the males can be very social with each other. Female home ranges never overlap, though a male's home range often overlaps that of several females. The male aye-ayes live in large areas up to {{convert|80|acre|m2}}, while females have smaller living spaces that goes up to {{convert|20|acre|m2}}. It is difficult for the males to defend a singular female because of the large home range. They are seen exhibiting polygyny because of this.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = |title = Patterns of Range Use and Social Organization in Aye-ayes (Daubentonia madagascariensis) on Nosy Mangabe|last = Sterling|first = Eleanor|date = 1993|journal = Lemur Social Systems and Their Ecological Basis|doi = |pmid = |access-date = |editor-last = Kappeler|publication-place = Plenum Press, New York}}&lt;/ref&gt; Regular scent marking with their cheeks and neck is how aye-ayes let others know of their presence and repel intruders from their territory.{{r|Durrell}}

Like many other prosimians, the female aye-aye is dominant to the male. They are not typically monogamous, and will often challenge each other for mates. Male aye-ayes are very assertive in this way, and sometimes even pull other males away from a female during mating. Males are normally locked to females during mating in sessions that may last up to an hour. Outside of mating, males and females interact only occasionally, usually while foraging.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}} The aye-aye is thought to be the only primate which uses [[Animal echolocation|echolocation]] to find its prey.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Aye-Aye|url=http://animals.nationalgeographic.com/animals/mammals/aye-aye/?source=A-to-Z|publisher=National Geographic Society|accessdate=7 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Distribution and habitat==
[[File:Aye-aye at night in the wild in Madagascar.jpg|thumb|right|220px|Aye-ayes are nocturnal]]
The aye-aye lives primarily on the east coast of Madagascar. Its natural habitat is [[rainforest]] or [[deciduous]] forest, but many live in cultivated areas due to deforestation. Rainforest aye-ayes, the most common, dwell in canopy areas, and are usually sighted above 700 meters altitude. They sleep during the day in nests built in the forks of trees.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}}

==Conservation==
The aye-aye was thought to be extinct in 1933, but was rediscovered in 1957. Nine individuals were transported to [[Nosy Mangabe]], an island near [[Maroantsetra]] off eastern Madagascar, in 1966.{{LoM3 Sfn|pp=605–606}} Recent research shows the aye-aye is more widespread than was previously thought, but its conservation status was changed to [[Endangered species|Endangered]] in 2014.&lt;ref name=IUCN/&gt; This is for four main reasons: the aye-aye is considered evil, the forests of Madagascar are being destroyed, and the farmers will kill aye-ayes to protect their crops and for poaching. However, there is no direct evidence to suggest aye-ayes pose any legitimate threat to crops and therefore are killed based on superstition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Hill|first=Catherine M.|title=Primate Conservation and Local Communities-Ethical Issues and Debates|journal=American Anthropologist|date=December 2002|volume=104|issue=4|pages=1184–1194|doi=10.1525/aa.2002.104.4.1184}}&lt;!--|accessdate=24 July 2012--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

As many as 50&amp;nbsp;aye-ayes can be found in zoological facilities worldwide.{{LoM3 Sfn|p=609}}

===Folk belief===
[[Image:Daubentonia madagascariensis - dead 01.jpg|upright|thumb|Aye-ayes are commonly thought to be bad omens by some of the Malagasy people, although other legends consider them a good omen. When spotted, they are killed on sight and hung up so that the evil spirit will be carried away by travelers.]]

Researchers in Madagascar report remarkable fearlessness in the aye-aye; some accounts tell of individual animals strolling nonchalantly in village streets or even walking right up to naturalists in the rainforest and sniffing their shoes.{{r|2010Knowles}}

However, the aye-aye is often viewed as a harbinger of evil and killed on sight. Others believe, if one points its narrowest finger at someone, they are marked for death. Some say the appearance of an aye-aye in a village predicts the death of a villager, and the only way to prevent this is to kill it. The [[Sakalava]] people go so far as to claim aye-ayes sneak into houses through the thatched roofs and murder the sleeping occupants by using their middle finger to puncture the victim's [[aorta]].{{r|2007Piper}}

===Captive breeding===
The conservation of this species has been aided by captive breeding, primarily at the [[Duke Lemur Center]] in [[Durham, North Carolina]]. This center has been influential in keeping, researching and breeding aye-ayes and other lemurs. They have sent multiple teams to capture lemurs in Madagascar and have since created captive breeding groups for their lemurs. Specifically, they were responsible for the first aye-aye born into captivity and studied how he and the other aye-aye infants born at the center develop through infancy. They have also revolutionized the understanding of the aye-aye diet.&lt;ref name=Haring/&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em|refs=

&lt;ref name=IUCN&gt;{{IUCN | id = 6302 | taxon = Daubentonia madagascariensis | assessor = Andriaholinirina, N. | display-assessors = etal | assessment_year = 2012 | version = 2014.1 | accessdate = 12 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;2012Dunkel_et_al&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Dunkel | first1 = A.R. | last2 = Zijlstra | first2 = J.S. | last3 = Groves | first3 = C.P. | title = Giant rabbits, marmosets, and British comedies: etymology of lemur names, part 1 | url = http://www.aeecl.org/lemurnews/lemurnews2011_16.pdf | format = PDF | journal = Lemur News | volume = 16 | year = 2011–2012 | issn = 1608-1439 | pages = 64–70}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;2007Piper&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Piper | year = 2007 | title = Extraordinary Animals: An Encyclopedia of Curious and Unusual Animals | publisher = Greenwood Press | first = Ross}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Durrell&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.durrell.org/Animals/Mammals/Ayeaye/ | title = Aye-Aye | work = [[Durrell Wildlife Conservation Trust]] | date = 2006-10-26 | accessdate = 2011-12-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;2010Knowles&quot;&gt;[http://www.aolnews.com/science/article/superstitious-villagers-are-killing-off-harmless-primate-called-aye-aye/19416515?icid=main|main|dl1|link3|http%3A%2F%2Fwww.aolnews.com%2Fscience%2Farticle%2Fsuperstitious-villagers-are-killing-off-harmless-primate-called-aye-aye%2F19416515 Harmless Creature Killed Because of Superstition], David Knowles, March 27, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

==Literature cited==
{{Refbegin}}

* &lt;!-- {{Sfn|Ankel-Simons|2007}} --&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Ankel-Simons | first1 = F. | title= Primate Anatomy | edition = 3rd | publisher = Academic Press | year = 2007 |isbn= 0-12-372576-3 | ref = harv}}
* &lt;!-- {{Sfn|Beck|2009}} --&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Beck | first1 = R. M. D. | doi = 10.1111/j.1095-8312.2009.01171.x | title = Was the Oligo-Miocene Australian metatherian Yalkaparidon a ‘mammalian woodpecker’? | journal = Biological Journal of the Linnean Society | volume = 97 | issue = 1 | pages = 1–17 | year = 2009 | pmid =  | pmc = | ref = harv }}
* &lt;!-- {{Sfn|Groves|2005}} --&gt;{{MSW3 Primates|id=12100099}}
* &lt;!-- {{LoM3 Sfn}} --&gt;{{LoM3}}
* &lt;!-- {{Sfn|Mittermeier|Ganzhorn|Konstant|Glander|2008}} --&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Mittermeier | first1 = R. A. | last2 = Ganzhorn | first2 = J. U. | last3 = Konstant | first3 = W. R. | last4 = Glander | first4 = K. | last5 = Tattersall | first5 = I. | last6 = Groves | first6 = C. P. | last7 = Rylands | first7 = A. B. | last8 = Hapke | first8 = A. | last9 = Ratsimbazafy | first9 = J. | authorlink1 = Russell Mittermeier | last10 = Mayor| authorlink5 = Ian Tattersall | first10 = M. I.| authorlink6 = Colin Groves | last11 = Louis | first11 = E. E. | last12 = Rumpler | first12 = Y. | last13 = Schwitzer | first13 = C. | last14 = Rasoloarison | first14 = R. M.| title = Lemur Diversity in Madagascar | journal = International Journal of Primatology | volume = 29 | issue = 6| pages = 1607–1656 | year = 2008 | url = http://www.aeecl.org/documents/28.pdf| format = PDF| doi = 10.1007/s10764-008-9317-y| ref = harv}}
* &lt;!-- {{Sfn|Nowak|1999}} --&gt;{{cite book | last = Nowak | first = R.M. | year = 1999 | publisher = Johns Hopkins University Press | title = Walker's Primates of the World | edition = 6th | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=unODoWa7CM4C&amp;printsec=frontcover |location = Baltimore, Maryland | isbn = 0-8018-6251-5 | ref = harv}}
* &lt;!-- {{Sfn|Sterling|2003}} --&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Sterling | first1 = E. | contribution = ''Daubentonia madagascariensis'', Aye-aye, ''Aye-aye'' | editor1-last = Goodman | editor1-first = S.M. | editor2-last = Benstead | editor2-first = J.P. | title = The Natural History of Madagascar | publisher = University of Chicago Press | isbn = 0-226-30306-3 | pages = 1348–1351 | year = 2003 | ref = harv}}
* &lt;!-- {{Sfn|Yoder|Vilgalys|Ruvolo|1996}} --&gt;{{Cite journal 
| last1 = Yoder | first1 = A. D. 
| last2 = Vilgalys | first2 = R. 
| last3 = Ruvolo | first3 = M. 
| title = Molecular evolutionary dynamics of cytochrome ''b'' in strepsirrhine primates: The phylogenetic significance of third-position transversions 
| journal = Molecular Biology and Evolution 
| volume = 13 
| issue = 10 
| pages = 1339–1350 
| year = 1996
| url = http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/content/13/10/1339.full.pdf
| format = PDF
| issn = &lt;!-- 0737-4038 --&gt;
| pmid = 8952078
| ref = harv
 | doi=10.1093/oxfordjournals.molbev.a025580
}}

== External links ==
{{Commons+cat|Daubentonia madagascariensis|Daubentonia madagascariensis}}
{{Wikispecies|Daubentonia madagascariensis}}
* [http://members.tripod.com/uakari/ayeaye.html Primate Behavior: Aye-Aye]
* ARKive - [http://www.arkive.org/species/GES/mammals/Daubentonia_madagascariensis/ images and movies of the aye-aye ''(Daubentonia madagascariensis)'']
* [http://pin.primate.wisc.edu/factsheets/entry/aye-aye Primate Info Net ''Daubentonia madagascariensis'' Factsheet]
* [http://ecos.fws.gov/species_profile/servlet/gov.doi.species_profile.servlets.SpeciesProfile?spcode=A00P U.S. Fish &amp; Wildlife Service Species Profile]
{{Subject bar | book = Lemurs | portal1 = Animals | portal2 = Mammals | portal3 = Primates | portal4 = Madagascar | commons = y | commons-search = Category:Daubentonia madagascariensis | species = y | species-search = Daubentonia madagascariensis | wikt = y}}

{{Primates}}

[[Category:Animals described in 1788]]
[[Category:EDGE species]]
[[Category:Lemurs]]
[[Category:Mammals of Madagascar]]</text>
      <sha1>6spi2wccy8x1370oo69iwahee9go4xi</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
