<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.28.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2600" case="first-letter">Topic</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Pliska</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>750560</id>
    <revision>
      <id>731636210</id>
      <parentid>725540865</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-07-26T16:01:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender235</username>
        <id>88026</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Secondary sources */clean up; http-&gt;https (see [[WP:VPR/Archive 127#RfC: Should we convert existing Google and Internet Archive links to HTTPS?|this RfC]]) using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14590">{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2013}}
{{Infobox military conflict|
conflict=Battle of Pliska|
image=[[File:The Great Basilica Klearchos 2.jpg|300px]]|
caption=Ruins of Pliska|
|partof=the [[Byzantine–Bulgarian Wars]]
|date=26 July 811|
place=[[Pliska]] and Vărbitsa Pass|
result=Decisive Bulgarian victory|
combatant1=[[First Bulgarian Empire|Bulgarian Empire]]|
combatant2=[[Byzantine Empire]]|
commander1=[[Krum]]|
commander2=[[Nikephoros I]]{{KIA}}|
strength1=62,000&lt;ref&gt;Scriptor Incertus, p.148-149&lt;/ref&gt; (uncertain)|
strength2=60,000–80,000 (estimated)&lt;ref name=&quot;Ivanov&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Ivanov |first=Ivo |title=The Address of a Victory |journal=Bulgarian Soldier |volume=6 |pages=Online Edition (in Bulgarian) |url=http://bgsoldier.eamci.bg/Scripts/isapiVWB.dll/theme?THEMEID=87232 |date=June 2007 |nopp=true }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rakovski&quot;&gt;[http://rdsc.md.government.bg/BG/About/VoennaIstoria/1_08Krum.php Military history of Bulgaria]&lt;/ref&gt;
|
casualties1=Unknown|
casualties2=almost the whole army, including the emperor|
}}
{{Byzantine-Bulgarian Wars}}
The '''Battle of Pliska''' or '''Battle of Vărbitsa Pass''' was a series of battles between troops, gathered from all parts of the [[Byzantine Empire]], led by the Emperor [[Nicephorus I|Nicephorus I Genik]], and [[Bulgaria]], governed by Khan [[Krum]]. The Byzantines plundered and burned the Bulgar capital [[Pliska]] which gave time for the Bulgarians to block passes in the [[Balkan Mountains]] that served as exits out of Bulgaria. The final battle took place on 26 July 811, in some of the passes in the eastern part of the Balkans, most probably the [[Varbitsa Pass|Vărbitsa Pass]]. There, the Bulgarians used the tactics of ambush and surprise night attacks to effectively trap and immobilize the Byzantine forces, thus annihilating almost the whole army, including the Emperor. After the battle, Krum encased Nicephorus's skull in silver, and used it as a cup for wine-drinking. This is one of the best documented instances of the custom of the [[skull cup]].

The Battle of Pliska was one of the worst defeats in Byzantine history. It deterred Byzantine rulers from sending their troops north of the Balkans for more than 150 years afterwards, which increased the influence and spread of the Bulgarians to the west and south of the Balkan Peninsula, resulting in a great territorial enlargement of the [[First Bulgarian Empire]].

== Initial campaigns ==
When [[Nicephorus I]] became [[Byzantine emperor|emperor]] in 802, he planned to reincorporate Bulgar-held territory back into the empire. In 807 he launched a campaign but only reached [[Odrin]] and achieved nothing because of a conspiracy in his capital.&lt;ref&gt;Theophanes Confessor. ''Chronographia'', p.482-484&lt;/ref&gt; That attempted attack, however, gave reason for the Bulgar Khan [[Krum]] to undertake military operations against the Byzantine Empire. The main objective was an extension to the south and south-west. In the next year a Bulgar army penetrated the [[Struma (river)|Struma]] Valley and defeated the Byzantines. The Bulgar troops captured 1,100 ''litres'' (roughly 332 to 348 kilograms)&lt;ref&gt;http://www.greece.org/Byzantium/konstantinato.htm&lt;/ref&gt; of gold and killed many enemy soldiers including all ''strategoi'' and most of the commanders.&lt;ref&gt;Theophanes Confessor. ''Chronographia'', p.484-486&lt;/ref&gt; In 809 the Khan personally besieged the strong fortress of [[Serdica]] and [[siege of Serdica (809)|seized the city]], killing the whole garrison of 6,000.&lt;ref&gt;Theophanes Confessor. Chronographia, p.485&lt;/ref&gt;

== Preparation for an invasion ==
In 811, the Byzantine Emperor organised a large campaign to conquer Bulgaria once and for all. He gathered an enormous army from the Anatolian and European ''[[Theme (Byzantine district)|thema]]ta'', and the imperial bodyguard (the ''[[tagma (military)|tagmata]]''); they were joined by a number of irregular troops who expected a swift victory and plunder. The conquest was supposed to be easy, and most of the high-ranking officials and aristocrats accompanied him, including his son [[Stauracius]] and his brother-in-law [[Michael I Rangabe]].&lt;ref&gt;Anonymus Vaticanus, p.148&lt;/ref&gt; The whole army consisted of around 80,000 soldiers.

== Sack of Pliska ==
The army gathered in May, and by 10 July had set up camp at the fortress of Marcelae (present-day [[Karnobat]]) near the Bulgarian frontier. Nicephorus intended to confuse them and over the next ten days launched several supposed attacks, which were immediately called back. Krum assessed the situation and estimated that he could not repulse the enemy and offered peace, which Nicephorus haughtily rejected. Theophanes wrote that the Emperor, &quot;was deterred from his own ill thoughts and the suggestions of his advisors who were thinking like him&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Theophanes Confessor. Chronographia, p.486&lt;/ref&gt; Some of his military chiefs considered the invasion of Bulgaria to be imprudent and too risky, but Nicephorus was convinced of his ultimate success.

In June he invaded the Bulgarian lands and marched through the Balkan passes towards the capital of [[Pliska]]. On 20 July Nicephorus divided the army into three columns, each marching by a different route towards Pliska. He met little resistance&lt;ref&gt;Chronique de Michel le Syrien, p.17&lt;/ref&gt; and after three days he reached the capital where the Byzantines met an army of 12,000 elite soldiers who guarded the stronghold. The Bulgarians were defeated and most of them perished. Another hastily assembled army of 50,000 soldiers had a similar fate.&lt;ref&gt;Anonymus Vaticanus, p.148-149&lt;/ref&gt; On 23 July the Byzantines quickly captured the defenseless capital. The city was sacked and the countryside destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;Ioannes Zonaras. Epistome historiatus, p.372-373&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Georgius Monachus. Chroniconq, p.774&lt;/ref&gt; Khan Krum attempted once more to negotiate for peace. According to the historian Theophanes, Krum’s proclamation stated, &quot;Here you are, you have won. So take what you please and go with peace.&quot; Nicephorus, overconfident from his success, ignored him. He believed that Bulgaria was thoroughly conquered.

[[Michael the Syrian]], patriarch of the Syrian Jacobites in the twelfth century, described in his Chronicle the brutalities and atrocities of Nicephorus's troops: &quot;Nicephorus, emperor of the Romans, walked in Bulgarians land: he was victorious and killed a great number of them. He reached their capital, took it over and devastated it. His savagery went to such a point that he ordered to bring their small children, got them tied down on earth and made thresh grain stones to smash them.&quot; The Byzantine soldiers looted and plundered; burnt down the unharvested fields, cut the tendons of the oxen, slaughtered sheep and pigs.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Anonymus Vaticanus, p.150&lt;/ref&gt; The Emperor took over Krum's treasury, locked it and did not allow his troops to reach it.&lt;ref&gt;Anastasius Bibliothecarius. Chronographia tripertita, p.329&lt;/ref&gt;

== Battle ==
While Nicephorus and his army were busy plundering the Bulgarian capital, Krum mobilized his people (including women and [[Pannonian Avars|Avar]] mercenaries&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Geoffrey |last=Regan |title=Military Blunders |page=74}}&lt;/ref&gt;) to set traps and ambushes in the mountain passes.&lt;ref&gt;Theophanes Confessor. ''Chronographia'', p.430&lt;/ref&gt; Initially Nicephorus intended to march through [[Moesia]] and reach Serdica before returning to Constantinople but the news of these preparations for a battle changed his decision and he chose the shortest way to his capital.&lt;ref&gt;Anonymus Vaticanus, p.152&lt;/ref&gt; The overconfident Emperor neglected to scout ahead. On 25 July his army entered the Varbica Pass but his cavalry told him the road was barred with thick wooden walls and Krum's detachments watched from the heights around.&lt;ref&gt;Theophanes Confessor.'' Chronographia'', p.490-491&lt;/ref&gt; The Emperor became panicked by the situation and repeatedly stated to his companions &quot;Even if we have had wings we could not have escaped from peril.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Theophanes Confessor p.489-492&quot;&gt;Theophanes Confessor. ''Chronographia'', pp. 489–492&lt;/ref&gt; Before they could retreat, the Bulgars blocked the valley entrance too.

Nicephorus, unable to face attacking one of the palisades, simply set up camp, despite his generals' misgivings. By the third night Byzantine morale was shattered, while Bulgar troops banged their shields and taunted them.

On that night the Bulgarians gathered their troops and tightened the belt around the trapped enemy. At dawn they rushed down and started to kill the panicked and totally confused Byzantines. The ''tagmata'' were the first to be attacked. The Byzantines fruitlessly resisted for a short time and perished. Upon seeing their comrades' fate, the next units immediately ran away.

On their way south the Byzantine forces hit a muddy river which was difficult to cross. As they could not find a ford quickly enough, many Byzantines fell into the river. The first stalled in the mud with their horses and were trampled by those who came next. The river was filled with so many dead that the chasing Bulgarians easily passed over them and continued the pursuit. Those who passed through the river reached the wooden wall which was high and thick. The Byzantines left their horses and began climbing the wall with hands and legs and hung over the other side. The Bulgarians had dug a deep moat from the inner side and when the Byzantine soldiers were getting across the ramparts, they fell from the high wall, breaking their limbs. Some of them died instantly, others hobbled some time before falling to the ground and dying from thirst and hunger. The Byzantine troops burned the wall at several places but as they were rushing to get across it, they too fell into the moat along with the burning parts of the palisade. Almost everyone perished; some were killed by the sword, others drowned in the river or were mortally injured after falling from the wall and some of them died in the fire. Among the nobles killed were the [[patrikios|patricians]] Theodosios Salibaras and [[Sisinnios Triphyllios]]; the ''[[strategos]]'' of the [[Anatolics]] Romanos and the ''strategos'' of [[Thrace (theme)|Thrace]]; as well as the commanders of the [[Excubitors]] and [[Vigla (tagma)|Vigla]] ''tagmata''.

Reportedly, only a few survived the defeat. The most notable person to be killed, however, was Emperor Nicephorus, who according to historians died on a dunghill on the day of the battle.&lt;ref&gt;Anonymus Vaticanus, p.153&lt;/ref&gt; Nicephorus's son, Stauracius, was carried to safety by the Imperial bodyguard after receiving a paralyzing wound to his neck.&lt;ref name=&quot;Theophanes Confessor p.489-492&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ioannes Zonaras. Epistome historiatus, p.373&lt;/ref&gt; Six months later, his wounds finally killed him. According to tradition, Krum had the Emperor's head on a spike, then lined his skull with silver and used it as a drinking cup.

== Footnotes ==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== Sources ==
{{Wikisource}}

=== Primary sources ===
* [[Theophanes the Confessor]], ''Chronographia'', Ed. Carl de Boor, vol. I, 1883, vol. II, 1885, Leipzig. &lt;!-- {{ws | [[s:Chronographia/Chapter 61|Chronographia/Chapter 61]] in ''Chronographia'' by Theophanes Confessor}} DEAD LINK--&gt;
* Scriptor Incertus. Anonymous Vatican Narration (Narratio anonyma e codice Vaticano), In: Codice Vaticano graeca 2014 (XII s.) ff. 119–122; Ivan Duychev (1936) New Biographic Data on the Bulgarian Expedition of Nicephorus I in 811, Proc. Bulg. Acad. Sci. 54:147–188 (in Bulgarian); H. Grégoire (1936) Un nouveau fragment du &quot;Scriptor incertus de Leone Armenio&quot;, Byzantion, 11:417–427; Beshevliev, V (1936) The New Source About the Defeat of Nicephorus I in Bulgaria in 811, Sofia University Annual Reviews, 33:2 (In Bulgarian).{{ws | [[s:Scriptor Incertus|Scriptor Incertus]] in ''Scriptor Incertus''}}
* Mannases Chronicle, 1335–1340. Apostolic Library. The Vatican.
* [[Michael the Syrian]], ''[http://www.worldcat.org/wcpa/ow/4321714 Chronique de Michel le Syrien, Patriarche Jacobite d'Antioche (1166–1199)]'', published by Jean Baptiste Chabot (in French). 1st Ed. Paris : Ernest Leroux, 1899–1910, OCLC 39485852; 2nd Ed. Bruxelles: Culture et Civilisation, 1963, OCLC 4321714
* B. Flusin (trans.), J.-C. Cheynet (ed.), ''Jean Skylitzès: Empereurs de Constantinople'', Ed. Lethielleux, 2004, ISBN 2-283-60459-1.
* [[Joannes Zonaras]].  Epitome historiarum, ed. L. Dindorfii, 6 vol., Lipsiae (BT), 1858—75. {{Ws | [[s:Epitomae Historiarum/Chapter 24|Epitomae Historiarum/Chapter 24]] in ''Epitomae Historiarum'' by Ioannis Zonarae}}

=== Secondary sources ===
* {{Cite book |last=Zlatarski |first=Vasil N. |authorlink=Vasil Zlatarski |title=Medieval History of the Bulgarian State, Vol I: History of the First Bulgarian Empire, Part I: Age of Hun-Bulgar Domination (679–852) |publisher=Science and Arts Publishers, 2nd Edition (Petar Petrov, Ed.), Zahari Stoyanov Publishers, 4th Edition, 2006 |year=1918 |location=Sofia |language=Bulgarian |url=http://www.kroraina.com/knigi/vz1a/index.html |isbn=954-739-928-4}}
* {{Cite book |last=Runciman |first=Steven |authorlink=Steven Runciman |title=A History of the First Bulgarian Empire |publisher=G. Bell &amp; Sons, London |year=1930 |url=http://www.questia.com/library/book/a-history-of-the-first-bulgarian-empire-by-steven-runciman.jsp }}
* {{Cite book |last=Fine, Jr. |first=John V.A. |year=1991 |title=The Early Medieval Balkans |url=http://worldcat.org/oclc/59968940&amp;referer=one_hit |publisher=[[University of Michigan]] Press |location=[[Ann Arbor, Michigan|Ann Arbor]] |isbn=978-0-472-08149-3 }}
* {{Cite book |last=Bury |first=J.-B. |authorlink=J. B. Bury |title=A History of the Eastern Roman Empire from the fall of Irene to the accession of Basil I (802—867) |publisher=Macmillan &amp; Co., Ltd., London |year=1912 |url=https://archive.org/details/historyofeastern00buryiala |isbn=1176683276}}
* {{Cite book |last=Jireček |first=K. J. |authorlink=Konstantin Josef Jireček |title=Geschichte der Bulgaren |publisher=Nachdr. d. Ausg. Prag 1876, Hildesheim, New York : Olms 1977 |year=1876 |language=German |url=https://books.google.com/?id=VBhThVLpc4MC&amp;pg=PA88&amp;dq=isbn=3487064081 |isbn=3-487-06408-1}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Pliska 811}}
[[Category:811 in Europe]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 811]]
[[Category:Balkan mountains]]
[[Category:9th century in Bulgaria]]
[[Category:811 in the Byzantine Empire]]
[[Category:Battles involving the First Bulgarian Empire]]
[[Category:Battles of the Byzantine–Bulgarian Wars]]
[[Category:Pliska]]
[[Category:Night battles]]</text>
      <sha1>dhdon65l0ighi37mzgel7kmgp3ugoau</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
