<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Commission to Inquire into Child Abuse</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6699231</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748963882</id>
      <parentid>747959846</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-11T13:30:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>178.167.254.168</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Changed the name of Justice Sean Ryan to Mr Justice Sean Ryan. 'Justice' is not a title in the Irish legal system and is used in error frequently.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="52919">{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2011}}
The '''Commission to Inquire into Child Abuse''' (CICA) is one of a range of measures introduced by the [[Government of Ireland|Irish Government]] to investigate the extent and effects of [[Child abuse|abuse on children]] from 1936 onwards. It is commonly known in Ireland as the '''Ryan Commission''' (previously &quot;the [[Mary Laffoy|Laffoy]] Commission&quot;), after its chair, [[Seán Ryan (Irish judge)| Mr Justice Seán Ryan]]. Judge Laffoy resigned on 2 September 2003, following a departmental review on costs and resources. She felt that: &quot;...the cumulative effect of those factors effectively negated the guarantee of independence conferred on the Commission and militated against it being able to perform its statutory functions.&quot;  The Commission's work started in 1999 and it published its public report, commonly referred to as the '''Ryan report''', on 20 May 2009.

The Commission's remit was to investigate all forms of child abuse in Irish institutions for children; the majority of allegations it investigated related to the system of sixty residential &quot;Reformatory and Industrial Schools&quot; operated by [[Catholic Church]] orders, funded and supervised by the Irish [[Department of Education and Skills (Ireland)|Department of Education]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Commission Report_2009 1.1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.childabusecommission.com/rpt/01-01.php |publisher=The Commission to Inquire into Child Abuse  |title=Commission Report Vol 1 Ch. 1|accessdate=2009-07-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Commission's report said testimony had demonstrated beyond a doubt that the entire system treated children more like prison inmates and slaves than people with legal rights and human potential, that some religious officials encouraged ritual beatings and consistently shielded their orders amid a &quot;culture of self-serving secrecy&quot;, and that government inspectors failed to stop the abuses.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC_8059826&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/8059826.stm |publisher=[[BBC News]] |title=Irish church knew abuse 'endemic' |date=20 May 2009 |accessdate=2009-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Among the more extreme allegations of abuse were beatings and rapes, subjection to naked beatings in public, being forced into oral sex, and subjection to beatings after failed rape attempts by brothers.&lt;ref name=&quot;The abused - in their own words&quot;/&gt; The abuse has been described by some as Ireland's [[Holocaust]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ireland contemplates its 'holocaust of abuse', and decades of denial&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://network.nationalpost.com/np/blogs/fullcomment/archive/2009/05/21/ireland-contemplates-its-holocaust-of-abuse-and-decades-of-denial.aspx|title=Ireland contemplates its 'holocaust of abuse', and decades of denial|date=21 May 2009|accessdate=2009-05-23|publisher=''[[National Post]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Child abuse scandal was Ireland’s nightmare from hell&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.belfasttelegraph.co.uk/opinion/letters/child-abuse-scandal-was-irelandrsquos-nightmare-from-hell-14312313.html|title=Child abuse scandal was Ireland’s nightmare from hell|date=23 May 2009|accessdate=2009-05-23|publisher=''[[The Belfast Telegraph]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt; The abuse was said to be &quot;[[wiktionary:Endemic|endemic]]&quot; in the institutions that dealt with boys.&lt;ref name=&quot;This week they said&quot;/&gt; The UK based ''[[The Guardian|Guardian]]'' newspaper, described the abuse as &quot;the stuff of nightmares&quot;, citing the adjectives used in the report as being particularly chilling: &quot;systemic, pervasive, chronic, excessive, arbitrary, endemic&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;An abuse too far by the Catholic church&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/belief/2009/may/21/catholic-abuse-ireland-ryan|title=An abuse too far by the Catholic church|date=21 May 2009|accessdate=2009-05-23|publisher=''[[The Guardian]]'' | location=London | first=Madeleine | last=Bunting}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Report's conclusions section (Chapter 6) supports the overall tenor of the accusations without exception.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.childabusecommission.com/rpt/04-06.php Ryan Report, Chapter 6; Conclusions section]&lt;/ref&gt; But, the Commission's recommendations were restricted in scope by two rules imposed by the Irish government, and therefore do not include calls for the prosecution or sanction of any of the parties involved.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.childabusecommission.com/rpt/04-07.php Ryan Report Chapter 7; Recommendations section]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
Chapter 2 of the Report outlines the history of institutional assistance for children in Ireland.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.childabusecommission.com/rpt/01-02.php Ryan Report Chapter 2; History]&lt;/ref&gt;
UK Acts of Parliament had provided for:
* Reformatory schools for younger criminals from 1858, and
* Industrial schools for destitute and/or orphaned children from 1868,

where they could learn life skills, and be fed and educated. This was considered an improvement on the [[Workhouse]] system of poor relief. The harsh system was improved over decades, particularly by the [[Children Act 1908]] that was enacted by the [[Liberal Government 1905–1915|Liberal government]]. Though the 2009 Report deals with each type of school separately, they and similar schools are referred to generally as &quot;residential institutions&quot;.

Where the children were from Catholic families, the [[Roman Catholicism in Ireland|Roman Catholic Church in Ireland]] insisted on supervising their care and upbringing by running most of these institutions in Ireland. A handful of Irish Catholic authors such as [[Michael McCarthy (Irish lawyer)|Michael McCarthy]]&lt;ref&gt;See ''Rome in Ireland'' London: Hodder &amp; Stoughton 1904&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Frank Hugh O'Donnell]]&lt;ref&gt;See O'Donnell's ''Paraguay on Shannon'' Hodges &amp; Figgis, Dublin, 1908&lt;/ref&gt; criticised the Church's un-audited state funding, and the state's inadequate supervision in 1900-1910. They were generally ignored by the growing [[Irish nationalism|Nationalist]] movement that had firm support from the Church, and also by the British administration based in [[Dublin Castle]].

==Continuance by Irish Free State==
After the establishment of the [[Irish Free State]] in 1922, little was done to update the 1908 Act or to ensure that its rules were observed, particularly those on corporal punishment. The purpose of the Act was to humanise reformatory and industrial schools and orphanages, and to reduce physical punishment. The 1908 Act regulations remained in force in Ireland almost unchanged until the 1970s, while elsewhere in Europe more progressive regimes developed, mainly after 1945. In contrast, the 1941 Children's Act, drafted while [[Éamon de Valera]] was briefly Minister of the Department of Education, reduced the minimum age of inmates to below 6 years, allowing small children to be detained because of their parents' poverty.

From the 1850s on day-to-day management had passed to several Orders affiliated to the Irish [[Roman Catholicism in Ireland|Catholic Church]], as it insisted on educating its younger members. Oversight was the duty of the British administration in Ireland, and then of the Irish Department of Education from 1922 on. 5 [[Anglican|Protestant]] schools had also existed, with the last one closing in 1917. Maintenance costs were paid by the department on a capitation (head-counting) basis, but the internal accounts of each school were never published. Over decades the Orders would typically answer any official complaint by pointing to the low capitation amount.

A major review of the system by [[Thomas Derrig]] in 1933-36 left it largely unchanged, as did the 1941 Children's Act. It has been suggested that Derrig refused to reform the system in line with the  British reforms of 1923 and 1933 because of his strongly anti-British stance during the Irish independence process in 1916-23.&lt;ref&gt;[[Bruce Arnold (author)|Arnold, B.]] ''The Irish Gulag'' Gill &amp; Macmillan, Dublin 2009. ISBN 978-0-7171-4614-7 at page 41.&lt;/ref&gt; The critical Cussen Report (1936) that followed, and a report in 1946-48 by the [[Irish-American]] priest [[Father Flanagan]], were shelved. [[John Charles McQuaid|Archbishop McQuaid]] of Dublin sought a private report on Artane from Father Moore in 1962, but this was also shelved.

Other bodies such as the [[Irish Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children]] (ISPCC; before 1956 the [[National Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children|NSPCC]]) were also involved in sending needy children to the institutions, for want of alternatives. Some 60% of their cases were referred by the parents. In the 1940s the Society had pointed out that higher social welfare payments to poor families would be cheaper than paying the capitation amounts to industrial schools.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.childabusecommission.ie/about/documents/public_transcript_day228_gilligan_june202006.pdf Gilligan ISPCC evidence 2006; answer to Q.31.]&lt;/ref&gt;

The numbers of child inmates peaked in the early to mid-1940s. Numbers declined after the introduction of &quot;children's allowance&quot; payments in the 1940s. The Adoption Act 1952 and increased wealth and other social welfare measures reduced the number of needy children in the 1950s. Family shame often sent the mothers of illegitimate children to similarly-run [[Magdalen Asylums]].

==Reform starts in the 1960s==
The [[OECD]] reported on Irish schools and levels of education in 1962-68, as an essential part of the process of Ireland's [[European Economic Community#Enlargement and elections|1973 accession]] into the [[European Economic Community|EEC]], providing the vital external stimulus for reform.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arnold&quot;&gt;Arnold B., op.cit., chapter 5.&lt;/ref&gt; Finally the 1970 Kennedy Report, prepared in 1967-70, though flawed in parts, led to the abolition of the schools over the next decade, starting with [[Artane Industrial school|Artane]] in 1969.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arnold&quot;/&gt; In the interim, tens of thousands of children had been inmates, some from infancy. Despite frequent complaints and enquiries that called for reforms, the official line until the 1990s was that nobody in government, the church or the civil service really knew what was taking place. Notably, [[Micheal Martin]] stated on 13 May 1999 that: ''The concept of the child as a separate individual with rights came late to this country.''&lt;ref&gt;Statement of 13 May 1999; see Arnold, B. op. cit., page 16.&lt;/ref&gt;

==The CICA legislation, 1999-2005==
A series of media revelations in the 1990s led to legal actions by former inmates that the government realised would succeed, resulting in substantial [[damages]] and [[legal costs]]. Principally the &quot;[[States of fear]]&quot; television series made by [[Mary Raftery]] for [[RTÉ]] caused questions to be raised in the [[Dáil]] in April 1999.&lt;ref&gt;[http://193.178.1.112/debates-99/29apr99/sect6.htm Dáil adjournment comments, 29 April 1999]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Taoiseach]] [[Bertie Ahern]] promptly apologised in May 1999: ''On behalf of the State and of all citizens of the State, the Government wishes to make a sincere and long overdue apology to the victims of childhood abuse for our collective failure to intervene, to detect their pain, to come to their rescue.'' In April–May 2000 his government passed the &quot;Commission to Inquire into Child Abuse Act, 2000&quot;. The institutions were renamed &quot;residential institutions&quot; inclusively comprising &quot;a school, an industrial school, a reformatory school, an orphanage, a hospital, a children’s home and any other place where children are cared for other than as members of their families.''

*The CICA was initially envisaged as an independent statutory body for the former inmates to record their experiences.
*A &quot;Redress Board&quot; was created alongside CICA under a 2002 Act, and would pay compensation as recommended.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rirb.ie/ Redress Board website]&lt;/ref&gt;

CICA's investigations were made through two sub-committees:
* A Confidential Committee that allowed the complainants to recite their experiences &quot;in a confidential setting&quot;.
* A more pro-active Investigation Committee where witnesses could be compelled to attend.&lt;ref&gt;Ryan Report, sections 1.07-1.16.&lt;/ref&gt;

Though funded by the Department of Education, the CICA has found itself occasionally hindered by it and by various church bodies, particularly for lack of documents. As a result its first chairman, Judge Laffoy, resigned in 2003, in part because of a lengthy review process that caused a 9-month delay. This review was sponsored by the Department and headed by Seán Ryan, a senior [[barrister]], who then became CICA's next chairman.

Mr Ryan's appointment was accompanied by a government comment by [[Noel Dempsey]] that he was also to be made a judge. This was a surprise at the time, as [[Irish High Court]] judges are limited in number by law, and no vacancies then existed.&lt;ref&gt;Arnold B., op.cit., pp. 215-216.&lt;/ref&gt; Questions arose on the impartiality of CICA, but in the event its final Report has been thoroughly researched. CICA's limitations were imposed by the 2000 Act, and it reconsidered its approach and focus in the &quot;Emergence Hearings&quot; which began in mid-2004, requiring all the parties involved to complete a series of questionnaires.&lt;ref&gt;Emergence Hearings; Ryan Report section 2, 141-146.&lt;/ref&gt; It also published a number of interim reports.&lt;ref&gt;[http://childabusecommission.ie/events/documents/Ryan%20Review.pdf 2004 Interim Report.]&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the Emergence Hearings the 2000 Act was amended by a further Act in 2005. A principal reform (section 8) was to prohibit the identification of an alleged abuser unless convicted of the abuse in question.

Notably, while every witness to the Commission gave evidence of frequent [[corporal punishment]], applied contrary to the regulations and therefore criminally, no Church witness came forward to certify a single such case. Difficulties arose where complainants or the accused were involved in parallel criminal or civil cases, such as the [[vaccination|vaccine]] trials performed on inmate children. With such divergent views the CICA's task has been difficult and contentious, but it has agreed with the evidence given by the complainants. Given Mr. Ahern's general apology in 1999, it would be hard to conclude otherwise.&lt;ref name=&quot;vaccine&quot; /&gt;

== Establishment and functions ==
The Commission was first established on an administrative basis in May 1999, under Judge [[Mary Laffoy]].  The first objective set for the Commission was to consider the broad terms of reference then provided to it, determine if these needed refining, and recommend to Government the powers and safeguards it would need to do its work effectively. The Commission reported to the Government in September and October 1999. The Commission to Inquire into Child Abuse Act, 2000 (the Act) was enacted on 26 April 2000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irishstatutebook.ie/ZZSI280Y2001.html Commission to Inquire into Child Abuse Act 2000, at www.irishstatutebook.ie]&lt;/ref&gt; The 2000 Act followed closely the recommendations in the reports of the non-statutory Commission, and was extended by the Commission to Inquire into Child Abuse (Amendment) Act, 2005.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irishstatutebook.ie/2005/en/act/pub/0017/index.html Commission to Inquire into Child Abuse (Amendment) Act 2005, at www.irishstatutebook.ie]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Statutory Commission established under the 2000–2005 Acts had four primary functions:

* to listen to victims of childhood abuse who want to recount their experiences to a sympathetic forum;
* to fully investigate all allegations of abuse made to it, except where the victim does not wish for an investigation;
* to consider whether the way institutions were managed, administered, supervised and regulated contributed to the occurrence of abuse and
* to publish a report on its findings to the general public, with recommendations to address the effects of abuse on those who suffered and to prevent future abuse of children in institutions.

A &quot;child&quot; was defined to be anyone under the age of 18, an &quot;institution&quot; was any place where children were cared for other than as members of their families, and four types of abuse were included in the Commission's mandate:&lt;ref name=&quot;About_Commission&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.childabusecommission.ie/about/index.html |publisher=The Commission to Inquire into Child Abuse  |title=About the Commission |accessdate=2009-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* ''[[Physical abuse]]'' – infliction of, or failure to prevent, physical injury to the child.
* ''[[Sexual abuse]]'' – the use of the child for sexual arousal or sexual gratification.
* ''[[Neglect]]'' – failure to care for the child which risks or causes serious impairment or serious adverse effects.
* ''[[Emotional abuse]]'' – any other acts or omissions towards the child which risk or cause serious impairment or serious adverse effects.

The Commission worked through two complementary teams.  The &quot;Confidential Committee&quot; provided a private forum for witnesses to &quot;recount in full the abuse suffered by them in an atmosphere that is sympathetic to, and understanding of, them, and as informally as is possible in the circumstances.&quot; [§4 (b) of the 2005 Act].  This committee’s report was not permitted to identify witnesses, or persons against whom they made allegations, or the institutions in which they alleged they were abused. There was &quot;no opportunity for anyone involved to challenge the veracity of the statements made.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;About_Commission&quot; /&gt;

The &quot;Investigation Committee&quot; on the other hand heard evidence from witnesses who wished to have their allegations investigated.  For this reason, respondents from Religious Orders and others could also give evidence and might be compelled to attend and/or produce documents required by the Committee. All parties were entitled to legal representation and to cross examine.  26 public hearings were held in 2005 and transcripts published,&lt;ref name=&quot;Public_Transcripts_2005&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.childabusecommission.ie/public_hearings/transarchive.html |publisher=The Commission to Inquire into Child Abuse  |title=Transcripts of Public Hearings |accessdate=2009-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; but most hearings were held in private.&lt;ref name=&quot;About_Commission&quot; /&gt;

== Public report ==
The Commission's report was published on 20 May 2009 in five volumes with an executive summary containing 43 conclusions and 20 recommendations.&lt;ref name=&quot;CICA_Executive_Summary&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.childabusecommission.ie/rpt/pdfs/CICA-Executive%20Summary.pdf |publisher=The Commission to Inquire into Child Abuse  |title=Executive Summary |date=20 May 2009 |accessdate=2009-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/northern_ireland/8059973.stm |publisher=[[BBC News]] |title=Abuse report - At a glance |date=20 May 2009 |accessdate=2009-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Conclusions===
Conclusions included:

'''Overall'''.  Physical and emotional abuse and neglect were features of the institutions. Sexual abuse occurred in many of them, particularly boys’ institutions. Schools were run in a severe, regimented manner that imposed unreasonable and oppressive discipline on children and even on staff.

'''Physical abuse'''.  The Reformatory and Industrial Schools depended on rigid control by means of severe [[corporal punishment]] and the fear of such punishment.  A climate of fear, created by pervasive, excessive and arbitrary punishment, permeated most of the institutions and all those run for boys. Children lived with the daily terror of not knowing where the next beating was coming from.

'''Sexual abuse'''.  Sexual abuse was endemic in boys’ institutions. The schools investigated revealed a substantial level of sexual abuse of boys in care that extended over a range from improper touching and fondling to rape with violence. Perpetrators of abuse were able to operate undetected for long periods at the core of institutions. When confronted with evidence of sexual abuse, the response of the religious authorities was to transfer the offender to another location where, in many instances, he was free to abuse again. The safety of children in general was not a consideration. The situation in girls’ institutions was different. Although girls were subjected to predatory sexual abuse by male employees or visitors or in outside placements, sexual abuse was not systemic in girls’ schools.

'''Neglect'''.  Poor standards of physical care were reported by most male and female complainants. Children were frequently hungry and food was inadequate, inedible and badly prepared in many schools. Accommodation was cold, spartan and bleak. Sanitary provision was primitive in most boys’ schools and general hygiene facilities were poor.

'''Emotional abuse'''.  Witnesses spoke of being belittled and ridiculed on a daily basis. Private matters such as bodily functions and personal hygiene were used as opportunities for degradation and humiliation. Personal and family denigration was widespread. There was constant criticism and verbal abuse and children were told they were worthless.

'''Supervision by the Department of Education'''.  The system of inspection by the Department was fundamentally flawed and incapable of being effective. Complaints by parents and others made to the Department were not properly investigated. The Department did not apply the standards in the rules and their own guidelines when investigating complaints, but sought to protect and defend the religious Congregations and the schools. The Department dealt inadequately with complaints about sexual abuse, which were generally dismissed or ignored.

===Limits of Scope===
The scope of the CICA's recommendations was limited from the outset to two categories; a limitation that has been widely criticised. In essence, the Irish taxpayer is to pay for the Commission's costs and any compensation, but without knowing who exactly was to blame, and without prosecutions for what were clearly criminal acts or omissions. CICA acknowledged that it ''.. was required to make recommendations under two headings:''

:(i)To alleviate or otherwise address the effects of the abuse on those who suffered

:(ii)To prevent where possible and reduce the incidence of abuse of children in institutions and to protect children from such abuse.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.childabusecommission.com/rpt/04-07.php Ryan Report, section 7.01]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Name and shame'''. It was originally intended that abusers would be publicly named in the Commission's report. However the Commission was blocked from doing so by a legal challenge from the [[Congregation of Christian Brothers|Christian Brothers]]. The Brothers sought and received permission to deal with abusers anonymously. Thus the report does not state whether all abusers were or were not members of the religious orders in charge of the schools, or whether external parties were involved.

'''External impact'''. The report does not consider the effects of the abuse on the psychological welfare of the parents of children who were in the control of the system. That at least some parents were concerned about their children was clearly shown by the lengths to which one father went to obtain the return of his children in the celebrated case ''in re Doyle'', which was the subject of the 2002 film ''[[Evelyn (film)|Evelyn]]''.

'''Motivation'''. The conclusions of the report do not consider the motivations of the abusers; although the inclusion of a financial report by the accountancy firm of Mazars, and various financial references combine to create an impression of financial motivation, this is not discussed or challenged. The report refers to, but makes no attempt to explain, the enthusiasm of the judiciary and the ISPCC for incarcerating children.

===Allegations and their extent===
The report dealt with allegations collected over a period of nine years between 2000 and 2008. These related to experiences between 1914 and the opening of the commission.&lt;ref name=&quot;Commission Report_2009 3.2&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.childabusecommission.com/rpt/03-02.php |publisher=The Commission to Inquire into Child Abuse  |title=Commission Report Vol 3 Ch. 2|accessdate=2009-07-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Hearings were held in Ireland, the UK and elsewhere. Of the approximately 25,000 children who had attended the institutions in the time period concerned, around 1,500 persons came forward with complaints to the commission.&lt;ref name=&quot;Commission Report_2009 3.2&quot;/&gt; Commission records show that 474 claims of physical abuse and 253 claims of sexual abuse were made by boys against the institutions in that period.&lt;ref name=&quot;Commission Report_2009 3.7&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.childabusecommission.com/rpt/03-07.php |publisher=The Commission to Inquire into Child Abuse  |title=Commission Report Vol 3 Ch. 7|accessdate=2009-07-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Records show that 383 claims of physical abuse and 128 claims of sexual abuse were made by girls against institutions over the years concerned. These claims covered all levels of abuse from the most serious down, and were made against both religious and lay personnel. The majority of sexual abuse claims by girls were against staff that should have been supervised by the religious orders.&lt;ref name=&quot;Commission Report_2009 3.9&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.childabusecommission.com/rpt/03-09.php |publisher=The Commission to Inquire into Child Abuse  |title=Commission Report Vol 3 Ch. 9|accessdate=2009-07-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Among some of the strongest abuse claims: one person described how they attempted to tell nuns they had been molested by an ambulance driver, only to be &quot;stripped naked and whipped by four nuns to 'get the devil out of you'&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;The abused - in their own words&quot;/&gt; Another described how they were removed from their bed and &quot;made to walk around naked with other boys whilst brothers used their canes and flicked at their penis&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;The abused - in their own words&quot;/&gt; Yet another was &quot;tied to a cross and raped whilst others masturbated at the side&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;The abused - in their own words&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/opinion/2009/0523/1224247210382.html|title=The abused - in their own words|date=23 May 2009|accessdate=2009-05-23|publisher=''[[The Irish Times]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Reactions to the report ==

=== Irish reaction ===
''[[The Irish Times]]'' called the report &quot;a devastating indictment of Church and State authorities,&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC_8060333&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/8060333.stm |title=In quotes: Reaction to Irish abuse |publisher=[[BBC News]] |date=20 May 2009 |accessdate=2009-05-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;the map of an Irish hell.&quot; &quot;The sheer scale and longevity of the torment inflected on defenceless children – over 800 known abusers in over 200 Catholic institutions during a period of 35 years – should alone make it clear that it was not accidental or opportunistic but systematic. Abuse was not a failure of the system. It was the system.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/opinion/2009/0521/1224247034262.html |publisher=''[[The Irish Times]]'' |title=The savage reality of our darkest days (Top Story) |date=21 May 2009 |accessdate=2009-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Irish [[President of Ireland|President]] [[Mary McAleese]] called the abuse &quot;an atrocious betrayal of love&quot;, saying: &quot;My heart goes out to the victims of this terrible injustice, an injustice compounded by the fact that they had to suffer in silence for so long.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Reopening of redress agreement not ruled out&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2009/0521/abuse.html|title=Reopening of redress agreement not ruled out|date=21 May 2009|accessdate=2009-05-23|publisher=[[Raidió Teilifís Éireann|RTÉ]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Irish [[Minister for Finance (Ireland)|Minister for Finance]], [[Brian Lenihan, Jnr|Brian Lenihan]], called for religious orders to increase their contributions to the State compensation fund.&lt;ref name=&quot;Church should increase compensation - Lenihan&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2009/0524/abuse.html|title=Church should increase compensation - Lenihan|date=24 May 2009|accessdate=2009-05-25|publisher=[[Raidió Teilifís Éireann|RTÉ]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Irish [[Minister for Justice and Equality|Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform]], [[Dermot Ahern]], said the report would be examined by members of the [[Garda Síochána]] to check for possible criminal prosecutions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Orders say 'No' to new abuse deal&quot;/&gt;

A book of solidarity was opened at the [[Mansion House, Dublin|Mansion House]] in Dublin, with more than 2,000 people having signed it by 23 May 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thousands sign book of solidarity&quot;/&gt; [[Lord Mayor of Dublin]], [[Eibhlin Byrne]], described how citizens were approaching her to personally express their solidarity as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thousands sign book of solidarity&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2009/0523/abuse.html|title=Thousands sign book of solidarity|date=23 May 2009|accessdate=2009-05-25|publisher=[[Raidió Teilifís Éireann|RTÉ]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Seán Brady|Cardinal Seán Brady]] (leader of the Catholic Church in Ireland) said he was &quot;profoundly sorry and deeply ashamed that children suffered in such awful ways in these institutions. This report makes it clear that great wrong and hurt were caused to some of the most vulnerable children in our society. It documents a shameful catalogue of cruelty: neglect, physical, sexual and emotional abuse, perpetrated against children.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC_8059826&quot;/&gt;  He declared that anyone responsible for abusing children in Catholic-run institutions should be held to account.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC_8060788&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/8060788.stm |title=Abusers 'must be held to account' |publisher=[[BBC News]] |date=21 May 2009 |accessdate=2009-05-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  This was echoed by [[Vincent Nichols|Most Reverend Vincent Nichols]] (leader of the Catholic Church in England and Wales) &quot;no matter how long ago it happened&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC_8059826&quot;/&gt;

Father Michael Mernagh, the 70-year-old [[Augustinians|Augustinian]] priest who recently made a 272&amp;nbsp;km pilgrimage from [[Cobh]] to [[Dublin]] in atonement for the church's response to clerical child sex abuse&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2009/0106/mernaghm.html|title=Priest completes atonement pilgrimage|date=6 January 2009|accessdate=2009-05-21|publisher=[[Raidió Teilifís Éireann|RTÉ]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; said he was appalled at the extent and longevity of the abuse, &quot;particularly at the role of the state and the government that seem to have colluded in actually encouraging children to be brought into these institutions to keep up the numbers.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC_8060056&quot; /&gt;

The report itself cannot be used for criminal proceedings (in part because the [[Congregation of Christian Brothers|Christian Brothers]] [[Sexual abuse scandal in the Congregation of Christian Brothers#Commission to Inquire into Child Abuse|successfully sued the commission]] to prevent its members from being named in the report) and victims say they feel &quot;cheated and deceived&quot; by the lack of prosecutions,&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC_8060442&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/8060442.stm |title=Irish abused 'cheated of justice' |publisher=[[BBC News]] |date=20 May 2009 |accessdate=2009-05-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;because of that this inquiry is deeply flawed, it's incomplete and many might call it a whitewash.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC_8060056&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/8060056.stm |title=Reaction to Irish abuse report |publisher=[[BBC News]] |date=20 May 2009 |accessdate=2009-05-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Counselling services reported a significant rise in calls following the release of the report, with some centres being inundated despite bringing in extra volunteers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/breaking/2009/0521/breaking32.htm |publisher=''[[The Irish Times]]'' |title=Helplines witness surge in calls after abuse report |date=21 May 2009 |accessdate=2009-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Callers included people who had never spoken of their abuse before, publication of the report having re-opened their old wounds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2009/0521/abuse.html |title=Bishop angers child protection groups |date=21 May 2009|accessdate=2009-05-21|publisher=[[Raidió Teilifís Éireann|RTÉ]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 25 May 2009, the ''[[Irish Times]]'' printed the reaction of [[Diarmuid Martin]], the [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Dublin|Archbishop of Dublin]], who said (partially quoting a correspondent),&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;'there is always a price to pay for not responding'. The church will have to pay that price in terms of its credibility. The first thing the church has to do is to move out of any mode of denial. Where the church is involved in social care it should be in the vanguard. That is different to a situation in which the church proclaims that it is in the vanguard....  in a very short time another report on the sexual abuse of children will be published, this time about [[Sexual abuse scandal in Dublin archdiocese|how such abuse was managed]] in the [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Dublin|Archdiocese of Dublin]] of which I am archbishop.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/opinion/2009/0525/1224247324722.html The Irish Times]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

On 10 June 2009 a solidarity march for victims of abuse was held in Dublin, going from the [[Garden of Remembrance (Dublin)|Garden of Remembrance]] in [[Parnell Square]] to [[Leinster House]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rte.ie/news/2009/0610/abuse.html Solidarity march for abuse victims], [[RTÉ News]], 10 June 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Westminster controversy ===
The Catholic [[Archbishop of Westminster]], [[Vincent Nichols]], was quoted as saying:
&lt;blockquote&gt;I think of those in religious orders and some of the clergy in Dublin who have to face these facts from their past, which instinctively and quite naturally they’d rather not look at. That takes courage, and also we shouldn’t forget that this account today will also overshadow all of the good that they also did.&lt;ref name=&quot;This week they said&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
The quote sparked controversy,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/breaking/2009/0521/breaking34.html Controversy over Nichols remark], Éanna Ó Caollaí, [[The Irish Times]], 21 May 2009, retrieved 29 May 2009&lt;/ref&gt; with John Kelly of Irish Survivors of Child Abuse, saying it was an &quot;outrageous statement to make&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;This week they said&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/opinion/2009/0523/1224247209591.html|title=This week they said|date=23 May 2009|accessdate=2009-05-23|publisher=''[[The Irish Times]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== International reaction ===
The findings were covered by media from across the world in the days following their publication. As of 23 May 2009, letters were still being sent to ''[[The Guardian]]'' in the UK and ''[[The Sydney Morning Herald]]'' in Australia, expressing horror at the revelations.&lt;ref name=&quot;We want real contrition for our abuse&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/may/23/letters-catholic-abuse|title=We want real contrition for our abuse|date=23 May 2009|accessdate=2009-05-23|publisher=''[[The Guardian]]'' | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Enough Catholic spin: more transparency is needed&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.smh.com.au/opinion/letters/enough-catholic-spin-more-transparency-is-needed-20090522-bi6k.html|title=Enough Catholic spin: more transparency is needed|date=23 May 2009|accessdate=2009-05-23|publisher=''[[The Sydney Morning Herald]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The Canberra Times]]'' described the publication as a &quot;major new report&quot;, reporting that Australia's clergy would be examined for any links to the &quot;grim sexual abuse allegations&quot; from Ireland.&lt;ref name=&quot;Australia's top Catholic vows action on abuse&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.canberratimes.com.au/news/local/news/general/australias-top-catholic-vows-action-on-abuse/1520481.aspx|title=Australia's top Catholic vows action on abuse|date=22 May 2009|accessdate=2009-05-23|publisher=''[[The Canberra Times]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Arab News]]'', an English language newspaper from the [[Middle East]], said the report made &quot;appalling reading&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Editorial: Abuse of kids in Ireland&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arabnews.com/?page=7&amp;section=0&amp;article=122787&amp;d=23&amp;m=5&amp;y=2009|title=Editorial: Abuse of kids in Ireland|date=23 May 2009|accessdate=2009-05-23|publisher=''[[ArabNews]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[Taipei Times]]'' reported on the &quot;shocking scale&quot; of sexual and physical abuse in Ireland's educational institutions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Abuse ‘endemic’ at Catholic establishments in Ireland&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.taipeitimes.com/News/front/archives/2009/05/22/2003444234|title=Abuse ‘endemic’ at Catholic establishments in Ireland|date=22 May 2009|accessdate=2009-05-23|publisher=''[[Taipei Times]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt; American networks, including [[ABC News]] and [[CNN]], covered the story,&lt;ref name=&quot;Irish Child Abuse Report: 'People Know The Truth'&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://abcnews.go.com/International/story?id=7645342&amp;page=1|title=Irish Child Abuse Report: 'People Know The Truth'|date=22 May 2009|accessdate=2009-05-23|publisher=[[ABC News]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Report reveals decades of child abuse in Irish institutions&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2009/WORLD/europe/05/20/ireland.catholic.report.abuse/|title=Report reveals decades of child abuse in Irish institutions|date=20 May 2009|accessdate=2009-05-23|publisher=[[CNN]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; as did the [[BBC]], [[Canadian Broadcasting Corporation|CBC]], and [[Sky News]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Irish church knew abuse 'endemic'&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/8059826.stm|title=Irish church knew abuse 'endemic'|date=20 May 2009|accessdate=2009-05-23|publisher=[[BBC]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Church-run schools in Ireland condoned decades of abuse: report&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cbc.ca/canada/newfoundland-labrador/story/2009/05/20/ireland-catholic-church-abuse-report.html|title=Church-run schools in Ireland condoned decades of abuse: report|date=20 May 2009|accessdate=2009-05-23|publisher=[[Canadian Broadcasting Corporation|CBC]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;'Thousands Abused In Catholic Church Care'&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.sky.com/skynews/Home/World-News/Ireland-Catholic-Church-Covered-Up-Decades-Of-Child-Abuse-Says-Report-By-Judge-Sean-Ryan/Article/200905315285008?lpos=World_News_Top_Stories_Header_0&amp;lid=ARTICLE_15285008_Ireland%3A_Catholic_Church_Covered_Up_Decades_Of_Child_Abuse_Says_Report_By_Judge_Sean_Ryan|title='Thousands Abused In Catholic Church Care'|date=20 May 2009|accessdate=2009-05-23|publisher=[[Sky News]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' reviewed the &quot;most depraved acts&quot; committed in its coverage of the story.&lt;ref name=&quot;For Ireland's Catholic Schools, a Catalog of Horrors&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,1900120,00.html|title=For Ireland's Catholic Schools, a Catalog of Horrors|date=21 May 2009|accessdate=2009-05-23|publisher=''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt; The front page of 21 May 2009 edition of ''[[The New York Times]]'' told of &quot;Ireland's shameful tragedy&quot;, leading to reactions describing a &quot;[[Nuremberg Trials|Nuremberg trial]], Irish-style, with no names, no prosecution and no court appearances.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;A Legacy of Shame for Ireland and the Church&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/05/22/opinion/l22ireland.html?ref=opinion|title=A Legacy of Shame for Ireland and the Church|date=21 May 2009|accessdate=2009-05-23|publisher=''[[The New York Times]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2009, on a visit to the Vatican, bishops Martin and Brady heard from [[Pope Benedict XVI]] that he had: &quot;''... urged them to establish the truth of what has happened, ensure that justice is done for all, put in place the measures that will prevent these abuses happening again, with a view to healing for survivors.''&quot;

== 2002 Compensation deal and the question of blame ==
A further contentious aspect arises from an &quot;indemnity deal&quot; signed on 5 June 2002. This was between two representatives of the [[Conference of Religious of Ireland|Conference of Religious of Ireland (Cori)]] (an umbrella group representing 138 religious congregations) on behalf of 18 religious Orders that had run the residential institutions, and the then Minister [[Michael Woods (politician)|Michael Woods]]. This indemnified the Orders from legal action, whereby any costs would now be met by the Irish taxpayer, in return for a transfer of property and assets to the government worth €128 million. No representatives of the victims were involved in these negotiations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bishop-accountability.org/news2009/05_06/2009_05_27_Turlish_PublicApologies.htm Catholic Sex Abuse Archive]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/ireland/2009/0530/1224247747976.html The Irish Times]&lt;/ref&gt; The original plan was to provide adequate funds for the Redress Board, but in the interim an unexpectedly large number of claimants has come forward.

Not only was the deal inadequate to cover the costs of CICA itself, let alone any compensation, but it remained secret until revealed by the media in January 2003. Further, the deal was completed under a caretaker government, at the time of the [[Irish general election, 2002|2002 election]], on the last day possible, and could thus neither be approved by Cabinet nor be debated in the [[Dáil]]. Given that Catholic Orders insisted on educating all the children in question {{Citation needed|date=July 2013}}, it unfairly imposes indirect costs on non-Catholic or non-Christian taxpayers{{Citation needed|date=July 2013}}.

In the circumstances, and given a net cost to the Irish taxpayer approaching €1,000,000,000, its legality may be questioned.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.labour.ie/press/listing/1242914492533390.html Labour Party comment 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; Mr. Woods was criticised by [[Fine Gael]] leader [[Enda Kenny]] amidst calls to reopen negotiations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Woods defends compensation deal&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2009/0522/abuse.html|title=Woods defends compensation deal|date=22 May 2009|accessdate=2009-05-25|publisher=[[Raidió Teilifís Éireann|RTÉ]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The religious Orders involved&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/breaking/2009/0525/breaking14.html?via=mr The Irish Times]&lt;/ref&gt; initially refused to reopen compensation negotiation proceedings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Orders say 'No' to new abuse deal&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2009/0525/abuse.html|title=Orders say 'No' to new abuse deal|date=25 May 2009|accessdate=2009-05-25|publisher=[[Raidió Teilifís Éireann|RTÉ]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Then in April 2010 an agreement was announced whereby another €348m would be paid.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.taoiseach.gov.ie/eng/Government_Press_Office/Government_Press_Releases_2010/_Government_Statement_following_meetings_with_Religious_Congregations_and_with_Survivors_of_Child_Abuse,_Thursday_15th_April,_2010.html Government statement 15 April 2010]&lt;/ref&gt; This followed negotiations in late 2009 with 18 church groups, though it seems that the letters of offer were accepted as such by government, without proof of any effort to increase the amounts offered.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.education.ie/servlet/blobservlet/pub_religious_offers.pdf List of offers with original letters viewable online]&lt;/ref&gt; The 2010 announcement also confirmed for the first time that the entire process since 1999 had led to &quot;.. costs of well over a billion euro being incurred by the State&quot;.

The Republic of Ireland's government is also aware of the [[Settlements and bankruptcies in Catholic sex abuse cases|enormous compensation awards]] made in the USA, where prosecution of alleged criminals is more robust&quot;{{Citation needed|date=July 2013}}&quot;. Ireland is currently (2011) undergoing a [[Post-2008 Irish economic downturn|financial crisis]], making it much harder to justify the costs of prosecutions and compensation.

Though still a matter for debate, the indemnity deal has complicated the question of ultimate blame. For decades the Government and Department of Education were to blame for lack of oversight, various parts of the Catholic Church refused to reform internal systems, the police generally ignored complaints, and the courts sent small children to the institutions with little concern for their rights. The 2002 deal has appeared in hindsight to be a well-intentioned but unsatisfactory attempt at a quick fix. In May 2009 CORI agreed to contribute more to the envisaged higher compensation amounts.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.breakingnews.ie/ireland/cori-chief-backs-call-for-more-compensation-for-abuse-victims-412556.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Church of Ireland Institutions==
Campaigners are also engaged in trying to extend the redress scheme to victims of institutional abuse in places such as the ''[[Bethany Home|Bethany Mother and Child Home]]'' in Rathgar.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://historical-debates.oireachtas.ie/D/0639/D.0639.200710110022.html |title=Dáil Éireann - Volume 639 - 11&amp;nbsp;October 2007.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/opinion/2009/0701/1224249837505.html |title=Protestant abuse victims must also be heard, Irish Times, 1 July 2009. | work=The Irish Times | date=7 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Often girls &quot;in trouble&quot; were brought to the home by a Protestant minister. While these were affiliated to the [[Church of Ireland]], and used by its parishioners, it is claimed the home was not run by the church itself,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/ireland/2010/0522/1224270894237.html Graves of Bethany children 'located at Mount Jerome' by Patsy McGarry] Irish Times, 21 May 2010&lt;/ref&gt; however members of the church sat on the board of the home and the home was designated by the Church of Ireland as ''a suitable place for Protestant girls on remand'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-northern-ireland-foyle-west-11500850 Bethany Home Church of Ireland link claimed] BBC Website 8 October 2010&lt;/ref&gt; and recognised by the courts as a place of detention.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.derekleinster.com/guardian.html Private Lives: First Person, Derek Leinster] The Guardian, 16 September 2009&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Bethany Survivors Group'' continues to campaign to the newly elected government for inclusion in the redress scheme.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.indymedia.ie/article/99220 | title=Letter to the new Minister for Education Ruairi Quinn | author=Bethany Survivors Group | date=11 March 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some residential institutions founded and run by members of the Church of Ireland such as ''Stewart's Hospital'' and ''Miss Carr's Children's Home,'' due to their connection with the Eastern Health Board do come under the remit of the redress board scheme and thus, victims are entitled to petition it for compensation.&lt;ref name=&quot;rira2002&quot; /&gt; These were added to the redress list following complaints and campaigns that they were being excluded.

Campaigners also campaigned for a number of Protestant run children's residences and former orphanages such as ''[[Ellen Smyly|The Smyly Homes]]'' which were regulated by the state, and subject to departmental inspection, to be included in the Redress scheme.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.independent.ie/national-news/protestant-homes-may-join-list-eligible-for-abuse-payout-140405.html | title=Protestant homes may join list eligible for abuse payout | first=David (Religious Affairs Correspondent) | last=Quinn | newspaper=Irish Independent | date=11 December 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;
There are eleven Mrs. Smyly's homes which the government has been in dialogue with over some contribution to the redress fund.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/special/2005/redress/index.pdf Page 32., 4.123., Report into the Residential Institutions Redress Scheme] - Dáil Éireann
Committee of Public Accounts., March 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

Former residents of other homes and orphanages which were designated by the Church of Ireland for protestant children such as [[Westbank Orphanage]], Greystones and Ovoca House in Wicklow, have demanded inclusion in the 2002 redress scheme, and an apology.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.herald.ie/news/protestant-homes-survivors-want-apology-30385146.html Protestant homes survivors want an apology] BY Laura Larkin, The Hearld, 26 June 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some Church of Ireland run institutions for older children like the Cottage Home and Birds Nest have been included in the list of institutions for the Redress Scheme,&lt;ref name=&quot;rira2002&quot;&gt;[http://www.rirb.ie/documents/LongGuide.doc A GUIDE TO THE REDRESS SCHEME UNDER THE RESIDENTIAL INSTITUTIONS REDRESS ACT, 2002] www.rirb.ie&lt;/ref&gt; since these homes were found to have allowed a vaccines to be tested on their residents in trials by the Department of Medical Microbiology at [[University College Dublin]].&lt;ref name=&quot;vaccine&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.independent.ie/national-news/the-forgotten-children-of-irelands-hidden-scandal-2305062.html | title=The forgotten children of Ireland's hidden scandal | first=Patricia | last=McDonagh | newspaper=Irish Independent | date=20 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Trudder House==
Trudder House in Newtownmountkennedy, Co Wicklow, was a residential home set up by Dublin Committee for Travelling People (a voluntary group), in 1975, the home was for children from the travelling community who had appeared before the courts. The home was funded by the Eastern Health Board, and boys were sent to the home after being sentenced by the courts. In August 1985 New Hibernia magazine reported ''irregularities'' at the home and allegations of beatings and homosexual child abuse.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.ie/unsorted/features/a-scandalous-country-521220.html Trudder House - A scandalous country] Sunday Independent, Sunday 31 October 1999&lt;/ref&gt; In the mid-1990s some 19 young travelers had made allegations of sexual abuse against six people associated with the residential home.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.ie/national-news/vicious-paedophile-who-headed-a-brutal-regime-451261.html Vicious paedophile who headed a brutal regime] Irish Independent, Tuesday, 10 March 1998&lt;/ref&gt; The home closed in April 1995.&lt;ref&gt;[http://historical-debates.oireachtas.ie/D/0461/D.0461.199602080036.html Written Answers. - Trudder House (Wicklow) Allegations] Dáil Éireann - Volume 461 - 8 February 1996.&lt;/ref&gt; Victims are entitled to redress from the Redress Board.

== See also ==
* [[Catholic sexual abuse scandal in Ireland]]
* [[Abuse by priests in Roman Catholic orders]]
* [[Catholic sex abuse cases]]
* [[Ferns Report]]
* [[Industrial school]]
* [[Magdalene Asylum]]
* [[Sexual abuse scandal in Dublin archdiocese]]
* [[Murphy Report]]
* [[St Joseph's Industrial School, Letterfrack]]

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book |last=Arnold |first=B. |title=The Irish Gulag |publisher=Gill &amp; Macmillan |location=Dublin |year=2009 |isbn=978-0-7171-4614-7 }}

== External links ==
*[http://www.tv3.ie/videos.php?date_mode=0&amp;full_episodes=1&amp;locID=1.65.388 Abuse of Trust] Documentary on RTÉ TV3 16 June 2009
*[http://www.independent.ie/opinion/analysis/state-lost-highstakes-game-with-two-nuns-1747597.html State Lost High-Stakes Game With Two Nuns]
*[http://www.rte.ie/news/2009/0526/morningireland_av.html?2550199,null,209  CORI Director General  Marianne O'Connor on RTÉ Morning Ireland] 26 May 2009
*[http://www.herald.ie/entertainment/tv-radio/defending-the-indefensible-in-horrific-scandal-1755256.html John Costello, Defending the Indefensible in Horrific Scandal]
*[http://www.rte.ie/podcasts/2009/pc/pod-v-280509-1sthour-29m00s-morningireland.mp3 President Mary McAleese reaction on RTÉ Morning Ireland] 28 May 2009
* [http://www.childabusecommission.ie/ The Commission's website], [http://www.childabusecommission.ie/index.html complete report and summary], [http://www.childabusecommission.ie/rpt/pdfs/ individual chapters of report]
* [http://www.nova.ie/ The National Office for Victims of Abuse - for adults who have experienced childhood abuse]
* [[Henry McDonald (writer)|Henry McDonald]], ''[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/may/20/child-abuse-catholic-schools-ireland/print Thousands raped and abused in Catholic schools in Ireland]'',  [[The Guardian]], 2009-05-20
* [http://www.tv3.ie/videos.php?video=9501&amp;locID=1.2.141 Chris Heaphy, a victim of abuse at Greenmont Industrial School, Cork, delivers an emotional speech on Patrick St, Cork], 28 May 2009
* [http://www.communityservices.qld.gov.au/community/redress-scheme/documents/forde_comminquiry.pdf Text of the similar &quot;Commission of Inquiry into Child Abuse in Queensland institutions&quot; (Forde Enquiry), 1999, Queensland, Australia]

{{Abuse}}
{{SACC}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Commission To Inquire Into Child Abuse}}
[[Category:Roman Catholic Church sex abuse cases in Ireland]]
[[Category:Public inquiries in Ireland]]
[[Category:2009 in Ireland]]
[[Category:Industrial schools in the Republic of Ireland]]
[[Category:2009 in Christianity]]
[[Category:2009 in law]]</text>
      <sha1>owp0qhyp7868lf32537gckx4pd1lt4y</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
