<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Creativity</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>142910</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745206390</id>
      <parentid>745204494</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-19T21:24:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Theroadislong</username>
        <id>2001020</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/Jadertor|Jadertor]] ([[User talk:Jadertor|talk]]): Blog spam. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="117299">{{Redirect|Creative engineering|the animatronic and arcade games manufacturer|Creative Engineering Inc.}}
'''Creativity''' is a phenomenon whereby something new and somehow valuable is formed. The created item may be intangible (such as an [[idea]], a [[scientific theory]], a [[musical composition]], or a [[joke]]) or a physical object (such as an [[invention]], a [[Literature|literary work]], or a [[painting]]).

Scholarly interest in creativity involves many definitions and concepts pertaining to a number of disciplines: [[psychology]], [[cognitive science]], [[education]], [[philosophy]] (particularly [[philosophy of science]]), [[technology]], [[theology]], [[sociology]], [[linguistics]], [[business studies]], [[Songwriter|songwriting]], and [[economics]], covering  the relations between creativity and general intelligence, mental and neurological processes, personality type and creative ability, creativity and mental health; the potential for fostering creativity through education and training, especially as augmented by technology; the maximisation of creativity for national economic benefit, and the application of creative resources to improve the effectiveness of teaching and learning.

==Definition==
In a summary of scientific research into creativity, Michael Mumford suggested: &quot;Over the course of the last decade, however, we seem to have reached a general agreement that creativity involves the production of novel, useful products&quot; (Mumford, 2003, p.&amp;nbsp;110),&lt;ref&gt;Mumford, M. D. (2003). Where have we been, where are we going? Taking stock in creativity research. ''[[Creativity Research Journal]]'', 15, 107–120.&lt;/ref&gt; or, in [[Robert Sternberg]]'s words, the production of &quot;something original and worthwhile&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sternberg Cognitive Psychology 2011&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Sternberg|first1=Robert J.|title=Cognitive Psychology|date=2011|publisher=Cengage Learning|isbn=978-1-133-38701-5|page=479|edition=6|chapter=Creativity}}&lt;/ref&gt; Authors have diverged dramatically in their precise definitions beyond these general commonalities: Peter Meusburger reckons that over a hundred different analyses can be found in the literature.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meusburger1&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Meusburger|first=Peter|title=Milieus of Creativity: An Interdisciplinary Approach to Spatiality of Creativity|year=2009|publisher=Springer|isbn=978-1-4020-9876-5 |editor=Meusburger, P. |editor2=Funke, J. |editor3=Wunder, E.|chapter=Milieus of Creativity: The Role of Places, Environments and Spatial Contexts}}&lt;/ref&gt; As an illustration, one definition given by [[Ellis Paul Torrance|Dr. E. Paul Torrance]] described it as &quot;a process of becoming sensitive to problems, deficiencies, gaps in knowledge, missing elements, disharmonies, and so on; identifying the difficulty; searching for solutions, making guesses, or formulating hypotheses about the deficiencies: testing and retesting these hypotheses and possibly modifying and retesting them; and finally communicating the results.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Torrance Test Manual Verbal&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Torrance|first1=Paul|title=The Torrance Tests of Creative Thinking-Norms-Technical Manual Research Edition|publisher=Personnel Press|location=Princeton, New Jersey|page=6|chapter=Verbal Tests. Forms A and B-Figural Tests, Forms A and B.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aspects==
Theories of creativity (particularly investigation of why some people are more creative than others) have focused on a variety of aspects. The dominant factors are usually identified as &quot;the four Ps&quot; — process, product, person, and place (according to [[James Melvin Rhodes|Mel Rhodes]]).&lt;ref&gt;Mel Rhodes: [http://www.jstor.org/discover/10.2307/20342603?uid=3737864&amp;uid=2&amp;uid=4&amp;sid=21103750220081''An Analysis of Creativity.''] in Phi Delta Kappan 1961, Vol. 42,  No. 7, p. 306–307&lt;/ref&gt; A focus on ''process'' is shown in cognitive approaches that try to describe thought mechanisms and techniques for creative thinking. Theories invoking divergent rather than convergent thinking (such as [[J. P. Guilford|Guilford]]), or those describing the staging of the creative process (such as [[Graham Wallas|Wallas]]) are primarily theories of creative process. A focus on creative ''product'' usually appears in attempts to measure creativity (psychometrics, see below) and in creative ideas framed as successful [[memetics|memes]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Gabora&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=[[Liane Gabora|Gabora, Liane]]|year=1997|title= The Origin and Evolution of Culture and Creativity|journal=Journal of Memetics – Evolutionary Models of Information Transmission|volume=1|url=http://cogprints.org/794/1/oecc.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; The psychometric approach to creativity reveals that it also involves the ability to produce more.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sternberg 2009 468&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Sternberg|first=Robert J.|title=Cognitive Psychology|year=2009|publisher=CENGAGE Learning|isbn=978-0-495-50629-4|page=468|editor=Jaime A. Perkins |editor2=Dan Moneypenny |editor3=Wilson Co}}&lt;/ref&gt;
A focus on the nature of the creative ''person'' considers more general intellectual habits, such as openness, levels of [[Ideation (creative process)|ideation]], autonomy, expertise, exploratory behavior, and so on. A focus on ''place'' considers the circumstances in which creativity flourishes, such as degrees of autonomy, access to resources, and the nature of gatekeepers. Creative lifestyles are characterized by nonconforming attitudes and behaviors as well as flexibility.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sternberg 2009 468&quot; /&gt;

==Etymology==
The [[lexeme]] in the English word ''creativity'' comes from the [[Latin]] term ''creō'' &quot;to create, make&quot;: its [[Morphological derivation|derivational suffixes]] also come from Latin. The word &quot;create&quot; appeared in English as early as the 14th century, notably in Chaucer, to indicate divine creation&lt;ref name=&quot;RuncoAlbert&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Runco|first=Mark A.|title=The Cambridge Handbook of Creativity|year=2010|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|isbn=978-0-521-73025-9|author2=Albert, Robert S.|editor=[[James C. Kaufman]] |editor2=Robert J. Sternberg|chapter=Creativity Research}}&lt;/ref&gt; (in [[The Parson's Tale]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;And eke Job saith, that in hell is no order of rule. And albeit that God hath '''created''' all things in right order, and nothing without order, but all things be ordered and numbered, yet nevertheless they that be damned be not in order, nor hold no order.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;). However, its modern meaning as an act of human creation did not emerge until after [[Age of Enlightenment|the Enlightenment]].&lt;ref name=RuncoAlbert /&gt;

==History of the concept==
{{Main article|History of the concept of creativity}}
[[File:Plato-raphael.jpg|thumb|150px|right|Greek philosophers like Plato rejected the concept of creativity, preferring to see art as a form of discovery. Asked in ''[[Republic (Plato)|The Republic]]'', &quot;Will we say, of a painter, that he makes something?&quot;, Plato answers, &quot;Certainly not, he merely [[mimesis|imitates]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Six Ideas p. 244&quot;&gt;[[Władysław Tatarkiewicz]], ''A History of Six Ideas: an Essay in Aesthetics'', p. 244.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

===Ancient views===
Most ancient cultures, including thinkers of [[Ancient Greece]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Six Ideas p. 244&quot; /&gt; [[History of China#Ancient China|Ancient China]], and [[Outline of ancient India|Ancient India]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Albert99&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Albert|first= R. S.|author2=Runco, M. A.|year=1999|editor = Sternberg, R. J.|title= Handbook of Creativity|publisher= [[Cambridge University Press]]|chapter=:A History of Research on Creativity}}&lt;/ref&gt; lacked the concept of creativity, seeing art as a form of discovery and not creation. The [[Ancient Greece|ancient Greeks]] had no terms corresponding to &quot;to create&quot; or &quot;creator&quot; except for the expression &quot;''poiein''&quot; (&quot;to make&quot;), which only applied to ''poiesis'' (poetry) and to the ''poietes'' (poet, or &quot;maker&quot;) who made it. [[Plato]] did not believe in art as a form of creation. Asked in ''[[Republic (Plato)|The Republic]]'',&lt;ref&gt;Plato, The Republic, Book X – [[wikisource:The Republic/Book X]]&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Will we say, of a painter, that he makes something?&quot;, he answers, &quot;Certainly not, he merely [[mimesis|imitates]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Six Ideas p. 244&quot; /&gt;

It is commonly argued that the notion of &quot;creativity&quot; originated in [[Western culture]] through [[Christianity]], as a matter of [[Revelation|divine inspiration]].&lt;ref name=&quot;RuncoAlbert&quot; /&gt; According to the historian [[Daniel J. Boorstin]], &quot;the early Western conception of creativity was the [[Genesis creation narrative|Biblical story of creation]] given in the ''[[Book of Genesis|Genesis]]''.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Albert2&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Albert|first= R. S.|author2=Runco, M. A.|year=1999|editor = Sternberg, R. J.|title= Handbook of Creativity|publisher= [[Cambridge University Press]]|chapter=:A History of Research on Creativity|page=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, this is not creativity in the modern sense, which did not arise until the [[Renaissance]]. In the Judaeo-Christian tradition, creativity was the sole province of God; humans were not considered to have the ability to create something new except as an expression of God's work.&lt;ref name=&quot;NiuSternberg&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1037/h0091265|last=Niu|first=Weihua|author2=Sternberg, Robert J.|title=The Philosophical Roots of Western and Eastern Conceptions of Creativity|journal=Journal of Theoretical and Philosophical Psychology|year=2006|volume=26|pages=18–38|url=http://www.westga.edu/~stpp/JTPP_Aticles/26-2/THE1210.pdf|accessdate=23 October 2010}}; cf. [[Michel Weber]], &quot;[http://www.academia.edu/3640181/_Creativity_Efficacy_and_Vision_Ethics_and_Psychology_in_an_Open_Universe_2006_ Creativity, Efficacy and Vision: Ethics and Psychology in an Open Universe],&quot; in Michel Weber and Pierfrancesco Basile (eds.), ''Subjectivity, Process, and Rationality'', Frankfurt/Lancaster, ontos verlag, Process Thought XIV, 2006, pp. 263-281.&lt;/ref&gt; A concept similar to that of Christianity existed in Greek culture, for instance, [[Muse]]s were seen as mediating inspiration from the Gods.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dacey&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Dacey|first=John|title=Encyclopedia of Creativity, Vol. 1|year=1999|isbn=0-12-227076-2|editor=Mark A. Runco |editor2=Steven R. Pritzer|chapter=Concepts of Creativity: A history|publisher=[[Elsevier]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Romans and Greeks invoked the concept of an external creative &quot;[[daemon (classical mythology)|daemon]]&quot; (Greek) or &quot;[[genius]]&quot; (Latin), linked to the sacred or the divine. However, none of these views are similar to the modern concept of creativity, and the individual was not seen as the cause of creation until the [[Renaissance]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Albert3&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Albert|first= R. S.|author2=Runco, M. A.|year=1999|editor = Sternberg, R. J.|title= Handbook of Creativity|publisher= [[Cambridge University Press]]|chapter=:A History of Research on Creativity|page=6}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was during the Renaissance that creativity was first seen, not as a conduit for the divine, but from the abilities of &quot;[[Great Man theory|great men]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Albert3&quot; /&gt;

===The Enlightenment and after===
The rejection of creativity in favor of discovery and the belief that individual creation was a conduit of the divine would dominate the West probably until the [[Renaissance]] and even later.&lt;ref name=&quot;NiuSternberg&quot; /&gt; The development of the modern concept of creativity begins in the [[Renaissance]], when creation began to be perceived as having originated from the abilities of the individual, and not God. This could be attributed to the leading intellectual movement of the time, aptly named [[humanism]], which developed an intensely human-centric outlook on the world, valuing the intellect and achievement of the individual.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Humanism - Rome Reborn: The Vatican Library &amp; Renaissance Culture {{!}} Exhibitions - Library of Congress|url = http://www.loc.gov/exhibits/vatican/humanism.html|website = www.loc.gov|date = 1993-01-08|accessdate = 2015-11-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; From this philosophy arose the [[Renaissance man]] (or polymath), an individual who embodies the principals of humanism in their ceaseless courtship with knowledge and creation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Leonardo da Vinci {{!}} Italian artist, engineer, and scientist|url = http://www.britannica.com/biography/Leonardo-da-Vinci|website = Encyclopedia Britannica|accessdate = 2015-11-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of the most well-known and immensely accomplished examples is [[Leonardo da Vinci]].

However, this shift was gradual and would not become immediately apparent until the Enlightenment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Albert3&quot; /&gt; By the 18th century and the [[Age of Enlightenment]], mention of creativity (notably in [[aesthetics]]), linked with the concept of [[imagination]], became more frequent.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tatarkiewicz80&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Tatarkiewicz, Władysław |authorlink=Władysław Tatarkiewicz |title=A History of Six Ideas: an Essay in Aesthetics |location=Translated from the Polish by [[Christopher Kasparek]], The Hague |publisher=Martinus Nijhoff |year=1980}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the writing of [[Thomas Hobbes]], imagination became a key element of human cognition;&lt;ref name=&quot;RuncoAlbert&quot; /&gt; [[William Duff (writer)|William Duff]] was one of the first to identify imagination as a quality of [[genius]], typifying the separation being made between talent (productive, but breaking no new ground) and genius.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dacey&quot; /&gt;

As a direct and independent topic of study, creativity effectively received no attention until the 19th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dacey&quot; /&gt; Runco and Albert argue that creativity as the subject of proper study began seriously to emerge in the late 19th century with the increased interest in individual differences inspired by the arrival of [[Darwinism]]. In particular, they refer to the work of [[Francis Galton]], who through his [[Eugenics|eugenicist]] outlook took a keen interest in the heritability of intelligence, with creativity taken as an aspect of genius.&lt;ref name=&quot;RuncoAlbert&quot; /&gt;

In the late 19th and early 20th centuries, leading mathematicians and scientists such as [[Hermann von Helmholtz]] (1896) and [[Henri Poincaré]] (1908) began to reflect on and publicly discuss their creative processes.

===Twentieth century to the present day===
The insights of Poincaré and von Helmholtz were built on in early accounts of the creative process by pioneering theorists such as [[Graham Wallas]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Wallas26&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Wallas, G. |title=Art of Thought |year=1926 |authorlink=Graham Wallas}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Max Wertheimer]]. In his work ''Art of Thought'', published in 1926, Wallas presented one of the first models of the creative process. In the Wallas stage model, creative insights and illuminations may be explained by a process consisting of 5 stages:
:(i) ''preparation'' (preparatory work on a problem that focuses the individual's mind on the problem and explores the problem's dimensions),
:(ii) ''incubation'' (where the problem is internalized into the unconscious mind and nothing appears externally to be happening),
:(iii) ''intimation'' (the creative person gets a &quot;feeling&quot; that a solution is on its way),
:(iv) ''illumination'' or insight (where the creative idea bursts forth from its [[preconscious]] processing into conscious awareness);
:(v) ''verification'' (where the idea is consciously verified, elaborated, and then applied).
Wallas' model is often treated as four stages, with &quot;intimation&quot; seen as a sub-stage.

Wallas considered creativity to be a legacy of the [[evolution]]ary process, which allowed humans to quickly adapt to rapidly changing environments. Simonton&lt;ref name=&quot;Simonton99&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Simonton, D. K. |year=1999 |title=Origins of genius: Darwinian perspectives on creativity |publisher=Oxford University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; provides an updated perspective on this view in his book, ''Origins of genius: Darwinian perspectives on creativity''.

In 1927, [[Alfred North Whitehead]] gave the Gifford Lectures at the University of Edinburgh, later published as ''[[Process and Reality]].''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Whitehead|first=Alfred North|title=Process and reality : an essay in cosmology ; Gifford Lectures delivered in the University of Edinburgh during the session 1927–28|year=1978|publisher=Free Press|location=New York|isbn=0-02-934580-4|edition=Corrected}}&lt;/ref&gt; He is credited with having coined the term &quot;creativity&quot; to serve as the ultimate category of his metaphysical scheme: &quot;Whitehead actually coined the term – our term, still the preferred currency of exchange among literature, science, and the arts. . . a term that quickly became so popular, so omnipresent, that its invention within living memory, and by Alfred North Whitehead of all people, quickly became occluded&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Meyer|first=Steven|title=Introduction: Whitehead Now|journal=Configurations|year=2005|volume=1|issue=13|pages=1–33}}. Cf. [[Michel Weber]] and Will Desmond (eds.). ''[http://www.academia.edu/279955/Handbook_of_Whiteheadian_Process_Thought Handbook of Whiteheadian Process Thought]'' (Frankfurt / Lancaster, Ontos Verlag, Process Thought X1 &amp; X2, 2008) and Ronny Desmet &amp; Michel Weber (edited by), ''[http://www.academia.edu/279940/Whitehead._The_Algebra_of_Metaphysics Whitehead. The Algebra of Metaphysics. Applied Process Metaphysics Summer Institute Memorandum]'', Louvain-la-Neuve, Les Éditions Chromatika, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The formal [[Psychometrics|psychometric]] measurement of creativity, from the standpoint of orthodox [[Psychology|psychological]] literature, is usually considered to have begun with [[J. P. Guilford]]'s 1950 address to the [[American Psychological Association]], which helped popularize the topic&lt;ref name=&quot;Sternberg99&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Sternberg, R. J. |author2=Lubart, T. I. |chapter=The Concept of Creativity: Prospects and Paradigms |editor=Sternberg, R. J. |title=Handbook of Creativity |year=1999 |publisher= Cambridge University Press |authorlink=Robert Sternberg |isbn=0-521-57285-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; and focus attention on a scientific approach to conceptualizing creativity. (It should be noted that the London School of Psychology had instigated psychometric studies of creativity as early as 1927 with the work of H. L. Hargreaves into the Faculty of Imagination,&lt;ref&gt;(Hargreaves, H. L. (1927). &quot;The faculty of imagination: An enquiry concerning the existence of a general faculty, or group factor, of imagination.&quot; British Journal of Psychology Monograph Supplement 3: 1-74.)&lt;/ref&gt; but it did not have the same impact.) Statistical analysis led to the recognition of creativity (as measured) as a separate aspect of human cognition to [[Intelligence quotient|IQ]]-type intelligence, into which it had previously been subsumed. Guilford's work suggested that above a threshold level of IQ, the relationship between creativity and classically measured intelligence broke down.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kozbelt&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Kozbelt|first=Aaron|title=The Cambridge Handbook of Creativity|year=2010|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|isbn=978-0-521-73025-9 |author2=Beghetto, Ronald A. |author3=Runco, Mark A.|editor=[[James C. Kaufman]] |editor2=Robert J. Sternberg|chapter=Theories of Creativity}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===&quot;Four C&quot; model===
[[James C. Kaufman]] and Beghetto introduced a &quot;four C&quot; model of creativity; ''mini-c'' (&quot;transformative learning&quot; involving &quot;personally meaningful interpretations of experiences, actions, and insights&quot;), ''little-c'' (everyday problem solving and creative expression), ''Pro-C'' (exhibited by people who are professionally or vocationally creative though not necessarily eminent) and ''Big-C'' (creativity considered great in the given field). This model was intended to help accommodate models and theories of creativity that stressed competence as an essential component and the historical transformation of a creative domain as the highest mark of creativity. It also, the authors argued, made a useful framework for analyzing creative processes in individuals.&lt;ref name=&quot;KaufBeg2009&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1037/a0013688|last=Kaufman|first=James C.|author2=Beghetto, Ronald A.|title=Beyond Big and Little: The Four C Model of Creativity|journal=[[Review of General Psychology]]|year=2009|volume=13|issue=1|pages=1–12|authorlink=James C. Kaufman}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The contrast of terms &quot;Big C&quot; and &quot;Little c&quot; has been widely used. Kozbelt, Beghetto and Runco use a little-c/Big-C model to review major theories of creativity.&lt;ref name=Kozbelt /&gt; [[Margaret Boden]] distinguishes between h-creativity (historical) and p-creativity (personal).&lt;ref name=&quot;Boden2004&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Boden|first=Margaret|title=The Creative Mind: Myths And Mechanisms|year=2004|publisher=Routledge|isbn=0-297-82069-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Robinson&lt;ref name=&quot;allourfutures&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Robinson|first=Ken|title=All our futures: Creativity, culture, education|year=1998|publisher=National Advisory Committee on Creative and Cultural Education|url=http://sirkenrobinson.com/skr/pdf/allourfutures.pdf|accessdate=2 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Anna Craft&lt;ref name=&quot;Craft1&quot; /&gt; have focused on creativity in a general population, particularly with respect to education. Craft makes a similar distinction between &quot;high&quot; and &quot;little c&quot; creativity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Craft1&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Craft|first=Anna|title=Creativity in education|year=2001|publisher=Continuum International|isbn=978-0-8264-4863-7 |editor=Craft, A. |editor2=Jeffrey, B. |editor3=Leibling, M. |chapter='Little C' creativity}}&lt;/ref&gt; and cites [[Ken Robinson (educationalist)|Ken Robinson]] as referring to &quot;high&quot; and &quot;democratic&quot; creativity. [[Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Csik1&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Csíkszentmihályi |first=Mihály|title=Creativity:Flow and the Psychology of Discovery and Invention|year=1996|publisher=Harper Collins|isbn=978-0-06-092820-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; has defined creativity in terms of those individuals judged to have made significant creative, perhaps domain-changing contributions. Simonton has analysed the career trajectories of eminent creative people in order to map patterns and predictors of creative productivity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Simonton97&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1037/0033-295X.104.1.66|last=Simonton|first=D. K.|title=Creative Productivity: A Predictive and Explanatory Model of Career Trajectories and Landmarks|journal=Psychological Review|year=1997|volume=104|issue=1|pages=66–89}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Theories of creative processes ==
There has been much empirical study in [[psychology]] and [[cognitive science]] of the processes through which creativity occurs. Interpretation of the results of these studies has led to several possible explanations of the sources and methods of creativity.

=== Incubation ===
Incubation is a temporary break from creative problem solving that can result in insight.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoC Incubation&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Smith|first=S. M.|title=Encyclopedia of Creativity Volume I|year=2011|publisher=Academic Press|isbn=978-0-12-375039-6|pages=653–657|edition=2nd|editor=M. A. Runco |editor2=S. R. Pritzker|chapter=Incubation}}&lt;/ref&gt; There has been some empirical research looking at whether, as the concept of &quot;incubation&quot; in Wallas' model implies, a period of interruption or rest from a problem may aid creative problem-solving. Ward&lt;ref name=&quot;Ward2003&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Ward, T. |year=2003 |chapter=Creativity |editor= Nagel, L. |title=Encyclopaedia of Cognition |location=New York |publisher=Macmillan}}&lt;/ref&gt; lists various hypotheses that have been advanced to explain why incubation may aid creative problem-solving, and notes how some [[empirical evidence]] is consistent with the hypothesis that incubation aids creative problem-solving in that it enables &quot;forgetting&quot; of misleading clues. Absence of incubation may lead the problem solver to become [[fixation (psychology)|fixated]] on inappropriate strategies of solving the problem.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith1995&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Smith|first=Steven M.|title=The Creative Cognition Approach|year=1995|publisher=[[MIT Press]]|editor=Steven M. Smith |editor2=Thomas B. Ward |editor3=Ronald A. Finke|chapter=Fixation, Incubation, and Insight in Memory and Creative Thinking}}&lt;/ref&gt; This work disputes the earlier hypothesis that creative solutions to problems arise mysteriously from the unconscious mind while the conscious mind is occupied on other tasks.&lt;ref name=Anderson2000&gt;&quot;{{cite book |author=Anderson, J. R. |year=2000 |title=Cognitive psychology and its implications |publisher=Worth Publishers |isbn=0-7167-1686-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
This earlier hypothesis is discussed in [[Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi|Csikszentmihalyi]]'s five phase model of the creative process which describes incubation as a time that your unconscious takes over. This allows for unique connections to be made without your consciousness trying to make logical order out of the problem.&lt;ref&gt;Csikszentmihalyi, Mihaly (1996). ''Creativity : Flow and the Psychology of Discovery and Invention.'' New York: Harper Perennial. ISBN 0-06-092820-4&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Convergent and divergent thinking ===
[[J. P. Guilford]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Guilford67&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Guilford, J. P. |year=1967 |title=The Nature of Human Intelligence |authorlink=J. P. Guilford}}&lt;/ref&gt; drew a distinction between [[convergent and divergent production]] (commonly renamed convergent and divergent thinking). Convergent thinking involves aiming for a single, correct solution to a problem, whereas divergent thinking involves creative generation of multiple answers to a set problem. Divergent thinking is sometimes used as a synonym for creativity in psychology literature. Other researchers have occasionally used the terms ''flexible'' thinking or [[fluid and crystallized intelligence|fluid intelligence]], which are roughly similar to (but not synonymous with) creativity.{{citation needed|date=June 2012}}

=== Creative cognition approach ===
In 1992, Finke et al. proposed the &quot;Geneplore&quot; model, in which creativity takes place in two phases: a generative phase, where an individual constructs mental representations called preinventive structures, and an exploratory phase where those structures are used to come up with creative ideas. Some evidence shows that when people use their imagination to develop new ideas, those ideas are heavily structured in predictable ways by the properties of existing categories and concepts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ward1995&quot;&gt;Ward, T.B. (1995). What’s old about new ideas. In S. M. Smith, T. B. Ward &amp; R. A. &amp; Finke (Eds.) ''The creative cognition approach'', 157–178, London: MIT Press.&lt;/ref&gt; Weisberg&lt;ref name=&quot;Weisberg93&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Weisberg, R. W. |year=1993 |title=Creativity: Beyond the myth of genius |publisher=Freeman |isbn=0-7167-2119-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; argued, by contrast, that creativity only involves ordinary cognitive processes yielding extraordinary results.

=== The Explicit–Implicit Interaction (EII) theory ===

Helie and Sun&lt;ref name=&quot;HelieSun2010&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Helie S. |author2=Sun R. | year = 2010 | title = Incubation, insight, and creative problem solving: A unified theory and a connectionist model | url = | journal = Psychological Review | volume = 117 | issue = | pages = 994–1024 | doi=10.1037/a0019532}}&lt;/ref&gt; recently proposed a unified framework for understanding [[creative problem-solving|creativity in problem solving]], namely the Explicit–Implicit Interaction (EII) theory of creativity. This new theory constitutes an attempt at providing a more unified explanation of relevant phenomena (in part by reinterpreting/integrating various fragmentary existing theories of [[Incubation (psychology)|incubation]] and [[insight]]).

The EII theory relies mainly on five basic principles, namely:
# The co-existence of and the difference between explicit and implicit knowledge; 
# The simultaneous involvement of implicit and explicit processes in most tasks; 
# The redundant representation of explicit and implicit knowledge; 
# The integration of the results of explicit and implicit processing;
# The iterative (and possibly bidirectional) processing. 
A computational implementation of the theory was developed based on the [[CLARION (cognitive architecture)|CLARION cognitive architecture]] and used to simulate relevant human data. This work represents an initial step in the development of process-based theories of creativity encompassing incubation, insight, and various other related phenomena.

=== Conceptual blending ===
{{Main article|Conceptual blending}}
In ''[[The Act of Creation]]'', [[Arthur Koestler]] introduced the concept of ''bisociation'' — that creativity arises as a result of the intersection of two quite different frames of reference.&lt;ref name=&quot;Koestler64&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Koestler, A. |title=The Act of Creation |year=1964 |authorlink=Arthur Koestler |isbn=0-330-73116-5 |publisher=Pan Books |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; This idea was later developed into conceptual blending. In the '90s, various approaches in cognitive science that dealt with [[metaphor]], [[analogy]], and [[structure mapping]] have been converging, and a new integrative approach to the study of creativity in science, art and humor has emerged under the label [[conceptual blending]].

=== Honing theory ===
Honing theory, developed principally by psychologist [[Liane Gabora]], posits that creativity arises due to the self-organizing, self-mending nature of a worldview. The creative process is a way in which the individual hones (and re-hones) an integrated worldview. Honing theory places emphasis not only on the externally visible creative outcome but also the internal cognitive restructuring and repair of the worldview brought about by the creative process. When faced with a creatively demanding task, there is an interaction between the conception of the task and the worldview. The conception of the task changes through interaction with the worldview, and the worldview changes through interaction with the task. This interaction is reiterated until the task is complete, at which point not only is the task conceived of differently, but the worldview is subtly or drastically transformed as it follows the natural tendency of a worldview to attempt to resolve dissonance and seek internal consistency amongst its components, whether they be ideas, attitudes, or bits of knowledge.

A central feature of honing theory is the notion of a potentiality state.&lt;ref&gt;Gabora, L. &amp; Saab, A. (2011). Creative interference and states of potentiality in analogy problem solving. ''Proceedings of the Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society''. July 20–23, 2011, Boston MA.&lt;/ref&gt; Honing theory posits that creative thought proceeds not by searching through and randomly ‘mutating’ predefined possibilities, but by drawing upon associations that exist due to overlap in the distributed neural cell assemblies that participate in the encoding of experiences in memory. Midway through the creative process one may have made associations between the current task and previous experiences, but not yet disambiguated which aspects of those previous experiences are relevant to the current task. Thus the creative idea may feel ‘half-baked’. It is at that point that it can be said to be in a potentiality state, because how it will actualize depends on the different internally or externally generated contexts it interacts with.

Honing theory is held to explain certain phenomena not dealt with by other theories of creativity, for example, how different works by the same creator are observed in studies to exhibit a recognizable style or 'voice' even through in different creative outlets. This is not predicted by theories of creativity that emphasize chance processes or the accumulation of expertise, but it is predicted by honing theory, according to which personal style reflects the creator's uniquely structured worldview. Another example is in the environmental stimulus for creativity. Creativity is commonly considered to be fostered by a supportive, nurturing, trustworthy environment conducive to self-actualization. However, research shows that creativity is also associated with childhood adversity, which would stimulate honing.

=== Everyday imaginative thought ===
In everyday thought, people often spontaneously imagine alternatives to reality when they think &quot;if only...&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Roese, N. J. &amp; Olson, J. M. (1995). ''What Might Have Been: The Social Psychology of Counterfactual Thinking''. Mahwah, New Jersey: Erlbaum&lt;/ref&gt; Their [[counterfactual thinking]] is viewed as an example of everyday creative processes.&lt;ref&gt;Markman, K. Klein, W. &amp; Suhr, E. (eds) (2009). ''Handbook of mental simulation and the human imagination.'' Hove, Psychology Press&lt;/ref&gt; It has been proposed that the creation of counterfactual alternatives to reality depends on similar cognitive processes to rational thought.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ruth M. J. Byrne|Byrne, R. M. J.]] (2005). The Rational Imagination: How People Create Counterfactual Alternatives to Reality. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Assessing individual creative ability ==

=== Creativity quotient ===
Several attempts have been made to develop a ''creativity quotient'' of an individual similar to the [[intelligence quotient]] (IQ); however, these have been unsuccessful.&lt;ref&gt;(Kraft, 2005)&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Psychometric approach ===
[[J. P. Guilford]]'s group,&lt;ref name=&quot;Guilford67&quot; /&gt; which pioneered the modern [[Psychometrics|psychometric]] study of creativity, constructed several tests to measure creativity in 1967:
* Plot Titles, where participants are given the plot of a story and asked to write original titles.
* Quick Responses is a word-association test scored for uncommonness.
* Figure Concepts, where participants were given simple drawings of objects and individuals and asked to find qualities or features that are common by two or more drawings; these were scored for uncommonness.
* Unusual Uses is finding unusual uses for common everyday objects such as bricks.
* Remote Associations, where participants are asked to find a word between two given words (e.g. Hand _____ Call)
* Remote Consequences, where participants are asked to generate a list of consequences of unexpected events (e.g. loss of gravity)

Building on Guilford's work, [[Ellis Paul Torrance|Torrance]]&lt;ref&gt;(Torrance, 1974)&lt;/ref&gt; developed the [[Torrance Tests of Creative Thinking]] in 1966.&lt;ref&gt;http://people.uncw.edu/caropresoe/GiftedFoundations/SocialEmotional/Creativity-articles/Kim_Can-we-trust-creativity-tests.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; They involved simple tests of divergent thinking and other problem-solving skills, which were scored on:
* '''Fluency''' – The total number of interpretable, meaningful, and relevant ideas generated in response to the stimulus.
* '''Originality''' – The statistical rarity of the responses among the test subjects.
* '''Elaboration''' – The amount of detail in the responses.

The [[Creativity Achievement Questionnaire]], a self-report test that measures creative achievement across 10 domains, was described in 2005 and shown to be reliable and valid when compared to other measures of creativity and to independent evaluation of creative output.&lt;ref&gt;(Carson, 2005)&lt;/ref&gt;

Such tests, sometimes called ''Divergent Thinking (DT)'' tests have been both supported&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Kim | first1 = K. H. | doi = 10.1207/s15326934crj1801_2 | title = Can We Trust Creativity Tests? A Review of the Torrance Tests of Creative Thinking (TTCT) | journal = Creativity Research Journal | volume = 18 | pages = 3–1 | year = 2006 | pmid =  | pmc = }}&lt;/ref&gt; and criticized.&lt;ref name=&quot;doi10.1080/10400419.2011.545713&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Zeng | first1 = L. | last2 = Proctor | first2 = R. W. | last3 = Salvendy | first3 = G. | title = Can Traditional Divergent Thinking Tests Be Trusted in Measuring and Predicting Real-World Creativity? | doi = 10.1080/10400419.2011.545713 | journal = Creativity Research Journal | volume = 23 | pages = 24 | year = 2011 | pmid =  | pmc = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Considerable progress has been made in automated scoring of [[divergent thinking]] tests using semantic approach. When compared to human raters, [[Natural language processing|NLP]] techniques were shown to be reliable and valid in scoring the originality (when compared to human raters).&lt;ref&gt;Forster, E. A., &amp; Dunbar, K. N. (2009). Creativity evaluation through latent semantic analysis. In Proceedings of the 31st Annual meeting of the Cognitive Science Society (pp. 602–607).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Harbison, I. J., &amp; Haarmann, H. (2014). Automated scoring of originality using semantic representations. In Proceedings of the 36th Annual meeting of the Cognitive Science Society (poster paper).&lt;/ref&gt; The reported computer programs were able to achieve a correlation of 0.60 and 0.72 respectively to human graders.

Semantic networks were also used to devise originality scores that yielded significant correlations with socio-personal measures.&lt;ref&gt;Acar, S., &amp; Runco, M. A. (2014). Assessing associative distance among ideas elicited by tests of Divergent Thinking. Creativity Research Journal 26(2), pp. 229-238.&lt;/ref&gt; Most recently, an NSF-funded&lt;ref&gt;NSF SBIR Grant Number 1315053.&lt;/ref&gt; team of researchers led by [[James C. Kaufman]] and Mark A. Runco&lt;ref&gt;Other members include Kenes Beketayev PhD Computer Science; Liberty Lidz, PhD Linguistics; Perman Gochyyev, PhD Statistics&lt;/ref&gt; combined expertise in creativity research, natural language processing, computational linguistics, and statistical data analysis to devise a scalable system for computerized automated testing (SparcIt Creativity Index Testing system). This system enabled automated scoring of [[Divergent thinking|DT]] tests that is reliable, objective, and scalable, thus addressing most of the issues of [[Divergent thinking|DT]] tests that had been found and reported.&lt;ref name=&quot;doi10.1080/10400419.2011.545713&quot; /&gt; The resultant computer system was able to achieve a correlation of 0.73 to human graders.&lt;ref&gt;Beketayev, K., &amp; Runco, M. A. (2016). Scoring Divergent Thinking Tests by Computer With a Semantics-Based Algorithm. ''Europe’s Journal of Psychology, 12''(2), 210-220.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Social-personality approach ===
Some researchers have taken a social-personality approach to the measurement of creativity. In these studies, personality traits such as independence of judgement, self-confidence, attraction to complexity, aesthetic orientation, and risk-taking are used as measures of the creativity of individuals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sternberg99&quot; /&gt; A [[meta-analysis]] by Gregory Feist showed that creative people tend to be &quot;more open to new experiences, less conventional and less conscientious, more self-confident, self-accepting, driven, ambitious, dominant, hostile, and impulsive.&quot; Openness, conscientiousness, self-acceptance, hostility, and impulsivity had the strongest effects of the traits listed.&lt;ref name=Feist /&gt; Within the framework of the [[Big Five personality traits|Big Five]] model of personality, some consistent traits have emerged.&lt;ref name=&quot;Batey, M. 2006 p. 355-429&quot;&gt;Batey, M. &amp; Furnham, A. (2006). Creativity, intelligence and personality: A critical review of the scattered literature. Genetic, Social, and General Psychology Monographs, 132, p. 355-429.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Openness to experience]] has been shown to be consistently related to a whole host of different assessments of creativity.&lt;ref&gt;Batey, M., Furnham, A. F. &amp; Safiullina, X. (2010). Intelligence, General Knowledge and Personality as Predictors of Creativity. Learning and Individual Differences, 20, p. 532-535.&lt;/ref&gt; Among the other Big Five traits, research has demonstrated subtle differences between different domains of creativity. Compared to non-artists, artists tend to have higher levels of openness to experience and lower levels of conscientiousness, while scientists are more open to experience, [[Conscientiousness|conscientious]], and higher in the confidence-dominance facets of extraversion compared to non-scientists.&lt;ref name=Feist&gt;Feist, G. J. (1998). A meta-analysis of the impact of personality on scientific and artistic creativity. Personality and Social Psychological Review, 2, 290–309.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Creativity and intelligence ==

The potential relationship between creativity and [[intelligence]] has been of interest since the late 1900s, when a multitude of influential studies – from Getzels &amp; Jackson,&lt;ref name=&quot;Getzels, J. W. 1962&quot;&gt;Getzels, J. W., &amp; Jackson, P. W. (1962). Creativity and intelligence: Explorations with gifted students. New York: Wiley.&lt;/ref&gt; Barron,&lt;ref name=&quot;Barron, F. 1963&quot;&gt;Barron, F. (1963). Creativity and psychological health. Princeton: D. Van Nostrand Company.&lt;/ref&gt; Wallach &amp; Kogan,&lt;ref name=&quot;Wallach, M. A. 1965&quot;&gt;Wallach, M. A., &amp; Kogan, N. (1965). Modes of thinking in young children: A study of the creativity-intelligence distinction. New York: Holt, Rinehart and Winston.&lt;/ref&gt; and Guilford&lt;ref name=&quot;Guilford, J. P. 1967&quot;&gt;Guilford, J. P. (1967). The nature of human intelligence. New York: McGraw-Hill.&lt;/ref&gt; – focused not only on creativity, but also on intelligence. This joint focus highlights both the theoretical and practical importance of the relationship: researchers are interested not only if the constructs are related, but also how and why.&lt;ref&gt;Plucker, J., &amp; Renzulli, J. S. (1999). Psychometric approaches to the study of human creativity. In R. J. Sternberg (Ed.), Handbook of creativity (pp. 35–60). New York: Cambridge University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;

There are multiple theories accounting for their relationship, with the 3 main theories as follows:

*Threshold Theory – Intelligence is a necessary, but not sufficient condition for creativity. There is a moderate positive relationship between creativity and intelligence until IQ ~120.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barron, F. 1963&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Guilford, J. P. 1967&quot; /&gt;
*Certification Theory – Creativity is not intrinsically related to intelligence. Instead, individuals are required to meet the requisite level intelligence in order to gain a certain level of education/work, which then in turn offers the opportunity to be creative. Displays of creativity are moderated by intelligence.&lt;ref&gt;Hayes, J. R. (1989). Cognitive processes in creativity. In J. A. Glover, R. R. Ronning, &amp; C. R. Reynolds (Eds.), Handbook of creativity (pp. 135–145). New York: Plenum.&lt;/ref&gt;
*Interference Theory – Extremely high intelligence might interfere with creative ability.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sternberg, R. J. 1996&quot;&gt;Sternberg, R. J. (1996). Successful Intelligence. NewYork: Simon &amp; Schuster.&lt;/ref&gt;

Sternberg and O’Hara&lt;ref name=&quot;Sternberg, R. J. 1999 pp. 251&quot;&gt;Sternberg, R. J., &amp; O’Hara, L. A. (1999). Creativity and intelligence. In R. J. Sternberg (Ed.), Handbook of creativity (pp. 251–272). Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; proposed a framework of 5 possible relationships between creativity and intelligence:
#Creativity is a subset of intelligence
#Intelligence is a subset of creativity
#Creativity and intelligence are overlapping constructs
#Creativity and intelligence are part of the same construct (coincident sets)
#Creativity and intelligence are distinct constructs (disjoint sets)

=== Creativity as a subset of intelligence ===

A number of researchers include creativity, either explicitly or implicitly, as a key component of intelligence.

''Examples of theories that include creativity as a subset of intelligence''

*Gardner’s  [[Theory of multiple intelligences]] (MIT)&lt;ref&gt;Gardner, H. (1993). Creating minds. New York: Basic Books.&lt;/ref&gt; – implicitly includes creativity as a subset of MIT. To demonstrate this, Gardner cited examples of different famous creators, each of whom differed in their types of intelligences e.g. Picasso (spatial intelligence); Freud (intrapersonal); Einstein (logical-mathematical); and Gandhi (interpersonal).
*Sternberg’s Theory of Successful intelligence&lt;ref name=&quot;Sternberg, R. J. 1996&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sternberg, R. J. 1999 pp. 251&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sternberg, R. J., Kaufman, J. C., &amp; Grigorenko, E. L. (2008). Applied intelligence. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; (see [[Triarchic theory of intelligence]]) includes creativity as a main component, and comprises 3 sub-theories: Componential (Analytic), Contextual (Practical), and Experiential (Creative). Experiential sub-theory – the ability to use pre-existing knowledge and skills to solve new and novel problems – is directly related to creativity.
*The [[Cattell–Horn–Carroll theory]] includes creativity as a subset of intelligence. Specifically, it is associated with the broad group factor of long-term storage and retrieval (Glr). Glr narrow abilities relating to creativity include:&lt;ref&gt;Kaufman, J. C., Kaufman, S. B., &amp; Lichtenberger, E. O. (2011). Finding creativity on intelligence tests via divergent production. Canadian Journal of School Psychology, 26, 83–106.&lt;/ref&gt; ideational fluency, associational fluency, and originality/creativity. Silvia et al.&lt;ref&gt;Silvia, P. J., Beaty, R. E., &amp; Nusbaum, E. C. (2013). Verbal fluency and creativity: General and specific contributions of broad retrieval ability (Gr) factors to divergent thinking. Intelligence, 41, 328–340.&lt;/ref&gt; conducted a study to look at the relationship between divergent thinking and verbal fluency tests, and reported that both fluency and originality in divergent thinking were significantly affected by the broad level Glr factor. Martindale&lt;ref&gt;Martindale, C. (1999). Biological bases of creativity. In R. J. Sternberg (Ed.), Handbook of creativity (pp. 137– 152). New York: Cambridge University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; extended the CHC-theory in the sense that it was proposed that those individuals who are creative are also selective in their processing speed Martindale argues that in the creative process, larger amounts of information are processed more slowly in the early stages, and as the individual begins to understand the problem, the processing speed is increased.
*The Dual Process Theory of Intelligence&lt;ref&gt;Kaufman, J.C., Kaufman, S.B., &amp; Plucker, J.A. (2013). Contemporary theories of intelligence. In J. Reisberg (Ed.), The Oxford Handbook of Cognitive Psychology (pp. 811-822). New York, NY: Oxford University Press&lt;/ref&gt; posits a two-factor/type model of intelligence. Type 1 is a conscious process, and concerns goal directed thoughts, which are explained by ''g''. Type 2 is an unconscious process, and concerns spontaneous cognition, which encompasses daydreaming and implicit learning ability. Kaufman argues that creativity occurs as a result of Type 1 and Type 2 processes working together in combination. The use of each type in the creative process can be used to varying degrees.

=== Intelligence as a subset of creativity ===

In this relationship model, intelligence is a key component in the development of creativity.

''Theories of creativity that include intelligence as a subset of creativity''

*Sternberg &amp; Lubart’s Investment Theory.&lt;ref&gt;Sternberg, R. J. and Lubart, T. I. (1991). An investment theory of creativity and its development, Human Development, 34, 1-32.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sternberg, R. J. and Lubart, T. I. (1992). Buy low and sell high: An investment approach to creativity, Current Directions in Psychological Science, 1 (1), 1-5.&lt;/ref&gt; Using the metaphor of a stock market, they demonstrate that creative thinkers are like good investors – they buy low and sell high (in their ideas). Like under/low-valued stock, creative individuals generate unique ideas that are initially rejected by other people. The creative individual has to persevere, and convince the others of the ideas value. After convincing the others, and thus increasing the ideas value, the creative individual ‘sells high’ by leaving the idea with the other people, and moves onto generating another idea. According to this theory, six distinct, but related elements contribute to successful creativity: intelligence, knowledge, thinking styles, personality, motivation, and environment. Intelligence is just one of the six factors that can either solely, or in conjunction with the other five factors, generate creative thoughts.
*Amabile’s Componential Model of Creativity.&lt;ref&gt;Amabile, T. M. (1982). Social psychology of creativity: A consensual assessment technique. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 43, 997–1013.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Amabile, T. M. (1996). Creativity in context: Update to “The Social Psychology of Creativity”. Boulder: Westview Press.&lt;/ref&gt; In this model, there are 3 within-individual components needed for creativity – domain-relevant skills, creativity-relevant processes, and task motivation – and 1 component external to the individual: their surrounding social environment. Creativity requires a confluence of all components. High creativity will result when an individual is: intrinsically motivated, possesses both a high level of domain-relevant skills and has high skills in creative thinking, and is working in a highly creative environment.
*Amusement Park Theoretical Model.&lt;ref&gt;Baer, J., &amp; Kaufman, J. C. (2005). Bridging generality and specificity: The Amusement Park Theoretical (APT) Model of creativity. Roeper Review, 27, 158–163.&lt;/ref&gt; In this 4-step theory, both domain-specific and generalist views are integrated into a model of creativity. The researchers make use of the metaphor of the amusement park to demonstrate that within each of these creative levels, intelligence plays a key role:
**To get into the amusement park, there are initial requirements (e.g., time/transport to go to the park). Initial requirements (like intelligence) are necessary, but not sufficient for creativity. They are more like prerequisites for creativity, and if an individual does not possess the basic level of the initial requirement (intelligence), then they will not be able to generate creative thoughts/behaviour.
**Secondly are the subcomponents – general thematic areas – that increase in specificity. Like choosing which type of amusement park to visit (e.g. a zoo or a water park), these areas relate to the areas in which someone could be creative (e.g. poetry).
**Thirdly, there are specific domains. After choosing the type of park to visit e.g. waterpark, you then have to choose which specific park to go to. Within the poetry domain, there are many different types (e.g. free verse, riddles, sonnet, etc.) that have to be selected from.
**Lastly, there are micro-domains. These are the specific tasks that reside within each domain e.g. individual lines in a free verse poem / individual rides at the waterpark.

=== Creativity and intelligence as overlapping yet distinct constructs ===

This possible relationship concerns creativity and intelligence as distinct, but intersecting constructs.

''Theories that include Creativity and Intelligence as Overlapping Yet Distinct Constructs''

*Renzulli’s Three-Ring Conception of Giftedness.&lt;ref&gt;Renzulli, J. S. (1978). What makes giftedness? Reexamining a definition. Phi Delta Kappan, 60, 180–261.&lt;/ref&gt; In this conceptualisation, giftedness occurs as a result from the overlap of above average intellectual ability, creativity, and task commitment. Under this view, creativity and intelligence are distinct constructs, but they do overlap under the correct conditions.
*[[PASS theory of intelligence]]. In this theory, the planning component – relating to the ability to solve problems, make decisions and take action – strongly overlaps with the concept of creativity.&lt;ref&gt;Naglieri, J. A., &amp; Kaufman, J. C. (2001). Understanding intelligence, giftedness, and creativity using PASS theory. Roeper Review, 23, 151–156.&lt;/ref&gt;
*Threshold Theory (TT). A number of previous research findings have suggested that a threshold exists in the relationship between creativity and intelligence – both constructs are moderately positively correlated up to an IQ of ~120. Above this threshold of an IQ of 120, if there is a relationship at all, it is small and weak.&lt;ref name=&quot;Getzels, J. W. 1962&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Barron, F. 1963&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Torrance, E. P. (1962). Guiding creative talent. Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice-Hall.&lt;/ref&gt; TT posits that a moderate level of intelligence is necessary for creativity.

In support of the TT, Barron&lt;ref name=&quot;Barron, F. 1963&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Barron, F. (1969). Creative person and creative process. New York: Holt, Rinehart &amp; Winston.&lt;/ref&gt; reported finding a non-significant correlation between creativity and intelligence in a gifted sample; and a significant correlation in a non-gifted sample. Yamamoto&lt;ref&gt;Yamamoto, K. (1964). Creativity and sociometric choice among adolescents. Journal of Social Psychology, 64, 249–261.&lt;/ref&gt; in a sample of secondary school children, reported a significant correlation between creativity and intelligence of ''r'' = .3, and reported no significant correlation when the sample consisted of gifted children. Fuchs-Beauchamp et al.&lt;ref&gt;Fuchs-Beauchamp, K. D., Karnes, M. B., &amp; Johnson, L. J. (1993). Creativity and intelligence in preschoolers. Gifted Child Quarterly, 37, 113–117.&lt;/ref&gt; in a sample of preschoolers found that creativity and intelligence correlated from ''r'' = .19 to ''r'' = .49 in the group of children who had an IQ below the threshold; and in the group above the threshold, the correlations were ''r'' = &lt;.12. Cho et al.&lt;ref&gt;Cho, S. H., Nijenhuis, J. T., van Vianen, N. E. M., Kim, H.-B., &amp; Lee, K. H. (2010). The relationship between diverse components of intelligence and creativity. Journal of Creative Behavior, 44, 125–137.&lt;/ref&gt; reported a correlation of .40 between creativity and intelligence in the average IQ group of a sample of adolescents and adults; and a correlation of close to ''r'' = .0 for the high IQ group. Jauk et al.&lt;ref&gt;Jauk, E., Benedek, M., Dunst, B., &amp; Neubauer, A. C. (2013). The relationship between intelligence and creativity: New support for the threshold hypothesis by means of empirical breakpoint detection. Intelligence, 41, 212–221.&lt;/ref&gt; found support for the TT, but only for measures of creative potential; not creative performance.

Much modern day research reports findings against TT. Wai et al.&lt;ref&gt;Wai, J., Lubinski, D., &amp; Benbow, C. P. (2005). Creativity and occupational accomplishments among intellectually precocious youths: An age 13 to age 33 longitudinal study. Journal of Educational Psychology, 97, 484–492.&lt;/ref&gt; in a study using data from the longitudinal Study of Mathematically Precocious Youth – a cohort of elite students from early adolescence into adulthood – found that differences in SAT scores at age 13 were predictive of creative real-life outcomes 20 years later. Kim’s&lt;ref&gt;Kim, K. H. (2005). Can only intelligent people be creative? Journal of Secondary Gifted Education, 16, 57–66.&lt;/ref&gt; meta-analysis of 21 studies did not find any supporting evidence for TT, and instead negligible correlations were reported between intelligence, creativity, and divergent thinking both below and above IQ's of 120. Preckel et al.,&lt;ref&gt;Preckel, F., Holling, H., &amp; Wiese, M. (2006). Relationship of intelligence and creativity in gifted and non-gifted students: An investigation of threshold theory. Personality and Individual Differences, 40, 159–170.&lt;/ref&gt; investigating fluid intelligence and creativity, reported small correlations of ''r'' = .3 to ''r'' = .4 across all levels of cognitive ability.

=== Creativity and intelligence as coincident sets ===

Under this view, researchers posit that there are no differences in the mechanisms underlying creativity in those used in normal problem solving; and in normal problem solving, there is no need for creativity. Thus, creativity and Intelligence (problem solving) are the same thing. Perkins&lt;ref&gt;Perkins, D. N. (1981) The mind’s best work. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; referred to this as the ‘nothing-special’ view.

Weisberg &amp; Alba&lt;ref&gt;Weisberg, R. W. &amp; Alba, J. W. (1981). An examination of the alleged role of “fixation” in the solution of several “insight” problems. Journal of Experimental Psychology: General, 110, 169 – 192.&lt;/ref&gt; examined problem solving by having participants complete the 9-dot problem (see [[Thinking outside the box#Nine dots puzzle]]) – where the participants are asked to connect all 9 dots in the 3 rows of 3 dots using 4 straight lines or less, without lifting their pen or tracing the same line twice. The problem can only be solved if the lines go outside the boundaries of the square of dots. Results demonstrated that even when participants were given this insight, they still found it difficult to solve the problem, thus showing that to successfully complete the task it is not just insight (or creativity) that is required.

=== Creativity and intelligence as disjoint sets ===

In this view, creativity and intelligence are completely different, unrelated constructs.

Getzels and Jackson&lt;ref name=&quot;Getzels, J. W. 1962&quot; /&gt; administered 5 creativity measures to a group of 449 children from grades 6-12, and compared these test findings to results from previously administered (by the school) IQ tests. They found that the correlation between the creativity measures and IQ was ''r'' = .26. The high creativity group scored in the top 20% of the overall creativity measures, but were not included in the top 20% of IQ scorers. The high intelligence group scored the opposite: they scored in the top 20% for IQ, but were outside the top 20% scorers for creativity, thus showing that creativity and intelligence are distinct and unrelated.

However, this work has been heavily criticised. Wallach and Kogan&lt;ref name=&quot;Wallach, M. A. 1965&quot; /&gt; highlighted that the creativity measures were not only weakly related to one another (to the extent that they were no more related to one another than they were with IQ), but they seemed to also draw upon non-creative skills. McNemar&lt;ref&gt;McNemar, O. (1964) Lost: Our Intelligence? Why? American Psychologist, 19, 871 – 882.&lt;/ref&gt; noted that there were major measurement issues, in that the IQ scores were a mixture from 3 different IQ tests.

Wallach and Kogan&lt;ref name=&quot;Wallach, M. A. 1965&quot; /&gt; administered 5 measures of creativity, each of which resulted in a score for originality and fluency; and 10 measures of general intelligence to 151 5th grade children. These tests were untimed, and given in a game-like manner (aiming to facilitate creativity). Inter-correlations between creativity tests were on average ''r'' = .41. Inter-correlations between intelligence measures were on average ''r'' = .51 with each other. Creativity tests and intelligence measures correlated ''r'' = .09.

== Neuroscience ==
The [[neuroscience]] of creativity looks at the operation of the brain during creative behaviour. It has been addressed&lt;ref name=&quot;NeuroPsychiatry&quot;&gt;[http://neurology.med.ohio-state.edu/cognitivelab/CreativityMechanisms.pdf Kenneth M Heilman, MD, Stephen E. Nadeau, MD, and David Q. Beversdorf, MD. &quot;Creative Innovation: Possible Brain Mechanisms&quot; Neurocase (2003)]&lt;/ref&gt; in the article &quot;Creative Innovation: Possible Brain Mechanisms.&quot; The authors write that &quot;creative innovation might require coactivation and communication between regions of the brain that ordinarily are not strongly connected.&quot; Highly creative people who excel at creative innovation tend to differ from others in three ways:
* they have a high level of specialized knowledge,
* they are capable of [[convergent and divergent production|divergent thinking]] mediated by the [[frontal lobe]].
* and they are able to modulate [[neurotransmitter]]s such as [[norepinephrine]] in their frontal lobe.

Thus, the frontal lobe appears to be the part of the [[cerebral cortex|cortex]] that is most important for creativity.

This article also explored the links between creativity and sleep, [[mood disorder|mood]] and [[substance dependence|addiction disorders]], and [[depression (mood)|depression]].

In 2005, Alice Flaherty presented a three-factor model of the creative drive. Drawing from evidence in brain imaging, drug studies and lesion analysis, she described the creative drive as resulting from an interaction of the frontal lobes, the [[temporal lobe]]s, and [[dopamine]] from the [[limbic system]]. The frontal lobes can be seen as responsible for idea generation, and the temporal lobes for idea editing and evaluation. Abnormalities in the frontal lobe (such as depression or anxiety) generally decrease creativity, while abnormalities in the temporal lobe often increase creativity. High activity in the temporal lobe typically inhibits activity in the frontal lobe, and vice versa. High dopamine levels increase general [[arousal]] and goal directed behaviors and reduce [[latent inhibition]], and all three effects increase the drive to generate ideas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Flaherty AW | year = 2005 | title = Frontotemporal and dopaminergic control of idea generation and creative drive | url = | journal = J Comp Neurol | volume = 493 | issue = 1| pages = 147–53 | pmid = 16254989 | pmc = 2571074 | doi=10.1002/cne.20768}}&lt;/ref&gt;  A 2015 study on creativity found that it involves the interaction of multiple neural networks, including the those that support associative thinking, along with other [[default mode network]] functions.&lt;ref name=PMID_26003860&gt;{{ cite journal |last1 = Mayseless |first1 = Naama |last2 = Eran |first2 = Ayelet |last3 = Shamay-Tsoory |first3 = Simone G |year = 2015 |title = Generating original ideas: The neural underpinning of originality. |journal = NeuroImage |quote = These results are in line with the dual model of creativity, according to which original ideas are a product of the interaction between a system that generates ideas and a control system that evaluates these ideas. |laysummary = http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26003860 |doi = 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2015.05.030|pmid = 26003860 |pages = 232–9 |volume = 116 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Working memory and the cerebellum ===
Vandervert&lt;ref&gt;Vandervert 2003a, 2003b; Vandervert, Schimpf &amp; Liu, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; described how the brain's frontal lobes and the cognitive functions of the [[cerebellum]] collaborate to produce creativity and innovation. Vandervert's explanation rests on considerable evidence that all processes of [[working memory]] (responsible for processing all thought&lt;ref&gt;Miyake &amp; Shah, 1999&lt;/ref&gt;) are adaptively modeled for increased efficiency by the cerebellum.&lt;ref&gt;Schmahmann, 1997, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; The cerebellum (consisting of 100 billion neurons, which is more than the entirety of the rest of the brain&lt;ref&gt;Andersen, Korbo &amp; Pakkenberg, 1992.&lt;/ref&gt;) is also widely known to adaptively model all bodily movement for efficiency. The cerebellum's adaptive models of working memory processing are then fed back to especially frontal lobe working memory control processes&lt;ref&gt;Miller &amp; Cohen, 2001&lt;/ref&gt; where creative and innovative thoughts arise.&lt;ref&gt;Vandervert, 2003a&lt;/ref&gt; (Apparently, creative insight or the &quot;aha&quot; experience is then triggered in the temporal lobe.&lt;ref&gt;Jung-Beeman, Bowden, Haberman, Frymiare, Arambel-Liu, Greenblatt, Reber &amp; Kounios, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;)

According to Vandervert, the details of creative adaptation begin in &quot;forward&quot; cerebellar models which are anticipatory/exploratory controls for movement and thought. These cerebellar processing and control architectures have been termed Hierarchical Modular Selection and Identification for Control (HMOSAIC).&lt;ref&gt;Imamizu, Kuroda, Miyauchi, Yoshioka &amp; Kawato, 2003&lt;/ref&gt; New, hierarchically arranged levels of the cerebellar control architecture (HMOSAIC) develop as mental mulling in working memory is extended over time. These new levels of the control architecture are fed forward to the frontal lobes. Since the cerebellum adaptively models all movement and all levels of thought and emotion,&lt;ref&gt;Schmahmann, 2004,&lt;/ref&gt; Vandervert's approach helps explain creativity and innovation in sports, art, music, the design of video games, technology, mathematics, the [[child prodigy]], and thought in general.

Essentially, Vandervert has argued that when a person is confronted with a challenging new situation, visual-spatial working memory and speech-related working memory are decomposed and re-composed (fractionated) by the cerebellum and then blended in the cerebral cortex in an attempt to deal with the new situation. With repeated attempts to deal with challenging situations, the cerebro-cerebellar blending process continues to optimize the efficiency of how working memory deals with the situation or problem.&lt;ref&gt;Vandervert, in press-a&lt;/ref&gt; Most recently, he has argued that this is the same process (only involving visual-spatial working memory and pre-language vocalization) that led to the evolution of language in humans.&lt;ref&gt;Vandervert, 2011, in press-b&lt;/ref&gt; Vandervert and Vandervert-Weathers have pointed out that this blending process, because it continuously optimizes efficiencies, constantly improves prototyping attempts toward the invention or innovation of new ideas, music, art, or technology.&lt;ref&gt;Vandervert &amp; Vandervert-Weathers, 2013&lt;/ref&gt; Prototyping, they argue, not only produces new products, it trains the cerebro-cerebellar pathways involved to become more efficient at prototyping itself. Further, Vandervert and Vandervert-Weathers believe that this repetitive &quot;mental prototyping&quot; or mental rehearsal involving the cerebellum and the cerebral cortex explains the success of the self-driven, individualized patterning of repetitions initiated by the teaching methods of the [[Khan Academy]]. The model proposed by Vandervert has, however, received incisive critique from several authors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Brown | first1 = J. | year = 2007 | title = On Vandervert et al. &quot;Working memory cerebellum, and creativity&quot; | url = | journal = Creat. Res. J. | volume = 19 | issue = | pages = 25–29 | doi=10.1080/10400410709336875|display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Abraham | first1 = A. | year = 2007 | title = Can a neural system geared to bring about rapid, predictive, and efficient function explain creativity? | url = | journal = Creat. Res. J. | volume = 19 | issue = | pages = 19–24 | doi=10.1080/10400410709336874}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== REM sleep ===
Creativity involves the forming of associative elements into new combinations that are useful or meet some requirement. Sleep aids this process.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.1038/nature02223 |author1=Wagner U. |author2=Gais S. |author3=Haider H. |author4=Verleger R. |author5=Born J. | year = 2004 | title = Sleep inspires insight | url = | journal = Nature | volume = 427 | issue = 6972| pages = 352–5 | pmid = 14737168 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Rapid eye movement sleep|REM]] rather than [[Non-rapid eye movement sleep|NREM sleep]] appears to be responsible.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cai&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0900271106 |author1=Cai D. J. |author2=Mednick S. A. |author3=Harrison E. M. |author4=Kanady J. C. |author5=Mednick S. C. | year = 2009 | title = REM, not incubation, improves creativity by priming associative networks | url = | journal = Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A | volume = 106 | issue = 25| pages = 10130–10134 | pmid = 19506253 | pmc = 2700890 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Walker MP, Liston C, Hobson JA, Stickgold R |title=Cognitive flexibility across the sleep-wake cycle: REM-sleep enhancement of anagram problem solving |journal=Brain Res Cogn Brain Res |volume=14 |issue=3 |pages=317–24 |date=November 2002 |pmid=12421655 |doi= 10.1016/S0926-6410(02)00134-9|url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; This has been suggested to be due to changes in [[cholinergic]] and [[Norepinephrine|noradrenergic]] [[neuromodulation]] that occurs during REM sleep.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cai&quot; /&gt; During this period of sleep, high levels of acetylcholine in the [[hippocampus]] suppress feedback from the hippocampus to the [[neocortex]], and lower levels of acetylcholine and norepinephrine in the neocortex encourage the spread of associational activity within neocortical areas without control from the hippocampus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Hasselmo ME | authorlink=Michael Hasselmo |title=Neuromodulation: acetylcholine and memory consolidation |journal=Trends Cogn. Sci. (Regul. Ed.) |volume=3 |issue=9 |pages=351–359 |date=September 1999 |pmid=10461198 |doi= 10.1016/S1364-6613(99)01365-0|url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is in contrast to waking consciousness, where higher levels of norepinephrine and acetylcholine inhibit recurrent connections in the neocortex. It is proposed that REM sleep adds creativity by allowing &quot;neocortical structures to reorganize associative hierarchies, in which information from the hippocampus would be reinterpreted in relation to previous semantic representations or nodes.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cai&quot; /&gt;

== Affect ==
Some theories suggest that creativity may be particularly susceptible to affective influence. As noted in [[voting behavior]], the term &quot;affect&quot; in this context can refer to liking or disliking key aspects of the subject in question. This work largely follows from findings in psychology regarding the ways in which affective states are involved in human judgment and decision-making.&lt;ref name=Winkielman2007&gt;{{Citation
 | title = Affective Influence on Judgments and Decisions: Moving Towards Core Mechanisms
 | last1 = Winkielman | first1 = P.
 | last2 = Knutson | first2 = B.
 | year = 2007
 | journal = Review of General Psychology | volume = 11 | number = 2 | pages = 179–192 | doi=10.1037/1089-2680.11.2.179
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Positive affect relations ===
According to [[Alice M. Isen|Alice Isen]], positive affect has three primary effects on cognitive activity:
# Positive affect makes additional cognitive material available for processing, increasing the number of cognitive elements available for association;
# Positive affect leads to defocused attention and a more complex cognitive context, increasing the breadth of those elements that are treated as relevant to the problem;
# Positive affect increases cognitive flexibility, increasing the probability that diverse cognitive elements will in fact become associated. Together, these processes lead positive affect to have a positive influence on creativity.

[[Barbara Fredrickson]] in her [[broaden-and-build]] model suggests that positive emotions such as joy and love broaden a person's available repertoire of cognitions and actions, thus enhancing creativity.

According to these researchers, positive emotions increase the number of cognitive elements available for association (attention scope) and the number of elements that are relevant to the problem (cognitive scope).

Various meta-analyses, such as Baas et al. (2008) of 66 studies about creativity and affect support the link between creativity and positive affect.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Mark A. Davis |title=Understanding the relationship between mood and creativity: A meta-analysis |journal=Organizational Behavior and Human Decision Processes |volume=100 |issue=1 |pages=25–38 |date=January 2009 |doi=10.1016/j.obhdp.2008.04.001 |url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science?_ob=ArticleURL&amp;_udi=B6WP2-4SJR2DD-2&amp;_user=10&amp;_coverDate=01%2F31%2F2009&amp;_rdoc=1&amp;_fmt=high&amp;_orig=search&amp;_origin=search&amp;_sort=d&amp;_docanchor=&amp;view=c&amp;_searchStrId=1591960036&amp;_rerunOrigin=scholar.google&amp;_acct=C000050221&amp;_version=1&amp;_urlVersion=0&amp;_userid=10&amp;md5=124ef41f3adc2879e442ae692bd64fc1&amp;searchtype=a}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;positive&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Baas, Matthijs |author2=De Dreu Carsten K. W. |author3=Nijstad, Bernard A. |lastauthoramp=yes |title=A meta-analysis of 25 years of mood-creativity research: Hedonic tone, activation, or regulatory focus? |journal=Psychological Bulletin |volume=134 |issue=6 |pages=779–806 |date=November 2008 |doi=10.1037/a0012815 |url=http://home.medewerker.uva.nl/m.baas/bestanden/MBaas_mood-creativity.pdf |pmid=18954157}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Creativity and artificial intelligence ==
[[Jürgen Schmidhuber]]'s formal [[theory]] of creativity&lt;ref&gt;Schmidhuber, Jürgen (2006), Developmental Robotics, Optimal Artificial Curiosity, Creativity, Music, and the Fine Arts. Connection Science, 18(2): 173-187&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Schmidhuber, Jürgen (2010), Formal Theory of Creativity, Fun, and Intrinsic Motivation (1990–2010). IEEE Transactions on Autonomous Mental Development, 2(3):230-247&lt;/ref&gt; postulates that creativity, curiosity, and interestingness are by-products of a simple [[Computational learning theory|computational]] principle for measuring and optimizing learning progress. Consider an agent able to manipulate its environment and thus its own [[sensory system|sensory]] inputs. The agent can use a [[black box]] optimization method such as [[reinforcement learning]] to learn (through informed trial and error) sequences of actions that maximize the expected sum of its future [[reward system|reward]] signals. There are extrinsic reward signals for achieving externally given goals, such as finding food when hungry. But Schmidhuber's [[Loss function|objective function]] to be maximized also includes an additional, intrinsic term to model &quot;wow-effects.&quot; This non-standard term motivates purely creative behavior of the agent even when there are no external goals. A wow-effect is formally defined as follows. As the agent is creating and predicting and encoding the continually growing history of actions and sensory inputs, it keeps improving the predictor or encoder, which can be implemented as an [[artificial neural network]] or some other [[machine learning]] device that can exploit regularities in the data to improve its performance over time. The improvements can be measured precisely, by computing the difference in computational costs (storage size, number of required synapses, errors, time) needed to encode new observations before and after learning. This difference depends on the encoder's present subjective knowledge, which changes over time, but the theory formally takes this into account. The cost difference measures the strength of the present &quot;wow-effect&quot; due to sudden improvements in [[data compression]] or computational speed. It becomes an intrinsic reward signal for the action selector. The objective function thus motivates the action optimizer to create action sequences causing more wow-effects. Irregular, random data (or noise) do not permit any wow-effects or learning progress, and thus are &quot;boring&quot; by nature (providing no reward). Already known and predictable regularities also are boring. Temporarily interesting are only the initially unknown, novel, regular patterns in both actions and observations. This motivates the agent to perform continual, open-ended, active, creative exploration.

According to Schmidhuber, his objective function explains the activities of scientists, artists, and [[comedian]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Video of [[Jürgen Schmidhuber]]'s keynote at the 2011 Winter Intelligence Conference, Oxford: [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fnbZzcruGu0 Universal AI and Theory of Fun and Creativity. Youtube, 2012]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Video of [[Jürgen Schmidhuber]]'s talk at the 2009 [[Singularity Summit]], NYC: [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ipomu0MLFaI Compression Progress: The Algorithmic Principle Behind Curiosity and Creativity. Youtube, 2010]&lt;/ref&gt;
For example, [[physicist]]s are motivated to create experiments leading to observations obeying previously unpublished [[physical law]]s permitting better [[data compression]]. Likewise, composers receive intrinsic reward for creating non-arbitrary melodies with unexpected but regular harmonies that permit wow-effects through data compression improvements.
Similarly, a comedian gets intrinsic reward for &quot;inventing a novel joke with an unexpected [[punch line]], related to the beginning of the story in an initially unexpected but quickly learnable way that also allows for better compression of the perceived data.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Kurzweil AI: [http://www.kurzweilai.net/when-creative-machines-overtake-man Transcript] of [[Jürgen Schmidhuber]]'s TEDx talk (2012): [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KQ35zNlyG-o&amp;list=PL194623EBA834DB77&amp;index=11 When creative machines overtake man]&lt;/ref&gt;
Schmidhuber argues that ongoing [[computer hardware]] advances will greatly scale up rudimentary [[artificial intelligence|artificial]] scientists and artists{{clarify|date=January 2013}} based on simple implementations of the basic principle since 1990.&lt;ref&gt;Schmidhuber, J. (1991), Curious model-building control systems. In Proc. ICANN, Singapore, volume 2, pp 1458–1463. IEEE.&lt;/ref&gt;
He used the theory to create [[low-complexity art]]&lt;ref&gt;Schmidhuber, J. (2012), A Formal Theory of Creativity to Model the Creation of Art. In McCormack, Jon and M. d'Inverno (eds), Computers and Creativity, Springer 2012&lt;/ref&gt; and an attractive [[Face|human face]].&lt;ref&gt;Schmidhuber, J. (2007), Simple Algorithmic Principles of Discovery, Subjective Beauty, Selective Attention, Curiosity &amp; Creativity. In V. Corruble, M. Takeda, E. Suzuki, eds., Proc. 10th Intl. Conf. on Discovery Science 2007 pp 26-38, LNAI 4755, Springer&lt;/ref&gt;

== Mental health ==
{{Main article|Creativity and mental illness}}
A study by psychologist [[J. Philippe Rushton]] found creativity to correlate with [[intelligence]] and [[psychoticism]].&lt;ref&gt;(Rushton, 1990)&lt;/ref&gt; Another study found creativity to be greater in [[Schizotypal personality disorder|schizotypal]] than in either normal or [[Schizophrenia|schizophrenic]] individuals. While divergent thinking was associated with bilateral activation of the [[prefrontal cortex]], schizotypal individuals were found to have much greater activation of their ''right'' prefrontal cortex.&lt;ref&gt;http://exploration.vanderbilt.edu/news/news_schizotypes.htm ([http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.schres.2005.06.016 Actual paper])&lt;/ref&gt; This study hypothesizes that such individuals are better at accessing both hemispheres, allowing them to make novel associations at a faster rate. In agreement with this hypothesis, [[ambidexterity]] is also associated with [[Schizotypal personality disorder|schizotypal]] and [[Schizophrenia|schizophrenic]] individuals. Three recent studies by Mark Batey and Adrian Furnham have demonstrated the relationships between schizotypal&lt;ref&gt;Batey, M. Furnham, A. (2009). The relationship between creativity, schizotypy and intelligence. Individual Differences Research, 7, p.272-284.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Batey, M. &amp; Furnham, A. (2008). The relationship between measures of creativity and schizotypy. Personality and Individual Differences, 45, p.816-821.&lt;/ref&gt; and hypomanic personality&lt;ref&gt;Furnham, A., Batey, M., Anand, K. &amp; Manfield, J. (2008). Personality, hypomania, intelligence and creativity. Personality and Individual Differences, 44, p.1060-1069.&lt;/ref&gt; and several different measures of creativity.

Particularly strong links have been identified between creativity and [[mood disorder]]s, particularly [[Bipolar disorder|manic-depressive disorder]] (a.k.a. [[bipolar disorder]]) and [[Major depressive disorder|depressive disorder]] (a.k.a. [[Major depressive disorder|unipolar disorder]]). In ''Touched with Fire: Manic-Depressive Illness and the Artistic Temperament'', [[Kay Redfield Jamison]] summarizes studies of mood-disorder rates in '''[[writer]]s''', '''[[poet]]s''', and '''[[artist]]s'''. She also explores research that identifies [[mood disorder]]s in such famous writers and artists as [[Ernest Hemingway]] (who shot himself after [[Electroconvulsive therapy|electroconvulsive treatment]]), [[Virginia Woolf]] (who drowned herself when she felt a depressive episode coming on), composer [[Robert Schumann]] (who died in a mental institution), and even the famed [[Visual arts|visual artist]] [[Michelangelo]].

A study looking at 300,000 persons with schizophrenia, bipolar disorder, or unipolar depression, and their relatives, found overrepresentation in creative professions for those with bipolar disorder as well as for undiagnosed siblings of those with schizophrenia or bipolar disorder. There was no overall overrepresentation, but overrepresentation for artistic occupations, among those diagnosed with schizophrenia. There was no association for those with unipolar depression or their relatives.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Kyaga | first1 = S. | last2 = Lichtenstein | first2 = P. | last3 = Boman | first3 = M. | last4 = Hultman | first4 = C. | last5 = Långström | first5 = N. | last6 = Landén | first6 = M. | title = Creativity and mental disorder: Family study of 300 000 people with severe mental disorder | doi = 10.1192/bjp.bp.110.085316 | journal = The British Journal of Psychiatry | volume = 199 | issue = 5 | pages = 373–379 | year = 2011 | pmid =  21653945| pmc = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another study involving more than one million people, conducted by Swedish researchers at the Karolinska Institute, reported a number of correlations between creative occupations and mental illnesses. Writers had a higher risk of anxiety and bipolar disorders, schizophrenia, unipolar depression, and substance abuse, and were almost twice as likely as the general population to kill themselves. Dancers and photographers were also more likely to have bipolar disorder.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc health-19959565&quot;&gt;Roberts, Michelle. Creativity 'closely entwined with mental illness'. http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/health-19959565. 16 October 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

However, as a group, those in the creative professions were no more likely to suffer from psychiatric disorders than other people, although they were more likely to have a close relative with a disorder, including anorexia and, to some extent, autism, the Journal of Psychiatric Research reports.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc health-19959565&quot; /&gt;

According to psychologist Robert Epstein, PhD, creativity can be obstructed through stress.&lt;ref name=&quot;apa.org&quot;&gt;http://www.apa.org/gradpsych/2009/01/creativity.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;

== Creativity and personality ==
Creativity can be expressed in a number of different forms, depending on unique people and environments. A number of different theorists have suggested models of the creative person. One model suggests that there are kinds to produce growth, innovation, speed, etc. These are referred to as the four &quot;Creativity Profiles&quot; that can help achieve such goals.&lt;ref&gt;(DeGraff, Lawrence 2002)&lt;/ref&gt;
:(i) ''Incubate'' (Long-term Development)
:(ii) ''Imagine'' (Breakthrough Ideas)
:(iii) ''Improve'' (Incremental Adjustments)
:(iv) ''Invest'' (Short-term Goals)

Research by Dr Mark Batey of the Psychometrics at Work Research Group at [[Manchester Business School]] has suggested that the creative profile can be explained by four primary creativity traits with narrow facets within each

: (i) &quot;Idea Generation&quot; (Fluency, Originality, Incubation and Illumination)
: (ii) &quot;Personality&quot; (Curiosity and Tolerance for Ambiguity)
: (iii) &quot;Motivation&quot; (Intrinsic, Extrinsic and Achievement)
: (iv) &quot;Confidence&quot; (Producing, Sharing and Implementing)

This model was developed in a sample of 1000 working adults using the statistical techniques of Exploratory Factor Analysis followed by Confirmatory Factor Analysis by Structural Equation Modelling.&lt;ref&gt;(Batey &amp; Irwing, 2010) http://www.e-metrixx.com/creativity-profit/me2-spec/&lt;/ref&gt;

An important aspect of the creativity profiling approach is to account for the tension between predicting the creative profile of an individual, as characterised by the [[Psychometrics|psychometric]] approach, and the evidence that team creativity is founded on diversity and difference.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Nijstad B. A. |author2=De Dreu C. K. | year = 2002 | title = Creativity and Group Innovation | url = | journal = Applied Psychology | volume = 51 | issue = | pages = 400–406 | doi = 10.1111/1464-0597.00984 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

One characteristic of creative people, as measured by some psychologists, is what is called ''divergent production''. ''divergent production'' is the ability of a person to generate a diverse assortment, yet an appropriate amount of responses to a given situation.&lt;ref&gt;(Guilford, 1950)&lt;/ref&gt; One way of measuring ''divergent production'' is by administering the Torrance Tests of Creative Thinking.&lt;ref&gt;(Torrance, 1974, 1984)&lt;/ref&gt; The Torrance Tests of Creative Thinking assesses the diversity, quantity, and appropriateness of participants responses to a variety of open-ended questions.

Other researchers of creativity see the difference in creative people as a cognitive process of dedication to problem solving and developing expertise in the field of their creative expression. Hard working people study the work of people before them and within their current area, become experts in their fields, and then have the ability to add to and build upon previous information in innovative and creative ways. In a study of projects by design students, students who had more knowledge on their subject on average had greater creativity within their projects.&lt;ref&gt;(Christiaans &amp; Venselaar, 2007)&lt;/ref&gt;

The aspect of motivation within a person's personality may predict creativity levels in the person. Motivation stems from two different sources, intrinsic and extrinsic motivation. Intrinsic motivation is an internal drive within a person to participate or invest as a result of personal interest, desires, hopes, goals, etc. Extrinsic motivation is a drive from outside of a person and might take the form of payment, rewards, fame, approval from others, etc. Although extrinsic motivation and intrinsic motivation can both increase creativity in certain cases, strictly extrinsic motivation often impedes creativity in people.&lt;ref&gt;(Amabile, 1996; Prabhu et al., 2008)&lt;/ref&gt;

From a personality-traits perspective, there are a number of traits that are associated with creativity in people.&lt;ref&gt;(Feist, 1998, 1999; Prabhu et al., 2008; Zhang &amp; Sternberg, 2009)&lt;/ref&gt; Creative people tend to be more open to new experiences, are more self-confident, are more ambitious, self-accepting, impulsive, driven, dominant, and hostile, compared to people with less creativity.

From an evolutionary perspective, creativity may be a result of the outcome of years of generating ideas. As ideas are continuously generated, the need to evolve produces a need for new ideas and developments. As a result, people have been creating and developing new, innovative, and creative ideas to build our progress as a society.&lt;ref&gt;(Campbell, 1960)&lt;/ref&gt;

In studying exceptionally creative people in history, some common traits in lifestyle and environment are often found. Creative people in history usually had supportive parents, but rigid and non-nurturing. Most had an interest in their field at an early age, and most had a highly supportive and skilled mentor in their field of interest. Often the field they chose was relatively uncharted, allowing for their creativity to be expressed more in a field with less previous information. Most exceptionally creative people devoted almost all of their time and energy into their craft, and after about a decade had a creative breakthrough of fame. Their lives were marked with extreme dedication and a cycle of hard-work and breakthroughs as a result of their determination.&lt;ref&gt;(Gardner, 1993a, Policastro &amp; Gardner, 1999)&lt;/ref&gt;

Another theory of creative people is the ''investment theory of creativity''. This approach suggest that there are many individual and environmental factors that must exist in precise ways for extremely high levels of creativity opposed to average levels of creativity. In the ''investment'' sense, a person with their particular characteristics in their particular environment may see an opportunity to devote their time and energy into something that has been overlooked by others. The creative person develops an undervalued or under-recognised idea to the point that it is established as a new and creative idea. Just like in the financial world, some investments are worth the buy in, while others are less productive and do not build to the extent that the investor expected. This ''investment theory of creativity'' views creativity in a unique perspective compared to others, by asserting that creativity might rely to some extent on the right investment of effort being added to a field at the right time in the right way.&lt;ref&gt;(Sternberg &amp; Lubart, 1991, 1995, 1996)&lt;/ref&gt;

== Creativity across cultures ==
Creativity is viewed differently in different countries.&lt;ref&gt;Sternberg RJ 'Introduction' in Kaufman JC and Sternberg RJ (2006) (eds) ''The International Handbook of Creativity'' pp 1-9. Cambridge University Press ISBN 0-521-54731-8&lt;/ref&gt; For example, cross-cultural research centred on [[Hong Kong]] found that Westerners view creativity more in terms of the individual attributes of a creative person, such as their aesthetic taste, while Chinese people view creativity more in terms of the social influence of creative people e.g. what they can contribute to society.&lt;ref&gt;Niu W (2006) 'Development of Creativity Research in Chinese Societies' in Kaufman JC and Sternberg RJ (eds) ''The International Handbook of Creativity'' pp 386-387. Cambridge University Press ISBN 0-521-54731-8&lt;/ref&gt; Mpofu et al. surveyed 28 African languages and found that 27 had no word which directly translated to 'creativity' (the exception being [[Arabic]]).&lt;ref&gt;Mpofu E et al (2006) 'African Perspectives on Creativity' in Kaufman JC and Sternberg RJ (eds) ''The International Handbook of Creativity'' p 465. Cambridge University Press ISBN 0-521-54731-8&lt;/ref&gt; The principle of [[linguistic relativity]], i.e. that language can affect thought, suggests that the lack of an equivalent word for 'creativity' may affect the views of creativity among speakers of such languages. However, more research would be needed to establish this, and there is certainly no suggestion that this linguistic difference makes people any less (or more) creative; [[Africa]] has a rich heritage of creative pursuits such as [[music]], [[art]], and [[storytelling]]. Nevertheless, it is true that there has been very little research on creativity in Africa,&lt;ref&gt;Mpofu E et al (2006) 'African Perspectives on Creativity' in Kaufman JC and Sternberg RJ (eds) ''The International Handbook of Creativity'' p 458. Cambridge University Press ISBN 0-521-54731-8&lt;/ref&gt; and there has also been very little research on creativity in Latin America.&lt;ref&gt;Preiss DD and Strasser K (2006) 'Creativity in Latin America' in Kaufman JC and Sternberg RJ (eds) ''The International Handbook of Creativity'' p 46. Cambridge University Press ISBN 0-521-54731-8&lt;/ref&gt; Creativity has been more thoroughly researched in the northern hemisphere, but here again there are cultural differences, even between countries or groups of countries in close proximity. For example, in Scandinavian countries, creativity is seen as an individual attitude which helps in coping with life's challenges,&lt;ref&gt;Smith GJW and Carlsson I (2006) 'Creativity under the Northern Lights' in Kaufman JC and Sternberg RJ (eds) ''The International Handbook of Creativity'' p 202. Cambridge University Press ISBN 0-521-54731-8&lt;/ref&gt; while in Germany, creativity is seen more as a process that can be applied to help solve problems.&lt;ref&gt;Preiser S (2006) 'Creativity Research in German-Speaking Countries' in Kaufman JC and Sternberg RJ (eds) ''The International Handbook of Creativity'' p 175. Cambridge University Press ISBN 0-521-54731-8&lt;/ref&gt;

== In organizations ==
[[File:Training meeting in a ecodesign stainless steel company in brazil.JPG|thumb|right|Training meeting in an eco-design stainless steel company in [[Brazil]]. The leaders among other things wish to cheer and encourage the workers in order to achieve a higher level of creativity.]]

It has been the topic of various research studies to establish that organizational effectiveness depends on the creativity of the workforce to a large extent. For any given organization, measures of effectiveness vary, depending upon its mission, environmental context, nature of work, the product or service it produces, and customer demands. Thus, the first step in evaluating organizational effectiveness is to understand the organization itself — how it functions, how it is structured, and what it emphasizes.

Amabile&lt;ref name=&quot;Amabile98&quot;&gt;(Amabile, 1998; Sullivan and Harper, 2009)&lt;/ref&gt; argued that to enhance creativity in business, three components were needed:
* Expertise (technical, procedural and intellectual knowledge),
* Creative thinking skills (how flexibly and imaginatively people approach problems),
* and Motivation (especially [[intrinsic motivation]]).

There are two types of motivation:
* [[Motivation|extrinsic motivation]] – [[Externality|external]] factors, for example [[threat]]s of being fired or money as a reward,
* [[intrinsic motivation]] – comes from inside an individual, satisfaction, enjoyment of work, etc.

Six managerial practices to encourage motivation are:
* Challenge – matching people with the right assignments;
* Freedom – giving people [[autonomy]] choosing means to achieve goals;
* [[Resource]]s – such as time, money, space, etc. There must be balance fit among resources and people;
* Work group features – [[Cultural diversity|diverse]], supportive teams, where members share the excitement, willingness to help, and recognize each other's talents;
* [[Supervisor]]y encouragement – recognitions, cheering, praising;
* Organizational support – value emphasis, information sharing, [[collaboration]].

Nonaka, who examined several successful Japanese companies, similarly saw creativity and knowledge creation as being important to the success of organizations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nonaka91&quot;&gt;(Nonaka, 1991)&lt;/ref&gt; In particular, he emphasized the role that [[tacit knowledge]] has to play in the creative process.

In business, [[originality]] is not enough. The idea must also be appropriate—useful and [[Cause of action|actionable]].&lt;ref&gt;Amabile, T. M. (1998). &quot;How to kill creativity&quot;. Harvard Business Review&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Siltala, R. 2010. Innovativity and cooperative learning in business life and teaching. University of Turku&lt;/ref&gt; [[Competitive intelligence|Creative competitive intelligence]] is a new solution to solve this problem. According to Reijo Siltala it links creativity to [[innovation]] process and [[competitive intelligence]] to creative workers.

Creativity can be encouraged in people and professionals and in the workplace. It is essential for innovation, and is a factor affecting economic growth and businesses. In 2013, the sociologist Silvia Leal Martín, using the Innova 3DX method, suggested measuring the various parameters that encourage creativity and innovation: corporate culture, work environment, leadership and management, creativity, self-esteem and optimism, locus of control and learning orientation, motivation, and fear.&lt;ref&gt;Leal, S. y Urrea J. &quot;Ingenio y Pasión&quot; (2013), Lid Publishers (Spanish) and Forbes India Magazine http://forbesindia.com/article/ie/new-trends-in-innovation-management/33905/1#ixzz2iiuuDxVq&lt;/ref&gt;

==Economic views of creativity==
Economic approaches to creativity have focussed on three aspects — the impact of creativity on economic growth, methods of modelling markets for creativity, and the maximisation of economic creativity (innovation).

In the early 20th century, [[Joseph Schumpeter]] introduced the economic theory of ''[[creative destruction]]'', to describe the way in which old ways of doing things are endogenously destroyed and replaced by the new. Some economists (such as [[Paul Romer]]) view creativity as an important element in the recombination of elements to produce new technologies and products and, consequently, economic growth. Creativity leads to [[capital (economics)|capital]], and creative products are protected by [[intellectual property]] laws.

[[Mark A. Runco]] and Daniel Rubenson have tried to describe a &quot;[[Behavioral economics|psychoeconomic]]&quot; model of creativity.&lt;ref name=&quot;RubRunc1992&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1016/0732-118X(92)90021-Q|last=Rubenson|first=Daniel L.|author2=Runco, Mark |authorlink2=Mark A. Runco |title=The psychoeconomic approach to creativity|journal=New Ideas in Psychology|year=1992|volume=10|issue=2|pages=131–147}}&lt;/ref&gt; In such a model, creativity is the product of endowments and active investments in creativity; the costs and benefits of bringing creative activity to market determine the supply of creativity. Such an approach has been criticised for its view of creativity consumption as always having positive [[utility]], and for the way it analyses the value of future innovations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Diamond1992&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1016/0732-118X(92)90023-S|last=Diamond|first=Arthur M.|title=Creativity and Interdisciplinarity: A Response to Rubenson and Runco|journal=New Ideas in Psychology|year=1992|volume=10|issue=2|pages=157–160}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''[[creative class]]'' is seen by some to be an important driver of modern economies. In his 2002 book, ''The Rise of the Creative Class'', [[economist]] [[Richard Florida]] popularized the notion that regions with &quot;3 T's of economic development: Technology, Talent and Tolerance&quot; also have high concentrations of [[creative professional]]s and tend to have a higher level of economic development.

==Fostering creativity==
{{Main article|Creativity techniques}}
Daniel Pink, in his 2005 book ''A Whole New Mind'', repeating arguments posed throughout the 20th century, argues that we are entering a new age where creativity is becoming increasingly important. In this ''conceptual age'', we will need to foster and encourage ''right-directed thinking'' (representing creativity and emotion) over ''left-directed thinking'' (representing logical, analytical thought). However, this simplification of 'right' versus 'left' brain thinking is not supported by the research data.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/lives-the-brain/201004/creativity-the-brain-and-evolution&lt;/ref&gt;

Nickerson&lt;ref name=&quot;Nickerson99handbook&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Nickerson|first=R. S.|title=Handbook of Creativity|year=1999|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|editor=R. J. Sternberg|chapter=Enhancing creativity|editor-link=Robert Sternberg}}&lt;/ref&gt; provides a summary of the various creativity techniques that have been proposed. These include approaches that have been developed by both academia and industry:
# Establishing purpose and intention
# Building basic skills
# Encouraging acquisitions of domain-specific knowledge
# Stimulating and rewarding curiosity and exploration
# Building motivation, especially internal motivation
# Encouraging confidence and a willingness to take risks
# Focusing on mastery and self-competition
# Promoting supportable beliefs about creativity
# Providing opportunities for choice and discovery
# Developing self-management (metacognitive skills)
# Teaching techniques and strategies for facilitating creative performance
# Providing balance

Some see the conventional system of [[education|schooling]] as &quot;stifling&quot; of creativity and attempt (particularly in the [[preschool]]/[[kindergarten]] and early school years) to provide a creativity-friendly, rich, imagination-fostering environment for young children.&lt;ref name=Nickerson99handbook /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Csik99handbook&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Csíkszentmihályi|first=Mihály|title=Handbook of Creativity|year=1999|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|editor=R. J. Sternberg|chapter=Implications of a systems perspective for the study of creativity|authorlink=Mihály Csíkszentmihályi|editor-link=Robert Sternberg}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RobAzzam2009&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Robinson|first=K.|author2=Azzam, A. M.|title=Why creativity now?|journal=Educational Leadership|year=2009|volume=67|issue=1|pages=22–26|authorlink=Ken Robinson (British author)}}&lt;/ref&gt; Researchers have seen this as important because technology is advancing our society at an unprecedented rate and creative problem solving will be needed to cope with these challenges as they arise.&lt;ref name=RobAzzam2009 /&gt; In addition to helping with problem solving, creativity also helps students identify problems where others have failed to do so.&lt;ref name=Nickerson99handbook /&gt;&lt;ref name= Csik99handbook /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Paris, C., Edwards, N., Sheffield, E., Mutinsky, M., Olexa, T., Reilly, S., &amp; Baer, J. (2006). How early school experiences impact creativity. In J. C. Kaufman &amp; J. Baer (Eds.), Creativity and Reason in Cognitive Development (pp. 333-350). New York, NY: Cambridge University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; See the Waldorf School as an example of an education program that promotes creative thought.

Promoting intrinsic motivation and problem solving are two areas where educators can foster creativity in students. Students are more creative when they see a task as intrinsically motivating, valued for its own sake.&lt;ref name=Csik99handbook /&gt;&lt;ref name=RobAzzam2009 /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ByrgeHanson2009&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Byrge|first=C.|author2=Hanson. S.|title=The creative platform: A new paradigm for teaching creativity|journal=Problems of Education in the 21st Century|year=2009|volume=18|pages=33–50}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Csikszentmihalyi, M. (1993). Evolution and flow. In M. Csikszentmihalyi (Ed.), The evolving self: A psychology for the third millennium (pp. 175-206). New York: Harper Perennial.&lt;/ref&gt; To promote creative thinking, educators need to identify what motivates their students and structure teaching around it. Providing students with a choice of activities to complete allows them to become more intrinsically motivated and therefore creative in completing the tasks.&lt;ref name=Nickerson99handbook /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;National Advisory Committee on Creative and Cultural Education (1998). All our futures: Creativity, culture, and education. UK: NACCCE&lt;/ref&gt;

Teaching students to solve problems that do not have well defined answers is another way to foster their creativity. This is accomplished by allowing students to explore problems and redefine them, possibly drawing on knowledge that at first may seem unrelated to the problem in order to solve it.&lt;ref name=Nickerson99handbook /&gt;&lt;ref name=Csik99handbook /&gt;&lt;ref name= RobAzzam2009 /&gt;&lt;ref name=ByrgeHanson2009 /&gt;

Several different researchers have proposed methods of increasing the creativity of an individual. Such ideas range from the [[Psychology|psychological]]-cognitive, such as [[Alex Faickney Osborn|Osborn]]-[[Sid Parnes|Parnes]] [[Creative Problem Solving Process]], [[Synectics]], science-based creative thinking, Purdue Creative Thinking Program, and [[Edward de Bono]]'s [[lateral thinking]]; to the highly structured, such as [[TRIZ]] (the Theory of Inventive Problem-Solving) and its variant Algorithm of Inventive Problem Solving (developed by the Russian scientist [[Genrich Altshuller]]), and Computer-Aided [[Morphological analysis (problem-solving)|morphological analysis]].

Creativity has also been identified as one of the key [[21st century skills]] and as one of the  [[Four Cs of 21st century learning]] by educational leaders and theorists in the United States.

==List of academic journals addressing creativity==
{{columns-list|3|
* ''[[Creativity Research Journal]]''
* ''[[Creativity. Theories – Research - Applications]]''
* ''[[International Journal of Creative Computing]]''
* ''[[International Journal of Creativity and Problem Solving]]''
* ''[[Journal of Creative Behavior]]''
* ''[[Psychology of Aesthetics, Creativity, and the Arts]]''
* ''[[Thinking Skills and Creativity]]''
}}

==See also==
{{columns-list|3|
* [[Adaptive performance]]
* [[Brainstorming]]
* [[Computational creativity]]
* [[Confabulation (neural networks)]]
* [[E-scape]], a technology and approach that looks specifically at the assessment of creativity and collaboration.
* [[Greatness]]
* [[Heroic theory of invention and scientific development]]
* [[Innovation]]
* [[Invention]] (such as &quot;artistic invention&quot; in the [[visual arts]])
* [[Lateral thinking]]
* [[Learned industriousness]]
* [[Malevolent creativity]]
* [[Multiple discovery#Mechanism|Multiple discovery]]
* [[Music therapy]]
* [[Musical improvisation]]
* ''[[Why Man Creates]]'' (film)
}}
{{Portal|Thinking}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== References ==
{{Refbegin|30em}}
* Amabile, Teresa M.; Barsade, Sigal G; Mueller, Jennifer S; Staw, Barry M., &quot;Affect and creativity at work,&quot; ''Administrative Science Quarterly'', 2005, vol. 50, pp.&amp;nbsp;367–403.
* {{cite journal |author=Amabile, T. M. |year=1998 |title=How to kill creativity |journal=[[Harvard Business Review]] |volume=76 |issue=5}}
* {{cite book |author=Amabile, T. M. |year=1996 |title=Creativity in context |publisher=Westview Press}}
* {{cite journal |author=Balzac, Fred |year=2006 |title=Exploring the Brain's Role in Creativity |journal=NeuroPsychiatry Reviews |volume=7 |issue=5 |pages=1, 19–20}}
* {{cite book |author=BCA |year=2006 |title=New Concepts in Innovation: The Keys to a Growing Australia |publisher=[http://www.bca.com.au/ Business Council of Australia]}}
* Brian, Denis, ''Einstein: A Life'' (John Wiley and Sons, 1996) ISBN 0-471-11459-6
* {{cite book |author=Byrne, R. M. J. |year=2005 |title=The Rational Imagination: How People Create Counterfactual Alternatives to Reality |publisher=MIT Press}}
* {{cite journal |author=Carson, S. H. |author2=Peterson, J. B. |author3=Higgins, D. M.  |year=2005 |title=Reliability, Validity, and Factor Structure of the Creative Achievement Questionnaire |journal=Creativity Research Journal |volume=17 |issue=1 |pages=37–50 |doi=10.1207/s15326934crj1701_4}}
* {{cite book |author=Craft, A. |year=2005 |title=Creativity in Schools: tensions and dilemmas |publisher=Routledge |authorlink=Anna Craft |isbn=0-415-32414-9}}
* {{cite journal |author=Dorst, K. |author2=Cross, N. |year=2001 |title=Creativity in the design process: co-evolution of problem–solution |journal=Design Studies |volume=22 |issue=5 |pages=425–437 |doi= 10.1016/S0142-694X(01)00009-6}}
* {{cite book |author=Feldman, D. H. |chapter=The Development of Creativity |editor= Sternberg, R.J. |title=Handbook of Creativity |year=1999 |publisher=Cambridge University Press}}
* {{cite book |author=Finke, R. |author2=Ward, T. B. |author3=Smith, S. M. |year=1992 |title=Creative cognition: Theory, research, and applications |publisher=MIT Press |isbn=0-262-06150-3}}
* {{cite journal |author=Flaherty, A. W. |year=2005 |journal=Journal of Comparative Neurology |title=Frontotemporal and dopaminergic control of idea generation and creative drive |volume=493 |issue=1 |pages= 147–153 |pmid=16254989 |doi=10.1002/cne.20768 |pmc=2571074}}
* {{cite book |author=Florida, R. |year=2002 |title=The Rise of the Creative Class: And How It's Transforming Work, Leisure, Community and Everyday Life |publisher=Basic Books |authorlink=Richard Florida |isbn= 0-465-02476-9}}
* {{cite journal | doi = 10.1037/0003-066X.56.3.218 | author = Fredrickson B. L. | year = 2001 | title = The role of positive emotions in positive psychology: The broaden-and-build theory of positive emotions | url = | journal = American Psychologist | volume = 56 | issue = 3| pages = 218–26 | pmid = 11315248 | pmc=3122271}}
* [[Jacques Hadamard|Hadamard, Jacques]], ''The Psychology of Invention in the Mathematical Field'' (Dover, 1954) ISBN 0-486-20107-4
* {{cite book |author=Helmholtz, H. v. L. |title=Vorträge und Reden (5th edition) |year=1896 |publisher=Friederich Vieweg und Sohn}}
* {{cite journal | doi = 10.1037/0022-3514.52.6.1122 |author1=Isen A. M. |author2=Daubman K. A. |author3=Nowicki G. P. | year = 1987 | title = Positive affect facilitates creative problem solving | url = | journal = Journal of Personality and Social Psychology | volume = 52 | issue = 6| pages = 1122–31 | pmid = 3598858 }}
* {{cite book |author=Jeffery, G. |title=The Creative College: building a successful learning culture in the arts |year=2005 |publisher=Trentham Books |authorlink=Graham Jeffery}}
* {{cite book |author=Johnson, D. M. |title=Systematic introduction to the psychology of thinking |year=1972 |publisher=Harper &amp; Row}}
* {{cite book |author=Jullien, F.; Paula M. Varsano (translator) |title=In Praise of Blandness: Proceeding from Chinese Thought and Aesthetics |year=2004 |publisher=Zone Books, U.S.}} ISBN 1-890951-41-2; ISBN 978-1-890951-41-2
* [[Carl Jung|Jung, C. G.]], ''The Collected Works of C. G. Jung. Volume 8. The Structure and Dynamics of the Psyche''. (Princeton, 1981) ISBN 0-691-09774-7
* Kanigel, Robert, ''The Man Who Knew Infinity: A Life of the Genius Ramanujan'' (Washington Square Press, 1992) ISBN 0-671-75061-5
* {{cite journal |author=Kraft, U. |title=Unleashing Creativity |journal=[[Scientific American Mind]] |year=2005 |volume=April |pages=16–23}}
* {{cite journal |author=[[Pierre Kolp|Kolp, P.]], Lammé, A., Regnard, Fr., Rens, J. M. (ed.) |year=2009 |journal=Orphée Apprenti |title=Musique et créativité |publisher=Conseil de la Musique |volume=NS |issue=1 |pages=9–119}} D/2009/11848/5
* *[[Jonah Lehrer|Lehrer, Jonah]] (2012), ''Imagine: How Creativity Works''.
* {{cite book |author=McLaren, R. B. |chapter=Dark Side of Creativity |editor1=Runco, M. A. |editor2=Pritzker, S. R. |title=Encyclopedia of Creativity |year=1999 |publisher=Academic Press}}
* {{cite journal |author=McCrae, R. R. |title=Creativity, Divergent Thinking, and Openness to Experience |journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology |year=1987 |volume=52 |issue=6 |pages=1258–1265 |doi =10.1037/0022-3514.52.6.1258}}
* {{cite book |author=Michalko, M. |title=Cracking Creativity: The Secrets of Creative Genius |isbn=0-89815-913-X |year=1998 |publisher=Ten Speed Press |location=Berkeley, Calif.}}
* {{cite book |author=Nachmanovitch, Stephen |year=1990 |title=Free Play: Improvisation in Life and Art |publisher=Penguin-Putnam |authorlink=Stephen Nachmanovitch |isbn=0-87477-578-7}}
* {{cite book |author=National Academy of Engineering |year=2005 |title=Educating the engineer of 2020: adapting engineering education to the new century |publisher=National Academies Press |authorlink=National Academy of Engineering |isbn=0-309-09649-9}}
* {{cite journal |author=Nonaka, I. |year=1991 |title=The Knowledge-Creating Company |journal=Harvard Business Review |volume=69 |issue=6 |pages=96–104}}
* {{cite book |author1=O'Hara, L. A.  |author2=Sternberg, R. J. |chapter=Creativity and Intelligence |editor= Sternberg, R. J. |title=Handbook of Creativity |year=1999 |publisher=Cambridge University Press}}
* {{cite book |author=Pink, D. H. |year=2005 |title=A Whole New Mind: Moving from the information age into the conceptual age |publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin}}
* {{cite book |author=Poincaré, H. |chapter=Mathematical creation |editor= Ghiselin, B. |title=The Creative Process: A Symposium |origyear=1908|year=1952 |publisher=Mentor}}
* {{cite journal |author=[[James Melvin Rhodes|Rhodes, M.]] |year=1961 |title=An analysis of creativity |journal=Phi Delta Kappan |volume=42 |pages=305–311}}
* {{cite journal |author=Rushton, J. P. |title=Creativity, intelligence, and psychoticism |journal=Personality and Individual Differences |year=1990 |volume=11 |pages=1291–1298 |authorlink=J. Philippe Rushton |doi=10.1016/0191-8869(90)90156-L}}
* {{cite journal |author=Runco, M. A. |year=2004 |title=Creativity |journal=Annual Review of Psychology |volume=55 |pages=657–687 |doi=10.1146/annurev.psych.55.090902.141502 |pmid=14744230}}
* [[Sabaneev, Leonid]]. The Psychology of the Musico-Creative Process // Psyche. - Vol. 9 (July 1928). - pp.&amp;nbsp;37–54.
* {{cite journal |author1=Smith, S. M.  |author2=Blakenship, S.E. |date=1 April 1991 |journal=American Journal of Psychology |title=Incubation and the persistence of fixation in problem solving |volume=104 |pages=61–87 |doi=10.2307/1422851 |issn=0002-9556 |issue=1 |pmid=2058758 |jstor=1422851}}
* {{cite book |author=Taylor, C. W. |chapter=Various approaches to and definitions of creativity |editor= Sternberg, R. J. |title=The nature of creativity: Contemporary psychological perspectives |year=1988 |publisher=Cambridge University Press}}
* {{cite book |author=Torrance, E. P. |title=Torrance Tests of Creative Thinking |year=1974 |publisher=Personnel Press |authorlink=Ellis Paul Torrance}}
* [[Marie-Louise von Franz|von Franz, Marie-Louise]], ''Psyche and Matter'' (Shambhala, 1992) ISBN 0-87773-902-1
* {{cite journal | doi = 10.1002/cne.903260405 |author1=Andersen B. |author2=Korbo L. |author3=Pakkenberg B. | year = 1992 | title = A quantitative study of the human cerebellum with unbiased stereological techniques | url = | journal = The Journal of Comparative Neurology | volume = 326 | issue = 4| pages = 549–560 | pmid = 1484123 }}
* {{cite journal | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0835746100 |author1=Imamizu H. |author2=Kuroda T. |author3=Miyauchi S. |author4=Yoshioka T. |author5=Kawato M. | year = 2003 | title = Modular organization of internal models of tools in the cerebellum | url = | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences | volume = 100 | issue = 9| pages = 5461–5466 }}
* Jung-Beeman, M., Bowden, E., Haberman, J., Frymiare, J., Arambel-Liu, S., Greenblatt, R., Reber, P., &amp; Kounios, J. (2004). Neural activity when people solve verbal problems with insight. PLOS Biology, 2, 500-510.
* {{cite journal |author1=Miller E. |author2=Cohen J. | year = 2001 | title = An integrative theory of prefrontal cortex function | url = | journal = Annual Review of Neuroscience | volume = 24 | issue = | pages = 167–202 | pmid = 11283309 | doi = 10.1146/annurev.neuro.24.1.167 }}
* Miyake, A., &amp; Shah, P. (Eds.). (1999). Models of working memory: Mechanisms of active maintenance and executive control. New York: Cambridge University Press.
* Schmahmann, J. (Ed.). (1997). The cerebellum and cognition. New York: Academic Press.
* {{cite journal | author = Schmahmann J | year = 2004 | title = Disorders of the cerebellum: Ataxia, dysmetria of thought, and the cerebellar cognitive affective syndrome | url = | journal = Journal of Neuropsychiatry and Clinical Neuroscience | volume = 16 | issue = 3| pages = 367–378 | doi=10.1176/appi.neuropsych.16.3.367 | pmid=15377747}}
* Sullivan, Ceri and Graeme Harper, ed., ''The Creative Environment: Authors at Work'' (Cambridge: English Association/Boydell and Brewer, 2009)
* Vandervert, L. (2003a). How working memory and cognitive modeling functions of the cerebellum contribute to discoveries in mathematics. New Ideas in Psychology, 21, 159-175.
* Vandervert, L. (2003b). The neurophysiological basis of innovation. In L. V. Shavinina (Ed.) The international handbook on innovation (pp.&amp;nbsp;17–30). Oxford, England: Elsevier Science.
* Vandervert, L. (2011). The evolution of language: The cerebro-cerebellar blending of visual-spatial working memory with vocalizations. The Journal of Mind and Behavior, 32, 317-334.
* Vandervert, L. (in press). How the blending of cerebellar internal models can explain the evolution of thought and language. Cerebellum.
* Vandervert, L., Schimpf, P., &amp; Liu, H. (2007). How working memory and the cerebellum collaborate to produce creativity and innovation [Special Issue]. Creativity Research Journal, 19(1), 1-19.
* Vandervert, L., &amp; Vandervert-Weathers, K. (in press). New brain-imaging studies indicate how prototyping is related to entrepreneurial giftedness and innovation education in children. In L. Shavinina (Ed.), The International Handbook of Innovation Education. London: Routlage.
* {{cite book |author=DeGraff, J. |author2=Lawrence, K. |year=2002 |title=Creativity at Work |publisher=Jossey-Bass |isbn=0-7879-5725-9}}
* Gielen, P. (2013). Creativity and other Fundamentalisms. Mondriaan: Amsterdam.
{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |title=Creativity and Taoism, A Study of Chinese Philosophy, Art, and Poetry|last=Chung-yuan |first=Chang |date=1970 | publisher=Harper Torchbooks |location=New York|isbn=0-06-131968-6}}
* {{cite book |title=The Dark Side of Creativity |editor1-last=Cropley |editor1-first=David H. |editor2-last=Cropley |editor2-first=Arthur J. |editor3-last=Kaufman |editor3-first=James C. |editor4-last=Runco |editor4-first=Mark A.| display-editors = 3 |year=2010 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Cambridge |isbn=978-0-521-13960-1 |laysummary=http://www.cambridge.org/gb/knowledge/isbn/item2704083/?site_locale=en_GB |laydate=24 November 2010 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book |title=Sudden Genius?: The Gradual Path to Creative Breakthroughs |last=Robinson |first=Andrew |year=2010 |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |location=Oxford |isbn=978-0-19-956995-3 |page= |pages= |laysummary=http://ukcatalogue.oup.com/product/9780199569953.do |laydate=24 November 2010 |ref=harv }}
*[http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=creativity-roots-human-genius-deeper-than-expected ''The Roots of Human Genius Are Deeper Than Expected''] (March 10, 2013) [[Scientific American]]
* [[Isaac Asimov]] (2014-10-20) [http://www.technologyreview.com/view/531911/isaac-asimov-mulls-how-do-people-get-new-ideas/ on Cultivating Creativity]
* [[John Cleese]] (2014-08-08) [http://www.fastcocreate.com/1680999/4-lessons-in-creativity-from-john-cleese on Fostering Creativity]

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
;Videos
* Raphael DiLuzio (2012-06-28) on [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MRD-4Tz60KE 7 Steps of Creative Thinking]

{{Human intelligence topics}}
{{aesthetics}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Creativity| ]]
[[Category:Cognition]]
[[Category:Educational psychology]]
[[Category:Aptitude]]
[[Category:Problem solving skills]]</text>
      <sha1>rwu7idfwhwjjbw19fjcnebafrzzz74w</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
