<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>César Cui</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>143810</id>
    <revision>
      <id>733955484</id>
      <parentid>729687300</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-11T05:27:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Oliszydlowski</username>
        <id>19158033</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25851">[[Image:Cesar cui.jpg|thumb|right|280px|A portrait of Cui, published in ''What We Hear in Music'',1913.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | last        = Oberndorfer
 | first       = Anne Faulkner
 | year        = 1913
 | title       = What We Hear in Music: A Laboratory Course of Study in Music History and Appreciation, for Four Years of High School, Academy, College, Music Club Or Home Study ...
 | publisher   = Victor Talking Machine Company
 | location    = New Jersey, United States
 | pages       = 118
 | url         = https://books.google.com/books?id=0eMvAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=editions:LCCN33003207
 | accessdate  = 2009-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

'''César Antonovich Cui''' ({{lang-ru|Це́зарь Анто́нович Кюи́}}; {{OldStyleDate|18 January|1835|6 January}}{{spaced ndash}}13 March 1918)&lt;ref&gt;Назаров, А.ф. ''Цезарь Антонович Кюи'' (Moscow: Muzyka, 1989), p. 221.&lt;/ref&gt; was a [[Russia]]n [[composer]] and [[Music journalism|music critic]] of [[France|French]], [[Poles|Polish]] and [[Lithuanian people|Lithuanian]] descent.&lt;ref&gt;As Cui wrote to Felipe Pedrell in 1897:  &quot;Bien que russe, je suis d’origine mi-française, mi-lithuanienne.&quot; See Geoffrey Norris and Lyle Neff. &quot;Cui, César.&quot; Grove Music Online. Oxford Music Online. Oxford University Press,  accessed October 29, 2012, http://www.oxfordmusiconline.com/subscriber/article/grove/music/06938.&lt;/ref&gt; His profession was as an [[army]] [[Officer (armed forces)|officer]]  (he rose to the rank of Engineer-General   (compared to full general) of The Russian Imperial Army) and a teacher of [[fortification]]s, and his avocational life has particular significance in the history of [[music]]. In this sideline he is known as a member of [[The Five (composers)|The Five]], a group of Russian composers under the leadership of [[Mily Balakirev]] dedicated to the production of a specifically [[Ethnic Russian music|Russian type of music]].

== Biography ==

===Upbringing and career===
Cesarius-Benjaminus (Цезарий-Вениамин) Cui was born in [[Vilnius]], [[Vilna Governorate]], [[Russian Empire]] (now Vilnius, [[Lithuania]]), to a [[Roman Catholic Church|Roman Catholic]] family, the youngest of five children.  His French father Antoine (his name was later Russified as Anton Leonardovich), had entered Russia as a member of [[French invasion of Russia|Napoleon's army in 1812]], settled in Vilnius upon their defeat, and married a local woman named Julia Gucewicz.&lt;ref&gt;Назаров, p. 7-8.&lt;/ref&gt;  The young César grew up learning [[French language|French]], [[Russian language|Russian]], [[Polish language|Polish]] and [[Lithuanian language|Lithuanian]].&lt;ref&gt;Назаров, p. 14-15.&lt;/ref&gt;  Before finishing [[gymnasium (school)]], in 1850 Cui was sent to [[Saint Petersburg]] to prepare to enter the [[Military engineering-technical university|Chief Engineering School]], which he did the next year at age 16.&lt;ref&gt;Назаров, p. 15-16.&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1855 he was graduated from the Academy, and after advanced studies at the Nikolaevsky Engineering Academy, now [[Military engineering-technical university]], he began his military career in 1857 as an instructor in fortifications.&lt;ref&gt;Назаров, p. 22, 35.&lt;/ref&gt;  His students over the decades included several members of the [[Romanov|Imperial family]], most notably [[Nicholas II of Russia|Nicolas II]].&lt;ref&gt;Ильинский, А.А.; Пахулский, Г. ''Биографии композиторов с IV-XX век с портретами'' (Москва:  Изд. К.А. Дурново, 1904), p. 518.&lt;/ref&gt; Cui eventually ended up teaching at three of the military academies in [[Saint Petersburg]].&lt;ref&gt;Neef, Sigrid. ''Die Russischen Fünf:  Balakirew, Borodin, Cui, Mussorgski, Rimski-Korsakow'' (Berlin:  E.  Kuhn, 1992), p. 136.&lt;/ref&gt;  Cui's study of fortifications gained from frontline assignment during the [[Russo-Turkish War, 1877-1878|Russo-Turkish War of 1877-1878]] proved quite important for his career.  As an expert on military fortifications, Cui eventually attained the academic status of professor in 1880 and the military rank of [[general]] in 1906.&lt;ref&gt;Назаров, p. 106-110, 194.&lt;/ref&gt;  His writings on fortifications included textbooks that were widely used, in several successive editions (see bibliography below).

===Avocational life in music===
Despite his achievements as a professional military academic, Cui is best known in the West for his &quot;other&quot; life in music.  As a boy in Vilnius he received [[piano]] lessons, studied [[Frédéric Chopin|Chopin]]'s works, and began composing little pieces at fourteen years of age.  In the few months before he was sent to Petersburg, he managed to have some lessons in [[music theory]] with the Polish composer [[Stanisław Moniuszko]], who was residing in Vilnius at the time.&lt;ref&gt;
Кюи, Ц.А., “Первые композиторские шаги Ц.А. Кюи (письмо к редактору),”
''Избранные статьи'', составитель И.Л. Гусин (Ленинград: Гос. муз. изд-во, 1952), editor's notes, p. 542-543.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Назаров, p. 12-14.&lt;/ref&gt; Cui's musical direction changed in 1856, when he met [[Mily Balakirev]] and began to be more seriously involved with music.&lt;ref&gt;Назаров, p. 25-27.&lt;/ref&gt;

Even though he was composing music and writing music criticism in his spare time, Cui turned out to be an extremely prolific composer and [[feuilleton]]ist.  His public &quot;debut&quot; as a composer occurred 1859 with the performance of his orchestral Scherzo, Op. 1, under the baton of [[Anton Rubinstein]] and the auspices of the Russian Musical Society.&lt;ref&gt;Назаров, p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1869 the first public performance of an [[opera]] by Cui took place; this was his ''[[William Ratcliff (Cui)|William Ratcliff]]'' (based on the tragedy by [[Heinrich Heine]]); but it did not ultimately have success, partially because of the harshness of his own writings in the music press.&lt;ref&gt;Гозенпуд, А.А., ''Русский оперный театр XIX века, 1857-1872'' [''Russian Operatic Theater of the 19th Century, 1857-1872''] (Ленинград, Музыка, 1971), 228-235.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Назаров, p. 58-61.&lt;/ref&gt; All but one of his operas were composed to Russian texts; the one exception, ''[[Le flibustier (opera)|Le flibustier]]'' (based on a play by [[Jean Richepin]]), premiered at the [[Opéra-Comique]] in [[Paris]] in 1894 (twenty-five years after ''Ratcliff''), but it did not succeed either.&lt;ref&gt;Назаров, p. 132-135.&lt;/ref&gt;  Cui's more successful stage works during his lifetime were the one-act [[comic opera]] ''[[The Mandarin's Son]]'' (publicly premiered in 1878), the three-act ''[[Prisoner of the Caucasus (opera)|Prisoner of the Caucasus]]'' (1883), based on [[Alexander Pushkin|Pushkin]], and the one-act ''[[Mademoiselle Fifi (Cui)|Mademoiselle Fifi]]'' (1903), based on [[Guy de Maupassant]].&lt;ref&gt;Бернандт, Г.Б. ''Словарь опер впервые поставленных или изданных в дореволюционной России и в СССР, 1836-1959.'' [''Dictionary of Operas First Performed or Published in Pre-Revolutionary Russia and in the USSR, 1836-1959'']
 (Москва: Советский композитор, 1962). p. 125-126, 288, 170.&lt;/ref&gt; Besides ''Flibustier'', the only other operas by Cui performed in his lifetime outside of the [[Russian Empire]] were ''Prisoner of the Caucasus'' (in Liège, 1886) and the children's opera ''[[Puss in Boots (Cui)|Puss in Boots]]'' (in Rome, 1915).&lt;ref&gt;Бернандт, Г.Б. ''Словарь опер'', p. 125, 148.&lt;/ref&gt;    
[[Image:CuiBolshoiArtists 1902 CuiIP 273 600.jpg|thumb|300px|left|Cui among artists of the Moscow [[Bolshoi Theatre]], 1902]]
Cui's activities in musical life included also membership on the opera selection committee at the [[Mariinsky Theatre]]; this stint ended in 1883, when both he and [[Nikolai Rimsky-Korsakov|Rimsky-Korsakov]] left the committee in protest of its rejection of [[Modest Mussorgsky|Mussorgsky]]'s ''[[Khovanshchina]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Кюи, ''Избранные письма'' [''Selected Letters''], p. 112 (also editor’s notes, p. 571-572).&lt;/ref&gt;  During 1896-1904 he was director of the Petersburg branch of the [[Russian Musical Society]].&lt;ref&gt;Назаров, p. 147, 184.&lt;/ref&gt;

Among the many musicians Cui knew in his life, [[Franz Liszt]] looms large.  Liszt valued the music of Russian composers quite highly; for Cui's opera ''William Ratcliff'' he expressed some of the highest praise.&lt;ref&gt;Кюи, ''Избранные письма'', p. 506.&lt;/ref&gt;  Cui's book ''La musique en Russie'' and ''Suite pour piano'', Op. 21, are dedicated to the elder composer.  In addition, Cui's ''Tarantelle'' for orchestra, Op. 12, formed the basis for Liszt's last [[Arrangement|piano transcription]].

Two personalities of direct significance for Cui were women who were specially devoted to his music. In [[Belgium]], the [[Marie-Clotilde-Elisabeth Louise de Riquet, comtesse de Mercy-Argenteau|Comtesse de Mercy-Argenteau]] (1837–1890) was most influential in making possible the staging there of ''[[Prisoner of the Caucasus (opera)|Prisoner of the Caucasus]]'' in 1885.&lt;ref&gt;Назаров, p. 120.&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Moscow]], Mariya Kerzina, with her husband Arkadiy Kerzin, formed in 1896 the Circle of Russian Music Lovers, a performance society, which began in 1898 to give special place to works by Cui, among those of other Russian composers, in its concerts.&lt;ref&gt;Назаров, p. 150-157.&lt;/ref&gt;

In such a long and active musical life as Cui's there were many accolades.  In the late 1880s and early 1890s several foreign musical societies honored Cui with memberships.  Shortly after the staging of ''[[Le flibustier (opera)|Le flibustier]]'' in Paris, Cui was elected as a correspondent member of the [[Académie française]] and awarded the cross of the [[Légion d'honneur]].  In 1896 the Belgian Royal Academy of Literature and Art made him a member.&lt;ref&gt;Назаров, p. 35-36.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1909 and 1910 events were held in honor of Cui's 50th anniversary as a composer.&lt;ref&gt;Назаров, p. 201-205.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Family===
[[Image:Cui grave.jpg|thumb|right|Grave of Mal'vina and César Cui at [[Tikhvin Cemetery]] in Saint Petersburg]]
Cui married Mal'vina Rafailovna Bamberg (Мальвина Рафаиловна Бамберг) in 1858.  He had met her at the home of [[Alexander Dargomyzhsky]], from whom she was taking singing lessons&lt;ref&gt;Назаров, p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt;  Among the musical works Cui dedicated to her is the early Scherzo, Op. 1 (1857), which uses themes based on her maiden name (BAmBErG) and his own initials (C.C.), and the comic opera ''[[The Mandarin's Son]]''.  César and Mal'vina had two children, Lidiya and Aleksandr.  Lidiya, an amateur singer, married and had a son named Yuri Borisovich Amoretti; in the period before the [[October Revolution]] Aleksandr was a member of the Russian Senate.&lt;ref&gt;Кюи, ''Избранные письма'', editor’s notes, p. 635, 395, 703, 715-716.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Last years and death===
In 1916, the composer went blind, although he was able to compose small pieces by dictation.&lt;ref&gt;Кюи, ''Избранные письма'', p. 477.&lt;/ref&gt;  Cui died on 26 March 1918 from cerebral [[apoplexy]] and was buried next to his wife Mal'vina (who had died in 1899) at the Smolensk Lutheran Cemetery in Saint Petersburg. In 1939, his body was reinterred in [[Tikhvin Cemetery]] at the Alexander Nevsky Monastery, Saint Petersburg, to lie beside the other members of [[The Five (composers)|The Five]].&lt;ref&gt;Назаров, p. 155, 221-222.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Cui as a music critic ==
[[Image:AveCesar Raevsky CuiIP 177 600 cap.JPG|thumb|left|250px|Caricature of Cui by Rayevsky, based on a painting by [[Jean-Léon Gérôme]]. The gladiators in the center bear shields inscribed with the titles of Cui's operas ''[[William Ratcliff (Cui)|William Ratcliff]]'', ''[[The Mandarin's Son]]'', and ''[[Angelo (opera)|Angelo]] ]]
As a writer on music, Cui contributed almost 800 articles between 1864 and 1918 to various newspapers and other publications in Russia and Europe. (He &quot;retired&quot; from regular music criticism in 1900.) His wide coverage included concerts, recitals, musical life, new publications of music, and personalities.  A significant number of his articles (ca. 300) dealt with opera.&lt;ref&gt;Кюи, ''Избранные статьи'', Библиографический указатель статей Ц.А. Кюи, 1864-1918 [Bibligraphic index of articles by C.A. Cui, 1864-1918], p. 624-660.&lt;/ref&gt;  Several of his themed sets of articles were reissued as monographs; these covered topics as varied as the original 1876 production of [[Richard Wagner|Wagner]]'s ''[[Der Ring des Nibelungen]]'' in [[Bayreuth Festspielhaus|Bayreuth]], the development of the Russian romance ([[art song]]), music in Russia, and [[Anton Rubinstein]]'s seminal lectures on the history of [[piano]] music of 1888-1889.  (See list of writings below.) In addition, as indicated above as part of his profession, Cui also published many books and articles about military fortifications.

Because of rules related to his status in the Russian military, in the early years his musico-critical articles had to be published under a pseudonym, which consisted of three asterisks (***); in Petersburg musical circles, however, it became clear who was writing the articles.&lt;ref&gt;Назаров, p. 68-69.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Гозенпуд, А.А., ''Русский оперный театр XIX века, 1857-1872'', p. 235.&lt;/ref&gt; His musical reviews began in the ''[[St.Petersburg Vedomosti]]'', expressing disdain for music before [[Ludwig van Beethoven|Beethoven]] (such as [[Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart|Mozart]]) and his advocacy of originality in music.  Sarcasm was a regular feature of his [[feuilleton]]s.

Cui's primary goal as a critic was to promote the music of contemporary Russian composers, especially the works of his now better-known co-members of The Five.  Even they, however, were not spared negative reactions from him here and there, especially in his blistering review of the first production of Mussorgsky's ''[[Boris Godunov (opera)|Boris Godunov]]'' in 1874.&lt;ref&gt;Кюи, &quot;Театр и музыка.  ''Борис Годунов'', опера г. Мусоргского, дважды забракованная водивильным комитетом&quot; [&quot;Theatre and music.  ''Boris Godunov'', opera by Mr. Musorgsky, twice rejected by the vaudeville committee&quot;], ''Санкт-Петербургские ведомости'', 6 февр. 1874, No. 37, 1874&lt;/ref&gt;  (Later in life Cui championed the music of this late colleague of his, to the point of making the first completion of Mussorgsky's unfinished opera ''[[The Fair at Sorochyntsi]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Назаров, p. 214-215.&lt;/ref&gt;)

Russian composers outside of The Five, however, were often more likely to produce a negative reaction.  This derived at least partly from distrust of the western-style [[College or university school of music|conservatory]] system in favor of the autodidactic approach that The Five had practiced.  Cui lambasted Tchaikovsky's second performed opera, ''[[The Oprichnik (opera)|The Oprichnik]]'', for instance;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Музыкальные заметки.  ''Опричник'', опера г. Чайковского&quot; [Musical notes.  ''The Oprichnik'', opera by Mr. Tchaikovsky&quot;], ''Санкт-Петербургские ведомости'', 23 апр. 1874, No. 110, 1874.&lt;/ref&gt; and his stinging remarks about [[Symphony No. 1 (Rachmaninoff)|Rachmaninoff's Symphony No.1]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Театр и музыка.  Третий Русский симфонический концерт&quot; [&quot;Theatre and music.  Third Russian Symphony Concert&quot;], ''Новости и биржевая газета'', 17 марта No. 75, 1897.]&lt;/ref&gt; are often cited.  (Fortunately for posterity, both works have survived their unfavorable premieres.)

Of Western composers, Cui favored [[Hector Berlioz|Berlioz]] and [[Franz Liszt|Liszt]] as progressives.&lt;ref&gt;Кюи, &quot;Первые композиторские шаги&quot;, p. 554.&lt;/ref&gt;  He admired [[Richard Wagner|Wagner's]] aspirations concerning music drama, but did not agree with that composer's methods to achieve them (such as the [[leitmotif]] system and the predominance of the orchestra).&lt;ref&gt;Кюи, &quot;Несколько слов о современных оперных формах&quot;  [&quot;A Few Words about Contemporary Operatic Forms&quot;], ''Избранные статьи,'' p. 416.&lt;/ref&gt;

Late in life Cui's presumed progressiveness as espoused in the 1860s and '70s faded, and he showed firm hostility towards the younger &quot;modernists&quot; such as [[Richard Strauss]] and [[Vincent d'Indy]].&lt;ref&gt;Кюи, ''Избранные статьи'', p. 537-550&lt;/ref&gt;  Cui's very last published articles (from 1917) constituted merciless parodies, including the little song &quot;Hymn to [[Futurism (art)|Futurism]]&quot; and &quot;Concise Directions on How to Become a Modern Composer of Genius without Being a Musician&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Кюи, ''Избранные статьи'', p. 550-552.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Cui as a composer ==
[[Image:Ilya Repin - Cesar Cui.jpg|thumb|right|Portrait of César Cui by [[Ilya Repin]], 1890.]]
{{see also|List of compositions by César Cui}}

Cui composed in almost all genres of his time, with the distinct exceptions of the [[symphony]], [[symphonic poem]] and the [[solo concerto]] (unlike his compatriots Balakirev, Borodin, Mussorgsky and Rimsky-Korsakov).  By far [[art song]]s constitute the greatest number of works by Cui; these include a few vocal [[duet]]s and many [[children's song|songs for children]].  Several of his songs are available also in versions with orchestral accompaniment, including his ''Bolero'', Op. 17, which was dedicated to the singer [[Marcella Sembrich]].  Some of his most famous [[art song]]s include &quot;The Statue at [[Tsarskoye Selo]]&quot; (&quot;Царско-сельская статyя&quot;) and &quot;The Burnt Letter,&quot; (&quot;Сожжённое письмо&quot;), both based on poems by Cui's most valued poet, [[Alexander Pushkin]].

In addition, Cui wrote many works for [[piano]] and for [[Chamber music|chamber]] groups (including three [[string quartet]]s), numerous choruses, and several [[Orchestra|orchestral works]], but his most significant efforts are reflected in the operas, of which he composed fifteen of varying proportions.  Besides children's music (which includes four fairytale operas as well as the aforementioned songs), three other special categories of compositions stand out among his works: (1) pieces inspired by and dedicated to the Comtesse de Mercy-Argenteau (whom the composer knew from 1885 to her death in 1890; (2) works associated with the Circle of Russian Music Lovers (the &quot;Kerzin Circle&quot;); and (3) pieces inspired by the [[Russo-Japanese War]] and [[World War I]].

As to the current status of Cui the composer, in the last few decades one of his children's operas (of which he composed four) entitled ''[[Puss in Boots (Cui)|Puss-in-Boots]]'' (from [[Charles Perrault|Perrault]]) has had wide appeal in [[Germany]].&lt;ref&gt;Boas, Robert.  &quot;Nuremberg.&quot; Opera [London], v. 32 (1981), pp. 288-289.&lt;/ref&gt;  Nevertheless, despite the fact that more of Cui's music is being made available in recent years in recordings and in new printed editions, his status today in the repertoire is considerably small, based (in the West) primarily on some of his piano and chamber music (such as the [[violin]] and [[piano]] piece called ''Orientale'' (op. 50, No. 9)&lt;ref&gt;Score available at [http://nla.gov.au/nla.mus-an14448987 http://nla.gov.au/nla.mus-an14448987]&lt;/ref&gt;) and a number of solo songs.  The received wisdom that he is not a particularly talented composer, at least for large genres, has been cited as a cause for this state of affairs; his strongest talent is said to lie in the crystallization of mood at an instant as captured in his art songs and instrumental miniatures.&lt;ref&gt;Norris, Geoffrey and Neff, Lyle.  &quot;Cui, César [Kyui, Tsezar' Antonovich],&quot; ''Grove Music Online''. Ed. L. Macy. (Accessed 9 March 2008), &lt;[http://www.grovemusic.com http://www.grovemusic.com]&gt; (Subscription required).&lt;/ref&gt;  Although his abilities as an orchestrator, too, have been disparaged (notably by his compatriot Rimsky-Korsakov&lt;ref&gt;Ястребцев, В.В., ''Николай Андреевич Римский-Корсаков: воспоминания В.В. Ястребцева, [в двух томах], [''Nikolai Andreevich Rimsky-Korsakov:  Reminiscences by V. V. Iastrebtsev'', in two volumes] (Ленинград: Гос. муз. изд-во, 1959-1960), т. 1, p. 145, 149.&lt;/ref&gt;), some recent recordings (e.g., of his one-act opera ''[[Feast in Time of Plague (opera)|Feast in Time of Plague]]'',&lt;ref&gt;Cui, César, ''A Feast in Time of Plague'', Russian State Symphony Orchestra under Valery Polyansky, Chandos CD, CHAN 10201, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;  from Pushkin) suggest that Cui's dramatic music might be more interesting to pursue with regard to this feature.

Cui's works are not so nationalistic as those of the other members of [[The Five (composers)|The Five]]; with the exception of Pushkin, his operas do not display a strong attraction to Russian sources.  In the area of [[art song]], however, the vast majority of Cui's vocal music is based on Russian texts.  Overt attempts at Russian &quot;folk&quot; musical style can be detected in passages from his first act of the collaborative ''[[Mlada]]'' (1872), ''[[The Captain's Daughter (opera)|The Captain's Daughter]]'', a couple of the children's operas, and a few songs; many other passages in his music reflect the stylistic curiosities  associated with Russian art music of the 19th century, such as [[whole tone scale]]s and certain [[harmony|harmonic devices]].  Nevertheless, his style is more often compared to [[Robert Schumann]]&lt;ref&gt;Ларош, Герман Августович, &quot;Один из наших шуманистов:  Ц.А. Кюи как композитор опер и романсов&quot; [&quot;One of Our Schumannists:  C. A. Cui as Composer of Operas and Romances&quot;], ''Русский вестник'', т. 180 (1885), p. 985-1008.&lt;/ref&gt; and to [[France|French]] composers such as [[Charles Gounod|Gounod]]&lt;ref&gt;Abraham, Gerald, &quot;Heine, Cui, and William Ratcliff,&quot; his Essays on Russian and East European Music (Oxford:  Clarendon Press, 1985), p. 61-62.&lt;/ref&gt; than to [[Mikhail Glinka]] or to Cui's Russian contemporaries.

==Literary works==

A selected list of Cui's writings on music and military architecture can be found at [[List of literary works by César Cui]].

==General bibliography==
* Guglielmi, Edoardo.  &quot;Cesar Cui e l'Ottocento musicale russo,&quot; ''Chigiana'', v. 25, no. 5 (1968), p.&amp;nbsp;187-195.
* [[Marie-Clotilde-Elisabeth Louise de Riquet, comtesse de Mercy-Argenteau|Mercy-Argenteau, La Comtesse de]], ''César Cui: esquisse critique''. Paris: Fischbacher, 1888.
* Муселак, Анри [Musielak Henri].  &quot;Предки Кюи&quot; [&quot;Cui's Forbears&quot;], ''Советская Музыка'', 1979, no.10, p.&amp;nbsp;141-142.
* Назаров, Александр Федорович [Nazarov, Aleksandr Fedorovich]: ''Цезарь Антонович Кюи''. Москва, 1989. «Музыка». ISBN 5714001516
* Neef, Sigrid.  ''Handbuch der russischen und sowjetischen Oper''.  1. Aufl.  Kassel:  Bärenreiter, 1989, c1985.
* _______.  ''Die Russischen Fünf:  Balakirew, Borodin, Cui, Mussorgski, Rimski-Korsakow''.  Berlin:  E.  Kuhn, 1992.
* Neff, Lyle Kevin.  ''Story, style, and structure in the operas of César Cui''. Ph.D. dissertation, Indiana University, United States—Indiana. Retrieved June 20, 2010, from Dissertations &amp; Theses: A&amp;I. (Publication No. AAT 3054368) ([http://proquest.umi.com/pqdweb?did=726486041&amp;sid=1&amp;Fmt=2&amp;clientId=8331&amp;RQT=309&amp;VName=PQD Abstract])
* Norris, Geoffrey and Neff, Lyle.  &quot;Cui, César [Kyui, Tsezar' Antonovich],&quot; ''Grove Music Online''. Ed. L. Macy. (Accessed 9 March 2008), &lt;[http://www.grovemusic.com http://www.grovemusic.com]&gt; (Subscription required)
* [[Vladimir Vasilievich Stasov|Stasov, V.V.]] &quot;Цезарь Антонович Кюи:  биографический очерк&quot; [&quot;'''César Antonovich Cui:  A Biographical Sketch'''.&quot;]  ''Артист'' [''Artist''] [Moscow], no.  34 (1894); reprinted and edited in his ''Избранные сочинение: живопись, скульптура, музыка''. В трех томах. Т. 3. [''Selected Works:  Painting, Sculpture, Music''.  In three vols.  Vol. 3.]  Москва: Искусство, 1952, p.&amp;nbsp;387-408.

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{commons|César Cui}}
*{{IMSLP|id=Cui, César}}
*{{allmusicguide|id=césar-cui-mn0001205582}}
*{{findagrave|4353}}

{{The Five (composers)}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cui, Cesar}}
[[Category:1835 births]]
[[Category:1918 deaths]]
[[Category:19th-century classical composers]]
[[Category:19th-century Russian writers]]
[[Category:20th-century classical composers]]
[[Category:20th-century Russian writers]]
[[Category:Burials at Tikhvin Cemetery]]
[[Category:Military Engineering-Technical University alumni]]
[[Category:Military Engineering-Technical University faculty]]
[[Category:People from Vilna Governorate]]
[[Category:People from Vilnius]]
[[Category:Romantic composers]]
[[Category:Russian classical composers]]
[[Category:Russian male classical composers]]
[[Category:Russian military engineers]]
[[Category:Russian military personnel]]
[[Category:Russian music critics]]
[[Category:Russian opera composers]]
[[Category:Russian people of French descent]]
[[Category:Russian people of Lithuanian descent]]
[[Category:Russian Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:The Five]]</text>
      <sha1>nj3y8mbxn8vo8kkbnxsf5qf87qnjswq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
