<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.28.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2600" case="first-letter">Topic</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Dennis O'Neill case</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>16693564</id>
    <revision>
      <id>739239624</id>
      <parentid>714005980</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-13T15:23:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mountdrayton</username>
        <id>6442913</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Amplify and clarify</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13256">:''For other persons named Dennis O'Neil, see [[Dennis O'Neil (disambiguation)|Dennis O'Neil]]''
'''Dennis O'Neill''' (3 March 1932 &amp;ndash; 9 January 1945) was a 12-year-old [[Wales|Welsh]] boy whose death at the hands of his [[foster parents]] led to an inquiry into and overhaul of fostering provisions in [[Great Britain]].

==Circumstances of death==
Dennis O'Neill, 12, lived in [[Newport, Wales|Newport]], [[Monmouthshire (historic)|Monmouthshire]]. On 30 May 1944 Dennis and his younger brothers, Terence (Terry), 9, and Frederick (Freddie), 7, were committed to the care of [[Newport City Council|Newport County Borough Council]] by Newport Juvenile Court on the grounds that they were in need of care and attention.&lt;ref name=&quot;Causes&quot;&gt;&quot;Causes of Boy's Death&quot;, ''[[The Times]]'', 13 February 1945.&lt;/ref&gt; On 5 July 1944 the Newport Education Committee, exercising powers under the [[Children and Young Persons Act 1933]], sent Dennis and Terence to live with Reginald Gough, 31, and his wife Esther, 29, at their remote [[farm]], Bank Farm, in the [[Hope Valley, Shropshire|Hope Valley]], near [[Minsterley]], [[Shropshire]], [[England]]. Frederick was sent to a Mr and Mrs Pickering nearby.&lt;ref name=&quot;Inquiry&quot; /&gt;

At 1:00 pm on 9 January 1945, Esther Gough telephoned the local doctor to tell him that Dennis was having a fit. The doctor arrived at 3:30 pm to find that he was already dead and was in an appalling condition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Causes&quot; /&gt; An [[inquest]] found that he had died of [[cardiac failure]] after being struck several heavy blows on the chest, and had also been beaten with a stick on the back. He was undernourished, thin and wasted, and well below normal average weight for his age. He had a number of [[Sepsis|septic]] [[Ulcer (dermatology)|ulcers]] on his feet and his legs were severely [[wikt:chap#Etymology 2|chapped]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Underfed Boy Beaten with Stick&quot;, ''[[The Times]]'', 6 February 1945.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 3 February 1945, Reginald Gough was charged with [[manslaughter]] and Esther Gough with wilful ill-treatment, neglect and exposure likely to cause suffering and injury. On 12 February 1945 she, too, was charged with manslaughter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Causes&quot; /&gt;

==Committal==
On 13 February 1945 the Goughs appeared before [[Pontesbury]] [[Magistrates' Court (England and Wales)|Magistrates' Court]].

===Terence O'Neill's testimony===
On the first day of the committal proceedings, Terence testified that they were usually given three slices of [[bread]] and [[butter]] each per day, and that and [[tea]] was their only sustenance. They stole whatever they could from the [[pantry]] to supplement this. Dennis would suck [[milk]] from the [[teat]]s of the farm [[cow]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Causes&quot; /&gt; Every night both boys were given a severe thrashing on their hands and/or legs, sometimes up to 100 blows each.&lt;ref name=&quot;Foster&quot;&gt;&quot;Foster-Parents Charged&quot;, ''[[The Times]]'', 14 February 1945.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 6 January 1945, Dennis had been ordered out to collect sticks. He came home shivering with only a handful of sticks and was forced out again by Gough using his stick. He stood in the yard crying and was dragged to the [[wikt:spinney|spinney]] by his hair by Mrs Gough. That night he was thrashed for taking a bite from a [[rutabaga|swede]]. The following day he was stripped naked by Gough and thrashed with a stick so hard that it broke; Gough then thrashed him with another stick until his legs were blue and bleeding. The next day he was unable to stand up and when Terence came home from school he found his brother locked in a cubbyhole in the kitchen. His feet were by now in a terrible condition and Gough hit him to try to make him stop crying. Dennis complained that his back hurt. Gough beat him with his fists again the following morning; he died in the afternoon.&lt;ref name=&quot;Causes&quot; /&gt;

On the second day of the committal proceedings Terence gave another three hours of testimony about their mistreatment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Foster&quot;/&gt; The following day he was recalled again and admitted that the boys had sometimes misbehaved and deserved to be punished. Gough had played [[cricket]] and [[Association football|football]] with them and the Goughs insisted the boys said their [[prayer]]s every night. This time he said that they all ate the same food.&lt;ref name=&quot;Boy&quot;&gt;&quot;Boy's Death at Farm&quot;, ''[[The Times]]'', 15 February 1945.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other testimony===
Miss Eirlys Edwards, a clerk in Newport Education Department (with no training or experience in matters of child welfare), testified on the second day that she visited Bank Farm on 20 December 1944, and observed that the boys were treated with little affection, and while Terence appeared to be well cared for, Dennis appeared ill and frightened; she asked Mrs Gough to call a doctor to examine him, which she said she would do.&lt;ref name=&quot;Foster&quot; /&gt; She had recommended to her superiors that the boys be removed&lt;ref name=&quot;Foster&quot; /&gt; and Mr W. J. Edmonds, Newport's Deputy Director of Education, confirmed that he had requested Shropshire Education Committee to do so, although the Goughs had not yet been informed of this decision.&lt;ref name=&quot;Causes&quot; /&gt;

On the third day, Police Sergeant Macpherson testified that he had visited the farm following Dennis's death  and found that the boys' bedroom was dirty and poorly furnished, whereas the Goughs' room was pleasant, neat and tidy. He said that Mrs Gough stated that Dennis had started complaining that his feet hurt soon after he came to live with them and that he was always late getting up. She had stated that the boys had been fighting the night before Dennis's death and it was this that had caused the marks on his body. She and her husband had, she said, hit the boys only very rarely, and then only on the hand for misbehaving.&lt;ref name=&quot;Boy&quot; /&gt;

==Trial==
The Goughs were both committed for trial at [[Shrewsbury]] [[Assizes]] and were refused [[bail]]. However, on 27 February 1945, [[Malcolm Hilbery|Mr Justice Hilbery]] transferred the case to [[Stafford]] Assizes at the request of counsel.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Gough Trial: Transfer to Stafford Assizes&quot;, ''[[The Times]]'', 28 February 1945.&lt;/ref&gt;

The trial opened at Stafford on 15 March 1945, before [[Frederic Wrottesley|Mr Justice Wrottesley]]. W. H. Cartwright Sharp [[King's Counsel|KC]] prosecuted, J. F. Bourke represented Mr Gough, and A. J. Long KC represented Mrs Gough.&lt;ref name=&quot;Trial&quot;&gt;&quot;Foster Parents on Trial&quot;, ''[[The Times]]'', 16 March 1945.&lt;/ref&gt;

The court heard that the Goughs' contract required them to bring up Dennis O'Neill as one of their own children in return for £1 per week. The court heard much the same testimony as in the committal hearings. However, it appeared that Terence had initially been somewhat confused about the sequence of events. The prosecution claimed that Dennis was tied to a bench and beaten with a stick for eating a swede the day before he died.&lt;ref name=&quot;Trial&quot; /&gt;

Dr Holloway Davies, the local doctor called by Mrs Gough, testified that when he arrived Dennis had been dead for between four and six hours. That proved that Dennis had already been dead for some time when Mrs Gough called Dr Davies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Trial&quot; /&gt;

On the second day, Reginald Gough gave evidence. He claimed that he and his wife were kind to the boys and fed them very well. The boys were frequently naughty, but were rarely disciplined. He claimed that the incident with the bench occurred, but he was only having a joke, did not actually tie Dennis to the bench, did not beat him, and they were all laughing about it.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Foster Parents on Trial&quot;, ''[[The Times]]'', 17 March 1945.&lt;/ref&gt;

Mrs Gough gave evidence on the third day of the trial. She testified that she had married her husband in February 1942, having left the [[Women's Auxiliary Air Force]] (WAAF) in June 1941. They had no children of their own. She corroborated some of Terence's testimony about her husband's treatment of Dennis, and said she was afraid of her husband and that she believed that had she originally told the truth to the police she would also be dead. Her husband had told her that Dennis was dead and instructed her to lie to the doctor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Esther&quot;&gt;&quot;Trial of Foster Parents&quot;, ''[[The Times]]'', 19 March 1945.&lt;/ref&gt;

The judge instructed the [[jury]] that they could not find Mrs Gough guilty of manslaughter, since only Mr Gough was strong enough to have inflicted the trauma which killed Dennis, but they could still find her guilty of neglect.&lt;ref name=&quot;Esther&quot; /&gt;

On 19 March 1945, Reginald Gough was convicted of manslaughter and sentenced to six years in prison. Esther Gough was found guilty of neglect and sentenced to six months' imprisonment. The jury deliberated for only twenty minutes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Guilty&quot;&gt;&quot;Gough Found Guilty&quot;, ''[[The Times]]'', March 20, 1945.&lt;/ref&gt;

It transpired that Gough had been convicted of [[common assault]] against his wife in 1942 and she had left him in July of that year, applying for a [[separation order]] on the grounds of persistent cruelty on 6 August 1942, but had later returned to live with him. The judge said that he took this into account before sentencing her, but her own ill-treatment was no excuse for her neglect of the boys.&lt;ref name=&quot;Guilty&quot; /&gt;

==Inquiries==

===Parliament===
The case was first raised in the [[British House of Commons|House of Commons]] on 8 February 1945, by [[Kenneth Lindsay]] MP.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Parliament: Case of Dennis O'Neill&quot;, ''[[The Times]]'', 9 February 1945.&lt;/ref&gt; It was raised on a number of occasions thereafter.

===Public inquiry===
Politicians and the public were shocked by the case, especially that Gough had been given custody of the boys although he was known to the police and had a conviction for violence and that no inspection of the boys' welfare was made until they had been with the Goughs for six months. On 22 March 1945, the [[Home Secretary]], [[Herbert Morrison]], announced that a public inquiry would be held into the case. [[Walter Monckton|Sir Walter Monckton KC]] was appointed to conduct the inquiry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Home&quot;&gt;&quot;Home Office Inquiry in O'Neill Case&quot;, ''[[The Times]]'', 27 March 1945.&lt;/ref&gt;

The inquiry opened at [[Newport Civic Centre]] on 10 April 1945.&lt;ref name=&quot;Inquiry&quot;&gt;&quot;O'Neill Inquiry&quot;, ''[[The Times]]'', 11 April 1945&lt;/ref&gt; It reported on 28 May 1945. The report criticised both councils involved, but did not name any specific individual(s) and acknowledged that the failings were not deliberate.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Report on O'Neill Inquiry&quot;, ''[[The Times]]'', 29 May 1945.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Shropshire inquiry===
On 26 March 1945 [[Shropshire County Council]] began its own inquiry, although this was held in private.&lt;ref name=&quot;Home&quot; /&gt; It was chaired by [[Offley Wakeman|Sir Offley Wakeman]]. The inquiry reported on 30 June 1945, and called for a thorough reorganisation of the boarding-out of children. It accepted all blame placed upon the council by the public inquiry, but did not place any particular blame on any specific individual(s).&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Shropshire Council on Gough Case&quot;, ''[[The Times]]'', 2 July 1945.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Results==
On 1 January 1947 new [[Home Office]] and [[Ministry of Health (United Kingdom)|Ministry of Health]] regulations on the boarding-out of children came into force as a direct result of the Monckton Report. The principal requirements were:&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Children Boarded Out: New Rules for Local Authorities&quot;, ''[[The Times]]'', 13 December 1946.&lt;/ref&gt;
*Each local authority was required to appoint a boarding-out committee, at least three of whose members were to be women and which had to meet at least every three months. The committee was to be responsible for finding suitable foster homes and to exercise supervision over all the authority's foster children.
*An official was required to visit every foster child within a month of their being placed and thereafter at least once every six weeks. They were required to submit a written report, taking into account any complaint made by the child.
*A doctor was to be appointed for every foster child and was to examine the child within one month of their being placed and at least once a year thereafter.
*No child was to be fostered or remain fostered by a person with any criminal conviction rendering them unsuitable to be a foster parent or in any environment likely to be detrimental to them.

The case was a significant contributory factor leading to the [[Children Act 1948]].

In 1947 [[Agatha Christie]] wrote a radio play called ''[[Three Blind Mice (radio play and short story)|Three Blind Mice]]'' loosely based on the case. This eventually developed into the long-running play ''[[The Mousetrap]]''.

Terry O'Neill has published a non-fiction book about the case. Called ''Someone to Love Us'', it was released on 4 March 2010, the day after what would have been Dennis's 78th birthday.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.southwalesargus.co.uk/news/8450451.Newport_man_tells_his_tragic_story_behind_Agatha_Christie_classic/?ref=mr Terry O'Neill book]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Oneill, Dennis}}
[[Category:Foster care]]
[[Category:Child abuse in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:British manslaughter victims]]
[[Category:People from Newport, Wales]]
[[Category:1945 deaths]]
[[Category:Child abuse resulting in death]]
[[Category:1932 births]]</text>
      <sha1>2bnv10z3w6dihfawdlcymtu39ug5wcj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
