<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>John R. McCarl</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>39190048</id>
    <revision>
      <id>732919076</id>
      <parentid>730965837</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-04T03:53:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sadads</username>
        <id>563447</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>link [[slum clearance]] using [[User:Edward/Find link|Find link]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13662">{{Infobox Officeholder
|name        = John Raymond McCarl
|image       = File:John Raymond McCarl - Comptroller General of the United States - circa 1921 to 1936.jpg
|office      = [[Comptroller General of the United States]]
|president   = [[Warren G. Harding]]&lt;br&gt;[[Calvin Coolidge]]&lt;br&gt;[[Herbert Hoover]]&lt;br&gt;[[Franklin D. Roosevelt]]
|term_start  = July 1, 1921
|term_end    = June 30, 1936
|predecessor = None (first officeholder)
|successor   = [[Fred H. Brown]]
|birth_date  = {{birth date|1879|11|27}}
|birth_place = near [[Des Moines, Iowa]], [[United States|U.S.]]
|death_date  = {{death date and age|1940|08|02|1879|11|25}}
|death_place = [[Washington, D.C.]], U.S.
|party       = [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]]
|spouse      = Ethel Barnett McCarl
|alma_mater  = [[University of Nebraska–Lincoln]]
}}
'''John Raymond McCarl''' (November 27, 1879 – August 2, 1940) was an American [[lawyer]] and executive secretary of the national [[National Republican Congressional Committee|Republican Congressional Campaign Committee]]. He was the first [[Comptroller General of the United States]], serving from 1921 to 1936. During his time in office, he was one of the most powerful and controversial officials in the U.S. federal government.

==Early life and career==
McCarl was born in a [[log cabin]]&lt;ref name=&quot;WaPoObit&quot; /&gt; on November 27, 1879, near [[Des Moines, Iowa]]. His father was a veteran of the [[Union Army]] who fought in the [[American Civil War]]. John attended local public schools. McCarl's father died in 1893 at the age of 53.&lt;ref name=&quot;Downs55&quot;&gt;Downs, p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt;

After her husband's death, Sara McCarl moved John and his five siblings to [[McCook, Nebraska]]. John held part-time jobs during the school year, and in the summers worked for the [[Chicago, Burlington and Quincy Railroad]] and local lawyer Webster Morlan. He was a [[Halfback (American football)|halfback]] on the first [[American football|football team]] fielded by McCook High School, and sang in a local [[Quartet#Vocal quartet|vocal quartet]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Hein&quot;&gt;[http://www.mccookgazette.com/story/1047374.html Hein, Linda. &quot;Norris, McCarl Considered for Presidency in '36 Election.&quot; ''McCook Gazette.'' January 11, 2002.] Accessed 2013-04-22.&lt;/ref&gt;

McCarl graduated from McCook High School in 1897 and entered the [[University of Nebraska–Lincoln|University of Nebraska]]. He received a [[Bachelor of Laws]] degree from the university in 1903.&lt;ref name=&quot;Downs55&quot;/&gt; McCarl returned to McCook, where he took up the practice of law.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hein&quot; /&gt; On November 26, 1905, he married Ethel Barnett, daughter of Albert Barnett (a McCook lumber yard owner and one of the wealthiest men in the state).&lt;ref name=&quot;Hein&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Barnett-McCarl.&quot; ''McCook Republican.'' December 1, 1905; &quot;Albert Barnett, Nebraskan, Father-in-Law of John R. McCarl, Dies at 82.&quot; ''New York Times.'' June 3, 1938.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Government career==

===Congressional aide and GOP activism===
McCarl was a [[Factions in the Republican Party (United States)#Progressive Republicans|Progressive Republican]] and active in party politics.&lt;ref name=&quot;Trask49&quot;&gt;Trask, p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1914, Fletcher Merwin resigned as private secretary to progressive Republican [[United States Senate|Senator]] [[George W. Norris]] (also from the town of McCook). On Merwin's recommendation,&lt;ref name=&quot;Hein&quot; /&gt; McCarl applied for and won the position.&lt;ref name=&quot;Trask49&quot; /&gt;

In 1917, Norris opposed American entry into World War I. Worried that Norris would be denied renomination to the [[United States Senate]] in 1918, McCarl resigned.&lt;ref name=&quot;Trask49&quot; /&gt; Norris was deeply disappointed in McCarl's decision.&lt;ref&gt;Lowitt, p. 96.&lt;/ref&gt; Senator [[Simeon D. Fess]] subsequently appointed McCarl to be secretary of the national Republican Congressional Campaign Committee (which Fess chaired). McCarl was highly active during the 1918 congressional elections, and made numerous political contacts during this time. He continued to work with the committee in the 1920 presidential election, leaving him well-positioned to seek a job with the incoming administration of Warren G. Harding.&lt;ref name=&quot;Trask49&quot; /&gt;

===Comptroller General===
[[File:John Raymond McCarl - 1921.jpg|thumb|left|J.R. McCarl in 1921, shortly before his appointment as Comptroller General.]]
Since the final year of the [[William Howard Taft|Taft]] administration (1912), pressure had been building within the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]] for legislation which would impose modern financial accounting and budgeting procedures on the federal government. Worsening national debt due to expenditures required by World War I and a greatly enlarged federal government led to passage of the [[Budget and Accounting Act]] of 1921.&lt;ref&gt;Sundquist, p. 40-45.&lt;/ref&gt; This legislation, which President Harding signed into law on June 10, 1921,&lt;ref&gt;Sundquist, p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt; created the [[Government Accountability Office|Government Accounting Office]] (GAO), an independent agency answerable solely to Congress.&lt;ref&gt;Tierney, et al., p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt; The head of the GAO was the Comptroller General of the United States, a non-partisan position which could only be filled by the President of the United States with the [[Advice and consent#United States|advice and consent]] of the Senate. The Comptroller General served for a single, non-renewable, 15-year term.&lt;ref&gt;Walker, p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;

It is unclear how McCarl won appointment as the first Comptroller General of the United States. Some sources say that McCarl advised Harding on who should fill the position, and that Harding chose McCarl.&lt;ref&gt;Mosher, p. 68; Mansfield, p. 71.&lt;/ref&gt; But other sources say that Senator Norris&lt;ref name=&quot;WaPoObit&quot; /&gt; or Senator Fess&lt;ref&gt;Lowitt, p. 139.&lt;/ref&gt; pushed McCarl for the position. Although McCarl had no financial training or experience whatsoever,&lt;ref name=&quot;Trask50&quot;&gt;Trask, p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt; Harding nominated McCarl on June 28, 1921, and the Senate confirmed him the next day.&lt;ref&gt;Trask, p. 7; &quot;Proceedings of Congress and Committees in Brief.&quot; ''Washington Post.'' June 28, 1921.&lt;/ref&gt;

Historians Katie Louchheim and Jonathan Dembo note that McCarl had &quot;virtually unlimited power&quot; during his time in office.&lt;ref&gt;Louchheim and Dembo, p. 108.&lt;/ref&gt; He was a decisive leader of the organization, asserted a broad range of powers for himself, and fought strongly to make GAO an impartial and independent agency.&lt;ref name=&quot;Trask50&quot; /&gt; McCarl made a wide range of decisions on issues as diverse as individual [[expense account]]s, salary increases, statutory authority to incur expenses, and the right of federal employees to receive reimbursement for their work clothes.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTObit&quot; /&gt; He refused to authorize the expenditure of $100 million of [[Public Works Administration]] funds for [[slum clearance]] and declined to permit the [[United States Department of Agriculture|Department of Agriculture]] to use drought relief funds for the purchase of surplus [[Sheep|lamb]]s as a means of price support. He argued that the law simply did not authorize such actions.&lt;ref name=&quot;WaPoObit&quot; /&gt; He once voided contracts for the construction of the $12.5 million [[Arlington Memorial Bridge]] because they called for the hiring of a general contractor and not specific individuals, as he believed the law required.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Memorial Bridge Bids Will Be Let, Ignoring M'Carl.&quot; ''Washington Post.'' January 7, 1926; &quot;Bridge Commission to Study Contract for Memorial Span.&quot; ''Washington Post.'' February 17, 1926.&lt;/ref&gt; (Congress passed legislation changing the law.)&lt;ref&gt;&quot;House Action Fails to Halt Bridge Work.&quot; ''Washington Post.'' January 14, 1927.&lt;/ref&gt; His decisions were often highly controversial and he was widely unpopular within the government.&lt;ref&gt;Trask, p. 50-51.&lt;/ref&gt; He was very critical of the [[New Deal]] pushed by President [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]], claiming that New Deal agencies were set up hastily, spent far too much money, and had amorphous powers. He also criticized Congress for delegating too much authority to the executive branch.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Federal Shake-Up for 'Vast' Savings Is Urged By M'Carl.&quot; ''New York Times.'' June 30, 1936.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Political science|Political scientist]] Harvey Mansfield, writing in 1939, considered him a zealot and crusader when it came to accounting.&lt;ref&gt;Mansfield, p. 71.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Establishing GAO===
[[File:John Raymond McCarl - at his desk - Comptroller General of the United States - circa 1935.jpg|thumb|J.R. McCarl at his desk in 1935.]]
McCarl struggled to make GAO a competent and authoritative agency. In the first six years in office, he strictly controlled work start and stopping times, banned employees from discussing anything which was not work-related, and required employees to stay at their desks.&lt;ref&gt;Trask, p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt; He relaxed these rules significantly in 1927 after realizing they were harming staff morale.&lt;ref&gt;Trask, p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt;

GAO was created out of the office of the [[Comptroller of the Treasury]], and McCarl inherited most of that office's 1,700 workers. He largely retained the Treasury structure, although he concentrated approval authority for communication with Congress in his own office.&lt;ref&gt;Trask, p. 53-54.&lt;/ref&gt; He also created a legal office, and ordered that any interpretation of law issue only under his own signature.&lt;ref&gt;Trask, p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1922, he established a Bookkeeping Section to sign off on all government contractual expenditures, a Transportation Division to ensure that shipping costs were reasonable, and an Investigations Section to make investigations and inspections, write reports, and make recommendations regarding the operation and financial procedures of the federal government. This unit (later renamed the Office of Investigations in the late 1920s) quickly became the major arm of GAO.&lt;ref&gt;Trask, p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1923, McCarl collapsed five of the GAO's existing divisions into just two, Civil and Military. These two divisions were further consolidated into a single Audit Division in 1926.&lt;ref&gt;Trask, p. 56.&lt;/ref&gt; He established a Records Division the same year.  This organizational structure existed largely unchanged until his departure from office (although Bookkeeping was renamed Accounting and Bookkeeping in 1935).&lt;ref&gt;Trask, p. 57.&lt;/ref&gt; 

McCall was a constant critic of the lack of a central disbursing authority in the federal government. He believed that having a disbursing agent in each agency or department was a recipe for financial misappropriation. He applauded President Roosevelt's decision on June 10, 1933, to issue [[Executive order|Executive Order]] 6166, which created a Division of Disbursement within the [[United States Department of the Treasury|Treasury Department]] and eliminated this office within each agency.&lt;ref&gt;Trask, p. 57-62.&lt;/ref&gt;

GAO historian Robert Trask says that McCarl was obstinate and harsh,&lt;ref name=&quot;Trask50&quot; /&gt; but the ''[[The Washington Post|Washington Post]]'' at the time of his death called him &quot;mild-mannered&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;WaPoObit&quot; /&gt;

==Death==
After retiring as Comptroller General, McCarl practiced law in Washington, D.C. He suffered either a [[Myocardial infarction|heart attack]]&lt;ref name=&quot;WaPoObit&quot;&gt;&quot;John R. McCarl Dies of Heart Attack at 60.&quot; ''Washington Post.'' August 3, 1940.&lt;/ref&gt; or a [[stroke]]&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTObit&quot; /&gt; at his desk in his law office on August 2, 1940, and died immediately. His wife, Ethel, survived him.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTObit&quot;&gt;&quot;J.R. M'Carl Dead.&quot; ''New York Times.'' August 3, 1940.&lt;/ref&gt; The couple had no children.&lt;ref name=&quot;WaPoObit&quot; /&gt;

John R. McCarl was buried in McCook, Nebraska, at Memorial Park Cemetery.&lt;ref name=&quot;WaPoObit&quot; /&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
{{Commons category|John Raymond McCarl}}
*Downs, Winfield Scott. ''Encyclopedia of American Biography.'' New York: The American Historical Society, 1941.
*Louchheim, Katie and Dembo, Jonathan, eds. ''The Making of the New Deal: The Insiders Speak.'' Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press, 1983.
*Lowitt, Richard. ''George W. Norris: The Making of a Progressive, 1861-1912.'' Chicago: University of Illinois Press, 1971.
*Mansfield, Harvey C. ''The Comptroller General: A Study in the Law and Practice of Financial Administration.'' New Haven, Conn.: Yale University Press, 1939.
*Mosher, Frederick C. ''The GAO: The Quest for Accountability in American Government.'' Boulder, Colo.: Westview Press, 1979.
*Sundquist, James. ''The Decline and Resurgence of Congress.'' Washington, D.C.: Brookings Institution Press, 1981.
*Tierney, Cornelius E.; Kearney, Edward F.; Fernandez, Roland; and Green, Jeffrey W. ''Wiley Federal Accounting Handbook: Policies, Standards, Procedures, Practices.'' Hoboken, N.J.: John Wiley &amp; Sons, 2007.
*Trask, Roger R. ''Defender of the Public Interest: The General Accounting Office, 1921-1966.'' Washington, D.C.: U.S. General Accounting Office, 1996.
*Walker, David M. ''Organizational Transformation: Implementing Chief Operating Officer/Chief Management Officer Positions in Federal Agencies.'' GAO-08-322T. Washington, D.C.: Government Accountability Office, December 13, 2007.

{{Comptroller General of the United States}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:McCarl, John R.}}
[[Category:1879 births]]
[[Category:1940 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Red Willow County, Nebraska]]
[[Category:People from Polk County, Iowa]]
[[Category:Comptrollers General of the United States]]
[[Category:People from Washington, D.C.]]
[[Category:University of Nebraska–Lincoln alumni]]
[[Category:Nebraska lawyers]]
[[Category:Washington, D.C. lawyers]]
[[Category:Nebraska Republicans]]
[[Category:20th-century American lawyers]]</text>
      <sha1>98cbhbsm2h9lh2o1xktryie5n7h6onh</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
