<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.28.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2600" case="first-letter">Topic</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Mabel Boll</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>29655774</id>
    <revision>
      <id>684450562</id>
      <parentid>684319732</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-10-06T18:34:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Iridescent</username>
        <id>937705</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Flights in the Columbia */[[WP:AWB/T|Typo fixing]], [[WP:AWB/T|typo(s) fixed]]: three man → three-man using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12032">{{Infobox person
|name          = Mabel Boll
|image         = Mabel Boll (ca. 1920).jpg
|image_size    =
|caption       =  Boll circa 1920
|birth_name    = 
|birth_date    = December 1, 1893
|birth_place   = Rochester, New York
|death_date    = {{Death date and age|1949|04|11|1893|12|01}}
|death_place   = [[Manhattan Psychiatric Center|Manhattan State Hospital]]&lt;br&gt;[[Wards Island]], [[Manhattan, New York City]]
|death_cause   = 
|resting_place = 
|resting_place_coordinates = 
|residence     = 
|nationality   = 
|ethnicity     = 
|citizenship   = American
|other_names   = &quot;Queen of Diamonds&quot;, Mabel Boll Cella, Countess de la Porceerei, Senora Hernando Rocha-Schioos
|known_for     = Actress, aviation pioneer, jewelry
|education     =
|alma_mater    = 
|employer      = 
|occupation    = Actress
|title         = 
|salary        = 
|networth      = Over 1 million
|height        = 
|weight        = 
|term          = 
|predecessor   = 
|successor     = 
|party         = 
|boards        = 
|religion      = 
|spouse        = {{marriage|Robert Scott I|1909|1917}}&lt;br&gt;{{marriage|Hernando Rocha|1922|1930}}&lt;br&gt;{{marriage|Count Henri de Porceri|1931|1933}}&lt;br&gt;{{marriage|Theodore Cella|1940|1949}}
|partner       = 
|children      = Robert Scott II (1914-1942)
|parents       = George L. Boll&lt;br&gt;Josephine Snelgrove
|relations     = 
|signature     = 
|website       = 
|footnotes     = 
}}
'''Mabel Boll''' (December 1, 1893 &amp;ndash; April 11, 1949), known as the &quot;Queen of Diamonds&quot;, was an [[United States|American]] [[socialite]] involved in the early days of record-setting flights in the 1920s. She garnered nicknames from the press, including &quot;Broadway’s most beautiful blonde&quot; and the &quot;$250,000-a-day bride&quot;.

{{TOC limit|limit=2}}
==Early life==
[[Image:Bellanca wb 2.jpg|right|thumb|The ''Columbia'']]
Boll made many claims later in life that she was an heiress and was a member of a wealthy family. The truth was that her father, George, was a bartender in Rochester, New York. She was, however, attractive, a short, dark-eyed, and &quot;vividly blonde&quot; beauty. Her early employment was selling cigars in Rochester.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Aeronautics: Tale of Two.&quot; ''Time'', June 18, 1928.&lt;/ref&gt;  Boll became an experienced horse rider,&lt;ref&gt;Sloate 1990, p. 41.&lt;/ref&gt; and married businessman Robert Scott in 1909.&lt;ref name=obit/&gt; In 1914 she had a son, Robert Scott II.

Boll was known as &quot;The Queen of Diamonds&quot; because of the amount of jewelry she publicly displayed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Naughton&quot;&gt;Naughton, Russell. [http://www.ctie.monash.edu.au/hargrave/boll.html &quot;Mabel Boll.&quot;] ''The Centre for Telecommunications and Information Engineering (CTIE)'', 2015. Retrieved: February 7, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; At times, she would wear over $400,000 in jewelry in public and was photographed wearing a sweater made of gold and platinum.&lt;ref&gt;''The Atlantic Monthly'', Volume 159.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1922, Boll married Colombian coffee king [[Hernando Rocha]], who presented her with over a million dollars in jewels and an {{convert|46.57|carat|g|adj=on}} emerald-cut diamond bearing her name &quot;The Mabel Boll&quot;. The diamond was purchased by the [[Harry Winston]] collection upon Boll's death in 1949.

In 1934, Boll made headlines again as the &quot;Countess de la Porceerei&quot; in [[Nice, France]] when her 27-year-old boyfriend Georges Chariot shot himself on her lawn.&lt;ref&gt;''Rochester Evening Journal'', May 15, 1934.&lt;/ref&gt; In February 1940, Boll married for the fifth time, a harp player from Florida.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;&quot;A Woman's New York: Barrymore topic of day; Mabel Boll remarries.&quot; ''The Washington Post'', February 9, 1940.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aviation==

===Transatlantic fever===
1927 was full of publicity surrounding [[Charles Lindbergh]] winning the [[Orteig Prize]] for his non-stop flight from New York to Paris. Boll wanted publicity as well and felt that being the first woman to cross the Atlantic would be headline news. While living in Paris, France, Boll announced she would pay 100,000 francs to any pilot who would fly her across the Atlantic from Paris.&lt;ref&gt;Butler 1997, pp. 146–147.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Flights in the Columbia===
[[Admiral Byrd]] and [[Charles A. Levine]] competed for the Orteig prize, but missed out. Each completed record flights shortly thereafter. While in Europe, Boll attempted to get Levine to fly her to America in the [[Wright-Bellanca WB-2 Columbia|''Columbia'']], which was still in France after a record-setting flight from New York. The inexperienced owner of the aircraft, Levine, had plans to fly it back to America with a French pilot, [[Maurice Droughin]]. After disagreements with Droughin and lawyers left the aircraft guarded and grounded, Levine took off to England claiming he was just testing the engine. (Chamberlain claimed that Levine bribed the guards.) Boll followed Levine to England by boat, talking Levine into letting her be a passenger.

Just before the flight, Levine's new pilot, Capt. [[Walter G. R. Hinchliffe]], publicly refused to fly if Boll was a passenger and instead, she flew to Rome, dropping a present to [[Benito Mussolini]]'s son. Boll was invited to try an east-west flight from America and she set out for New York by boat in January 1928.&lt;ref&gt;Butler 1997, p. 180.&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 5, 1928, [[Wilmer Stultz]], [[Oliver Colin LeBoutillier]], and Boll on an improvised seat, made the first non-stop flight in the ''Columbia'' between New York City and [[Havana, Cuba]], placing Boll on the front page of the ''New York Times''. Boll was sued a month later by Levine's company for $12,000 plus interest.&lt;ref&gt;''The Milwaukee Journal'', May 22, 1928.&lt;/ref&gt; Boll was known as a temperamental passenger, once injuring pilot [[Erroll Boyd]] with an Alligator handbag in flight for making a premature landing in bad weather.&lt;ref&gt;Smyth 1997, pp. 68–69.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1928, the same teams that attempted to win the Orteig Prize were competing to be the first to fly a woman across the Atlantic (as a passenger). Levine chose the flamboyant Boll. On the other extreme, [[Amelia Earhart]] was chosen as a demure and capable pilot sponsored by [[George Palmer Putnam]] and [[Amy Phipps Guest]].

On June 26, 1928, Boll was filmed leaving [[Roosevelt Field]] in the Columbia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://service.nfo.ac.uk/purl/article/0005-0003-3546-0000-0-0000-0000-0 &quot;Mabel Boll in race to fly over Atlantic.&quot;] ''Gaumont.'' Retrieved: February 7, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; Boll was later spotted 1,100 miles away in [[Harbour Grace, Newfoundland]] as a passenger in the [[Wright-Bellanca WB-2 Columbia|Columbia]]. The aircraft was piloted by [[Oliver Colin LeBoutillier]] and [[Arthur Argles]] owned by [[Columbia Aircraft Corp]] Chairman Charles Levine.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Mabel Boll takes off; flies to Harbor Grace: Covers 1,100 miles while Stultz makes 7 vain attempts to get into air. Weather data conflict (Mabel Boll hops off; makes Harbor Grace).&quot;  ''The Washington Post'', June 13, 1928.&lt;/ref&gt; While Boll publicly announced her aspiration to be the first woman to fly across the Atlantic, Amelia Earhart was also in Newfoundland at the same time, along with the German [[Thea Rasche]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Naughton&quot;/&gt;

The newspapers focused their attention on the aspirations of “The Diamond Queen of Broadway”. Preparations for the trip were done with full publicity. At the same time in relative secrecy, pilots Wilmer Stultz and Gordon were believed by the press to be preparing Byrd’s Fokker “Friendship” for his planned trip to the South Pole. Stultz himself planned to be the pilot of the Columbia and defected to Byrd's crew.&lt;ref&gt;Thurman, Judith. &quot;Missing Woman Amelia Earhart’s flight.&quot; ''The New Yorker'', September 14, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; After several failed attempts days earlier, on June 17, the [[Fokker F.VII|“Friendship”]] took off from the bay at [[Trepassey|Trepassey, Newfoundland]] with Earhart on board while the crew of the Columbia were grounded for five days due to the weather.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;This World&quot;. ''San Francisco Chronicle'', Vol. 2, No. 21, September 11, 1938.&lt;/ref&gt; Upon learning of successful flight by Earhart and crew, Boll returned to America, donating $500 to the Newfoundland airstrip for development.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrgrace.ca/air.html &quot;Columbia: A little competition for Miss Earhart.&quot;] ''Harbour Grace Tourism''. Retrieved: February 7, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[image:Junkers W33.jpg|thumb|right|A Junkers W 33]]
Boll wanted a new nickname, &quot;The Queen of the Air&quot;. For her last serious record attempt, Levine purchased a customized long-range [[Junkers W 33]] for $50,000 emblazoned with the logo &quot;Queen of the Air&quot; across the sides. Plans were made for [[Bert Acosta]] to fly Boll and Levine from Paris to New York for a new record, which was changed to a London to New York attempt. By the time the aircraft arrived in late August 1928, the flying season was coming to an end and Levine was preoccupied with legal matters in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;Bak 2011, p. 168.&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;The Queen of the Air&quot; Junkers was transported back to America, damaged, and resold to William Rody. He renamed it to the &quot;de Espírito Santo Agostinho&quot; (ESA) and attempted a three-man transatlantic crossing record from [[Lisbon]] on September 13, 1931. The aircraft landed in the Atlantic Ocean, and the aircraft's empty tanks kept the crew afloat for several days before they were rescued.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.junkers.de/kalenderblatt/201009_kb39_ozeanflugversuch_w33.html &quot;10th September 1931: Der Ozeanflugversuch der W 33 &quot;ESA&quot; (10th September 1931: The ocean flight test of the W 33 &quot;ESA&quot;).] ''Junkers''. Retrieved: July 6, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Boll's last effort to become a transatlantic passenger was refused by aircraft owner, and entertainer [[Harry Richman]].&lt;ref&gt;''Rochester Journal'', September 11, 1936.&lt;/ref&gt; Boll avoided the perils of record setting flights until 1936, when she announced she had been cured of her flying obsession.

==Later life and death==
Boll continued to make headlines throughout the 1930s and 1940s, but gradually her star status faded.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Mabel Boll's ex-mate robbed of many gems.&quot; ''The Washington Post'', March 9, 1936.&lt;/ref&gt; She abandoned her home in Switzerland in 1939 as war in Europe broke out.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The 'Queen of Diamonds,' now plain Mabel Boll, visits D.C.: Troubles in fleeing Europe's danger zones told in interview.&quot; ''The Washington Post'', November 23, 1939.&lt;/ref&gt; She died of a stroke at the [[Manhattan Psychiatric Center|Manhattan State Hospital]], the psychiatric hospital on [[Wards Island]] on April 11, 1949 at the age of 55.&lt;ref name=obit&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9B01E0DB163BE23BBC4A52DFB2668382659EDE &quot;Mabel Boll dies. 'Diamond Queen'; bartender's daughter owned fabulous gems. Balked in efforts to fly Atlantic.&quot;] ''[[The  New York Times]]'', April 12, 1949. Retrieved: October 3, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|Quote in ''The New York Times'': &quot;Mrs. Mabel Boll Cella, who wanted to be Queen of the Air when the world knew her as the Queen of Diamonds, died Sunday of a stroke in Manhattan State Hospital for the mentally ill on Wards Island.&quot;|group=Note}}&lt;ref&gt;[https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1338&amp;dat=19490329&amp;id=19tXAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=YfYDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=3191,5577569&amp;hl=en &quot;Queen of Diamonds is reported in hospital.&quot;] ''[[Spokane Daily Chronicle]]'' ([[Associated Press]]), March 29, 1949. Retrieved: October 4, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|group=Note}}

===Citations===
{{Reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===
{{Refbegin}}
* Bak, Richard. ''The Big Jump: Lindbergh and the Great Atlantic Air Race''. Hoboken: John Wiley &amp; Sons. 2011. ISBN 978-0-471-47752-5.
* Butler, Susan. ''East to the Dawn: The Life of Amelia Earhart''. Reading, Massachusetts: Addison-Wesley, 1997. ISBN 0-306-80887-0.
* Sloate, Susan. ''Amelia Earhart: Challenging the Skies''. New York: Fawcett Books, 1990. ISBN 978-0-449-90396-4.
* Smyth, Ross. ''The Lindbergh of Canada: The Erroll Boyd Story.'' St. Catherine, Ontario, Canada: General Store Publishing House, 1997. ISBN 978-1-89618-261-2.
{{Refend}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Boll, Mabel}}
[[Category:American socialites]]
[[Category:1949 deaths]]
[[Category:1893 births]]</text>
      <sha1>kwxgg7taxp8jaod1g9wctu446w64vha</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
