<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.28.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2600" case="first-letter">Topic</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>National Library of Wales</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>784510</id>
    <revision>
      <id>740544404</id>
      <parentid>738499294</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-21T18:46:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yngvadottir</username>
        <id>7407280</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Consortium of European Research Libraries]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="104385">{{EngvarB|date=September 2013}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2013}}
{{Infobox library
| library_name       = ''Llyfrgell Genedlaethol Cymru'' 
| name_en            =The National Library of Wales
| library_logo       =
| image              = National Library of Wales.jpg
| caption            = The National Library of Wales, Aberystwyth
| country            =
| type               = [[National Library]]
| scope              =
| established        = 1907
| ref_legal_mandate  = Established by Royal Charter on 19 March 1907. Supplemental Charters were given to the Library in 1911, 1978 and 2006
| location           = Aberystwyth
| coordinates        = {{coord|52|24|52|N|4|4|8|W|display=inline,title}}
| branch_of          =
| num_branches       =
| items_collected    = Printed Works, Maps, Archives, Manuscripts, Audio Visual Material, Photographs, Paintings
| collection_size    = 5M Books, 1M Maps, 800,000 Photographs, 50,000 Works of Art
| criteria           = Acquisition through purchase, bequest and legal deposit
| legal_deposit      = Yes
| req_to_access      = Library open to all. Access to reading rooms restricted to over 16s without prior permission.
| annual_circulation =
| pop_served         =
| members            =
| budget             =
| director           = Linda Tomos
| num_employees      = around 300 [[Full-time equivalent|FTE]]
| website            ={{url|http://www.llgc.org.uk}}
| phone_num          = +44 1970 632800
}}

The '''National Library of Wales''' ({{lang-cy|Llyfrgell Genedlaethol Cymru}}), [[Aberystwyth]], is the national [[legal deposit]] library of [[Wales]] and is one of the [[Welsh Government sponsored bodies]]. It is the biggest library in Wales, holding over 6.5 million books and periodicals, and the largest collections of archives, portraits, maps and photographic images in Wales. The Library is also home to the national collection of Welsh manuscripts, the National Screen and Sound Archive of Wales, and the most comprehensive collection of paintings and topographical prints in Wales.&lt;ref name=NLWstrategy /&gt;&lt;ref name=NLWcdp /&gt; As the primary [[research library]] and archive in Wales&lt;ref name=&quot;Brinley Jones&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Brinley Jones|first1=R.|editor1-last=Fishlock|editor1-first=Trevor|title=In this place: the National Library of Wales|date=2007|publisher=National Library of Wales|location=Aberystwyth|isbn=9781862250543|page=6|chapter=Foreword}}&lt;/ref&gt; and one of the largest research libraries in the [[United Kingdom]], the National Library is a member of [[Research Libraries UK|Research Libraries UK (RLUK)]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=About us|url=http://www.rluk.ac.uk/about-us/|website=Research Libraries UK|accessdate=21 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Consortium of European Research Libraries]] (CERL).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=List of members|url=http://www.cerl.org/membership/list_members|website=[[Consortium of European Research Libraries]]|accessdate=21 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the very core of the National Library of Wales is the mission to collect and preserve materials related to Wales and Welsh life and those which can be utilised by the people of Wales for study and research.&lt;ref name=Wales_[journal]_1946&gt;{{cite journal|title=The National Library of Wales|journal=Wales|date=1946|issue=24|pages=61–73}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Welsh language|Welsh]] is the Library's main medium of communication but it does, however, aim to deliver all public services in Welsh and English.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.llgc.org.uk/fileadmin/documents/pdf/Welsh_Lang_Scheme.pdf Welsh Language Scheme: 2006] at NLW Official website. Retrieved 27 April 2013&lt;/ref&gt; In January 2015 the Library in partnership with Wikimedia UK appointed a full-time [[Wikipedian in Residence]] with the aim of developing further its resources on an open licence, to a world-wide audience.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.llgc.org.uk/blog/?p=9102&amp;lang=en National Library of Wales website;] accessed 20 January 2015&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://blog.wikimedia.org.uk#National Library of Wales with a birthday gift to Wikipedia [[Wikimedia UK]] blog;] accessed 20 January 2015&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
[[File:Sir John Williams, Bart, GCVO, MD - Christopher Williams .jpg|thumb|Sir John Williams, one of the principal founders of the National Library]]
In 1873, a committee was set up to collect Welsh material and house it at [[Aberystwyth University|University College]], Aberystwyth. In 1905, the government promised money in its budget to establish a National Library and a National Museum of Wales, and the [[Privy Council]] appointed a committee to decide on the location of the two institutions.&lt;ref name=about-nlw &gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.llgc.org.uk/index.php?id=6| title=About NLW|publisher=NLW official website}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[David Lloyd George]], who later became Prime Minister, supported the effort to establish the National Library in Aberystwyth,&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt; which was selected as the location of the library after a bitter fight with [[Cardiff]], partly because a collection was already available in the College. [[Sir John Williams, 1st Baronet, of the City of London|Sir John Williams]], physician and book collector, had also said he would present his collection (in particular, the [[Peniarth Manuscripts|Peniarth collection of manuscripts]]) to the library if it were established in Aberystwyth. He also eventually gave £20,000 to build and establish the library. Cardiff was eventually selected as the location of the [[National Museum of Wales]]. Funds for both the National Library and the National Museum were contributed by the subscriptions of the working classes, which was unusual in the establishment of such institutions. In a Prefatory Note to ''A List of Subscribers to the Building Fund'' (1924), the first librarian, John Ballinger, estimates that there were almost 110,000 contributors.&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt; The Library and Museum were established by [[Royal Charter]] on 19 March 1907.&lt;ref name=about-nlw /&gt;&lt;ref name=Fishlock&gt;{{cite book|last1=Fishlock|first1=Trevor|title=In this place: the National Library of Wales|date=2007|publisher=National Library of Wales|location=Aberystwyth|isbn=9781862250543|pages=11, 35, 86, 92–93, 139–141, 188–189, 193–197}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Charter stipulated that if the National Library of Wales should be removed from Aberystwyth then the manuscripts donated by Sir John Williams will become the property of the University College.&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt;&lt;ref name=nlw-sir-john&gt;{{cite web|title=Sir John Williams' Collection|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/learn-more/printedmaterials/syrjohnwilliamscollection/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=26 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; A new Royal Charter was granted in 2006.

The National Library of Wales was granted the privilege of legal deposit under the 1911 Copyright Act. Initially, however, the Library could only claim material deemed to be of Welsh and Celtic interest without any restrictions on expensive or limited edition publications.&lt;ref name=Walters &gt;{{cite book|last1=Walters|first1=Gwyn|editor1-last=Jones|editor1-first=Philip Henry|editor2-last=Rees|editor2-first=Eiluned|title=A nation and its books : a history of the book in Wales|date=1998|publisher=National Library of Wales|location=Aberystwyth|isbn= 9781862250093|chapter=The National Library of Wales, the art of the book, and Welsh bibliography|pages=387–398}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1987, the last of these restrictions were removed to make the legal deposit entitlement of the National Library of Wales equal to those of the [[Bodleian Library]], [[Cambridge University Library]], [[Trinity College Library]], Dublin and the [[National Library of Scotland]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Bell|first1=Hazel K.|title=Legal deposit in Euston Street|journal=Serials|date=1992|volume=5|issue=3|pages=53–57|url=http://serials.uksg.org/articles/10.1629/050353/galley/198/download/|accessdate=23 July 2015|doi=10.1629/050353}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first use of the [[Library of Congress Classification]] by a library in Britain was at the National Library of Wales in 1913.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Attar|first1=Karen|editor1-last=Howsam|editor1-first=Leslie|title=The Cambridge companion to the history of the book|date=2014|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Cambridge|pages=17–35|chapter=Books in the library}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Buildings===
On 15 July 1911 [[King George V]] and Queen Mary laid the foundation stone of the National Library of Wales.&lt;ref name=Griffiths&gt;{{cite book|last1=Griffiths|first1=Rhidian|title=Y ddinas ar y bryn : Llyfrgell Genedlaethol Cymru trwy luniau = The city on the hill : The National Library of Wales in pictures|date=2007|publisher=Llyfrgell Genedlaethol Cymru / The National Library of Wales|location=Aberystwyth|isbn=9781862250598}}&lt;/ref&gt; Designed by architect [[Sidney Greenslade]], who won the competition to design the building in 1909, the building at Grogythan,&lt;ref&gt;Wmffre, Iwan, 'National Library', ''The Place-Names of Cardiganshire'', Vol. III, pp. 980–981 (BRA British Series 379 (III), 2004, ISBN 1-84171-665-0)&lt;/ref&gt; off Penglais Hill, was ready for occupation in August 1915 but the task of transferring the collections was not completed until 1 March 1916, [[St. David's Day]].&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt; The central block, or ''[[corps de logis]]'', was added by [[Charles Holden]] to a modified version of Greenslade's design. It was completed in 1937 and is a [[Grade II* listed building]].&lt;ref name=Griffiths /&gt;
&lt;ref&gt; {{cite web|url=http://www.britishlistedbuildings.co.uk/wa-10417-national-library-of-wales-penglais-road-p#.Voq_r09_cnM|title=National Library of Wales, Penglais Road, Penglais, Aberystwyth Date Listed: 21 July 1961 Cadw Building ID: 10417 |publisher= British Listed Buildings|accessdate= 4 January 2016}} &lt;/ref&gt;

The Library is faced with Portland stone on the upper storeys which contrasts with the Cornish granite below it.&lt;ref name=Wales_[journal]_1946 /&gt; Restoration work was necessary in 1969 and 1983 due to the effects of weathering on the Portland stone.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title = The National Library of Wales: A history of the building.|last = Huws|first = Daniel|publisher = The National Library of Wales|year = 1994|isbn = 0907158676|location = Aberystwyth}}&lt;/ref&gt; In recent years many changes have been made to the front part of the building.

The large North Reading Room, where printed books are consulted, has &quot;the proportions of a Gothic Cathedral&quot;, being 175 feet long, 47 feet wide and 33 feet high. There are galleries at three levels above the floor. The feasibility of installing a mezzanine floor to make better use of the space has been considered on two occasions. The South Reading Room is used for consulting archives, manuscripts, maps and other printed materials. Carved above the entrance is the room's original name the Print and Maps Room. Above it on the second floor of the south wing is the Gregynog Gallery where temporary and permanent exhibitions display the treasures of the Library's collections.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

A six-storey bookstack, which was completed in 1931, was built to increase storage space for the rapidly expanding book collection.&lt;ref name=Griffiths /&gt; A second bookstack was officially opened in March 1982.&lt;ref name=Griffiths /&gt; In 1996, the Third Library Building was opened, doubling the storage capacity of the Library.&lt;ref name=Griffiths /&gt; The second phase of the building was built by T. Alun Evans (Aberystwyth) Ltd.

A fire on 26 April 2013 destroyed a section of roofing in an office area of the building.&lt;ref name=bbc-fire&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-wales-mid-wales-22318791 National Library of Wales fire investigation to begin] [[BBC news]], Mid Wales, 27 April 2013]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-wales-22312017 Fire at National Library of Wales, Aberystwyth] BBC News 26 April 2013&lt;/ref&gt; Restoration was assisted by a government grant of £625,000.&lt;ref name=NLWminsSep2013&gt;[http://www.llgc.org.uk/fileadmin/fileadmin/docs_gwefan/amdanom_ni/llywodraethiant_llgc/Cofnodion_saesneg/bdd_cof_130927S.pdf NLW Board Minutes, 27 September 2013] at official website&lt;/ref&gt;

===Wartime sanctuary===
During the [[Second World War]], many of Britain's most valuable artworks and manuscripts were stored in the National Library of Wales, which provided the evacuated treasures with a refuge from enemy bombing raids.&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt;&lt;ref name=BBC-da_vinci&gt;{{cite web|title=Da Vinci art put in cave in WWII|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/wales/mid/7820055.stm|publisher=BBC|accessdate=25 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The architect Charles Holden was instructed to design a tunnel for this purpose in the outcrop of rock close to the main building, with the [[British Museum]] sharing in the costs that this incurred. The tunnel was heated and ventilated to ensure the preservation of vellum, papyri and paper during its use from 18 July 1940 until 23 May 1945. In addition to an extensive consignment from the British Museum,&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt; which weighed over one hundred tons,&lt;ref name=&quot;The British Museum&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Letter relating to evacuation of the British Museum's collections during the Second World War|url=http://www.britishmuseum.org/explore/highlights/highlight_objects/archives/l/letter_relating_to_evacuation.aspx|publisher=The British Museum|accessdate=25 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Library received forty-six boxes of manuscript and printed books from [[Corpus Christi College, Cambridge]] and over a thousand pictures, eighty-two boxes of books and twenty members of staff from the [[National Gallery]].&lt;ref name=Jenkins&gt;{{cite book|last1=Jenkins|first1=David|title=A refuge in peace and war : the National Library of Wales to 1952|date=2002|publisher=National Library of Wales|location=Aberystwyth|isbn=1862250340|pages=xi, 60–65, 93, 96, 99–101, 129, 168, 174, 266–269}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Library also received irreplaceable items from other prestigious institutions such as the [[Ashmolean Museum]], Oxford, [[Dulwich College]] and [[the Royal Society]].&lt;ref name=Davies1945&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Davies|first1=William Ll.|title=War-time evacuation to the National Library of Wales|journal=Transactions of the Honourable Society of Cymmrodorion [Trafodion Anrhydeddus Gymdeithas y Cymmrodorion]|date=1945|pages=171–178|url=http://cylchgronaucymru.llgc.org.uk/browse/viewpage/llgc-id:1386666/llgc-id:1412891/llgc-id:1413072/getText|accessdate=26 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A number of distinguished scholars from the British Museum accompanied the collections to Aberystwyth.&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt; Their senior member of staff was Deputy Keeper of Printed Books, Victor Scholderer, who responded to a [http://www.britishmuseum.org/explore/highlights/highlight_image.aspx?image=ps342852.jpg&amp;retpage=16254 letter] from the Director, [[John Forsdyke|Sir John Forsdyke]], by insisting that he and his colleagues would continue to sleep in the Library so that the tunnel could be checked during the night to ensure that the air conditioning was functioning properly.&lt;ref name=&quot;The British Museum&quot;/&gt; Scholderer, an expert on [[incunabula]], produced ''A Handlist of Incunabula in the National Library of Wales'' in gratitude to the hospitality that was afforded to them by the Library.&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt; Likewise, [[Arthur E. Popham]], Keeper of Prints and Drawings, dedicated ''The Drawings of Leonardo da Vinci'' ″To the Librarian and staff of the National Library of Wales″.&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt;&lt;ref name=Davies1945 /&gt; Several other institutions donated funds to the Library as an expression of their gratitude&lt;ref name=Davies1945 /&gt; and Mrs. David Sassoon, London presented two works by Cicero that were printed at Venice in the fifteenth century.&lt;ref name=Dept._of_printed_books_(NLW-Journal) /&gt;

The artefacts that spent World War II in the care of the National Library include [[the Magna Carta]],&lt;ref name=BBC-da_vinci /&gt; drawings by [[Leonardo da Vinci]],&lt;ref name=BBC-da_vinci /&gt; paintings by [[Rembrandt]], [[Peter Paul Rubens|Rubens]] and [[Diego Velázquez|Velásquez]] from [[Dulwich College]],&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt; letters of the kings and queens of England,&lt;ref name=BBC-da_vinci /&gt; and manuscripts written by [[William Shakespeare]].&lt;ref name=BBC-da_vinci /&gt;

=== Librarians ===
*[[John Ballinger (librarian)|John Ballinger]] (1909–1930)
*[[William Llewelyn Davies]] (1930–1952)
*[[Thomas Parry (author)|Thomas Parry]] (1953–1958)
*[[E. D. Jones]] (1958–1969)
*[[David Jenkins (librarian)|David Jenkins]] (1969–1979)
*[[R. Geraint Gruffydd]] (1980–1985)
*[[Brynley F. Roberts]] (1985–1994)
*[[J. Lionel Madden]] (1994–1998)
*[[Andrew Green (librarian)|Andrew M. Green]] (1998–2013)
*[[Aled Gruffydd Jones]] (2013–2015)&lt;ref name=NLWminsSep2013/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aber.ac.uk/en/news/archive/2013/02/title-127142-en.html 'New National Librarian' – [[University of Aberystwyth]] Newsletter – 25 February 2013]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Linda Tomos (from 1 November 2015)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The National Library of Wales appoints Chief Executive and Librarian.|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/information-for/press-and-media/press-releases/2015-press-releases/the-national-library-of-wales-appoints-chief-executive-and-librarian/|publisher=The National Library of Wales|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 17 June 2015 [[Wales Online]] reported that National Librarian Aled Gruffydd Jones had resigned after a report was published criticising the handling of disciplinary proceedings against two senior managers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Shipton|first1=Martin|title=Wales' National Librarian resigns days after report criticises handling of disciplinary action against two senior managers|url=http://www.walesonline.co.uk/news/wales-news/wales-national-librarian-resigns-days-9682073|website=Welsh Online|accessdate=21 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.llgc.org.uk/fileadmin/fileadmin/docs_gwefan/amdanom_ni/llywodraethiant_llgc/Cofnodion_saesneg/nlw_independent_external_review_report_10072015.pdf The National Library of Wales: Independent external review] Final report of PricewaterhouseCoopers LLP, July 2015&lt;/ref&gt;

== Library collections ==
The collections of the National Library of Wales include over 6.5 million printed volumes,&lt;ref name=NLWstrategy&gt;{{cite web|title=Knowledge for all: NLW strategy 2014 – 2017|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/fileadmin/fileadmin/docs_gwefan/amdanom_ni/dogfennaeth_gorfforaethol/corff_strat_KnowledgeforAll_2014_2017S.pdf|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=21 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; including the first book printed in Welsh, ''[[Yny lhyvyr hwnn]]'' (1546).&lt;ref name=Yny-lhyvyr-hwnn&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.llgc.org.uk/index.php?id=ynylhyvyrhwnn| title=The first printed Welsh book: Yny lhyvyr hwnn (1546)| publisher=NLW official website}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to the printed book collections, there are about 25,000 manuscripts in the holdings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Manuscripts|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/learn-more/introduction0/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=27 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The archival collections at the Library include the Welsh Political Archive&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.llgc.org.uk/index.php?id=503| title=The Welsh Political Archive| publisher=NLW official website}}&lt;/ref&gt; and National Screen and Sound Archive of Wales.&lt;ref name=screen-archive &gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.archif.com/index.php?id=3977| title=National Screen and Sound Archive of Wales| publisher=National Library of Wales}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Library also keeps maps,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.llgc.org.uk/index.php?id=introduction3| title=The Map Collection| publisher=NLW official website}}&lt;/ref&gt; photographs,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.llgc.org.uk/index.php?id=introduction2| title=The National Collection of Welsh Photographs| publisher=NLW official website}}&lt;/ref&gt; paintings, topographical and landscape prints,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.llgc.org.uk/index.php?id=portraits| title=The Picture Collection| publisher=NLW official website}}&lt;/ref&gt; periodicals and newspapers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.llgc.org.uk/index.php?id=6169| title=Welsh Newspapers Online| publisher=NLW official website}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.llgc.org.uk/index.php?id=5669| title=List of the newspapers that have been identified for digitisation| publisher=NLW official website}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, the Peniarth Manuscript collection and [[The Life Story of David Lloyd George]] were amongst the first ten inscriptions on the [[UK Memory of the World Register]], a [[UNESCO]] record of documentary heritage of cultural significance.&lt;ref name=memory-of-the-world /&gt;

Collection development is focused on materials relating to the people of Wales, those in the Welsh language and resources for Celtic studies,&lt;ref name=NLWcdp&gt;{{cite web|title=Collections Development Policy|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/fileadmin/fileadmin/docs_gwefan/amdanom_ni/dogfennaeth_gorfforaethol/dog_gorff_pol_dat_cas_10S.pdf|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=21 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Brinley Jones&quot; /&gt; but other materials are collected for the purposes of education and literary and scientific research.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brinley Jones&quot; /&gt; As a [[copyright library|legal deposit library]], the National Library is entitled to request a copy of every work published in the United Kingdom and Ireland.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Introduction to legal deposit|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/legaldeposit/introduction/|publisher=NLW official website|accessdate=20 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Legal Deposit|url=https://www.tcd.ie/Library/collection-man/legal-deposit.php|publisher=Trinity College Dublin|accessdate=21 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Agency for the Legal Deposit Libraries|url=http://www.legaldeposit.org.uk/index.html|publisher=Agency for the Legal Deposit Libraries|accessdate=21 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; This has allowed the Library to collect modern Welsh, Irish and Gaelic language books for its Celtic collection.&lt;ref name=Dept._of_printed_books_(NLW-Journal) /&gt; The acquisition of material through legal deposit has been supplemented by purchases, international exchanges, donations and bequests.&lt;ref name=Walters /&gt;

The Celtic collection includes works in all six Celtic languages. A representative collection of [[Scottish Gaelic]] books has been assembled, primarily through purchase of earlier publications, guided by the standard bibliographies, and, for books published after 1911, by legal deposit. Irish literature, which is far more extensive, has been collected through a similar combination of purchase and deposit. However, many collections purchased by or donated to the Library have contained rare Irish books. The Library of Dr E. C. Quiggin, which was received in 1921, contained a large Irish collection and many early [[Breton language|Breton]] books. Further Breton books have been purchased or were acquired in the libraries of [[Edward Anwyl|Sir Edward Anwyl]], Thomas Powel, [[Thomas Gwynn Jones|Dr Thomas Gwynn Jones]], Dr Paul Diverres and [[Llywarch Reynolds]]. The holdings of Cornish and Manx printed books include practically everything that has been published in those languages, with a few facsimiles.&lt;ref name=Dept._of_printed_books_(NLW-Journal) /&gt;

The online catalogue of the National Library is available to search using [http://wales.aquabrowser.com/AquaBrowser]. The Library's holdings can also be found in the [[European Library]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Discover Contributors|url=http://www.theeuropeanlibrary.org/tel4/discover/contributors|publisher=The European Library|accessdate=28 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Copac]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Libraries on Copac|url=http://copac.jisc.ac.uk/about/libraries/|publisher=JISC|accessdate=28 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; union catalogues.

=== Manuscripts ===
The National Library of Wales keeps many rare and important manuscripts, including the [[Black Book of Carmarthen]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.llgc.org.uk/index.php?id=blackbookofcarmarthen| title=The Black Book of Carmarthen| publisher=NLW official website}}&lt;/ref&gt; (the earliest surviving manuscript entirely in Welsh), the [[Book of Taliesin]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.llgc.org.uk/index.php?id=bookoftaliesinpeniarthms2| title=The book of Taliesin : digital version| publisher=NLW official website}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Hendregadredd Manuscript]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Hendregadredd Manuscript|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/?id=253|publisher=NLW official website|accessdate=20 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the works of [[Geoffrey Chaucer]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.llgc.org.uk/index.php?id=thehengwrtchaucerpeniarth| title=The Hengwrt Chaucer| publisher=NLW official website}}&lt;/ref&gt; Around three hundred medieval manuscripts are deposited in the Library: about 100 are in Welsh.&lt;ref name=guide-to-mss-dept /&gt; The manuscript collection amalgamated a number of entire collections that were acquired in the early years of the Library's existence, including the Hengwrt-Peniarth, Mostyn, Llanstephan, Panton, Cwrtmawr, Wrexham and Aberdare manuscripts.&lt;ref name=guide-to-mss-dept&gt;{{cite book|last1=The National Library of Wales|title=Guide to the Department of Manuscripts and Records|date=1994|publisher=National Library of Wales|location=Aberystwyth|isbn=0907158803}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Handlist_of_Manuscripts_vol.1&gt;{{cite book|last1=National Library of Wales|title=Handlist of Manuscripts in the National Library of Wales, Volume I|date=1943|publisher=National Library of Wales|location=Aberystwyth}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Welsh manuscripts in these foundation collections were catalogued by Dr J. Gwenogvryn Evans in the ''Reports on manuscripts in the Welsh language'' that he compiled for the Historic Manuscripts Commission.&lt;ref name=Handlist_of_Manuscripts_vol.1 /&gt;

==== Peniarth Manuscripts ====
[[File:Laws of Hywel Dda (f.1.v) King Hywel.jpg|thumb|200px|Laws of Hywel Dda (f.1.[[recto and verso|v]]) King Hywel]] [[File:CHAUCER Hengwrt.jpg|thumb|200px|Hengwrt Chaucer]] [[File:Vaux Passional. Henry VIII (f.9).jpg|thumb|200px|Vaux Passional (f.9r). In the first miniature the sovereign (King Henry VII) is presented with this book while the infant Henry VIII (upper left) mourns the death of his mother.]]
The [[Peniarth Manuscripts|Peniarth Manuscripts collection]] is considered to be of global significance and the most important collection of manuscripts in the National Library of Wales. In 2010, it was included in the UK Memory of the World Register of documentary heritage.&lt;ref name=memory-of-the-world&gt;{{cite web|title=2010 UK Memory of the World Register|url=http://www.unesco.org.uk/2010-uk-memory-of-the-world-register/|publisher=United Kingdom National Commission for UNESCO|accessdate=26 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=nlw-peniarth&gt;{{cite web|title=The Peniarth Manuscripts|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/learn-more/introduction0/llawysgrifaupeniarth/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=26 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of the 561 volumes of manuscripts in the Peniarth collection, some four-fifths were collected by [[Robert Vaughan (antiquary)|Robert Vaughan]] (c. 1592–1667) for his library in Hengwrt, Meirioneth.&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt;&lt;ref name=memory-of-the-world /&gt;&lt;ref name=nlw-peniarth /&gt; Three of the [[Four Ancient Books of Wales]] are part of the Peniarth collection, and this is indicative of the overall quality of the manuscripts and their importance as part of Welsh heritage. There are, however, also manuscripts in Cornish, Latin and English that are themselves noteworthy.&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt;&lt;ref name=nlw-peniarth /&gt; The collection includes:
* The [[Black Book of Carmarthen]] (c. 1250), the earliest manuscript in Welsh (Peniarth MS 1).&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt;&lt;ref name=nlw-peniarth /&gt;
* The [[Book of Taliesin]] (c. 1350–1400) contains the oldest Welsh verse by the sixth-century poet Taliesin (Peniarth MS 2).&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt;&lt;ref name=nlw-peniarth /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Book of Taliesin|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/digital-gallery/digitalmirror-manuscripts/the-middle-ages/bookoftaliesinpeniarthms2/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=28 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[White Book of Rhydderch]] (c. 1350), a composite volume that contains the earliest version of the [[Mabinogion]] (Peniarth MS 4).&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt;&lt;ref name=nlw-peniarth /&gt;
* The earliest fragments of ''Branwen and Manawydan'' and two fragments of ''Geraint ap Erbin'' comprise the four parts of [[Peniarth 6|Peniarth MS 6]].
* ''Ystoryaeu Seint Greal'' (Tales of the Holy Grail), transcribed by Hywel Fychan around the year 1300, is the finest in a series of Romance manuscripts. A letter addressed to [[Lady Charlotte Guest]] concerning access to this text to have it copied is loose inside the volume (Peniarth MS 11).&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Ystoryaeu Seint Greal, [14–15 cents]|url=http://cat.llgc.org.uk/cgi-bin/gw/chameleon?lng=en&amp;search=KEYWORD&amp;function=CARDSCR&amp;u1=12101&amp;t1=004440952|website=Full catalogue|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=29 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Peniarth 20|Chronicle of the Princes]] in Peniarth MS 20 (c. 1330) is one of the two main versions of ''[[Brut y Tywysogion]]'', the other being the [[Red Book of Hergest]], which is in the [[Bodleian Library]], Oxford.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Chronicle of the Princes|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/digital-gallery/digitalmirror-manuscripts/the-middle-ages/chronicleoftheprincespeniar/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=28 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[History of the Kings (Peniarth 23C)|History of the Kings]] (Peniarth MS 23C), is a copy of ''[[Brut y Brenhinedd]]'', the Welsh translation of ''Historia Regum Britanniae'' by Geoffrey of Monmouth. It is a rare instance of an illustrated medieval Welsh manuscript. 
* The [[Cyfraith Hywel#Manuscripts|Laws of Hywel Dda]] (c. 1300–1350), the earliest extant text (in Latin) of native Welsh law ([[Peniarth 28|Peniarth MS 28]]).&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Peniarth 28 : a Latin text of the Laws of Hywel Dda|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/digital-gallery/digitalmirror-manuscripts/the-middle-ages/lawsofhyweldda/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=28 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; More than 50% of the manuscripts known to contain the laws of [[Hywel Dda]] are in the collections of the National Library, with the majority being in the Peniarth Collection (see the list of [[A list of Welsh Law manuscripts|Welsh Law manuscripts]]).
* ''Llyfr Du'r Waun'' (mid-13th century), also known as the [[Black Book of Chirk]], the earliest Welsh text of the laws of Hywel Dda (Peniarth MS 29).&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt;
* [[Peniarth 32]] is a 15th-century volume of the laws of Hywel Dda.
* The [[Peniarth 51]] manuscript contains poetry, Welsh grammar, vocabularies, and historical triads that was written, mostly in the hand of [[Gwilym Tew]], during the second half of the 15th century.
* ''[[Barddoniaeth Hywel Dafi]]'' (c. 1483–1500), a volume of poetry most by and possibly in the hand of Howel Davi.&lt;ref name=peniarth-poetry&gt;{{cite web|title=Dafydd ap Gwilym and the Cywyddwyr|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/index.php?id=dafyddapgwilymandthecywyddw|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=30 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Roberts&gt;{{cite book|last1=Roberts|first1=E. Stanton|title=Reprints of Welsh Manuscripts: Peniarth MS. 67|date=1918|publisher=The Guide of Graduates of the University of Wales|location=Cardiff|pages=iii–xiii}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other poets included in this volume are Bedo Brwynllys, Dafydd Llwyd, Llywelyn ap Morgan, Dafydd ap Gwilym and Ieuan ap Howel. The assumption that this manuscript was written by Howel Davi is challenged by evidence, such as slips of the pen that occur in poems of Davi's composition, that suggest the scribe was copying these poems. With the exception of two sections (42 and 43), which are an attempt at transcription by an unskilled hand, the entire manuscript appears to be the work of one scribe (Peniarth MS 67).&lt;ref name=Roberts /&gt;
* [[Beunans Meriasek]] (The Life Of St [[Meriasek]]) (1504), the earliest surviving manuscript in the [[Cornish language]] (Peniarth MS 105B).&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt;&lt;ref name=nlw-peniarth /&gt;&lt;ref name=Beunans /&gt; It is believed to have been completed in 1504 by Radolphus Ton, who was a canon during the final efflorescence of [[Cornish literature]] at [[Glasney College]], Penryn. This play, which is set in [[Camborne]], is a celebration of the life and work of [[St Meriasek]] that depicts the cultural links between [[Cornwall]] and [[Brittany]].&lt;ref name=Beunans &gt;{{cite web|title=Beunans Meriasek (The Life Of St Meriasek)|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/?id=265|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=23 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Kent|first1=Alan M.|title=The literature of Cornwall : continuity, identity, difference, 1000–2000|date=2000|publisher=Redcliffe Press|location=Bristol|isbn=1900178281|pages=45, 48}}&lt;/ref&gt; Beunans Meriasek was rediscovered by W. W. E. Wynne in the 1860s among the volumes from the Hengwrt Library that had been bequeathed to him in 1859.&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt;&lt;ref name=Beunans /&gt; It is the most important extant Cornish manuscript.&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt;
* ''Cywyddau'' and other poems, written in the hand of [[Lewys Glyn Cothi]], comprise the manuscript [[Peniarth 109]].
* ''[[Peniarth 164|Esboniadau ar Gyfraith Hywel Dda]]'' (Peniarth MS 164), is a volume of commentaries on the Laws of Hywel Dda from the early 15th century. 
* [[Peniarth 259B|Peniarth Manuscript 259B]] is a version of the Laws of Hywel Dda from the mid-16th century.
* The [[Hengwrt Chaucer]] (c. 1400–10), a folio volume of ''Canterbury Tales'' produced by the scribe [[Adam Pinkhurst]]. One of the treasures of the National Library of Wales and by far the most important of the Peniarth Manuscripts in English (Peniarth MS 392D).&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Hengwrt Chaucer|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/digital-gallery/digitalmirror-manuscripts/the-middle-ages/thehengwrtchaucerpeniarth/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=29 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The 15th century volume comprising ''Disticha Catonis'', the Battles of Alexander the Great, and History of the Three Kings ([[Peniarth 481]]D),  and the late 15th century ''[[Vaux Passional]]'' (Peniarth 482), which was prepared for [[Henry VII of England|Henry VII]], were acquired and deposited in the National Library by [[Gwendoline Davies|Gwendoline]] and [[Margaret Davies]] in 1921. These two fine illuminated manuscripts were retained by W. R. M. Wynne when he sold the Peniarth Manuscripts to Sir John Williams.&lt;ref name=Dept_of_MSS_(NLW_Journal)&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Jones|first1=E. D.|title=The Department of Manuscripts and Records|journal=National Library of Wales Journal|date=1947|volume=5|issue=2|pages=96–120}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* A bound volume containing books by Giovanni Battista Palatino and [[Ugo da Carpi]], both notable Italian masters of the 16th century, which is assumed to have been owned by [[John Jones of Gellilyfdy]] (Peniarth MS 522).&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt; 
* [[Bede]]'s ''De natura rerum'' (12th century), a scientific treatise in Latin that is believed to have been written in Wales. Contains decorative initials, including three that have a zoomorphic design similar to those found in Irish manuscripts from this time (Peniarth MS 540B).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Bede’s De natura rerum|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/digital-gallery/digitalmirror-manuscripts/the-middle-ages/de-natura-rerum/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=29 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Over forty manuscripts in the hand of John Jones of Gellilyfdy, embellished with initial capital letters and head- and tailpieces that demonstrate his calligraphic talent.&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt;

==== Llanstephan Manuscripts ====
The [[Llanstephan]] Collection of manuscripts was donated to the National Library of Wales by Sir John Williams in 1909. It had been his personal collection, which he kept in the library of his home, Llanstephan mansion, Carmarthenshire.&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt;&lt;ref name=llanstephan /&gt; The collection is composed of the 154 manuscripts which had belonged to [[Moses Williams (antiquarian)|Moses Williams]] (1685–1742),&lt;ref name=guide-to-mss-dept /&gt; that were purchased from [[Shirburn Castle]], Oxfordshire and other manuscripts of diverse origins collected by Sir John. Medieval Welsh prose is well represented in the Shirburn Castle collection, with chronicles, legends, fables, theological tracts and collections of works by eminent poets of the period. These manuscripts include a Welsh translation of Geoffrey of Monmouth's ''Historia'' from the 13th century, the [[Gutun Owain]] Manuscript and the Red Book of Talgarth.&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt;&lt;ref name=llanstephan&gt;{{cite web|title=The Llanstephan Manuscripts|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/learn-more/introduction0/llawysgrifaullanstephan/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=30 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Cwrtmawr Manuscripts ====
{{main|Cwrtmawr manuscripts}}
The Cwrtmawr Manuscripts are one of the significant manuscript collections that were transferred to the National Library of Wales in the early years of its existence. They are from the personal collection of [[John Humphreys Davies]], who was the Principal of University College, Aberystwyth.&lt;ref name=Cwrtmawr-Manuscripts&gt;{{cite web|title=The Cwrtmawr Manuscripts|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/learn-more/introduction0/llawysgrifaucwrtmawr/|publisher=The National Library of Wales|accessdate=14 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Davies was a barrister and a keen book collector who acquired the manuscripts gradually from a number of sources. The largest group of manuscripts are those acquired from [[Myrddin Fardd|John Jones ('Myrddin Fardd')]], but there are several other substantial groups including those from a Welsh clerical family, the Richards of Darowen, [[Peter Bailey Williams]] and his brother Rev. St George Armstrong Williams, William John Roberts (‘Gwilym Cowlyd’), and [[Daniel Silvan Evans]].&lt;ref name=Cwrtmawr_catalogue&gt;{{cite book|last1=Owens|first1=B.G.|last2=McDonald|first2=R.W.|title=A catalogue of the Cwrtmawr manuscripts presented and bequeathed by John Humphreys Davies|date=1980|publisher=National Library of Wales|location=Aberystwyth}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== General Manuscript Collection ====
{{main|National Library of Wales General Manuscript Collection}}
[[File:Llanbeblig Hours (f. 2r.) The Annunciation, The Virgin Mary enthroned under a green canopy..jpg|thumb|150px|Llanbeblig Hours (f. 2r.) The 'Lily Crucifixion' Annunciation scene with The Virgin Mary enthroned under a green canopy.]][[File:Medieval Astronomy (f.4v).jpg|thumb|150px|Medieval Astronomy (f.4v)]]
[[File:Liber Lanavensis f.5.png|thumb|150px|NLW MS 17110E ''Liber Lanavensis'' f.5r]]

In addition to the Peniarth and Llanstephan manuscripts, the collection that Sir John Williams donated to the National Library included 500 manuscripts in the general collection (NLW MS 1–500). These manuscripts are an amalgamation of the various purchases that Sir John made between 1894 and 1899, including groups of manuscripts from the Welsh philologist Egerton Phillimore, [[Sir Thomas Phillipps]] of Middle Hill, the Ashburn library and [[Sir Edmund Buckley, 1st Baronet|Sir Edmund Buckley]] of Plas Dinas Mawddwy. Descriptions of 446 of these manuscripts are provided by J. H. Davies in ''Additional Manuscripts in the Collections of Sir John Williams'', which the Library published in 1921.&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt;&lt;ref name=Handlist_of_Manuscripts_vol.1 /&gt; The manuscripts in the National Library which are not part of the foundation collections are the focus of the ''Handlist of manuscripts'', which was first published in 1941.&lt;ref name=guide-to-mss-dept /&gt; All manuscripts acquired by donation or purchase are added to this open-ended series, either singly or in groups, if they are: a) in a format compatible with the collection, i.e. manuscript books or rolls, or unbound material that can be filed; and b) not integral to an archive or individual collection. There is, however, much archival material, most notably correspondence, held in the General Manuscript Collection.&lt;ref name=guide-to-mss-dept /&gt; Individual manuscripts of particular interest include:

*A volume of medieval astronomy texts is the oldest scientific manuscript in the National Library ([[NLW MS 735C Astronomy|NLW MS 735C]]). The first section of the volume was written around 1000 and the second dates from c.1150. Both sections were copied in the [[Limousin]] region of France. The Latin text describes the constellations with the aid of diagrams and colour illustrations of Zodiac images.&lt;ref name=Fishlock /&gt;&lt;ref name=astronomy&gt;{{cite web|title=Medieval Astronomy|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/digital-gallery/digitalmirror-manuscripts/the-middle-ages/medievalastronomy/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=21 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The [[Black Book of Basingwerk]] (NLW MS 7006D) is a 15th-century manuscript containing a version of ''Brut y Brenhinedd'', a Welsh translation of Geoffrey of Monmouth's ''[[Historia Regum Britanniae]]''. Particular features of interest include the medieval wooden board binding and the decorated initials embellished with gold.&lt;ref name=Fishlock /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Black Book of Basingwerk|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/digital-gallery/digitalmirror-manuscripts/the-middle-ages/blackbookofbasingwerknlwms/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=10 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The [[Llywarch Reynolds]] Manuscripts (NLW MS 970 to 997) are the 28 volumes that Llywarch Owain Reynolds bequeathed to the Library in 1916. The most notable among them is the 17th century collection of Welsh poetry, ''Llyuyr Hir Llywarch Reynolds''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Llywarch Reynolds Manuscripts|url=http://cat.llgc.org.uk/cgi-bin/gw/chameleon?sessionid=2015080622292101406&amp;skin=full&amp;lng=en&amp;inst=consortium&amp;host=lisbon.llgc.org.uk%2b9901%2bDEFAULT&amp;patronhost=lisbon.llgc.org.uk%209901%20DEFAULT&amp;search=KEYWORD&amp;function=FRBRSCR&amp;sourcescreen=CARDSCR&amp;pos=1&amp;rootsearch=KEYWORD&amp;elementcount=1&amp;u1=12101&amp;t1=004294683&amp;linkedbibid=4294683|website=Full Catalogue.|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=6 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The [[Book of Llandaff]] (NLW MS 17110E), also known as ''Liber Landavensis'', is an ecclesiastical manuscript written between 1120 and 1140.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = The Book of Llandaff|url = https://www.llgc.org.uk/discover/digital-gallery/digitalmirror-manuscripts/the-middle-ages/the-book-of-llandaff/|website = National Library of Wales|accessdate = 27 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The [[Llanbeblig Book of Hours]] (NLW MS 17520A) is a small manuscript book compiled around 1390. The manuscript has a number of entries in the calendar that connect it to Wales, including a celebration of the dedication of the church of Saint Peblig, Caernarfon. Isabella Godynogh (d. 1413) was possibly its original owner. The full-page miniatures, illuminated with gold, and the fine lettering indicate the value of the book.&lt;ref name=Fishlock /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Llanbeblig Book of Hours|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/digital-gallery/digitalmirror-manuscripts/the-middle-ages/thellanbebligbookofhoursnl/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=13 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Llanbeblig Hours is the only known illuminated manuscript that contains the iconographical Lily Crucifixion motif, and may be the earliest example of its use in any media.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Duggan|first1=E. J. M.|title=Notes concerning the 'Lily Crucifixion' in the Llanbeblig Hours|journal=National Library of Wales Journal|date=1991|volume=27|issue=1|pages=39–48}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[NLW MS 20143A]] is a manuscript of the laws of Hywel Dda written in Welsh around 1350. It is unusual in that it retains a medieval binding. 
*The Tintern Abbey Bible (NLW MS 22631C) is a 13th-century Bible that has a known association with the medieval library of the Cistercian monastery at Tintern, Monmouthshire. It was purchased by the National Library for £30,000 in a [[Christie's]] sale in December 1988&lt;ref name=Fishlock /&gt;&lt;ref name=Huws&gt;{{cite book|last1=Huws|first1=Daniel|title=Medieval Welsh manuscripts|date=2000|publisher=Univ. of Wales Press|location=Cardiff|isbn=0708316026|pages=158–168}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is the second book known to have survived from the Tintern library.&lt;ref name=Huws /&gt; Under ultraviolet light the erased 15th-century inscription ''Ista biblia olim Abbathie de Tinternie'' (This Bible used to [belong to] Tintern Abbey) is visible to confirm the provenance of the manuscript.&lt;ref name=Huws /&gt;
*[[Beunans Ke]] (NLW MS 23849D) is a 16th-century Cornish manuscript discovered among the papers of Professor J. E. Caerwyn Williams after they were deposited in the National Library in 2000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Beunans Ke|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/digital-gallery/digitalmirror-manuscripts/early-modern-period/beunanskenlwms23849d/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=6 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Groups of manuscripts in the general collection include:
{{columns-list|colwidth=25em|
* [[National Library of Wales General Manuscript Collection#Panton Manuscripts .28NLW MSS 1970-2068.29|Panton (NLW MSS 1970–2068)]]
* [[National Library of Wales General Manuscript Collection#Mostyn Manuscripts .28NLW MSS 3020-76.29|Mostyn (NLW MSS 3021-76 and 21238-54)]]
* [[National Library of Wales General Manuscript Collection#Bourdillon Manuscripts .28NLW MSS 5001-5148.29|Bourdillon (NLW MSS 5001–5148)]]
* [[National_Library_of_Wales_General_Manuscript_Collection#Llanover_Manuscripts_.28NLW_MSS_13061-184.29|Llanover (NLW MSS 13061-184)]]
* Gwysaney (NLW MSS 17110-62).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=National Library of Wales|title=General Manuscripts Collection|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/learn-more/introduction0/casgliadaullawysgrifcyffredino/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=11 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

=== Rare books ===
There are many rare books in the National Library of Wales including the three earliest books printed in Welsh,&lt;ref name=nlw-sir-john /&gt; ''Yny lhyvyr hwnn'' (1546),&lt;ref name=nlw-sir-john /&gt;&lt;ref name=Yny-lhyvyr-hwnn /&gt; ''Oll synnwyr pen Kembero ygyd'' (1547)&lt;ref name=nlw-sir-john /&gt; and ''A Dictionary in Englyshe and Welshe'' (1547) by [[William Salesbury]].&lt;ref name=nlw-sir-john /&gt; The Library also holds the first [[Welsh Bible|Welsh translation of the complete Bible]] (1588).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.llgc.org.uk/index.php?id=1588welshbible| title=Welsh Bible 1588| publisher=NLW official website}}&lt;/ref&gt; The National Library's rare books include collections of incunabula, sixteenth-century European imprints, private press publications, bindings and scientific works.&lt;ref name=Walters /&gt;

Thanks to the collections of printed books that were donated by Sir John Williams, J. H. Davies and Edward Humphrey Owen, the Library has particularly strong holdings of publications in the Welsh language from before 1912. Of the two hundred and eighty-six Welsh books published between 1546 and 1710, the National Library possesses copies of two hundred and ten, and has facsimiles of others that exist as a unique copy in another institution.&lt;ref name=Dept._of_printed_books_(NLW-Journal)&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Williams|first1=William|last2=Jones|first2=J.J.|last3=Lloyd|first3=D. Myrddin|title=The Department of Printed Books|journal=National Library of Wales Journal|date=1947|volume=5|issue=2|pages=121–154}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many of the named collections of printed books include early or otherwise rare books:
{{columns-list|colwidth=35em|
* Anderson Collection (purchased 1981): twenty-four [[Short-title catalogue|Short-title catalogue (STC)]] (1475–1640) and twenty-two [[Donald Wing#The Short-Title Catalogue .28STC.29|Wing]] (1641–1700) books; five editions from the [[Nonesuch Press]].
* [[Bangor Baptist College]] Collection: some thirty STC, ninety-five Wing and 185 eighteenth century items. 
* Castell Gorfod Collection (deposited in 1920): includes twenty STC and ninety Wing books.  
* [[Chirk Castle]] Collection: around seventy-five Wing items and many 18th century imprints.
* Early Law Collection: Approximately 120 works which include twenty STC, forty Wing and sixty [[English Short Title Catalogue|ESTC]] items.
* [[Llandaff Cathedral]] Library (deposited 1943, purchased 1984): one incunabulum, twenty-two STC and 234 Wing items.  
* [[St Asaph Cathedral]] Library (deposited 1970): around 2,500 volumes which include approximately 200 STC and 900 Wing items.
* [[Trefeca]] Collection (includes the collection of [[Howel Harris]]): 1,500 volumes with fifty STC and 350 Wing items. 
* [[United Theological College, Aberystwyth]] (deposited 1982): ten STC and forty Wing items.
* [[Rowland Williams (theologian)|Rowland Williams]] collection (deposited 1966): six STC, twelve Wing, and 191 ESTC books.&lt;ref name=A_directory_of_rare_books /&gt;  
}}

==== Sir John Williams Collection ====
[[File:Yny Lhyvyr hwnn title page.jpg|thumb|150px|Yny Lhyvyr hwnn. Attributed to Sir John Price, 1546]][[File:1588 First Welsh Bible.jpg|thumb|150px|First Welsh Bible, 1588]]
The Sir John Williams Collection forms the nucleus of the Library's printed books collection. The collection of approximately 23,360 volumes contains many items of importance to the history of Welsh printing, which were donated to the Library when it was established in 1907. Nineteen of the first twenty-two books published in Welsh are present,&lt;ref name=nlw-sir-john /&gt; of which fourteen were acquired from the Shirburn Castle library with the Llanstephan Manuscripts. The collection from Shirburn Castle comprises 193 printed books and pamphlets that were all printed before 1750; a superb miscellany of books from the first century of Welsh printing.&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt; Some of the particularly significant items that belonged to Sir John are:

* ''Yny lhyvyr hwnn ...'' [In this book ...] (1546) by [[John Prise|Sir John Prise]], the only known copy of the first book printed in Welsh.&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt;&lt;ref name=nlw-sir-john /&gt;
* ''Oll synnwyr pen Kembero ygyd'' by [[Gruffudd Hiraethog]] (1547).&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt;&lt;ref name=nlw-sir-john /&gt;
* William Salesbury's ''A Dictionary in Englyshe and Welshe'' (1547).&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt; 
* A translation of the New Testament by Salesbury (1567).&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt; The difficulty of reading Salesbury's pendantic translation prompted [[William Morgan (Bible translator)|William Morgan]], vicar of Llanrhaeadr-ym-Mochnant, to begin his translation of the Bible in 1578.&lt;ref name=Fishlock /&gt;
* ''Y drych Cristionogawl'' [The Christian Mirror] (1586–7), probably the earliest book printed in Wales.&lt;ref name=A_directory_of_rare_books /&gt;
* The first Welsh translation of the complete Bible by William Morgan (1588).&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt; Morgan's Bible not only strengthened the hold of the Protestant faith in Wales, it also created a new and accessible prose.&lt;ref name=Fishlock /&gt;
* [[John Penry|John Penry's]] pamphlet of 1588, ''An exhortation unto the governours.''&lt;ref name=A_directory_of_rare_books /&gt;
* The Welsh translation of the first part of Canisius's ''Opus catechisticum'' by Rosier Smyth, published in Paris, 1609.&lt;ref name=A_directory_of_rare_books /&gt; 
* ''Cân o senn iw hên Feistr Tobacco'' [A Diatribe against Tobacco] (1718), the only extant copy.&lt;ref name=Jenkins /&gt;
* Early editions of [[Morgan Llwyd]], [[Robert Recorde]], Henry and Thomas Vaughan, and the epigrammist John Owen.&lt;ref name=A_directory_of_rare_books /&gt;
* A comprehensive collection of publications from the [[Kelmscott Press]].&lt;ref name=Dept._of_printed_books_(NLW-Journal) /&gt;
* An 1488 edition of ''Lancelot du lac,'' part of a large Arthurian collection.&lt;ref name=A_directory_of_rare_books /&gt;
* A Fourth Folio of Shakespeare (1685).&lt;ref name=Dept._of_printed_books_(NLW-Journal) /&gt;

==== Ty Coch Collection ====
Purchased in 1910, the library of Edward Humphrey Owen (1850–1904), from Ty Coch, Caernarfon, is the third of the National Library of Wales' foundation collections. The 3,680 volumes are mainly of Welsh interest, with the 1567 New Testament and 1588 Bible to be found among some twenty books from the sixteenth century. Other items of interest are a first edition of Milton's ''Paradise lost'' (1668), numerous first editions of [[John Ruskin]] and [[George Borrow]], and books from the Baskerville and [[Strawberry Hill Press|Strawberry Hill]] presses.&lt;ref name=A_directory_of_rare_books /&gt;

==== John Humphreys Davies Bequest ====
When John Humphreys Davies died on 10 August 1926 he bequeathed his collection of over 10,000 printed volumes to the National Library of Wales. Davies was a keen bibliographer who acquired multiple copies of some works for variants in the typography and accumulated an important collection of Welsh literature, discovering some previously unrecorded works in the process. Some of the early Welsh books that Davies collected contain leaves or signatures that were not in the copies that the National Library already possessed.&lt;ref name=Dept._of_printed_books_(NLW-Journal) /&gt; The rare books include:
* ''Annerch ir Cymru'' (1721) by Ellis Pugh was the first Welsh book to be printed in America.&lt;ref name=Dept._of_printed_books_(NLW-Journal) /&gt;  
* A complete first edition of part one of ''Aleluja, neu, Casgliad o hymnau, ar amryw ystyriaethau'' (1744) by [[William Williams Pantycelyn|William Williams]] of Pantycelyn.&lt;ref name=Dept._of_printed_books_(NLW-Journal) /&gt;
* ''Testament Newydd'' (1567).&lt;ref name=Dept._of_printed_books_(NLW-Journal) /&gt; 
* ''Y Bibl'' (1630).&lt;ref name=Dept._of_printed_books_(NLW-Journal) /&gt;
* ''Ystyriaethau Drexelivs ar dragywyddoldeb'' (1661),&lt;ref name=Dept._of_printed_books_(NLW-Journal) /&gt; Ellis Lewis' Welsh translation, from the English translation by Winterton, of Jeremias Drexel's ''De aeternitate considerationes.''
* A previously unrecorded large paper issue of ''Y Bibl'' (1690).&lt;ref name=Dept._of_printed_books_(NLW-Journal) /&gt;
* A copy of the 1688 edition of ''Taith neu siwrnai y pererin'' [Pilgrim's Progress] is one of the seventy-three works by John Bunyan.&lt;ref name=Dept._of_printed_books_(NLW-Journal) /&gt;
* Eighty-three volumes of the works of [[William Williams Pantycelyn|William Williams]] of Pantycelyn.&lt;ref name=Dept._of_printed_books_(NLW-Journal) /&gt;

There are also substantial collections of pamphlets, elegies, almanacs, ballads, satires and tracts that Davies had collected.&lt;ref name=Dept._of_printed_books_(NLW-Journal) /&gt;

==== Bourdillon Collection ====
In 1922 the National Library of Wales purchased the collection of French medieval literary texts and early illustrated books that had been assembled by [[Francis William Bourdillon]] (1852–1921). Bourdillon's library included twenty-three editions of the ''Roman de la Rose'' and an important group of works on the Arthurian legend. The 6,178 printed volumes include sixty-six incunabula, 180 ''[[English Short Title Catalogue|English short title catalogue]]'' books (1475–1800), including twenty-five [[Short-title catalogue|''STC'']] and fifty [[Donald Wing#The Short-Title Catalogue .28STC.29|''Wing'']] books. Further, there are 320 volumes that were printed in continental Europe during the sixteenth century, and another 260 items which date from the 17th and 18th centuries.&lt;ref name=A_directory_of_rare_books /&gt;

==== Incunabula ====
The National Library has a collection of about 250 [[incunabula]], which are predominantly German, Italian and French imprints.&lt;ref name=Walters /&gt; Sixty-six of the incunabula, including seven different editions of the ''Roman de la Rose,''&lt;ref name=Walters /&gt; with the accepted first edition among them,&lt;ref name=Scholderer&gt;{{cite book|last1=Scholderer|first1=Victor|title=Handlist of Incunabula in the National Library of Wales; and Handlist ... Addenda &amp; Corrigenda I|date=1940|publisher=National Library of Wales|location=Aberystwyth|edition=National Library of Wales Journal Supplement Ser. I, No. 1; and I (2)}}&lt;/ref&gt;  are part Francis William Bourdillon's collection that was purchased by the Library in 1922. At least three of the incunabules acquired from Bourdillon's library are not known in any other copy: a ''Quatre fils Aymon,'' a ''Destruction de Jerusalem,'' and a ''Vie de Ste. Catherine.''&lt;ref name=Scholderer /&gt; Sir Charles Thomas-Stanford presented or bequeathed eighteen incunabula in total, half of which were printed in Germany.&lt;ref name=Dept._of_printed_books_(NLW-Journal) /&gt;

Three examples of early English printing were donated to the Library by Gwendoline and Margaret Davies of Gregynog in 1921. Two of these books were printed by [[William Caxton]]: ''Speculum Vitae Christi'' of 1488, and the copy of [[Ranulf Higden|Ranulf Higden's ''Polychronicon'']] (1482) that had previously been the property of Higden's Monastery, St. Werburgh's Abbey at Chester. The third is another copy of the Polychronicon, printed by Caxton's successor [[Wynkyn de Worde]] in 1495.&lt;ref name=Dept._of_printed_books_(NLW-Journal) /&gt; Nine specimens of early printed books (three German, five Italian and one printed in Ghent) were deposited by Lord Harlech between 1938 and 1941.&lt;ref name=Scholderer /&gt; Other notable incunabules in the Library are the ''Astronomica'' by [[Marcus Manilius]] (1474) with illuminated initials and borders, and [[Hartmann Schedel]]'s ''Liber Chronicarum'' (1493).&lt;ref name=Walters /&gt;

During the time that the incunabula expert, Dr. Victor Scholderer, Deputy-Keeper in the Department of Printed Books at the British Museum, spent in Aberystwyth during the Second World War, he took an interest in the National Library's small collection of fifteenth-century printed books and produced a ''Hand-list of incunabula'' that was published as a supplement to ''the National Library of Wales Journal.'' The hand-list and its addenda and corrigenda describes 129 books, mostly printed in Germany, Italy and France, although examples from the Netherlands and England were also listed. Scholderer noted that some of the forty-five books printed in France, particularly those in the vernacular, were very rare.&lt;ref name=Scholderer /&gt;

==== Sixteenth-century imprints ====
There are approximately 2,500 sixteenth-century European imprints in the Library. Works from the leading scholar-printers of the early sixteenth-century are represented in the collection, which covers a broad array of subjects.&lt;ref name=Walters /&gt;
&lt;ref name=A_directory_of_rare_books /&gt; These include [[Johann Froben]] (Basle), [[Jodocus Badius]] (Lyons and Paris), [[Robert Estienne]] (Paris) and [[Aldus Manutius]] (Venice). Aldus Manutius of Venice, who is known for his dolphin and anchor [[printer's device]], was the finest of the Italian printers of this period and about a hundred examples of his works, known as Aldines, are in the National Library. The Library's also owns works from the sixteenth-century Antwerp press of [[Christophe Plantin]] and his son-in-law, [[Balthasar Moretus]], who published De Symbolis Heroicis (1634) with its title-page designed by [[Peter Paul Rubens]].&lt;ref name=Walters /&gt; The collection of French medieval romances and editions of the ''Roman de la rose'' from the library of F. W. Bourdillon and the Aldines, which are from the collection of J. Burleigh James, are important features.&lt;ref name=&quot;A_directory_of_rare_books&quot; /&gt;

The National Library of Wales has one of the two copies of the 1539 edition of Miles Coverdale's [[Great Bible]], that were printed on vellum and illuminated throughout. The other copy is in the library of [[St John's College, Cambridge|St. John's College, Cambridge]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = http://welshjournals.llgc.org.uk/browse/viewpage/llgc-id:1277425/llgc-id:1277426/llgc-id:1277446/get650|title = A vellum copy of the 'Great Bible'|last = Sheppard|first = Leslie A.|date = 1939|journal = National Library of Wales Journal|doi = |pmid = |access-date = 2 December 2015|issue = 1|pages = 9–20|volume = 1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Private presses ====
The Library has a substantial private press collection, some 1,800 volumes in total, with representative examples from all of the important British presses.&lt;ref name=A_directory_of_rare_books /&gt; The holdings of ordinary and special bindings of the [[Gregynog Press]] books are comprehensive and along with the reference collection from Gregynog, form the core of the National Library's collection of private press editions.&lt;ref name=Walters /&gt; However, the Library also has a complete set of the [[Kelmscott Press]] publications that Sir John Williams collected, including ''The Works of Geoffrey Chaucer'' (1896). The private press collection has been developed through further acquisitions by donation, purchase and legal deposit, and contains examples of the productions by the [[Doves Press]], [[Ashendene Press]] and the [[Roxburghe Club]].&lt;ref name=Dept._of_printed_books_(NLW-Journal) /&gt; Works from foreign presses have been collected and include many publications of the [[Grolier Club]], the Bremer Presse edition of Luther's Bible (1926–8) and ''Eclogues'' of Virgil (1927) from the Cranach Press&lt;ref name=A_directory_of_rare_books /&gt;

==== Fine bindings ====
The National Library has many examples of books with fine bindings in its holdings. These include under-painted vellum, Victorian carved wood and papier-mâché bindings, French art nouveau bookbinding and bindings by Bernard C. Middleton and the Gregynog Press binder, George Fisher. In the late 1970s, the library acquired an archive recording the work of the Birdsall bindery, Northampton.&lt;ref name=Walters /&gt;

Bourdillon's library includes books printed before 1600 in their original pigskin or stamped calf bindings and some examples of modern fine binding.&lt;ref name=Dept._of_printed_books_(NLW-Journal) /&gt;

Examples of fore-edge paintings that depict topographical scenes in Wales have been collected by the National Library, including a view of Conway Castle and Bridge on a 1795 copy of ''The Poetical Works of John Cunningham'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Rees|first1=Eiluned|title=Bookbindings in the National Library of Wales|journal=National Library of Wales Journal|date=1985|volume=24|issue=2|pages=276–277}}&lt;/ref&gt; a rural view, stated to be Wales, painted on a 1795 edition of Milton's ''Paradise Lost'' bound by Edwards of Halifax, and a 1823 English-Welsh bilingual edition of ''The Book of Common Prayer'' with a double fore-edge painting of (1) Bangor and (2) Bangor Cathedral. Other locations in Wales include Barmouth and Neath Abbey, both painted on books published during the nineteenth century. The earliest volume with a fore-edge painting owned by the Library is the 1669 Book of Common Prayer with a depiction of the Crucifixion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Holmes|first1=John|title=Fore-edge paintings in the National Library of Wales|journal=National Library of Wales Journal|date=1996|volume=29|issue=3|pages=329–335}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== The Euclid Collection ====
The National Library's collection of works ascribed to Euclid contains more than 300 volumes, representing 270 editions,&lt;ref name=A_directory_of_rare_books&gt;{{cite book|editor1-last=Bloomfield|editor1-first=B. C.|title=A directory of rare books and special collections in the United Kingdom and the Republic of Ireland.|date=1997|publisher=Library Association|location=London|isbn=1856040631|edition=2nd}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is considered to be an important reference point for Euclidean bibliographical studies.&lt;ref name=Walters /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Rare Books at the National Library of Wales|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/learn-more/printedmaterials/rare-books/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=25 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The collection has been developed through additions to the initial thirty-nine volumes of early editions of the ''Elements'' that [[Sir Charles Thomas-Stanford]] donated in 1927,&lt;ref name=Walters /&gt;&lt;ref name=A_directory_of_rare_books /&gt; including further eleven volumes from Sir Charles in 1928.&lt;ref name=A_directory_of_rare_books /&gt; With the subsequent additions the collection covers all of Euclid's works, including ''Data, Phaenomena, Optica'' and ''Catoptrica'' along with numerous editions of the ''Elements,'' in many languages. There are two incunabula (Erhard Ratdolt, Venice, 1482 and Leonardus de Basilea &amp; Gulielmus de Papia, Vicenza, 1491) in the collection, as well as seventy-three volumes from the sixteenth century, including the first English (Reynold Wolfe, London, 1551) and Arabic (Typographia Medicea, Rome, 1594) editions.&lt;ref name=A_directory_of_rare_books /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = http://welshjournals.llgc.org.uk/browse/viewpage/llgc-id:1277425/llgc-id:1277426/llgc-id:1277438/get650|title = The Euclid Collection in the National Library|last = Gaslee|first = Stephen|date = 1939|journal = National Library of Wales Journal|doi = |pmid = |access-date = 1 December 2015|volume = 1|issue = 1|pages = 3–8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Archives ===
The National Library of Wales is home to the largest collection of archival material in Wales.&lt;ref name=NLWstrategy /&gt; Around 2,500 archives of various sizes have been collected since the library was founded.&lt;ref name=Archives-leaflet&gt;{{cite book|last1=The National Library of Wales|title=Archives. [Leaflet obtained in the National Library of Wales], 22 July 2015|publisher=National Library of Wales}}&lt;/ref&gt; These archives contain many different types of document, such as charters, estate records, correspondence, literary drafts and digital materials, which range from the medieval to contemporary periods. Many of the earlier archives are those of the landed gentry and their estates, which developed over many centuries, but these are supplemented by corporate archives including the Church of Wales archive and the archive of the Court of Great Sessions that the Library has received. The Library collects corporate archives, which are the records of institutions, societies and public bodies, and the personal archives of individuals who have played a significant role in the life of the nation. Personal archives contain a variety of material that is related to the life and work of notable individuals and families.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Archives|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/learn-more/introduction/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=3 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, the papers of Celtic scholar [[Sir Idris Foster]] include correspondence, personal papers, scholarly and academic notes, and papers relating to organisations and societies, such as the [[Honourable Society of Cymmrodorion]], the University of Wales and the Church in Wales.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Idris Foster Papers, 1924–1984 / Sir Idris Llewelyn Foster (1911–1984).|url=http://cat.llgc.org.uk/cgi-bin/gw/chameleon?sessionid=2015072921174029950&amp;skin=full&amp;lng=en&amp;inst=consortium&amp;host=lisbon.llgc.org.uk%2b9901%2bDEFAULT&amp;patronhost=lisbon.llgc.org.uk%209901%20DEFAULT&amp;search=KEYWORD&amp;function=FRBRSCR&amp;sourcescreen=CARDSCR&amp;pos=1&amp;rootsearch=KEYWORD&amp;elementcount=1&amp;u1=12101&amp;t1=003844155&amp;linkedbibid=3844155|website=The National Library of Wales. Full Catalogue|accessdate=29 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== The Welsh Political Archive ====
All materials concerning politics in Wales are kept in the Welsh Political Archive that the National Library established in 1983. This archive coordinates the collection of manuscript, printed and audiovisual records relating to the major political parties active in Wales, with the largest party archive being Plaid Cymru, and notable politicians including Lloyd George. The records of organisations including the Welsh National Council of the United Nations Association and the Association of Welsh Local Authorities also to be found in this archive, as are papers generated by the Parliament for Wales Campaign 1953-6, and several nationalist pressure groups.&lt;ref name=guide-to-mss-dept /&gt;

Some of the political archives cannot be accessed due to their embargo status.&lt;ref name=guide-to-mss-dept /&gt;

==== Modern Literary Archives ====
The Modern Literary Archives are home to the work of some of the most important Welsh poets and authors.&lt;ref name=Fishlock /&gt;&lt;ref name=mod-lit-arch&gt;{{cite web|title=Modern Literary Archives|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/learn-more/introduction/modern-literary-archives/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=4 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; An insight into the creation of prose and poetry is provided by the letters, manuscript and typescript drafts,&lt;ref name=Fishlock /&gt;&lt;ref name=mod-lit-arch /&gt; notebooks, proofs and other personal papers of 20th and 21st century writers.&lt;ref name=mod-lit-arch /&gt; Archives belonging to Welsh-language authors,&lt;ref name=Fishlock /&gt;&lt;ref name=mod-lit-arch /&gt; Welsh authors writing in English&lt;ref name=Fishlock /&gt;&lt;ref name=mod-lit-arch /&gt; and literary organisations are deposited in the National Library.&lt;ref name=mod-lit-arch /&gt;

Papers and manuscripts belonging to Welsh authors who achieved their fame during the 20th century have been collected by the Library. The Archives of Welsh Authors include the work of authors, poets, playwrights, scholars, journalists and [[archdruid]]s of the Gorsedd. Significant holding from these archives include draft copies of novels: ''Cysgod y Cryman'' [The Shadow of the Sickle] by Islwyn Ffowc Elis, ''Y Stafell Ddirgel'' [The Secret Room] by Marion Eames and ''Cyfres Rwdlan'' by Angharad Tomos; Saunders Lewis's letters, and the correspondence between Rhydwen Williams and Alwyn D. Rees; the diaries of Caradog Prichard and Euros Bowen; and, manuscript copies of poetry, such as ''Y Mynach'' by [[Gwenallt]], ''Y Mynydd'' by [[T. H. Parry-Williams]] and ''Cerddi'r Gaeaf'' by [[R. Williams Parry]].&lt;ref name=mod-lit-arch /&gt; Parry-Williams and Williams Parry were both first cousins of [[Thomas Parry (author)|Thomas Parry]], the National Librarian.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Morgan|first1=Derec Llwyd|title=Parry, Sir Thomas|url=http://yba.llgc.org.uk/en/s6-PARR-THO-1904.html|website=Dictionary of Welsh Biography|accessdate=2 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dylan Thomas is the most prominent name amongst the Anglo-Welsh authors and the Library has a large collection of his papers. Other important items in the Archives of Welsh Writers in English are Raymond Williams' drafts of the novels ''Border Country'' and ''People of the Black Mountains'' and the papers of David Jones, which include draft copies of ''In Parenthesis'' and ''The Anathemata.''&lt;ref name=mod-lit-arch /&gt;

Prominent holdings in the Archives of Literary Organisations, Journals and Publishers are the [[National Eisteddfod of Wales]], [[BBC Wales]], the [[Welsh Arts Council]] and the [[Welsh Academy]].&lt;ref name=mod-lit-arch /&gt; The archive of the National Eisteddfod of Wales contains the central office records, compositions, adjudications and criticisms from 1886 onwards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Archives of Literary Organisations, Journals and Publishers|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/learn-more/introduction/archives-of-literary-organisations-journals-and-publishers/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=8 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Eisteddfod is a unique institution and an important part of the literary tradition of Wales that celebrates poetry, song and the Welsh language.&lt;ref name=Fishlock /&gt; The substantial archive of BBC Wales includes radio drama scripts and talks by well-known authors.&lt;ref name=mod-lit-arch /&gt; A further collection of Welsh authors archives is available in the papers of the Welsh Arts Council.&lt;ref name=mod-lit-arch /&gt;

==== National Screen and Sound Archive ====
The National Screen and Sound Archive of Wales&lt;ref name=screen-archive /&gt; contains ''[[The Life Story of David Lloyd George]]'', a 1918 biographical film, which is thought to be the first feature-length biopic of a living politician. It was included on the UK Memory of the World Register in 2010.&lt;ref name=memory-of-the-world /&gt;

==== Penrice and Margam Estate Records ====
[[File:NLW Penrice and Margam Deeds 1 front (8865492665).jpg|thumb|150px|left|NLW Penrice and Margam Deeds 1]]

This extensive collection of estate and family records that was preserved at [[Penrice Castle]] in the possession of Miss Talbot of Margam contains manuscript material from the twelfth to nineteenth centuries. This includes the [[Margam Abbey]] archive which is one of the fullest surviving British monastic archives with charters from the period of the initial foundation of the Abbey at Pendar, its relocation to Margam, and the dissolution of the monastery.&lt;ref name=Penrice_and_Margam &gt;{{cite book|last1=Birch|first1=Walter de Gray|title=A descriptive catalogue of the Penrice and Margam Abbey manuscripts in the possession of Miss Talbot of Margam: First Series|date=1893|publisher=Privately Printed|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Along with the manuscripts are numerous seal impressions which are themselves of historic importance.&lt;ref name=Penrice_and_Margam /&gt; A collection of more than 30,000 seal impressions dating from the twelfth century onwards is preserved in the National Library of Wales, with examples including the seals of Welsh princes, ecclesiastic and papal seals, and in a variety of designs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Review of &quot;Images of Welsh History: Seals of the National Library of Wales&quot; by David H. Williams|journal=Medium Aevum|date=2008|volume=77|issue=2|page=379}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Pictures ===
[[File:J.M.W. Turner - Dolbadarn Castle - Study for Diploma Picture.jpg|thumb|150px|right|J. M. W. Turner – Dolbadarn Castle]]
The charter of the National Library of Wales states that pictures should be collected which portray places in Wales or people of Welsh background.&lt;ref name=Fishlock /&gt;&lt;ref name=picture-collection&gt;{{cite web|title=Pictures|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/learn-more/portraits/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=4 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Images in a number of different media are collected including paintings, drawings, prints and digital formats.&lt;ref name=picture-collection /&gt; The collection contains over 4000 framed paintings and drawings including paintings of [[Dolbadarn Castle]] and Aberdulais Mill by [[J. M. W. Turner]]&lt;ref name=Fishlock /&gt;&lt;ref name=paintings&gt;{{cite web|title=Paintings and Drawings|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/learn-more/portraits/paintings-and-drawings/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=4 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and examples of the work of the landscape artist [[Richard Wilson (painter)|Richard Wilson]],&lt;ref name=Fishlock /&gt;&lt;ref name=paintings /&gt; who influenced Turner, and Wilson's pupil, [[Thomas Jones (artist)|Thomas Jones of Pencerrig]].&lt;ref name=paintings /&gt;

A set of original drawings of Welsh scenes that [[Thomas Rowlandson]] made during his 1797 tour of Wales with Henry Wigstead, and a set of original drawings of castles, abbeys and cities by [[Samuel and Nathaniel Buck]] were donated by Sir John Williams. The Library also has some two hundred original watercolour drawings of Welsh landscapes by [[John Warwick Smith]], and collections of original drawings of Welsh interest by [[Philip James de Loutherbourg|Philip J. de Loutherbourg]] and [[Samuel Hieronymus Grimm|S. H. Grimm]]. The collection of engraved prints illustrate a wide variety of Welsh topography and aspects of Welsh culture, and also show the development of the art of engraving. Every method of engraving is represented in the collection, which also contains examples of the work of famous engravers.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|url = http://welshjournals.llgc.org.uk/browse/viewpage/llgc-id:1277425/llgc-id:1278567/llgc-id:1278644/get650|title = The Department of Prints, Drawings, and Maps|last = Ellis|first = Megan|date = 1947|journal = The National Library of Wales Journal|doi = |pmid = |access-date = 2 December 2015|issue = 2|edition = 5|pages = 155–161}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are around 15,000 Welsh portraits in various media and a further 50,000 photographs and negatives in the Library's collection.&lt;ref name=&quot;picture-collection&quot; /&gt; Portraits include the National Library's main benefactors, Sir John Williams, Sir John Herbert Lewis, Lord Rendel, and Lord Davies of Llandinam;&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|url = http://welshjournals.llgc.org.uk/browse/viewpage/llgc-id:1277425/llgc-id:1278567/llgc-id:1278644/get650|title = The Department of Prints, Drawings, and Maps|last = Ellis|first = Megan|date = 1947|journal = The National Library of Wales Journal|doi = |pmid = |access-date = 2 December 2015|issue = 2|edition = 5|pages = 155–161}}&lt;/ref&gt; prominent Welsh individuals including David Lloyd George and [[Hwfa Môn]]; and, those by artists with a connection to Wales, such as [[Hugh Hughes (painter)|Hugh Hughes]], [[William Roos]] and [[Christopher Williams (Welsh artist)|Christopher Williams]].&lt;ref name=&quot;picture-collection&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|url = http://welshjournals.llgc.org.uk/browse/viewpage/llgc-id:1277425/llgc-id:1278567/llgc-id:1278644/get650|title = The Department of Prints, Drawings, and Maps|last = Ellis|first = Megan|date = 1947|journal = The National Library of Wales Journal|doi = |pmid = |access-date = 2 December 2015|issue = 2|edition = 5|pages = 155–161}}&lt;/ref&gt; Self-portraits by modern Welsh artists are also collected and include Keith Andrew, [[David Jones (artist-poet)|David Jones]], Charles Tunnicliffe and Kyffin Williams.&lt;ref name=&quot;picture-collection&quot; /&gt; There are also many photographic portraits of Welsh individuals in the 1880s and 1890s that were taken by [[John Thomas (photographer)|John Thomas]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|url = http://welshjournals.llgc.org.uk/browse/viewpage/llgc-id:1277425/llgc-id:1278567/llgc-id:1278644/get650|title = The Department of Prints, Drawings, and Maps|last = Ellis|first = Megan|date = 1947|journal = The National Library of Wales Journal|doi = |pmid = |access-date = 2 December 2015|issue = 2|edition = 5|pages = 155–161}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There is a large collection of the iconic work of [[Kyffin Williams]] in the Library, which includes his paintings of north Wales, sketches and watercolours of the Welsh colony in Patagonia and caricature portraits.&lt;ref name=Fishlock /&gt;&lt;ref name=paintings /&gt; Kyffin Williams bequeathed a significant part of his estate, including his own works and archives, to the National Library when he died in 2006.&lt;ref name=Kyffin &gt;{{cite web|title=The Kyffin Williams Bequest Project|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/featured/kyffin-williams-bequest/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=25 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Photographs ===
[[File:CND rally, Aberystwyth (5184388447).jpg|thumb|150px|left|CND rally, Aberystwyth]][[File:John Talbot Dillwyn Llewelyn carrying a gun (4031401449).jpg|thumb|150px|John Talbot Dillwyn Llewelyn carrying a gun.]]

The Library holds a collection of more than 800,000 photographs,&lt;ref name=photos&gt;{{cite web|title=The National Collection of Welsh Photographs|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/learn-more/introduction2/|accessdate=15 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; including the earliest-known photograph in Wales.&lt;ref name=Fishlock /&gt; The [[daguerreotype]] of [[Margam Castle]], made by Reverend Calvert Richard Jones, dates from 1841.&lt;ref name=Fishlock /&gt; Many other examples of photography from the 1840s and 1850s, such as the early Swansea photography of the Dillwyn Llewelyn family, are kept in the National Collection of Welsh Photographs. This collection also contains mounted portraits by high-street photographers, topographic views and portraits by [[John Thomas (photographer)|John Thomas]] and scenic postcard photography by [[Francis Frith]] that are connected to Wales.&lt;ref name=photos /&gt;

During his career as a photojournalist, [[Geoff Charles]] produced a photographic archive that records life in Wales from the 1930s until the 1970s. The Geoff Charles Photographic Collection is the largest individual collection in the Library with 120,000 negatives. This unique contribution to Welsh photography is being preserved and digitised with sponsorship from the Big Lottery Fund.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Geoff Charles Photographic Collection|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/digital-gallery/photographs0/geoffcharles/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=9 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Maps ===
[[File:Cambriae Typus NLW.jpg|thumb|220px|left|The first printed map of Wales from 1574 – ''Cambriae Typus'' by Humphrey Llwyd]]
There are over a million maps in the Library's collections.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Maps|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/learn-more/introduction3/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=22 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are maps on paper, parchment, cloth, wood, metal and digital media. These formats include a range of material such as globles, manuscript items, a 15th-century woodcut print, copper printing plates, carpet-sized map of Britain and [[Ordnance Survey]] digital data.&lt;ref name=Maps-leaflet&gt;{{cite book|last1=The National Library of Wales|title=Mapiau/Maps.|publisher=National Library of Wales|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/fileadmin/fileadmin/docs_gwefan/ymweld_a_ni/darllen_yn_llgc/dar_taf_mapiau_153003D.pdf|format=Leaflet}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Ordnance Survey Maps Collection includes near-to-complete coverage for Wales, beginning with photocopies of the Ordnance Surveyor's drawings that formed the basis of the first edition of the one-inch-to-the-mile map which was published in 1818.&lt;ref name=Maps-leaflet /&gt;

The collection of antiquarian printed mapping is substantial and includes examples of Humphrey Llwyd's ''[[Cambriae Typus|Cambriae typus]]'' (1574), the first printed map specifically of Wales, and the first county maps of Wales.&lt;ref name=Maps-leaflet /&gt; In 2000, Peter Bellwood stole at least fifty antique maps from the Library, which were sold to private collectors for £70,000. Arrested in 2004, he was jailed for four and a half years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/wales/mid/3727676.stm| title=Man stole 50 maps from library| publisher=BBC News| date=8 October 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/wales/4118631.stm| title=£70,000 rare map thief is jailed| publisher=BBC News| date=22 December 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A complete set of [[tithe maps]], covering almost the whole of Wales, is housed in the National Library.&lt;ref name=Davies /&gt;&lt;ref name=NLW-tithe /&gt; The Welsh Church Commission Collection, which, in 1944, was deposited in the Library,&lt;ref name=NLW-tithe&gt;{{cite web|title=The Tithe Commutation Act 1836|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/learn-more/introduction3/tithe-maps-of-wales/the-tithe-commutation-act-1836/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=23 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; includes the diocesan copies of the tithe maps that were transferred to the Commission in 1920 following the [[Church in Wales#Disestablishment|disestablishment of the Church of Wales]].&lt;ref name=Davies /&gt;&lt;ref name=NLW-tithe /&gt; They are an important source for the study of mid-nineteenth century Wales and, therefore, are the most frequently used collection of maps and one of the most consulted categories of documents in the Library.&lt;ref name=Davies&gt;{{cite book|last1=Davies|first1=Robert|title=The tithe maps of Wales: a guide to the tithe maps and apportionments of Wales in the National Library of Wales|date=1999|publisher=National Library of Wales|location=Aberystwyth|isbn=1862250057|pages=5, 13–14,103}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Cynefin Project is digitising over 1100 tithe maps and transcribing the appointment documents to link them together. The project is planned for completion in September 2016.&lt;ref name=Cynefin &gt;{{cite web|title=Digitisation of Tithe Maps|url=http://cynefin.archiveswales.org.uk/en/sample-page-2/|website=The Cynefin Project|publisher=Archives Wales|accessdate=23 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{update after|2016|09}}

Other holdings in the maps collection include: manuscript estate maps, enclosure maps, estate sale catalogues, railway plans, architectural drawings, mining plans, and nautical and aeronautical charts.&lt;ref name=Maps-leaflet /&gt;

== Publications ==
The National Library of Wales has published a series of books about its history and collections, including manuscript catalogues, a bibliography of Welsh publications, Parish Registers of Wales, and academic studies of [[Gwen John]], [[Kyffin Williams]] and others. The Library also publishes the ''[[National Library of Wales Journal]]''.{{Fact|date=March 2016}}

Between 1909 and 1984, the Library published ''Bibliotheca Celtica'' in fulfilment of the terms of its charter to keep a register of books printed in Welsh and other Celtic languages or relating to Wales and the Celtic nations. In 1985 ''Bibliotheca Celtica'' was merged with the ''Subject Index to Welsh Periodicals'' to form ''A Bibliography of Wales (Llyfryddiaeth Cymru)''. In 1987, the retrospective bibliography ''Libri Walliae: a catalogue of Welsh books and books printed in Wales 1546–1820'' was published.&lt;ref name=Walters /&gt;

== Digital content ==

Many of the most important manuscripts and books at the Library have been digitised and made freely available to view on the library's website in its &quot;Digital Mirror&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.llgc.org.uk/index.php?id=122| title=Digital Mirror| publisher=NLW official website}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2012, the Library made a policy decision not to claim ownership of copyright in digital reproductions. This meant that the rights information attached to digital representations of works would reflect the copyright status of the original (i.e., that originals in the public domain would remain in the public domain in their digital form). The Library has applied this policy to projects delivered since then (the Welsh Journals Online and Cymru1914) and is still in the process of updating rights information for its pre-2012 projects. Metadata are released into the public domain using the CC0 licence.{{Fact|date=March 2016}}

The Library has experience of sharing content from its collections under open content licences on platforms such as Wikipedia (e.g., the [[John Thomas (photographer)|John Thomas]] photographic collection) and Flickr. In February 2013, the Library contributed 50 images relating to Monmouthshire to Wikipedia, a successful pilot project with [[Wikimedia UK]]. The following month, they became one of the cultural heritage organisations that partnered with [[Wikimedia Nederland]], Wikimedia UK and [[Wikimedia France]], together with [[Europeana]], to be part of their collaboration to provide a set of tools to mass upload material from GLAM institutions to Wikimedia Commons. Also in 2013, the Library was awarded the Wikimedia UK 'GLAM (Galleries, Libraries, Archives and Museums) of the Year Award', for being 'a reliable supporter of the Wikimedia movement aims.’ By January 2016 almost 8,000 images had been made available for free download.&lt;ref name=&quot;Walesonline160209&quot;&gt;{{cite news|publisher=Wales Online|date=9 February 2016|title=Millions have seen these historic Welsh images a librarian has helped share on Wikipedia|url=http://www.walesonline.co.uk/news/wales-news/millions-seen-historic-welsh-images-10859484#ICID=nsm|accessdate=9 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 'Cynefin: Mapping Wales’ Sense of Place' project has created a unified tithe map of Wales by digitising over a thousand tithe maps.&lt;ref name=NLW-tithe /&gt;&lt;ref name=Cynefin /&gt;&lt;ref name=cynefin-press-release&gt;{{cite web|title=Call for more volunteers to support Cynefin tithe map project|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/services/media-and-business/press-releases/call-for-more-volunteers-to-support-cynefin-tithe-map-project/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=19 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cynefin is a partnership between Archives Wales, the National Library of Wales and People’s Collection Wales&lt;ref name=Cynefin /&gt; that was launched in November 2014.&lt;ref name=cynefin-press-release /&gt; A valuable online tool for historical research is being produced by crowdsourcing the contributions of volunteers through the Cynefin website to transcribe the apportionment documents and link them to the digitised tithe maps.&lt;ref name=cynefin-press-release /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Gruffudd|first1=Einion|title=Digitising Tithe Maps|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/blog/?p=8219|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=19 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Kyffin Williams Bequest Project was set up to catalogue and digitise the material that Kyffin Williams bequeathed to the National Library of Wales on his death in 2006. In addition to the collection of artwork, the bequest also included funds to cover this project. The cataloguing work began in 2008 and the digitisation started in 2009.&lt;ref name=Kyffin /&gt;

&lt;gallery&gt;
Aberdyfi regatta NLW3362782.jpg|A group of men and boys standing on the quayside, Aberdyfi. Aberdyfi Regatta. John Thomas c. 1885
Chwarel Sets, Trefor NLW3363410.jpg|Chwarel Sets, at [[Trefor]]; John Thomas c. 1875
An old Gateway at Monmouth (3375361).jpg|Thomas Christopher Hofland's 'An old gateway at Monmouth' lithograph; 1825
Beatrice Street Church, Oswestry, Sunday School trip to Rhyl (7837615146).jpg|An image from the [[Geoff Charles]] (1909-2002) Collection: a Sunday school trip to Rhyl; Geoff Charles 20 July 1955
Dick Pugh NLW3362662.jpg|Dick Puw; John Thomas c. 1875
Festiniog and Blaenau Railway viaduct.jpg|Viaduct on the Festiniog and Blaenau Railway, Blaenau Ffestiniog, Wales; John Thomas c. 1875
&lt;/gallery&gt;

=== Welsh Journals Online ===
The National Library of Wales has digitised the back-numbers of 50 journals relating to Wales, in Welsh and English, in the Welsh Journals Online project funded by [[Jisc]]. It forms the largest body of Welsh text on the Web, and as well as allowing free access for all to scholarly articles on history, literature and science, and poems and book reviews. [[Optical character recognition|OCR]] of the page scans was undertaken to create [[Text Encoding Initiative|TEI]] searchable text versions. The website contains a total of 400,000 pages. It is intended to add new issues of the titles as they emerge from the embargo period agreed with the publisher.&lt;ref&gt;[http://welshjournals.llgc.org.uk/ Welsh Journals Online] at NLW official website&lt;/ref&gt;

The fifty titles include:&lt;ref&gt;[http://welshjournals.llgc.org.uk/browse/ Publications available] at NLW official website&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.llgc.org.uk/index.php?id=5668 List of the journals that have been identified for digitisation] at NLW official website&lt;/ref&gt;
{{columns-list|colwidth=35em|
*''[[Archaeologia Cambrensis]]'' 1846–1999
*''[[Arloeswr|Yr Arloeswr]]'' ('the pioneer') 1957–1960
*''[[Bathafarn (journal)|Bathafarn]]'' 1946–2003
*''[[Brycheiniog (magazine)|Brycheiniog]]'' 1955–2006
*''[[Bwletin Cymdeithas Emynau Cymru]]'' ('bulletin of the Welsh hymns society') 1968–2003
*''[[Cambria (geographical magazine)|Cambria]]: a Welsh geographical review'' 1974–1989
*''[[Cennad (magazine)|Cennad]]'' ('messenger') 1980–2001
*''[[Ceredigion (magazine)|Ceredigion]]'' 1951–2004
*''[[Y Cofiadur]]'' ('the recorder') 1923–2002
*''[[Contemporary Wales]]'' 1987–2001
*''[[Cristion (magazine)|Cristion]]'' ('Christian') 1983–2006
*''[[Cymmrodor|Y Cymmrodor]]'' 1822–1951
*''[[Cymru]]'' 1891–1927
*''[[Efrydiau Athronyddol]]'' 1938–2000
*''[[Fflam|Fflam, Y]]'' ('the flame') 1946–1952
*''[[Ford gron|Y ford gron]]'' ('the round table') 1930-1935
*''[[Gower (magazine)|Gower]]'' 1948–2005
*[[Gwent Local History Council#Gwent Local History|''Gwent Local History'']], the journal of [[Gwent Local History Council]] 1977–2006
*''[[Y Gwyddonydd]]'' ('the scientist') 1963–1996
*''[[Heddiw (journal)|Heddiw]]'' ('today') 1936–1942
*''[[Pembrokeshire Historian|Journal of the Pembrokeshire Historical Society]]'' 1985–2004
*''[[Journal of the Welsh Bibliographical Society]]'' 1910–1984
*''[[Journal of Welsh ecclesiastical history]]'' 1984–1992
*''[[Journal of Welsh Religious History]]'' 1993–2005
*''[[Llafur]]'' ('labour'), the journal of the Society for the Study of Welsh Labour History 1972–2004
*''[[:cy:Y Llenor (1922-55)|Y Llenor]]'' ('the reader') 1922–1955
*''[[:cy:Lleufer|Lleufer]]: cylchgrawn Cymdeithas Addysg y Gweithwyr yng Nghymru'' (Journal of the [[Workers' Educational Association]] in Wales) 1944–1979
*''[[Minerva (magazine)|Minerva]]: transactions of the Royal Institution of South Wales'' 1993–2006
*''[[Montgomeryshire collections]]'', relating to Montgomeryshire and its borders 1868–2002
*[[Morgannwg (magazine)|''Morgannwg'']], transactions of the Glamorgan Local History Society 1957–2006
*''[[National Library of Wales Journal]]'' 1939–2005
*''[[Nature in Wales]]'', the quarterly journal of the West Wales Field Society 1955–1987
*''[[Pembrokeshire historian]]'', journal of the Pembrokeshire Local History Society 1959–1981
*''Presenting Monmouthshire'', the journal of the Monmouthshire Local History Council (now [[Gwent Local History Council]]) 1956–1975
*''[[Proceedings of the South Wales Institute of Engineers]] '' 1857–1998
*''[[Radnorshire Society Transactions]]'' 1931–2004
*''[[Reports and Transactions, Cardiff Naturalists' Society]]'' 1867–1986
*''[[South Wales Record Society]] publications'' 1987–1994
*''[[Studia Celtica]]'' 1966–2000
*''[[Tir Newydd]]'' ('new land') 1935–1939
*''[[Y Traethodydd]]'' ('the essayist') 1845–2006
*''[[Ceredigion (magazine)|Transactions and archaeological record, Cardiganshire Antiquarian Society]]'' 1911–1938
*''Transactions of the [[Honourable Society of Cymmrodorion]]'' 1892–2005
*''[[Wales (magazine)|Wales]]'' 1937–1959
*''[[Welsh book studies]]'' (Llyfr yng Nghymru)) 1998–2007
*''[[Welsh history review]]'' (''Cylchgrawn hanes cymru'') 1959–2001
*''[[Welsh music history]]'' 1996–2004
*''[[Welsh outlook]]'' 1914–1933
}}

=== Welsh Newspapers Online ===
[[File:The Cardigan Bay Visitor Jun 24 1887.jpg|thumb|150px|''The Cardigan Bay Visitor'', 24 June 1887]] 
[[File:The Visitor's List and Guide June 22 1887.jpg|thumb|150px|''The Visitor's List and Guide'', 22 June 1887]] 
[[File:The Illustrated Usk Observer Jul 7 1855.jpg|thumb|150px|''The Illustrated Usk Observer'', 7 July 1855]] 
[[File:Y Dydd Jun 5 1868.jpg|thumb|150px|''Y Dydd'', 5 June 1868]]
[[Welsh Newspapers Online]] is an open access database of Welsh regional newspapers that has been created from the National Library of Wales' collection of historical newspapers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Newspapers|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/learn-more/printedmaterials/newspapers/|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=8 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=welsh-newspapers-online &gt;{{cite web|title=Welsh Newspapers Online|url=https://www.llgc.org.uk/index.php?id=4723|publisher=National Library of Wales|accessdate=8 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The database includes nearly 120 newspapers titles and provides access to over 1,100,000 pages from the years before 1919. Content relating to the First World War that has been digitised is also included in the database.&lt;ref name=welsh-newspapers-online /&gt; The following publications are included:&lt;ref name=welsh-newspapers-online /&gt;

{{columns-list|colwidth=35em|
* ''[[The Aberdare Leader|Aberdare Leader]]'' 1902–1910; 1913–1919
* ''[[The Aberdare Times|Aberdare Times]]'' 1861–1902
* ''Abergavenny Chronicle'' 1909–1910; 1914–1919
* ''Abergavenny Mail'' 1914
* ''[[The Aberystwyth Observer|Aberystwyth Observer]]'' 1858–1861; 1864–1900; 1902–1910
* ''[[Aberystwyth Times]]'' 1868–1870
* ''[[The Visitors' List and Guide|Aberystwyth Visitors' List and Guide]]'' 1887
* ''Adsain'' 1906; 1914–1919
* ''Amman Valley Chronicle'' 1913–1919
* ''Amserau'' 1846–59
* ''[[Baner ac Amserau Cymru]]'' 1857–1910; 1914–1919
* ''Barmouth and County Advertiser'' 1914–1917
* ''Barry Dock News'' 1889–1910; 1914–1918
* ''Barry Herald'' 1896–1910
* ''Brecon and Radnor Express'' 1914–1918
* ''[[The Brecon County Times|Brecon County Times]]'' 1866–1869; 1900; 1905–1910; 1913–1919
* ''[[The Brecon Reporter|Brecon Reporter]]'' 1865–1867
* ''[[Brython (newspaper)]]'' (Lerpwl) 1914–1919
* ''Brython Cymreig'' 1892–1901; 1906–1910
* ''[[Carnarvon and Denbigh Herald]]'' 1836–1910
* ''Cambrian Daily Leader'' 1913; 1914–1918; 1919
* ''[[The Cambrian|Cambrian]]'' 1804–1860; 1870–1910
* ''[[Cambrian News]]'' 1860–1910; 1914–1919
* ''Cardiff and Merthyr Guardian'' 1845–1874
* ''[[The Cardiff Times|Cardiff Times]]'' 1858–1910
* ''[[The Cardigan Bay Visitor|Cardigan Bay Visitor]]'' 1887–1905
* ''[[The Cardigan Observer|Cardigan Observer]]'' 1878–1897
* ''[[Carmarthen Journal]]'' 1810–1812; 1828–1831; 1889–1893; 1901–1910; 1913–1919
* ''[[Carmarthen Weekly Reporter]]'' 1860–1910; 1913–1919
* ''Cheshire Observer'' 1901–1908
* ''Chester Courant'' 1897–1908
* ''Clorianydd'' 1897–1907; 1909–1910; 1914–1919
* ''Colwyn Bay &amp; North Wales Weekly News'' 1892; 1894–1907
* ''County Echo'' [Pembrokeshire] 1893–1896; 1901–1910
* ''[[County Observer and Monmouthshire Central Advertiser]]'' 1867–1878; 1881–1884; 1899–1908
* ''Cymro a'r Celt Llundain'' 1907–1910
* ''Cymro'' [Lerpwl a'r Wyddgrug] 1890–1907; 1914–1919
* ''Darian'' 1914–1919
* ''[[The Demetian Mirror|Demetian Mirror]]'' 1840
* ''[[Denbigh, Ruthin and Vale of Clwyd Free Press|Denbighshire Free Press]]'' 1882–1910; 1914–1919
* ''Dinesydd Cymreig'' 1914–1919
* ''Drafod'' 1913–1919
* ''Drych'' 1875–1878; 1881–1900; 1914–1919
* ''Dydd'' 1868–1870; 1872–1890; 1892–1910; 1914–1919
* ''Evening Express'' 1891–1899; 1900–1910 1900–1910 
* ''[[Flintshire Observer]]'' 1864–1900; 1907–1910; 1913–1915
* ''Genedl'' 1914–1917
* ''Genedl Gymreig'' 1877–1900
* ''Glamorgan Free Press'' 1897–1899
* ''Glamorgan Gazette'' 1894–1895; 1906–1910; 1914–1919 
* ''[[Glamorgan Monmouth and Brecon Gazette and Merthyr Guardian|Glamorgan, Monmouth and Brecon Gazette and Merthyr Guardian]]'' 1832–1843
* ''[[Y Goleuad|Goleuad]]'' 1869–1910; 1914–1919 1869–1910 
* ''[[Gwalia (newspaper)|Gwalia]]'' 1883; 1897–1910
* ''[[Gwladgarwr]]'' 1858–1882
* ''Gwyliedydd'' 1877–1908
* ''Gwyliedydd Newydd'' 1910; 1914–1919
* ''[[Haverfordwest &amp; Milford Haven Telegraph|Haverfordwest and Milford Haven Telegraph]]'' 1857–1910; 1914–1919 
* ''Herald Cymraeg'' 1901–1910; 1914–1919 
* ''Herald of Wales and Monmouthshire Recorder'' 1897; 1914–1919
* ''[[The Illustrated Usk Observer|Illustrated Usk Observer]]'' 1855–1866
* ''[[Llais Y Wlad]]'' 1874–1884
* ''Llais Llafur'' 1914–1919
* ''Llandudno Advertiser and List of Visitors'' 1896–1910
* ''Llanelly Mercury'' 1897; 1909–1910
* ''Llanelly Star'' 1910; 1914–1919
* ''[[Llangollen Advertiser]]'' 1868–1873; 1875–1903; 1905–1908; 1909–1910; 1914–1919
* ''London Kelt – Celt Llundain'' 1895–1904
* ''London Welshman – Cymro Llundain'' 1904–1906
* ''Merthyr Express'' 1864–1869; 1909–1910
* ''[[Merthyr Pioneer]]'' 1914–1919
* ''[[The Merthyr Telegraph|Merthyr Telegraph]]'' 1855–1881
* ''Merthyr Times'' 1895–1897
* ''Monmouth Guardian'' 1914–1919
* ''[[Monmouthshire Merlin]]'' 1829–1884
* ''Montgomery County Times'' 1893–1900
* ''Montgomeryshire Express and Radnor Times'' 1892–1908
* ''Negesydd'' 1895–1909
* ''[[North Wales Chronicle]]'' 1827–1900; 1914–1919
* ''[[The North Wales Express|North Wales Express]]'' 1878–1910
* ''[[North Wales Gazette]]'' 1808–1816; 1823–1825
* ''North Wales Times'' 1897–1900
* ''[[North Wales Weekly News]]'' 1909–1910
* ''Papur Pawb'' 1893–1904; 1909–1910
* ''Pembroke County Guardian'' 1898–1910
* ''[[The Pembrokeshire Herald and General Advertiser|Pembrokeshire Herald]]'' 1844–1891; 1901–1910
* ''Penarth Chronicle'' 1895
* ''[[Pontypool Free Press]]'' 1859–1869; 1872–1893
* ''[[Pontypridd Chronicle]]'' 1881–1883; 1886–1905
* ''[[Potter's Electric News]]'' 1859–1868
* ''Prestatyn Weekly'' 1905–1910
* ''[[The Principality (newspaper)|Principality]]'' 1848–1850
* ''Rhedegydd'' 1878–1879; 1886; 1889; 1893–1910
* ''[[Rhondda Leader]]'' 1899–1910
* ''Rhos Herald'' 1909–1910
* ''[[The Rhyl Advertiser|Rhyl Advertiser]]'' 1878–1887; 1893
* ''Rhyl Journal'' 1889–1910
* ''Rhyl Record and Advertiser'' 1888–1910
* ''[[Seren Cymru]]'' 1851–1852; 1856–1857; 1860–1910; 1913; 1914–1918; 1919
* ''[[Seren Gomer]]'' 1814–1815
* ''[[South Wales Daily News]]'' 1872–1900
* ''South Wales Daily Post'' 1893–1900; 1910
* ''[[South Wales Echo]]'' 1880–1882; 1885–1900
* ''South Wales Star'' 1891–1894
* ''South Wales Weekly Post'' 1914–1919
* ''Swansea Gazette and Daily Shipping Register'' 1909–1910
* ''[[Tarian y Gweithiwr]]'' 1875–1910
* ''[[The Tenby Observer|Tenby Observer]]'' 1854–1860; 1867–1889; 1909–1910
* ''Towyn on Sea and Merioneth County Times'' 1897–1905
* ''Tyst a'r Dydd'' 1871–1891
* ''Tyst Cymreig'' 1867–1870
* ''Tyst'' 1892–1910; 1914–1917
* ''Udgorn'' 1913–1918
* ''[[The Weekly Mail|Weekly Mail]]'' 1879–1910
* ''Welsh Coast Pioneer'' 1900–1910
* ''Welsh Gazette'' 1899–1910
* ''Welshman'' 1835–1910
* ''Werin'' 1885–1900
* ''[[Western Mail (Wales)|Western Mail]]'' 1869–1900
* ''[[Wrexham and Denbigh Weekly Advertiser]]'' 1854–1900
* ''[[Wrexham Guardian]]'' 1875–1879
* ''Wythnos a'r Eryr'' 1899–1903; 1909–1910
* ''[[Y Celt]]'' 1878–1907 
* ''[[Y Drych]]'' 1875–1919
* ''[[Y Dydd]]'' 1868–1919
* ''[[Y Genedl Gymreig]]'' 1877–1900
* ''[[Y Goleuad]]'' 1869–1919
* ''[[Y Gwladgarwr]]'' 1858–1884
* ''[[Y Gwyliedydd]]'' 1877–1908
* ''[[Y Llan]]'' 1881–1919
* ''[[Y Rhedegydd]]'' 1878–1910
* ''[[Y Tyst a'r Dydd]]'' 1871–1891
* ''[[Y Tyst Cymreig]]'' 1867–1870
* ''Y Werin'' 1885–1900
* ''Yr Adsain'' 1906–1919
}}

== References ==
{{Commons category}}
{{reflist|33em}}

== Further reading ==
* Davies, J. H. (1921) ''The National Library of Wales: Catalogue of Manuscripts Vol. 1. Additional Manuscripts in the Collections of Sir John Williams.'' Aberystwyth: The National Library of Wales. 
* Fishlock, Trevor (2007) ''In this place: The National Library of Wales.'' Aberystwyth: The National Library of Wales. ISBN 978-1-86225-054-3
* ''Handlist of manuscripts in the National Library of Wales, Volume I'' (1943). Aberystwyth: The National Library of Wales. 
* ''Handlist of manuscripts in the National Library of Wales, Volume II'' (1951). Aberystwyth: The National Library of Wales. 
* [[David Jenkins (librarian)|Jenkins, David]] (2002) ''A Refuge in Peace and War: The National Library of Wales to 1952.'' Aberystwyth: The National Library of Wales. ISBN 1-86225-034-0
* Scholderer, V. (1940) ''Hand-list of incunabula in the National Library of Wales,'' National Library of Wales Journal Supplement, Series '''I''' (1); and,(1941) ''Hand-list ... Addenda &amp; Corrigenda,'' National Library of Wales Journal Supplement, '''I''' (2). 
* [[Geiriadur Prifysgol Cymru]] (the University of Wales ''Dictionary of the Welsh Language'')

== External links ==
* {{Official website|http://www.llgc.org.uk/|The National Library of Wales official website}}
*[http://www.llgc.org.uk/collections/ National Library of Wales: Collections] Key to LLGC collections, including digitised
*[http://screenandsound.llgc.org.uk/ The National Screen and Sound Archive of Wales]
*[http://welshjournals.llgc.org.uk Welsh Journals Online]
*[http://www.genuki.org.uk/big/wal/NLWjournals.html National Library of Wales Journal, Contents 1939–2000], UK &amp; Ireland Genealogy (Genuki)

{{Europe topic|prefix=National Library of | title=[[National library|National libraries]] of Europe}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:National Library Of Wales}}
[[Category:Welsh Government sponsored bodies]]
[[Category:Archives in Wales]]
[[Category:Libraries in Wales]]
[[Category:National libraries|Wales]]
[[Category:Organisations based in Wales with royal patronage]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Aberystwyth]]
[[Category:Geographic region-oriented digital libraries]]
[[Category:Charles Holden buildings]]
[[Category:1907 establishments in Wales]]
[[Category:Libraries established in 1907]]
[[Category:Library buildings completed in 1916]]
[[Category:Deposit libraries]]
[[Category:Organisations based in Aberystwyth]]
[[Category:Grade II* listed buildings in Ceredigion]]</text>
      <sha1>364jod6inbo4xmy5em9nj1jldql5uwv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
