<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.28.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2600" case="first-letter">Topic</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Nature (journal)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>43427</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744101893</id>
      <parentid>742263171</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-13T04:01:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Froid</username>
        <id>1971344</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Controversies */ Adding/improving reference(s) Spelling/grammar correction Fixing style/layout errors (rearranged in reverse chron. order)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="34939">{{Redirect2|Nature Magazine|Nature (magazine)|the U.S. magazine published in Baltimore between 1923 and 1959 |American Nature Association}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2010}}
{{Infobox journal
| title        = Nature
| cover        = [[File:Nature volume 536 number 7617 cover displaying an artist’s impression of Proxima Centauri b.jpg|220px|Cover page of the 7617th issue]]
| editor       = [[Philip Campbell (scientist)|Philip Campbell]]
| discipline   = [[Natural sciences]]
| abbreviation = Nature
| publisher    = [[Nature Research]] (subsidiary of [[Georg von Holtzbrinck Publishing Group]])
| country      = United Kingdom
| language     = English
| frequency    = Weekly
| history      = 1869–present 
| openaccess   = No
| license      =
| impact       = 38.138
| impact-year  = 2015
| website      = http://www.nature.com/nature/index.html
| link1        = http://www.nature.com/nature/current_issue.html
| link1-name   = Online access
| link2        = http://www.nature.com/nature/archive/index.html
| link2-name   = Online archive
| JSTOR        =
| OCLC         = 01586310
| LCCN         =
| CODEN        = NATUAS
| ISSN         = 0028-0836
| eISSN        = 1476-4687
}}
'''''Nature''''' is a British [[interdisciplinary]] [[scientific journal]], first published on 4 November 1869.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Huxley | first1 = T. H. | doi = 10.1038/001009a0 | title = Nature: Aphorisms by Goethe | journal = Nature | volume = 1 | pages = 9–11 | url = http://www.nature.com/nature/first/aphorisms.html| year = 1869 | pmid =  | pmc = |bibcode = 1869Natur...1....9H }}&lt;/ref&gt; It was ranked the world's most cited scientific journal by the Science Edition of the 2010 ''[[Journal Citation Reports]]'', is ascribed an [[impact factor]] of approximately 38.1, and is widely regarded as one of the few remaining academic journals that publishes original research across a wide range of scientific fields.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=About Nature|url=http://www.nature.com/nature/about/|work=nature.com|accessdate=12 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
''Nature'' claims an online readership of about 3 million unique readers per month.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.nature.com/news/announcement-a-new-ipad-app-for-nature-readers-1.12002 | title=Announcement: A new iPad app for Nature readers | work=Nature | date=12 December 2012 | accessdate=26 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The journal has a weekly circulation of around 53,000 but studies have concluded that on average a single copy is shared by as many as eight people.&lt;ref name=&quot;Demographics: Nature&quot;&gt;{{Citation |title=Demographics: Nature |url=http://www.nature.com/advertising/resources/pdf/2010naturemediakit.pdf?prod_code=NATURE&amp;prod=Nature |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110513233735/http://www.nature.com/advertising/resources/pdf/2010naturemediakit.pdf?prod_code=NATURE&amp;prod=Nature |archivedate=2011-05-13}}, a profile of Nature's readership. nature.com&lt;/ref&gt;

Research scientists are the primary audience for the journal, but summaries and accompanying articles are intended to make many of the most important papers understandable to scientists in other fields and the educated public. Towards the front of each issue are [[editorial]]s, news and feature articles on issues of general interest to scientists, including current affairs, science funding, business, scientific ethics and research breakthroughs. There are also sections on books and arts. The remainder of the journal consists mostly of research papers (articles or letters), which are often dense and highly technical. Because of strict limits on the length of papers, often the printed text is actually a summary of the work in question with many details relegated to accompanying ''supplementary material'' on the journal's website.

There are many fields of [[research]] in which important new advances and original research are published as either articles or letters in ''Nature.'' The papers that have been published in this journal are internationally acclaimed for maintaining high research standards.

In 2007 ''Nature'' (together with ''[[Science (journal)|Science]]'') received the [[Prince of Asturias Awards|Prince of Asturias Award]] for Communications and Humanity.&lt;ref name=SciNat&gt;
{{cite web
 | last = Ham
 | first = Becky 
 | authorlink =
 | author2 = AAAS News release
 | title = Science Receives Spain's Prince of Asturias Award for Excellence in Communication
 | quote = Science [magazine] shares this year's award with the journal Nature.
 | publisher = [[American Association for the Advancement of Science]] (AAAS) 
 | date = October 26, 2007
 | url = http://www.aaas.org/news/releases/2007/1026asturias.shtml
 | accessdate =2012-08-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Prince&gt;
{{cite web
 | title = Journals Nature and Science – Communication and Humanities 2007
 | quote = Some of the most important and innovative work of the last 150 years has appeared on the pages of Science and Nature...
 | publisher = [[Fundaciôn Principe de Asturias]] 
 | date = October 26, 2007
 | url = http://www.fpa.es/en/prince-of-asturias-awards/awards/2007-journals-nature-and-science.html?texto=trayectoria 
 | accessdate =2012-08-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

===Background===
The enormous progress in science and mathematics during the 19th century was recorded in journals written mostly in German or French, as well as in English. Britain underwent enormous technological and industrial changes and advances particularly in the latter half of the 19th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Schroeder |first1=Robert |first2= Gretta E.|last2= Siegel | doi = 10.1353/scp.2006.0006 | year = 2006 | title = A Cooperative Publishing Model for Sustainable Scholarship| journal = Journal of Scholarly Publishing | volume = 37 | issue = 2| pages = 86–98 (88)}}&lt;/ref&gt; In English the most respected scientific journals of this time were the refereed journals of the [[Royal Society]], which had published many of the great works from [[Isaac Newton]], [[Michael Faraday]] through to early works from [[Charles Darwin]]. In addition, during this period, the number of popular science periodicals doubled from the 1850s to the 1860s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bar3&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal 
| last1 = Barton | first1 = R. 
| title = Just before Nature: The purposes of science and the purposes of popularization in some english popular science journals of the 1860s 
| journal = Annals of Science 
| volume = 55 
| issue = 1 
| pages = 1–33 
| year = 1998 
| pmid = 11619805
 | doi=10.1080/00033799800200101
}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the editors of these popular science magazines, the publications were designed to serve as &quot;organs of science&quot;, in essence, a means of connecting the public to the scientific world.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bar3&quot;/&gt;

''Nature'', first created in 1869, was not the first magazine of its kind in Britain. One journal to precede ''Nature'' was ''[[Recreative Science: A Record and Remembrancer of Intellectual Observation]]'', which, created in 1859, began as a [[natural history]] magazine and progressed to include more physical observational science and technical subjects and less natural history.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bar7&quot;&gt;[[#Barton|Barton]], &quot;Just Before Nature,&quot; p. 7&lt;/ref&gt; The journal's name changed from its original title to ''Intellectual Observer: A Review of Natural History, Microscopic Research, and Recreative Science'' and then later to the ''Student and Intellectual Observer of Science, Literature, and Art''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bar6&quot;&gt;[[#Barton|Barton]], &quot;Just Before Nature,&quot; p. 6&lt;/ref&gt; While ''Recreative Science'' had attempted to include more physical sciences such as [[astronomy]] and [[archaeology]], the ''Intellectual Observer'' broadened itself further to include literature and art as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bar6&quot;/&gt; Similar to ''Recreative Science'' was the scientific journal ''[[Popular Science Review]]'', created in 1862,&lt;ref name=&quot;Bar13&quot;&gt;[[#Barton|Barton]], &quot;Just Before Nature,&quot; p. 13&lt;/ref&gt; which covered different fields of science by creating subsections titled &quot;Scientific Summary&quot; or &quot;Quarterly Retrospect&quot;, with book reviews and commentary on the latest scientific works and publications.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bar13&quot;/&gt; Two other journals produced in England prior to the development of ''Nature'' were the ''[[Quarterly Journal of Science]]'' and ''[[Scientific Opinion]]'', established in 1864 and 1868, respectively.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bar6&quot;/&gt; The journal most closely related to ''Nature'' in its editorship and format was ''The Reader'', created in 1864; the publication mixed science with literature and art in an attempt to reach an audience outside of the scientific community, similar to ''Popular Science Review''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bar6&quot;/&gt;

These similar journals all ultimately failed. The ''Popular Science Review'' survived longest, lasting 20 years and ending its publication in 1881; ''Recreative Science'' ceased publication as the ''Student and Intellectual Observer'' in 1871. The ''Quarterly Journal'', after undergoing a number of editorial changes, ceased publication in 1885. ''The Reader'' terminated in 1867, and finally, ''Scientific Opinion'' lasted a mere 2 years, until June 1870.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bar7&quot;/&gt;

===Creation ===
[[File:Nature cover, November 4, 1869.jpg|thumb|right|upright|First title page, November 4, 1869]]
Not long after the conclusion of ''The Reader'', a former editor, [[Norman Lockyer]], decided to create a new scientific journal titled ''Nature'',&lt;ref name=&quot;B248&quot;&gt;[[#Browne|Browne]], ''Charles Darwin: The Power of Place'', p. 248&lt;/ref&gt; taking its name from a line by [[William Wordsworth]]: &quot;To the solid ground of nature trusts the Mind that builds for aye&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bartleby.com/145/ww698.html Poem: &quot;A Volant Tribe of Bards on earth are found&quot;]. Bartleby.com. Retrieved on 2013-06-20.&lt;/ref&gt; First owned and published by [[Alexander Macmillan (publisher)|Alexander Macmillan]], ''Nature'' was similar to its predecessors in its attempt to &quot;provide cultivated readers with an accessible forum for reading about advances in scientific knowledge.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;B248&quot;/&gt; Janet Browne has proposed that &quot;far more than any other science journal of the period, ''Nature'' was conceived, born, and raised to serve polemic purpose.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;B248&quot;/&gt; Many of the early editions of ''Nature'' consisted of articles written by members of a group that called itself the [[X Club]], a group of scientists known for having liberal, progressive, and somewhat controversial scientific beliefs relative to the time period.&lt;ref name=&quot;B248&quot;/&gt; Initiated by [[Thomas Henry Huxley]], the group consisted of such important scientists as [[Joseph Dalton Hooker]], [[Herbert Spencer]], and [[John Tyndall]], along with another five scientists and mathematicians; these scientists were all avid supporters of Darwin's theory of evolution as [[common descent]], a theory which, during the latter-half of the 19th century, received a great deal of criticism among more conservative groups of scientists.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Browne|Browne]], ''Charles Darwin: The Power of Place'', p. 247&lt;/ref&gt; Perhaps it was in part its scientific liberality that made ''Nature'' a longer-lasting success than its predecessors. [[John Maddox]], editor of ''Nature'' from 1966 to 1973 as well as from 1980 to 1995, suggested at a celebratory dinner for the journal's centennial edition that perhaps it was the journalistic qualities of Nature that drew readers in; &quot;journalism&quot; Maddox states, &quot;is a way of creating a sense of community among people who would otherwise be isolated from each other. This is what Lockyer's journal did from the start.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dinner&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|year=1970|title=The 'Nature' Centenary Dinner|jstor=530861|journal=Notes and Records of the Royal Society of London|volume= 25|issue=1|doi=10.1098/rsnr.1970.0002 |pages=9–15(13)|author1=Maddox, John  |author2=Macmillan, Harold  |lastauthoramp=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, Maddox mentions that the financial backing of the journal in its first years by the Macmillan family also allowed the journal to flourish and develop more freely than scientific journals before it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dinner&quot;/&gt;
 
====Editors====
[[Norman Lockyer]], the founder of ''Nature'', was a professor at [[Imperial College]]. He was succeeded as editor in 1919 by [[Sir Richard Gregory, 1st Baronet|Sir Richard Gregory]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NPG&quot;&gt;[http://npg.nature.com/npg/servlet/Content?data=xml/02_history.xml&amp;style=xml/02_history.xsl Nature Publishing Group: History]. NPG.nature.com&lt;/ref&gt; Gregory helped to establish ''Nature'' in the international scientific community. His obituary by the Royal Society stated: &quot;Gregory was always very interested in the international contacts of science, and in the columns of ''Nature'' he always gave generous space to accounts of the activities of the International Scientific Unions.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Richard Arman Gregory, 1864–1952|journal= Obituary Notices of Fellows of the Royal Society|volume= 8|issue=22|pages=410–417 (413)|year=1953|doi=10.1098/rsbm.1953.0007 |author=Stratton, F. J. M. }}&lt;/ref&gt; During the years 1945 to 1973, editorship of ''Nature'' changed three times, first in 1945 to A. J. V. Gale and [[L. J. F. Brimble]] (who in 1958 became the sole editor), then to [[John Maddox]] in 1965, and finally to David Davies in 1973.&lt;ref name=&quot;NPG&quot;/&gt; In 1980, Maddox returned as editor and retained his position until 1995. [[Philip Campbell (scientist)|Philip Campbell]] has since become Editor-in-chief of all ''Nature'' publications.&lt;ref name=&quot;NPG&quot;/&gt;

====Expansion and development====
In 1970, ''Nature'' first opened its Washington office; other branches opened in New York in 1985, Tokyo and Munich in 1987, Paris in 1989, San Francisco in 2001, Boston in 2004, and Hong Kong in 2005. Starting in the 1980s, the journal underwent a great deal of expansion, launching over ten new journals. These new journals comprise the Nature Publishing Group, which was created in 1999 and includes ''Nature'', Nature Research Journals, Stockton Press Specialist Journals and Macmillan Reference (renamed NPG Reference).

In 1996, ''Nature'' created its own website&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.nature.com/npg_/company_info/timeline2.html|title = Branching out (1970-1999)|date = |accessdate = 2014-11-13|website = nature.com|publisher = Nature Publishing Group}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in 1999 Nature Publishing Group began its series of ''Nature Reviews''.&lt;ref name=&quot;NPG&quot; /&gt; Some articles and papers are available for free on the Nature website. Others require the purchase of premium access to the site.

''Nature'' claims a readership of about 424,000 total readers.{{Synthesis inline|date=October 2014}} The journal has a circulation of around 53,000 but studies have concluded that on average a single copy is shared by as many as 8 people.&lt;ref name=&quot;Demographics: Nature&quot;/&gt;

On 30 October 2008, ''Nature'' endorsed an American presidential candidate for the first time when it supported [[Barack Obama]] during his campaign in [[United States presidential election, 2008|America's 2008 presidential election]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.1038/4551149a | title = America's choice | year = 2008 | journal = Nature | volume = 455 | issue = 7217 | page = 1149 |bibcode = 2008Natur.455Q1149. | pmid = 18971969 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scholarsandrogues.com/2008/10/31/nature-endorses-obama/ Weekly science journal ''Nature'' endorses a presidential candidate: Barack Obama]. Scholarsandrogues.com (2008-10-31). Retrieved on 2013-06-20.&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 2012, an [[Nature Arabic Edition|Arabic edition]] of the magazine was launched in partnership with [[King Abdulaziz City for Science and Technology]]. As of the time it was released, it had about 10,000 subscribers.&lt;ref name=NatureME&gt;{{cite web | last = Yahia | first = Mohammed| title = Nature Arabic Edition launches| quote = The first issue of ''Nature Arabic Edition'', an Arabic translation of ''Nature'', has been released. The monthly print version is now available to 10,000 subscribers in the Arabic-speaking Middle East| publisher = Nature Middle East| date = October 18, 2012| url = http://www.nature.com/nmiddleeast/2012/121018/full/nmiddleeast.2012.149.html| accessdate =2013-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 2 December 2014, ''Nature'' announced that it would allow its subscribers and a group of selected media outlets to share links allowing free, &quot;read-only&quot; access to content from its journals. These articles are presented using the [[digital rights management]] system [[ReadCube]] (which is funded by the Macmillan subsidiary Digital Science), and does not allow readers to download, copy, print, or otherwise distribute the content. While it does, to an extent, provide free online access to articles, it is not a true [[open access]] scheme due to its restrictions on re-use and distribution.&lt;ref name=wired-naturefreeview&gt;{{cite web|title=Nature journal subscribers can now share article links globally|url=http://www.wired.co.uk/news/archive/2014-12/02/nature-publishing|website=Wired.co.uk|accessdate=3 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=guardian-npgreadonly&gt;{{cite news|title=Science journal ''Nature'' to make archives available online|url=http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2014/dec/02/nature-archives-free|accessdate=3 December 2014|work=The Guardian|date=2 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 15 January 2015, details of a proposed merger with Springer Science+Business Media were announced.&lt;ref&gt;Schuetze, Arno (January 15, 2015). [http://www.reuters.com/article/2015/01/15/publishing-ma-idUSF9N0TV00F20150115 &quot;Nature magazine publisher to merge with Springer Science&quot;]. [[Reuters]].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Publishing of articles==
{{Cleanup|section|The content of this section appears to need in-line citations from independent reliable sources.|date=July 2011}}

Having a paper (article or letter) published in ''Nature'' or any ''Nature'' publication such as ''Nature chemistry'' or ''Nature chemical biology'' is very prestigious, and the papers are often highly cited, which can lead to promotions, grant funding, and attention from the mainstream media. Because of these [[positive feedback]] effects, competition among scientists to publish in high-level journals like ''Nature'' and its closest competitor, ''[[Science (journal)|Science]]'', can be very fierce. ''Nature''{{'}}s [[impact factor]], a measure of how many citations a journal generates in other works, was 38.138 in 2015 (as measured by [[Institute for Scientific Information|Thomson ISI]]), among the highest of any science journal.

As with most other professional scientific journals, papers undergo an initial screening by the editor, followed by [[peer review]] (in which other scientists, chosen by the editor for expertise with the subject matter but who have no connection to the research under review, will read and critique articles), before publication. In the case of ''Nature'', they are only sent for review if it is decided that they deal with a topical subject and are sufficiently ground-breaking in that particular field. As a consequence, the majority of submitted papers are rejected without review.

According to ''Nature''{{'}}s original [[mission statement]]:
{{quote|It is intended, FIRST, to place before the general public the grand results of Scientific Work and Scientific Discovery; and to urge the claims of Science to a more general recognition in Education and in Daily Life; and, SECONDLY, to aid Scientific men themselves, by giving early information of all advances made in any branch of Natural knowledge throughout the world, and by affording them an opportunity of discussing the various Scientific questions which arise from time to time.&lt;ref name=nature1869&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nature.com/npg_/company_info/mission.html |title=Nature's mission statement |accessdate=11 September 2008 |work= nature.com|date=11 November 1869 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

This was revised in 2000 to:
{{quote|First, to serve scientists through prompt publication of significant advances in any branch of science, and to provide a forum for the reporting and discussion of news and issues concerning science. Second, to ensure that the results of science are rapidly disseminated to the public throughout the world, in a fashion that conveys their significance for knowledge, culture and daily life.&lt;ref name=nature2000&gt;[http://www.nature.com/nature/about/index.html Nature's mission statement]. www.nature.com&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Landmark papers===
Many of the most significant scientific breakthroughs in modern history have been first published in ''Nature''. The following is a selection of scientific breakthroughs published in ''Nature'', all of which had far-reaching consequences, and the citation for the article in which they were published.

*[[Wave nature]] of particles — {{Cite journal | author=[[C. Davisson]] and [[L. H. Germer]] | title=The scattering of electrons by a single crystal of nickel | journal=Nature | year=1927 | volume=119 | pages=558–560 | doi=10.1038/119558a0|bibcode = 1927Natur.119..558D | issue=2998}}
*The [[neutron]] — {{Cite journal | author=J. Chadwick | title=Possible existence of a neutron | journal=Nature | year=1932 | volume=129 | page=312 | doi=10.1038/129312a0|bibcode = 1932Natur.129Q.312C | issue=3252 | authorlink= J. Chadwick}}
*[[Nuclear fission]] — {{Cite journal | author=[[L. Meitner]] and [[O. R. Frisch]] | title=Disintegration of uranium by neutrons: a new type of nuclear reaction | journal=Nature | year=1939 | volume=143 | pages=239–240 | doi=10.1038/143239a0|bibcode = 1939Natur.143..239M | issue=3615}}
*The structure of [[DNA]] — {{Cite journal | author=[[J. D. Watson]] and [[F. H. C. Crick]] | title=[[Molecular structure of Nucleic Acids|Molecular structure of Nucleic Acids: A structure for deoxyribose nucleic acid]] | journal=Nature | year=1953 | volume=171 | pages=737–738 | doi=10.1038/171737a0 | pmid=13054692 | issue=4356|bibcode = 1953Natur.171..737W }}
*First molecular [[protein]] structure ([[myoglobin]]) — {{Cite journal | author= J. C. Kendrew, G. Bodo, H. M. Dintzis, R. G. Parrish, H. Wyckoff and D. C. Phillips | title=A three-dimensional model of the myoglobin molecule obtained by X-ray analysis | journal=Nature | year=1958 | volume=181 | pages=662–666 | doi = 10.1038/181662a0 | pmid= 13517261 | issue= 4610|bibcode = 1958Natur.181..662K }}
*[[Plate tectonics]] — {{Cite journal | author=J. Tuzo Wilson| title=Did the Atlantic close and then re-open? | journal=Nature | year=1966 | volume=211 | pages=676–681| doi=10.1038/211676a0|bibcode = 1966Natur.211..676W | issue=5050 | authorlink= J. Tuzo Wilson}}
*[[Pulsars]] — {{Cite journal | author=[[Antony Hewish|A. Hewish]], [[Jocelyn Bell Burnell|S. J. Bell]], J. D. H. Pilkington, P. F. Scott &amp; R. A. Collins| title=Observation of a Rapidly Pulsating Radio Source | journal=Nature | year=1968 | volume=217 | pages=709–713| doi=10.1038/217709a0 | bibcode=1968Natur.217..709H | issue=5130}}
*The [[ozone hole]] — {{Cite journal | author=J. C. Farman, B. G. Gardiner and J. D. Shanklin | title=Large losses of total ozone in Antarctica reveal seasonal ClOx/NOx interaction | journal=Nature | year=1985 | volume=315 | pages=207–210 | doi=10.1038/315207a0 | issue=6016|bibcode = 1985Natur.315..207F }}
*First [[cloning]] of a [[mammal]] ([[Dolly the sheep]]) — {{Cite journal | author=[[Ian Wilmut|I. Wilmut]], A. E. Schnieke, J. McWhir, A. J. Kind and [[Keith Campbell (biologist)|K. H. S. Campbell]] | title=Viable offspring derived from fetal and adult mammalian cells | journal=Nature | year=1997 | volume=385 | pages=810–813 | doi=10.1038/385810a0 | issue=6619 | pmid=9039911|bibcode = 1997Natur.385..810W }}
*The [[human genome]] — {{Cite journal | author=International Human Genome Sequencing Consortium | title=Initial sequencing and analysis of the human genome | journal=Nature | year=2001 | volume=409 | issue=6822 | pages=860–921 | doi=10.1038/35057062 | pmid=11237011}}

===Controversies===
When [[Paul Lauterbur]] and [[Peter Mansfield]] won a [[Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine]] for research initially rejected by ''Nature'' and published only after Lauterbur appealed the rejection, ''Nature'' acknowledged more of its own missteps in rejecting papers in an editorial titled, &quot;Coping with Peer Rejection&quot;:
{{quote|[T]here are unarguable ''faux pas'' in our history. These include the rejection of [[Čerenkov radiation|Cerenkov radiation]], [[Hideki Yukawa]]'s [[meson]], work on [[photosynthesis]] by [[Johann Deisenhofer]], [[Robert Huber]] and [[Hartmut Michel]], and the initial rejection (but eventual acceptance) of [[Stephen Hawking]]'s [[Hawking radiation|black-hole radiation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v425/n6959/full/425645a.html |journal=Nature |date=16 October 2003 |title=Coping with peer rejection |volume=425 |page=645 |doi=10.1038/425645a |pmid=14562060 |issue=6959 |bibcode=2003Natur.425..645.}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

From 2000-2001, a series of five fraudulent papers by [[Schön scandal|Jan Hendrik Schön]] was published in ''Nature''. The papers, about [[semiconductors]], were revealed to contain falsified data and other scientific fraud. In 2003, ''Nature'' retracted the papers. The Schön scandal was not limited to ''Nature''; other prominent journals, such as ''[[Science (journal)|Science]]'' and ''[[Physical Review]]'', also retracted papers by Schön.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v422/n6927/index.html |journal=Nature |date=6 March 2003 |title=Retractions' realities |volume=422 |issue=6927 |page=1 |doi=10.1038/422001a |pmid=12621394}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 1988, after nearly a year of guided scrutiny from its editors, ''Nature'' published a controversial and seemingly anomalous paper detailing Dr. [[Jacques Benveniste]] and his team's work studying human [[Basophil granulocyte|basophil]] [[degranulation]] in the presence of extremely dilute [[antibody]] serum.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://vet-servis.ru/downloads/nature333-30-1988.pdf |title=vet-servis.ru |publisher=Vet-servis.ru |date= |accessdate=2014-05-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; In short, their paper concluded that less than a single molecule of antibody could trigger an immune response in human basophils, defying the physical [[law of mass action]]. The paper excited substantial media attention in Paris, chiefly because their research sought funding from [[homeopathic]] medicine companies. Public inquiry prompted ''Nature'' to mandate an extensive, stringent and scientifically questionable experimental [[replication (statistics)|replication]] in Benveniste's lab, through which his team's results were categorically disputed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
| title   = &quot;High-dilution&quot; experiments a delusion
| volume  = 334
| issue   = 6180
| journal = Nature
| pages   = 287–291
| year    = 1988
| pmid    = 2455869
| last1   = Maddox
| first1  = J.
| last2   = Randi
| first2  = J.
| last3   = Stewart
| first3  = W.
| doi     = 10.1038/334287a0
| bibcode = 1988Natur.334..287M
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Before publishing one of its most famous discoveries, [[James D. Watson|Watson]] and [[Francis Crick|Crick]]'s 1953 [[Molecular Structure of Nucleic Acids: A Structure for Deoxyribose Nucleic Acid|paper]] on the [[structure of DNA]], ''Nature'' did not send the paper out for peer review. [[John Maddox]], ''Nature''{{'}}s editor, stated: &quot;the Watson and Crick paper was not peer-reviewed by ''Nature'' ... the paper could not have been refereed: its correctness is self-evident. No referee working in the field ... could have kept his mouth shut once he saw the structure&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Maddox |first1=J. |doi=10.1038/426119b |title=How genius can smooth the road to publication |journal=Nature |volume=426 |issue=6963 |page=119 |year=2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An earlier error occurred when [[Enrico Fermi]] submitted his breakthrough paper on the weak [[Fermi's interaction|interaction theory]] of [[beta decay]]. ''Nature'' turned down the paper because it was considered too remote from reality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Rhodes, Richard |title=The Making of the Atomic Bomb|publisher= Touchstone|location= New York|date= 1986|isbn= 0-671-44133-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fermi's paper was published by ''[[Zeitschrift für Physik]]'' in 1934,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Fermi |first1=E. |title=Versuch einer Theorie der β-Strahlen. I |journal=Zeitschrift für Physik |volume=88 |issue=3–4 |pages=161–177 |year=1934 |doi=10.1007/BF01351864 |bibcode=1934ZPhy...88..161F}}&lt;/ref&gt; and finally published by ''Nature'' five years later,{{citation needed|date=March 2011}} after Fermi's work had been widely accepted.

==Science fiction==
In 1999 ''Nature'' began publishing [[science fiction]] [[short stories]]. The brief &quot;[[vignette (literature)|vignettes]]&quot; are printed in a series called &quot;Futures&quot;. The stories appeared in 1999 and 2000, again in 2005 and 2006, and have appeared weekly since July 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;futures&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.nature.com/nature/focus/arts/futures/ | title=Futures | work=Nature | accessdate=August 9, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sister publication ''[[Nature Physics]]'' also printed stories in 2007 and 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;FuturesPhysics&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.nature.com/nphys/archive/categ_fut_012008.html |title=Futures Archive |work= [[Nature Physics]] |accessdate= 2014-05-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005, ''Nature'' was awarded the [[European Science Fiction Society]]'s Best Publisher award for the &quot;Futures&quot; series.&lt;ref name=&quot;ESFSAward&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.esfs.info/esfs-awards-2000.html#2005 |title= The ESFS Awards, Eurocon 2005: Glasgow – Scotland |author= [[European Science Fiction Society]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; One hundred of the ''Nature'' stories between 1999 and 2006 were published as the collection ''Futures from Nature'' in 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;FuturesCollection&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.tor-forge.com/futuresfromnature |title= ''Futures from Nature: 100 Speculative fictions from the pages of the leading science journal'' |author=  Henry Gee, editor |publisher= [[New York City]]: [[Tor Books]] (1/1/2008).  ISBN 0-7653-1805-9, ISBN 978-0-7653-1805-3 |quote= With stories from: [[Arthur C. Clarke]], [[Bruce Sterling]], [[Charles Stross]], [[Cory Doctorow]], [[Greg Bear]], [[Gregory Benford]], [[Oliver Morton (science writer)|Oliver Morton]], [[Ian R. MacLeod]], [[Rudy Rucker]], [[Greg Egan]], [[Stephen Baxter (author)|Stephen Baxter]], [[Barrington J. Bayley]], [[Brian Stableford]], [[Frederik Pohl]], [[Vernor Vinge]], [[Nancy Kress]], [[Michael Moorcock]], [[Vonda McIntyre]], [[Kim Stanley Robinson]], [[John M. Ford]] and eighty more. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Publication ==
[[File:Nature Materials Nov 2008.jpg|thumb|upright|''Nature Materials'', a specialized journal from Nature Research]]
''Nature'' is edited and published in the United Kingdom by [[Nature Research]], a subsidiary of [[Macmillan Publishers]] which in turn is owned by the [[Georg von Holtzbrinck Publishing Group]]. ''Nature'' has offices in London, New York City, San Francisco, Washington, D.C., [[Boston]], Tokyo, Hong Kong, Paris, [[Munich]], and [[Basingstoke]]. Nature Publishing Group also publishes other specialized journals including ''[[Nature Neuroscience]]'', ''[[Nature Biotechnology]],'' ''[[Nature Methods]]'', the ''[[Nature Clinical Practice (disambiguation)|Nature Clinical Practice]]&lt;!--deliberate link to DAB page--&gt;'' series of journals, ''[[Nature Structural &amp; Molecular Biology]]'', ''[[Nature Chemistry]]'', and the ''Nature Reviews'' series of journals.

Since 2005, each issue of ''Nature'' has been accompanied by a ''Nature Podcast''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.nature.com/nature/podcast/archive.html | work = Nature |title = Archive: Nature Podcast |accessdate = 2014-05-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt; featuring highlights from the issue and interviews with the articles' authors and the journalists covering the research. It is presented by Kerri Smith, and features interviews with scientists on the latest research, as well as news reports from Nature's editors and journalists. The Nature Podcast was founded - and the first 100 episodes were produced and presented - by clinician and virologist [[Chris Smith, The Naked Scientist|Chris Smith]] of Cambridge and [[The Naked Scientists]].

In 2007, Nature Publishing Group began publishing ''Clinical Pharmacology &amp; Therapeutics'', the official journal of the American Society of Clinical Pharmacology &amp; Therapeutics and ''Molecular Therapy'', the American Society of Gene Therapy's official journal, as well as the ''International Society for Microbial Ecology (ISME) Journal''. Nature Publishing Group launched ''Nature Photonics'' in 2007 and ''Nature Geoscience'' in 2008. ''Nature Chemistry'' published its first issue in April 2009.

Nature Research actively supports the self-archiving process and in 2002 was one of the first publishers to allow authors to post their contributions on their personal websites, by requesting an exclusive licence to publish, rather than requiring authors to transfer copyright. In December 2007, Nature Research introduced the Creative Commons attribution-non commercial-share alike unported licence for those articles in Nature journals that are publishing the primary sequence of an organism's genome for the first time. In 2008, a collection of articles from ''Nature'' was edited by John S. Partington under the title ''H. G. Wells in Nature, 1893–1946: A Reception Reader'' and published by Peter Lang.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Partington, John S.|year=2008|title=H. G. Wells in Nature, 1893–1946: A Reception Reader|place=Frankfurt|publisher= Peter Lang|isbn=3631571100}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.itconversations.com/shows/detail1864.html Interview with Timo Hannay, director of web publishing for Nature Publishing Group]. ITConversations. 2007-07-05&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes and references==
{{Reflist|35em}}

==Bibliography==
*{{cite journal|ref=Barton | last1 = Barton | first1 = R. | year = 1996 | title = Just Before Nature: The Purposes of Science and the Purposes of Popularization in Some English Popular Science Journals of the 1860s| journal = [[Annals of Science]] | volume = 55 | issue = 1|doi=10.1080/00033799800200101|pmid=11619805 | pages = 1–33 }}
*{{cite book|ref=Browne|author=Browne, J. |year=2002|title=Charles Darwin: The Power of Place|place= New York|publisher= Alfred A. Knopf, Inc. |isbn=0691114390}}

==External links==
* {{commons category inline|Nature (Scientific journal)}}
* {{official website|http://www.nature.com/}}
* [http://onlinebooks.library.upenn.edu/webbin/serial?id=nature Freely available scans of volumes 1–112 (1869–1923)]
*[http://www.natureindex.com/ Nature Index]

{{Georg von Holtzbrinck Publishing Group|state=collapsed}}
{{Portal bar|Science}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Nature (Journal)}}
[[Category:Nature Research academic journals]]
[[Category:English-language journals]]
[[Category:Multidisciplinary scientific journals]]
[[Category:Natural sciences]]
[[Category:Weekly journals]]
[[Category:1869 establishments in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Publications established in 1869]]</text>
      <sha1>19vxxd61x61ym8iywuctqsjxog5zhle</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
