<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.28.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2600" case="first-letter">Topic</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Nose ring (animal)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8050342</id>
    <revision>
      <id>735764927</id>
      <parentid>709318640</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-22T23:28:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2620:0:1000:3317:64A1:44F1:EE91:2A55</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Bull handling on the farm or ranch */ Clarify that we're talking about human fatalities; the non-human fatalities are mostly caused by humans slitting their throats</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17416">{{for|nose rings as jewelry|nose piercing}}
[[Image:Cattle In The Show Ring, Devon.jpg|thumb|Show halters and bulldog nose rings on cattle at an agricultural show in the United Kingdom]]
A '''nose ring''' is a ring made of metal designed to be installed through the nasal septum of domestic cattle, usually [[bull]]s.  Nose rings are often required for bulls when exhibited at agricultural shows. There also is a clip-on ring design used for controlling other cattle for showing or handling. Nose rings are also used to prevent [[pig]]s rooting, and to encourage the weaning of young [[calf|calves]] and other livestock by discouraging them from suckling.

==History==
[[File:Standard of ur.jpg|thumb|The Standard of Ur]]
Historically, the use of nose rings for controlling animals dates to the dawn of recorded civilization.  They were used in ancient [[Sumer]] and are seen on the [[Standard of Ur]], where they were used on both draught cattle and [[equidae|equines]].&lt;ref&gt;Calvin W. Schwabe, 'Cattle, Priests and Medicine', Vol.4, at p. 16 (U. of Minn. 1978), ISBN 0-8166-0825-3&lt;/ref&gt;

==Use==
The nose ring assists the handler to control a dangerous animal with minimal risk of injury or disruption by exerting stress on one of the most sensitive parts of the animal, the nose.  Bulls, especially, are powerful and sometimes unpredictable animals which, if uncontrolled, can kill or severely injure a human handler.&lt;ref name=Albright&gt;[http://www.vetmed.ucdavis.edu/vetext/INF-DA/INF-DA_CAREPRAX6.HTML Jack Albright, ''Why and how to read a cow or bull'', Hoard's Dairyman Magazine, W.D. Hoard and Sons Co., Fort Atkinson, Wis., (Nov. 2000)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Dairy Care Practices: Animal Care Series'', Dairy Workgroup University of California Cooperative Extension (2008)&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[File:Show halter.jpg|thumbnail|A nose ring is used to maintain control of this [[bull]] being exhibited at a livestock show.]]

Control of the bull may be done by holding the ring by hand, looping a piece of rope through it, clipping on a lead rope, or clipping on a stiff ''bull pole'' (''bull staff'').  A rope or chain from the ring may be attached to a bull's horns or to a [[Horse tack#Halters|head-collar]] for additional control.

With an aggressive bull, a short length of chain or rope may be left hanging loose from the ring, so when he ducks in a threatening manner, the bull will step on the chain and be deterred from attacking.&lt;ref&gt;Miller, William C., &amp; Robertson, Major E D S, ''Practical Animal Husbandry'' Oliver and Boyd, Edinburgh, 7th ed, 1959: p 16&lt;/ref&gt;  This lead may also facilitate capture and control of a frisky bull.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=Rebhun's diseases of dairy cattle |author=Thomas J. Divers, Simon Francis Peek |url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=PbEWJrEtECIC&amp;pg=PA35}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Construction and insertion==
Bull rings are usually about {{Convert|3|to|5|in|cm|0}} in diameter, depending on the size of the bull.  Bull rings are commonly made from aluminium, stainless steel or copper, in the form of a pair of hinged semicircles, held closed by a small [[brass]] bolt whose head is broken off during installation.  If a ring needs to be removed (for example, if the bull has grown out of it), it is cut or unscrewed.  

The ring is normally placed on the bull between 9 and 12 months of age.&lt;ref&gt;''Dairy Care Practices: Animal Care Series'', Dairy Workgroup University of California Cooperative Extension&lt;/ref&gt;  It is usually done by a [[veterinarian]], who pierces the septum with a [[scalpel]] or punch. Self-piercing rings (with sharp ends designed to be pressed through the septum and then pulled together with a screw) have been available for many years; these are also usually installed by a veterinarian rather than the farmer.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lifestyleblock.co.nz/articles/cattle/20_noseringing_bull.htm C. Dalton, ''Noseringing a Bull'']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vetmed.ucdavis.edu/vetext/INF-DA/INF-DA_CAREPRAX6.HTML ''Dairy Care Practices: Animal Care Series'', Dairy Workgroup University of California Cooperative Extension (2008)]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Other designs==
===Calf-weaning ring===
Calf-weaning nose rings or nosebands provide an alternative to separating calves from their mothers during the weaning period. They have plastic spikes which are uncomfortable for the cow, causing her to reject the calf's efforts at suckling. Weaning nose rings are also available for sheep and goats. These nose rings (usually made of plastic) clip onto the nose without piercing it, and are reusable.
[[Image:XN Bos taurus 00.jpg|left|thumb|left|A spiked ring which prevents suckling]]

===Bulldogs===
Self-locking or spring-closing show-lead nose rings, also called &quot;bulldogs&quot; or nose grips, are removable rings that do not require the nose to be pierced. They are often used on steers and cows, along with a halter, at [[agricultural show]]s, or when handling cattle for examination, marking or treatment.  They stay shut until released, and usually have a loop for the attachment of a cord or [[lead rope]].  They give similar control to a bull ring without the need for permanent attachment. 

[[Image:Nose rings.jpg|thumb|right|Show-lead nose ring (bulldogs), and bull tongs or bull-holders on the right]]

===Bull tongs===
Bull-holders, also known as bull-tongs, have a pliers action and are used for short periods on grown cattle when they are being [[Cattle age determination|mouthed]] or drenched. A chain, rope or strap keeps the grips closed and may be passed over a bar at the front of a head bail to elevate the head.  The thumb and forefinger may also used in this way on smaller animals.

==Pig rings==
[[Image:Rung pig 2.JPG|thumb|right|Nose rings on a young pig foraging on the [[New Forest]]]]
[[Pig]]s dig or &quot;root&quot; with their snouts, and such digging may be undesirable in some circumstances.  Nose rings make digging uncomfortable for the animal, although a rung pig is still able to forage freely through leaf litter and surface vegetation.  Pig ringing may sometimes be required by local regulations, as when pigs are turned out for [[pannage]] in public woods (such as on the [[New Forest]] in southern [[England]]).

Pig rings usually consist of open copper or steel wire rings with sharp ends, about one inch (about 2.5&amp;nbsp;cm) in diameter.  These are clipped to the rim of the nose, not through the nostrils.  Typically an adult pig will be given three or four rings, as they may sometimes become dislodged.  Alternatively a ring may be placed through the septum, similarly to a bull's ring.

==Bull handling in the show ring==
For safety reasons, many show societies require bulls over 12 months to be led with a nose ring.   A bull may be led by a rope tied through the ring, although a [[halter]] (headcollar) is usually also used so as not to rely unduly on the nose ring for control. If the bull has horns, the lead rope may also be fastened around those and then passed down through the nose ring.  Some shows require other cattle to be led with nose grips (bulldogs). Several methods exist for handling a bull with a ring installed.  One method of leading a bull is to have one person on either side of the bull with both halter lead ropes through the ring, which prevents the bull from gaining pace and also from running into the handlers.&lt;ref&gt;Land Newspaper, Rural Press, Richmond, 20 March 2008 - p. 68&lt;/ref&gt; Another practice is for one handler to use a rope and the other a bull-staff attached to the ring.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.buckscountyshow.co.uk/pdf/healthsafety.pdf Bucks County Agricultural Health and Safety Policy]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bridgendshow.org.uk/health_safety_policy.html Bridgend County Show Health and Safety Policy]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Bull parade.JPG|thumb|300px|left|Charolais &amp; Murray Grey bulls on parade with nose rings and a show lead ring, Australia]]

==Bull handling on the farm or ranch==
It is estimated that 42% of all livestock-related human fatalities are a result of bull attacks, and only about one in twenty victims of a bull attack survives.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cfa-fca.ca/upload/casw_livestock.pdf Canadian Farming Administration, ''Handling Livestock Successfully'', 2000]&lt;/ref&gt; Dairy breed bulls are particularly dangerous and unpredictable; the hazards of bull handling are a significant cause of injury and death for dairy farmers in some parts of the United States.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.extension.umn.edu/distribution/livestocksystems/DI0878.html Larry D. Jacobson, Extension Agricultural Engineer, ''Safe Work Practices on Dairy Farms'', University of Minnesota Extension Services (1989)](&quot;During the last 10 years, 12 farmers in Minnesota were mauled and gored to death by dairy bulls&quot;).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cumberlink.com/articles/2008/02/12/shipp_news/news390.txt Cumberland County (Pa.) Sentinel, Shippensburg, Pa., February 12, 2008] A farmer in Southampton County, Michigan, was killed by a 2000 pound Holstein bull in Cumberland County, Pennsylvania, in February, 2008, prompting comments from experts ranging from &quot;never trust a bull&quot; to &quot;always take a dog with you&quot; when handling a bull.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://readingeagle.com/article.aspx?id=200357 The Reading (Pennsylvania&amp;#93;Eagle), March 1, 2010]  On February 28, 2010, a farmer near Reading, Pennsylvania was trampled and gored to death by a 2000 lb. black Angus bull that he had been urged to get rid of by friends after earlier mishaps. Michelle Park, &quot;Bull attacks, kills owner at South Heidelberg Township farm&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;  Most cattle breeders recognize the importance of looking after expensive bulls that are expected to improve herds and profits. Nonetheless, the dangers of bull handling, particularly from dairy bulls in close quarters, are regularly proven by the obituaries.&lt;ref&gt;''See'' C. Parsons, ''Students Mourn Teacher: FFA Advisor Killed by Bull'', 81 Capital Press, No.38, page 1 (Sept. 19, 2008) (veteran agricultural instructor killed by a dairy bull after warning others not to enter pen)&lt;/ref&gt; Good bull management and safety practices require caution in handling beef and dairy bulls, and use of the nose ring and chain is a recommended precaution for modern farmers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cdc.gov/nasd/docs/d001001-d001100/d001018/d001018.html Kerri Ebert and Michael Dennis, Pa. Ag. Extension Service, ''Cattle Safety'', National Ag Safety Database, 2001]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://capitaldairy.cas.psu.edu/Column/2002/2-41BullsOnDairyFarm.htm B. Grove &amp; A. Mills, ''Bulls on the Dairy Farm'', Kansas State University, Oct. 4, 2002 ]&lt;/ref&gt;

However, in many regions, particularly in the beef industry, bulls do not have nose rings unless they are to be exhibited and they are generally driven about as other cattle would be.&lt;ref&gt;W A Beattie, ''Beef Cattle Breeding and Management'', Popular Books, 1990&lt;/ref&gt;   Cows with young calves can be particularly dangerous if protecting their young, and cattle in general, including calves, steers and bullocks, do cause many serious human injuries and deaths.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cfa-fca.ca/upload/casw_livestock.pdf Cfa-fca.ca]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bae.ncsu.edu/programs/extension/farm_safety/cow.html Serious Cattle-lnflicted Injuries]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.grandin.com/behaviour/principles/principles.html Grandin.com. Injuries are caused by a steer or cow]&lt;/ref&gt;

Generally the use of both a ring and a halter, and management of the bull by two people, is the preferred method today for controlling the bull.   Typically, a bull was led by a wooden staff with a steel end that snapped into the ring.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.antiquefarmtools.info/USERIMAGES/270.JPG An example of a bull staff]&lt;/ref&gt; A long rigid steel or wooden bull staff locked into the ring could also be used to push a bull out of a pen without requiring the handler to enter the pen for cleaning or feeding.&lt;ref&gt;''The James Way'', The James Manufacturing Co., Ft. Atkinson, Wisc. (1914), at p. 103&lt;/ref&gt; Because of the risk that the bull may drive the staff into the handler if the bull misbehaves&lt;ref&gt;V G Cole, ''Beef Production Guide'', Livestock &amp; Grain Producers Association of NSW, 1978&lt;/ref&gt; many handlers prefer to avoid their use nowadays.  One current veterinary text still recommends the use of a staff in addition to the halter: &lt;blockquote&gt;Many handlers rely on a nose ring to control a bull.  But a ring in his nose is no good unless you have a bull staff and use it.  A bull staff is a pole with a snap in the end that clips to the bull ring.  Leading a bull with a staff gives you a lot more handling power as the bull can't get any closer to you than the length of the staff allows. Leading him only by a chain in the ring lets him run over you at will.&lt;ref name=&quot;C.E. Spaulding, D.V.M. 1998 p. 27&quot;&gt;C.E. Spaulding, D.V.M. &amp; Jackie Clay, ''Veterinary Guide for Animal Owners'', Rodale Press, Inc., Emmaus, Pa. (2d ed. 1998), p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Most dairy or beef farms traditionally had at least one, if not several, bulls for breeding purposes.&lt;ref&gt;U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, Yearbook 1922, Government Printing Office, Washington D.C. (1922), pp. 325-28 (noting a national on-farm bull population of over 600,000 &quot;scrub&quot; bulls in addition to a multi-year supply of &quot;pure bred&quot; bulls)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;O.C. Gregg, Ed., Minnesota Farmer's Institute Annual No. 15, Pioneer Press, St. Paul, Minn. (1902), pp.129-32 (recommending the keeping and testing of sires for dairy herd improvement).&lt;/ref&gt; The handling of an aggressive, powerful animal was a practical issue with life-threatening consequences for the farmer.&lt;ref name=Albright/&gt;  The need to move the bull in and out of its pen to cover cows exposed the farmer to serious jeopardy of life and limb.&lt;ref&gt;Alvin H. Clement, ''We Gotta Have More Jails'', The Writer's Club Press, New York (1984-87), at pp. 79-80. A humorous description of moving a cow to a neighbor's Jersey bull for breeding purposes, and the use of a 12-foot bull staff to get the loose-running bull under control after he had already spotted the cow&lt;/ref&gt; Being trampled, jammed against a wall or gored by a bull was one of the most frequent causes of death in the dairy industry prior to 1940.&lt;ref&gt;O.C. Gregg, Ed., Minnesota Farmer's Institute Annual No. 15, Pioneer Press, St. Paul, Minn. (1902), at p. 125; The James Way, The James Manufacturing Co., Ft. Atkinson, Wisc. (1914), p. 103&lt;/ref&gt; As suggested in one popular farming magazine, &quot;Handle [the bull] with a staff and take no chances.  The gentle bull, not the vicious one, most often kills or maims his keeper.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Helpful Information for Dairymen, ''The Farmer'' Webb Publishing Co., St. Paul, Minnesota, Mar. 12, 1927, p. 6&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Image:Brahman bulls.jpg|thumb|Bulls respond well to a good handler]]

When allowed outside its pen, the bull typically was kept in a halter connected by a strap snapped into the ring in his nose for ease of control.&lt;ref&gt;O.C. Gregg, Ed., ''Minnesota Farmer's Institute Annual'' '''15''', p. 126, Pioneer Press, St. Paul, Minn. (1902)&lt;/ref&gt; In the bull pen, the use of a ring connected by a cable to a fixed point was recommended as a means of controlling and securing the bull while allowing a degree of movement by the subject bull.&lt;ref&gt;The James Way, The James Manufacturing Co., Ft. Atkinson, Wisc. (1930), p. 114&lt;/ref&gt;  If the pen was strong enough, the bull could be turned loose, and if needed, placed in a stanchion.&lt;ref&gt;The James Way, The James Manufacturing Co., Ft. Atkinson, Wisc. (1914), p. 103&lt;/ref&gt; Farmers who lacked an assistant, or a bull staff, had no choice but to adopt other means.  Some farmers elected to move their bulls by tying a rope to the ring and tying the other end of the rope to a farm [[tractor]], providing both motive power and a degree of protection from the angry bull.&lt;ref&gt;Sara De Luca, ''Dancing the Cows Home: A Wisconsin Girlhood'', Minn. Hist. Soc. Press, St. Paul, Minn. (1996) pp.99-100 (moving a heifer with a tractor)&lt;/ref&gt;  The efficacy of this technique is doubtful, and may depend on the size of the tractor and of the bull; one authority has &quot;seen a bull lift the front end of a tractor like a toy&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;C.E. Spaulding, D.V.M. 1998 p. 27&quot;/&gt;  Others used dogs and horses.  Not all farmers could afford specially designed and manufactured bull handling products, which were not readily available until the 1980s.  The experimental improvisation of techniques for bull handling, as in many aspects of [[family farm]]ing, was a common practice.&lt;ref&gt;M. Cotter &amp; B. Jackson, ''Voices of America: Growing Up on a Minnesota Farm'', Arcadia Publishing Co., Chicago, Ill. (2001), pp. 23-24 (driving a 1500 pound Hereford bull named &quot;Domino&quot; by repeatedly firing a shotgun loaded with birdshot into its rear end)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;C.E. Spaulding, D.V.M. &amp; Jackie Clay, ''Veterinary Guide for Animal Owners'', Rodale Press, Inc., Emmaus, Pa. (2d ed. 1998), p. 27 (bull got a man down, knelt on him, and &quot;ignored pitchforks stuck into him in an effort to get him away from the victim&quot;).&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Nose piercing#Septum piercing|Nasal septum piercing (humans)]]
* [[Animal husbandry]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Commonscat|Nose rings (animals)}}
*[http://www.fmb.com.au/index1.html The Farmers Mailbox]
*[http://www.dpi.nsw.gov.au/agriculture/livestock/beef/breeding/bulls/bull-management Bull management]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Nose Ring (Animal)}}
[[Category:Animal equipment]]
[[Category:Cattle]]
[[Category:Bulls]]
[[Category:Pigs]]
[[Category:Livestock]]</text>
      <sha1>0ukcixs6d3kgbowtm3pvticopf5glfa</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
