<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Reelin</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>62810</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750146906</id>
      <parentid>749415455</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-18T02:06:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Migueldiazacevedo</username>
        <id>29688330</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Discovery */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="132156">{{Infobox_gene}}
'''Reelin''' (RELN)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = RELN gene|url = http://ghr.nlm.nih.gov/gene/RELN|website = Genetics Home Reference|date = 2016-01-25|access-date = 2016-01-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a large secreted [[extracellular matrix]] [[glycoprotein]] that helps regulate processes of [[neuronal migration]] and positioning in the developing brain by controlling [[cell–cell interaction]]s. Besides this important role in early [[Developmental biology|development]], reelin continues to work in the adult brain. It modulates [[synaptic plasticity]] by enhancing the induction and maintenance of [[long-term potentiation]].&lt;ref name=&quot;LTP1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LTP2&quot; /&gt; It also stimulates dendrite&lt;ref name=&quot;Niu_2004&quot; /&gt; and [[dendritic spine]]&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18842893&quot; /&gt; development and regulates the continuing migration of [[neuroblast]]s generated in [[adult neurogenesis]] sites like [[subventricular zone|subventricular]] and [[subgranular zone]]s. It is found not only in the [[brain]], but also in the [[spinal cord]], [[blood]], and other body organs and tissues.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

Reelin has been suggested to be implicated in pathogenesis of several brain diseases. The expression of the protein has been found to be significantly lower in [[schizophrenia]] and psychotic [[bipolar disorder]],&lt;ref name=&quot;szconfirm1&quot; /&gt; but the cause of this observation remains uncertain as studies show that [[Reelin#Psychotropic medication|psychotropic medication itself affects reelin expression]].  Moreover, epigenetic hypotheses aimed at explaining the changed levels of reelin expression&lt;ref name=&quot;Schizophrenia Research Forum: Current Hypotheses&quot; /&gt; are controversial.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17870056&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18319075&quot; /&gt; Total lack of reelin causes a form of [[lissencephaly]]. Reelin may also play a role in [[Alzheimer's disease]], [[temporal lobe epilepsy]] and [[autism]].{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

Reelin's name comes from the abnormal reeling [[gait]] of ''[[reeler]]'' mice,&lt;ref name=&quot;falconer&quot; /&gt; which were later found to have a deficiency of this brain [[protein]] and were [[Zygosity|homozygous]] for mutation of the RELN gene.
The primary phenotype associated with loss of reelin function is a failure of neuronal positioning throughout the developing [[central nervous system]] (CNS). The mice [[Zygosity|heterozygous]] for the reelin gene, while having little neuroanatomical defects, display the [[endophenotype|endophenotypic]] traits linked to psychotic disorders.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid16769115&quot; /&gt;

== Discovery ==
[[File:Reeler 100kbps.ogg|230px|thumb|left|Video: the reeler mice mutants, first described in 1951 by [[D.S.Falconer]], were later found to lack reelin protein.]]

[[File:Reeler lamination.png|thumb|250px|Normal and [[Reeler]] mice brain slices.]]
Mutant mice have provided insight into the underlying molecular mechanisms of the development of the [[central nervous system]]. Useful spontaneous mutations were first identified by scientists who were interested in [[motor behavior]], and it proved relatively easy to screen [[littermate]]s for mice that showed difficulties moving around the cage. A number of such mice were found and given descriptive names such as reeler, weaver, lurcher, nervous, and staggerer.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

The &quot;[[reeler]]&quot; mouse was described for the first time in 1951 by [[Douglas Scott Falconer|D.S.Falconer]] in [[Edinburgh University]] as a spontaneous variant arising in a colony of mice maintained by geneticist [[Charlotte Auerbach]].&lt;ref name=&quot;falconer&quot; /&gt; [[Histopathology|Histopathological]] studies in the 1960s revealed that the [[cerebellum]] of reeler mice is dramatically decreased in size while the normal laminar organization found in several brain regions is disrupted.&lt;ref name=&quot;hamburgh&quot; /&gt; The 1970s brought about the discovery of cellular layer inversion in the mouse neocortex,&lt;ref name=&quot;caviness&quot; /&gt; which attracted more attention to the reeler mutation.

In 1994, a new [[allele]] of reeler was obtained by means of insertional [[mutagenesis]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid7972007&quot; /&gt; This provided the first [[molecular marker]] of the [[Locus (genetics)|locus]], permitting the RELN gene to be mapped to chromosome 7q22 and subsequently cloned and identified.&lt;ref name=&quot;Darcan1&quot; /&gt;  Japanese scientists at [[Kochi Medical School]] successfully raised antibodies against normal brain extracts in reeler mice, later these antibodies were found to be specific [[monoclonal antibodies]] for reelin, and were termed CR-50 (Cajal-Retzius marker 50).&lt;ref name=&quot;cr50&quot; /&gt; They noted that CR-50 reacted specifically with [[Cajal-Retzius cell|Cajal-Retzius neurons]], whose functional role was unknown until then.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

The Reelin receptors, [[ApoER2|apolipoprotein E receptor 2]] (ApoER2) and [[VLDLR|very-low-density lipoprotein receptor]] (VLDLR), were discovered by Trommsdorff, Herz and colleagues, who initially found that the cytosolic adaptor protein Dab1 interacts with the cytoplasmic domain of LDL receptor family members.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid9837937&quot; /&gt;  They then went on to show that the double [[Gene knockout|knockout]] mice for ApoER2 and VLDLR, which both interact with Dab1, had cortical layering defects similar to those in reeler.&lt;!-- this result implied that they were receptors it was the later papers that demonstrated Reelin binding that confirmed this identity.--&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;receptors_discovery&quot; /&gt;

The [[Upstream and downstream (transduction)|downstream]] [[neural pathway|pathway]] of reelin was further clarified with the help of other mutant mice, including [[yotari]] and [[Scrambler mouse|scrambler]]. These mutants have phenotypes similar to that of reeler mice, but without mutation in reelin. It was then demonstrated that the mouse ''disabled homologue 1'' ([[DAB1|Dab1]]) gene is responsible for the phenotypes of these mutant mice, as Dab1 protein was absent (yotari) or only barely detectable (scrambler) in these mutants.&lt;ref name=&quot;yotari_and_scrambler&quot; /&gt; Targeted disruption of Dab1 also caused a phenotype similar to that of reeler. Pinpointing the [[DAB1]] as a pivotal regulator of the reelin signaling cascade started the tedious process of deciphering its complex interactions.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

There followed a series of speculative reports linking reelin's genetic variation and interactions to schizophrenia, Alzheimer's disease, autism and other highly complex dysfunctions. These and other discoveries, coupled with the perspective of unraveling the evolutionary changes that allowed for the creation of human brain, highly intensified the research. As of 2008, some 13 years after the gene coding the protein was discovered, hundreds of scientific articles address the multiple aspects of its structure and functioning.&lt;ref name=&quot;reelin_G_scholar_search_title&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Reelin_book_2008&quot; /&gt;

== Tissue distribution and secretion ==
Studies show that reelin is absent from [[synaptic vesicle]]s and is secreted via [[secretory pathway|constitutive secretory pathway]], being stored in [[Golgi apparatus|Golgi]] secretory vesicles.&lt;ref name=&quot;golgi&quot; /&gt; Reelin's release rate is not regulated by [[depolarization]], but strictly depends on its synthesis rate. This relationship is similar to that reported for the secretion of other [[extracellular matrix]] proteins.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

During the brain development, reelin is secreted in the cortex and hippocampus by the so-called [[Cajal-Retzius cell]]s, Cajal cells, and Retzius cells.&lt;ref name=&quot;cr_cells&quot; /&gt; Reelin-expressing cells in the prenatal and early postnatal brain are predominantly found in the marginal zone (MZ) of the cortex and in the temporary [[subpial granular layer]] (SGL), which is manifested to the highest extent in human,&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid9671277&quot; /&gt; and in the hippocampal [[stratum lacunosum-moleculare]] and the upper marginal layer of the [[dentate gyrus]].

In the developing [[cerebellum]], reelin is expressed first in the external [[granule cell]] layer (EGL), before the granule cell migration to the internal granule cell layer (IGL) takes place.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schiffmann&quot; /&gt;

Having peaked just after the birth, the synthesis of reelin subsequently goes down sharply, becoming more diffuse compared with the distinctly laminar expression in the developing brain. In the adult brain, reelin is expressed by [[GABA]]-ergic [[interneuron]]s of the cortex and glutamatergic cerebellar neurons,&lt;ref name=&quot;Interneurons&quot; /&gt; and by the few extant Cajal-Retzius cells. Among GABAergic interneurons, reelin seems to be detected predominantly in those expressing [[calretinin]] and [[calbindin]], like [[bitufted neuron|bitufted]], [[horizontal neurons|horizontal]], and [[Martinotti cell]]s, but not [[parvalbumin]]-expressing cells, like [[chandelier cell|chandelier]] or [[basket neuron]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Regional_patterns_1998&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;No_parvalbumin_1999&quot; /&gt; In the white matter, a minute proportion of [[interstitial neuron]]s has also been found to stain positive for reelin expression.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19543540&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Schema of the Reelin protein vertical en.png|thumb|Schema of the reelin protein]]
Outside the brain, reelin is found in adult mammalian blood, [[liver]], pituitary [[pars intermedia]], and adrenal [[chromaffin cell]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;bodyexpr&quot; /&gt; In the liver, reelin is localized in [[hepatic stellate cell]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;liver2&quot; /&gt; The expression of reelin increases when the liver is damaged, and returns to normal following its repair.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kobold_2002_liver1&quot; /&gt;
In the eyes, reelin is secreted by [[retinal ganglion cell]]s and is also found in the [[Corneal endothelium|endothelial layer of the cornea]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17120005&quot; /&gt; Just as in the liver, its expression increases after an injury has taken place.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

The protein is also produced by the [[odontoblast]]s, which are cells at the margins of the dental pulp. Reelin is found here both during odontogenesis and in the mature tooth.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid10980418&quot; /&gt; Some authors suggest that odontoblasts play an additional role as sensory cells able to [[Transduction (physiology)|transduce]] pain signals to the nerve endings.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid16831873&quot; /&gt; According to the hypothesis, reelin participates in the process&lt;ref name=&quot;Reelin_book_2008&quot; /&gt; by enhancing the contact between odontoblasts and the nerve terminals.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15464360&quot; /&gt;

== Structure ==
[[File:2e26.png|thumb|left|250px|The structure of two [[mouse|murine]] ''reelin repeats'' as revealed by [[X-ray crystallography]] and electron tomography.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17548821&quot; /&gt;]]
Reelin is composed of 3461 amino acids with a relative molecular mass of 388 [[Atomic mass unit|kDa]]. It also has [[serine protease]] activity.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid11689558&quot; /&gt; Murine RELN gene consists of 65 [[exon]]s spanning approximately 450 [[base pair|kb]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid9417911&quot; /&gt; One exon, coding for only two amino acids near the protein's [[C-terminus]], undergoes [[alternative splicing]], but the exact functional impact of this is unknown.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reelin_book_2008&quot; /&gt; Two transcription initiation sites and two polyadenylation sites are identified in the gene structure.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid9417911&quot; /&gt;

The reelin protein starts with a signaling peptide 27 amino acids in length, followed by a region bearing similarity to [[spondin 1|F-spondin]] (the [[reeler domain]]), marked as &quot;SP&quot; on the scheme, and by a region unique to reelin, marked as &quot;H&quot;. Next comes 8 repeats of 300–350 amino acids. These are called ''reelin repeats'' and have an [[epidermal growth factor]] motif at their center, dividing each repeat into two subrepeats, ''A'' (the [[BNR/Asp-box repeat]]) and ''B'' (the [[EGF-like domain]]). Despite this interruption, the two subdomains make direct contact, resulting in a compact overall structure.&lt;ref name=&quot;reelinstructure2006japan&quot; /&gt;

The final reelin domain contains a highly basic and short C-terminal region (CTR, marked &quot;+&quot;) with a length of 32 amino acids. This region is highly conserved, being 100% identical in all investigated mammals. It was thought that CTR is necessary for reelin secretion, because the Orleans [[reeler]] mutation, which lacks a part of 8th repeat and the whole CTR, is unable to secrete the misshaped protein, leading to its concentration in cytoplasm. However, other studies have shown that the CTR is not essential for secretion itself, but mutants lacking the CTR were much less efficient in activating downstream signaling events.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nakano_2007_CTR_1&quot; /&gt;

Reelin is cleaved ''in vivo'' at two sites located after domains 2 and 6 – approximately between repeats 2 and 3 and between repeats 6 and 7, resulting in the production of three fragments.&lt;ref name=&quot;cleave&quot; /&gt; This splitting does not decrease the protein's activity, as constructs made of the predicted central fragments (repeats 3–6) bind to lipoprotein receptors, trigger [[DAB1|Dab1]] [[phosphorylation]] and mimic functions of reelin during [[cortical plate]] development.&lt;ref name=&quot;centralfragment&quot; /&gt; Moreover, the processing of reelin by embryonic neurons may be necessary for proper corticogenesis.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17442808&quot; /&gt;

== Function ==
[[File:Rostral migratory stream mouse cropped.jpg|thumb|280px|As they travel through the [[rostral migratory stream]], neuroblasts are held together, probably in part by [[thrombospondin-1]]'s binding to the reelin receptors [[ApoER2]] and [[VLDLR]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18946489&quot; /&gt; As they arrive to the destination, the groups are dispersed by reelin and cells strike out on their individual paths. A fragment of an [[:Commons:Image:Rostral migratory stream mouse.jpg|illustration]] from Lennington et al., 2003.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid14614786&quot; /&gt;]]
The primary functions of Reelin are the regulation of corticogenesis and neuronal cell positioning in the prenatal period, but the protein also continues to play a role in adults. Reelin is found in numerous tissues and organs, and one could roughly subdivide its functional roles by the time of expression and by localisation of its action.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

=== During development ===
A number of non-nervous tissues and organs express reelin during development, with the expression sharply going down after organs have been formed. The role of the protein here is largely unexplored, because the knockout mice show no major pathology in these organs. Reelin's role in the growing central nervous system has been extensively characterized. It promotes the differentiation of progenitor cells into [[radial glia]] and affects the orientation of its fibers, which serve as the guides for the migrating neuroblasts.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid12925587&quot; /&gt; The position of reelin-secreting cell layer is important, because the fibers orient themselves in the direction of its higher concentration.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18197264&quot; /&gt; For example, reelin regulates the development of layer-specific connections in hippocampus and entorhinal cortex.&lt;ref name=&quot;DerRio1997&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Borrell1999&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Reelin controls directed growth of radial fibers - journal.pone.0001454.g005 center cropped.jpg|thumb|280px|Reelin controls the direction of radial glia growth. A fragment of an [[Commons:Image:Journal.pone.0001454.g005.jpg|illustration]] from Nomura T. et al., 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18197264&quot; /&gt; Reelin-expressing cells (red) on C stimulate the growth of green glial fibers, while on B, where the red cells do not express reelin, radial glia is more disarrayed.]]

Mammalian [[corticogenesis]] is another process where reelin plays a major role. In this process the temporary layer called preplate is split into the marginal zone on the top and subplate below, and the space between them is populated by neuronal layers in the inside-out pattern. Such an arrangement, where the newly created neurons pass through the settled layers and position themselves one step above, is a distinguishing feature of mammalian brain, in contrast to the evolutionary older reptile cortex, in which layers are positioned in an &quot;outside-in&quot; fashion. When reelin is absent, like in the mutant [[reeler]] mouse, the order of cortical layering becomes roughly inverted, with younger neurons finding themselves to be unable to pass the settled layers. Subplate neurons fail to stop and invade the upper most layer, creating the so-called superplate in which they mix with [[Cajal-Retzius cell]]s and some cells normally destined for the second layer.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

[[File:An increase of Reelin-positive cells changes morphology of migrating neurons - journal.pone.0001454.g007.jpg|thumb|280px|Increased reelin expression changes the morphology of migrating neurons: unlike the round neurons with short branches (C) they assume bipolar shape (D) and attach themselves (E) to the [[radial glia]] fibers that are extending in the direction of reelin-expressing cells. Nomura T. et al., 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18197264&quot; /&gt;]]

There is no agreement concerning the role of reelin in the proper positioning of  cortical layers. The original hypothesis, that the protein is a stop signal for the migrating cells, is supported by its ability to induce the dissociation,&lt;ref name=&quot;roleofreelin1&quot; /&gt; its role  in asserting the compact granule cell layer in the hippocampus, and by the fact  that migrating neuroblasts evade the reelin-rich areas. But an experiment in which murine corticogenesis went normally despite the malpositioned reelin secreting layer,&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid16410414&quot; /&gt; and lack of evidence that reelin affects the growth cones and leading edges of neurons, caused some additional hypotheses to be proposed. According to one of them, reelin makes the cells more susceptible to some yet undescribed positional signaling cascade.{{citation needed|date=June 2013}}

Reelin may also ensure correct neuronal positioning in the [[spinal cord]]: according to one study, location and level of its expression affects the movement of sympathetic preganglionic neurons.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19412957&quot; /&gt;

The protein is thought to  act on migrating neuronal precursors and thus controls correct cell positioning in the cortex and other brain structures. The proposed role is one of a dissociation signal for neuronal groups, allowing them to separate and go from tangential chain-migration to radial individual migration.&lt;ref name=&quot;roleofreelin1&quot; /&gt; Dissociation detaches migrating neurons from the [[glial cell]]s that are acting as their guides, converting them into individual cells that can strike out alone to find their final position.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

[[File:Profile of intense and punctate reelin IR during hippocampal maturation journal pone 0005505 g001 cr.png|thumb|280px|Top: Representative image of somatic reelin immunoreactivities found in 12 day-in-vitro hippocampal neurons. Bottom: reelin immunofluorescence (red) overlaid with [[MAP2]] [[counterstain]] (green). A fragment of an [[Commons:Image:Profile of intense and punctate reelin IR during hippocampal maturation journal pone 0005505 g001.png|illustration]] from Campo et al., 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19430527&quot; /&gt;]]

Reelin takes part in the developmental change of [[NMDA receptor]] configuration, increasing mobility of [[NR2B]]-containing receptors and thus decreasing the time they spend at the [[synapse]].&lt;ref name=&quot;OlivierManzoni&quot; /&gt;{{Dead link|date=December 2011}}&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15987942&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17881522&quot; /&gt; It has been hypothesized that this may be a part of the mechanism behind the &quot;NR2B-NR2A switch&quot; that is observed in the brain during its postnatal development.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15470155&quot; /&gt;  Ongoing reelin secretion by GABAergic hippocampal neurons is necessary to keep NR2B-containing NMDA receptors at a low level.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19430527&quot; /&gt;

=== In adults ===
In the adult nervous system, reelin plays an eminent role at the two most active neurogenesis sites, the subventricular zone and the dentate gyrus. In some species, the neuroblasts from the subventricular zone migrate in chains in the [[rostral migratory stream]] (RMS) to reach the olfactory bulb, where reelin dissociates them into individual cells that are able to migrate further individually. They change their mode of migration from tangential to radial, and begin using the radial glia fibers as their guides. There are studies showing that along the RMS itself the two receptors, [[ApoER2]] and [[VLDLR]], and their intracellular adapter [[DAB1]] function independently of Reelin,&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17494763&quot; /&gt; most likely by the influence of a newly proposed ligand, [[thrombospondin-1]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18946489&quot; /&gt; In the adult dentate gyrus, reelin provides guidance cues for new neurons that are constantly arriving to the granule cell layer from subgranular zone, keeping the layer compact.&lt;ref name=&quot;dentate_gyrus&quot; /&gt;

Reelin also plays an important role in the adult brain by modulating cortical pyramidal neuron [[dendritic spine]] expression density, the branching of [[dendrite]]s, and the expression of [[long-term potentiation]]&lt;ref name=&quot;LTP2&quot; /&gt; as its secretion is continued diffusely by the GABAergic cortical interneurons those origin is traced to the medial [[ganglionic eminence]].

In the adult organism the non-neural expression is much less widespread, but goes up sharply when some organs are injured.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kobold_2002_liver1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17120005&quot; /&gt; The exact function of reelin upregulation following an injury is still being researched.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

==Evolutionary significance==
[[File:Cajal-Retzius cell drawing by Cajal 1891.gif|left|thumb|440px|[[Cajal-Retzius cell]]s, as drawn by Cajal in 1891. The development of a distinct layer of these reelin-secreting cells played a major role in brain evolution.]]
[[File:Schematic illustration of differences in neuronal specification and migration patterns between the mammalian and avian pallium.png|thumb|left|250px|Neuronal development: mammals (left) and avians (right) have different patterns of reelin expression (pink). Nomura T. et al., 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18197264&quot; /&gt;]]
Reelin-DAB1 interactions could have played a key role in the structural evolution of the cortex that evolved from a single layer in the common predecessor of the [[amniote]]s into multiple-layered cortex of contemporary mammals.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid11137154&quot; /&gt; Research shows that reelin expression goes up as the cortex becomes more complex, reaching the maximum in the human brain in which the reelin-secreting Cajal-Retzius cells have significantly more complex axonal arbour.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid16519657&quot; /&gt; Reelin is present in the telencephalon of all the vertebrates studied so far, but the pattern of expression differs widely. For example, [[zebrafish]] have no Cajal-Retzius cells at all; instead, the protein is being secreted by other neurons.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid11173219&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid12124768&quot; /&gt; These cells do not form a dedicated layer in amphibians, and radial migration in their brains is very weak.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid11173219&quot; /&gt;

As the cortex becomes more complex and convoluted, migration along the radial glia fibers becomes more important for the proper lamination. The emergence of a distinct reelin-secreting layer is thought to play an important role in this evolution.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18197264&quot; /&gt; There are conflicting data concerning the importance of this layer,&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid16410414&quot; /&gt; and these are explained in the literature either by the existence of an additional signaling positional mechanism that interacts with the reelin cascade,&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid16410414&quot; /&gt; or by the assumption that mice that are used in such experiments have redundant secretion of reelin&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17132178&quot; /&gt; compared with more localized synthesis in the human brain.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid9671277&quot; /&gt;

Cajal-Retzius cells, most of which disappear around the time of birth, coexpress reelin with the [[HAR1]] gene that is thought to have undergone the most significant evolutionary change in humans compared with chimpanzee, being the most &quot;evolutionary accelerated&quot; of the genes from the [[human accelerated regions]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid16915236&quot; /&gt; There is also evidence of that variants in the DAB1 gene have been included in a recent selective sweep in Chinese populations.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17542651&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT1&quot; /&gt;

==Mechanism of action==
[[File:Model of Reelin and Lis1 signaling - journal.pone.0000252.g008.png|thumb|280px|The main reelin signaling cascade (ApoER2 and VLDLR) and its interaction with [[LIS1]].  Zhang et al., 2008&lt;ref name=&quot;Zhang_2007_Pafah1b&quot; /&gt;&lt;br&gt; '''SFK''': [[Src Family Kinases|Src family kinases]].&lt;br&gt;'''JIP''': [[MAPK8IP1|JNK-interacting protein 1]]]]

=== Receptors ===
Reelin's control of cell–cell interactions is thought to be mediated by binding of reelin to the two members of [[low density lipoprotein receptor gene family]]: [[VLDL receptor|VLDLR]] and the [[low density lipoprotein receptor-related protein 8|ApoER2]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid10571240&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid10571241&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid12899622&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid12670700&quot; /&gt;  The two main reelin receptors seem to have slightly different roles: VLDLR conducts the stop signal, while ApoER2 is essential for the migration of late-born neocortical neurons.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17913789&quot; /&gt; It also has been shown that the N-terminal region of reelin, a site distinct from the region of reelin shown to associate with VLDLR/ApoER2 binds to the alpha-3-beta-1 [[integrin]] receptor.&lt;ref name=&quot;integrin&quot; /&gt; The proposal that the proto[[cadherin]] CNR1 behaves as a Reelin receptor&lt;ref name=&quot;cadherin&quot; /&gt; has been disproven.&lt;ref name=&quot;centralfragment&quot; /&gt;

As members of lipoprotein receptor superfamily, both VLDLR and ApoER2 have in their structure an internalization domain called [[NPxY]] [[Structural motif|motif]]. After binding to the receptors reelin is internalized by [[endocytosis]], and the N-terminal fragment of the protein is re-secreted.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19303411&quot; /&gt; This fragment may serve postnatally to prevent apical dendrites of cortical layer II/III pyramidal neurons from overgrowth, acting via a pathway independent of canonical reelin receptors.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19366679&quot; /&gt;

Reelin receptors are present on both [[neuron]]s and [[glial cell]]s.  Furthermore, [[radial glia]] express the same amount of [[Low density lipoprotein receptor-related protein 8|ApoER2]] but being ten times less rich in [[VLDL receptor|VLDLR]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid12925587&quot; /&gt;  [[CD29|beta-1 integrin receptors]] on glial cells play more important role in neuronal layering than the same receptors on the migrating neuroblasts.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18077697&quot; /&gt;

Reelin-dependent strengthening of [[long-term potentiation]] is caused by [[ApoER2]] interaction with [[NMDA receptor]]. This interaction happens when ApoER2 has a region coded by exon 19. ApoER2 gene is alternatively spliced, with the exon 19-containing variant more actively produced during periods of activity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reelin_ApoER2_Exon19_2005_Beffert&quot; /&gt; According to one study, the hippocampal reelin expression rapidly goes up when there is need to store a memory, as [[demethylase]]s open up the RELN gene.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17359920&quot; /&gt; The activation of dendrite growth by reelin is apparently conducted through [[Src (gene)|Src]] family [[kinase]]s and is dependent upon the expression of [[CRK (gene)|Crk]] family proteins,&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18477607&quot; /&gt; consistent with the interaction of Crk and CrkL with tyrosine-phosphorylated Dab1.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15062102&quot; /&gt; Moreover, a [[Cre-Lox recombination|Cre-loxP recombination]] mouse model that lacks [[CRK (gene)|Crk]] and [[CRKL|CrkL]] in most neurons&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19074029&quot; /&gt; was reported to have the [[reeler]] phenotype, indicating that Crk/CrkL lie between [[DAB1]] and [[AKT1|Akt]] in the reelin signaling chain.

=== Signaling cascades ===
Reelin activates the signaling cascade of [[NOTCH1|Notch-1]], inducing the expression of [[FABP7]] and prompting progenitor cells to assume [[radial glia]]l phenotype.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18593473&quot; /&gt; In addition, corticogenesis ''in vivo'' is highly dependent upon reelin being processed by embrionic neurons,&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17442808&quot; /&gt; which are thought to secrete some as yet unidentified [[metalloproteinase]]s that free the central signal-competent part of the protein. Some other unknown proteolytic mechanisms may also play a role.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid12959647&quot; /&gt; It is supposed that full-sized reelin sticks to the extracellular matrix fibers on the higher levels, and the central fragments, as they are being freed up by the breaking up of reelin, are able to permeate into the lower levels.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17442808&quot; /&gt; It is possible that as [[neuroblast]]s reach the higher levels they stop their migration either because of the heightened combined expression of all forms of reelin, or due to the peculiar mode of action of the full-sized reelin molecules and its homodimers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reelin_book_2008&quot; /&gt;

The intracellular adaptor [[DAB1]] binds to the VLDLR and ApoER2 through an [[NPxY]] motif and is involved in transmission of Reelin signals through these lipoprotein receptors. It becomes phosphorylated by [[Src (gene)|Src]]&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid9009273&quot; /&gt; and [[FYN|Fyn]]&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid12526739&quot; /&gt; kinases and apparently stimulates the [[actin]] cytoskeleton to change its shape, affecting the proportion of integrin receptors on the cell surface, which leads to the change in [[Cell adhesion|adhesion]]. Phosphorylation of DAB1 leads to its [[ubiquitination]] and subsequent degradation, and this explains the heightened levels of DAB1 in the absence of reelin.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17974915&quot; /&gt; Such [[negative feedback]] is thought to be important for proper cortical lamination.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18006681&quot; /&gt; Activated by two antibodies, VLDLR and ApoER2 cause DAB1 phosphorylation but seemingly without the subsequent degradation and without rescuing the [[reeler]] phenotype, and this may indicate that a part of the signal is conducted independently of DAB1.&lt;ref name=&quot;centralfragment&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Reelin induces GFAP and FABP7 via Notch1.jpg|thumb|280px|Reelin stimulates the progenitor cells to differentiate into radial glia, inducing the expression of radial glial marker [[FABP7|BLBP]] by affecting the [[NOTCH1]] cascade. A fragment of an [[Commons:Image:Reelin-induced radial glial phenotype is dependent on gamma-secretase activity.jpg|illustration]] from Keilani et al., 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18593473&quot; /&gt;]]

A protein having an important role in [[lissencephaly]] and accordingly called [[LIS1]] ([[PAFAH1B1]]), was shown to interact with the intracellular segment of VLDLR, thus reacting to the activation of reelin pathway.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zhang_2007_Pafah1b&quot; /&gt;

=== Complexes ===
Reelin molecules have been shown&lt;ref name=&quot;hugecomplex&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;complex&quot; /&gt; to form a large protein complex, a [[disulfide bond|disulfide-linked]] [[homodimer]]. If the homodimer fails to form, efficient tyrosine [[phosphorylation]] of DAB1 ''in vitro'' fails. Moreover, the two main receptors of reelin are able to form clusters&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid14729980&quot; /&gt; that most probably play a major role in the signaling, causing the intracellular adaptor DAB1 to dimerize or oligomerize in its turn. Such clustering has been shown in the study to activate the signaling chain even in the absence of Reelin itself.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid14729980&quot; /&gt; In addition, reelin itself can cut the peptide bonds holding other proteins together, being a [[serine protease]],&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid11689558&quot; /&gt; and this may affect the cellular adhesion and migration processes. Reelin signaling leads to phosphorylation of [[actin]]-interacting protein [[cofilin 1]] at ser3; this may stabilize the actin cytoskeleton and anchor the leading processes of migrating neuroblasts, preventing their further growth.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19129405&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19396394&quot; /&gt;

=== Interaction with Cdk5 ===
[[Cyclin-dependent kinase 5]] (Cdk5), a major regulator of neuronal migration and positioning, is known to phosphorylate [[DAB1]]&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid14645539&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid16529723&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid12077184&quot; /&gt; and other cytosolic targets of reelin signaling, such as [[Tau protein|Tau]],&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid8253190&quot; /&gt; which could be activated also via reelin-induced deactivation of [[GSK3B]],&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid12376533&quot; /&gt; and [[NDEL1|NUDEL]],&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid11163259&quot; /&gt; associated with [[PAFAH1B1|Lis1]], one of the DAB1 targets. [[Long-term potentiation|LTP]] induction by reelin in hippocampal slices fails in [[CDK5R1|p35]] knockouts.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid14985430&quot; /&gt; P35 is a key Cdk5 activator, and double p35/Dab1, p35/RELN, p35/ApoER2, p35/VLDLR knockouts display increased neuronal migration deficits,&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid14985430&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid11226314&quot; /&gt; indicating a synergistic action of reelin → ApoER2/VLDLR → DAB1 and p35/p39 → Cdk5 pathways in the normal corticogenesis.

== Possible pathological role ==

=== Lissencephaly ===
Disruptions of the RELN gene are considered to be the cause of the rare form of [[lissencephaly]] with [[cerebellar hypoplasia]] called [[Norman-Roberts syndrome]].&lt;ref name=&quot;liss2000&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;liss2001&quot; /&gt; The mutations disrupt [[Splicing (genetics)|splicing]] of the RELN [[Messenger RNA|mRNA]] transcript, resulting in low or undetectable amounts of reelin protein. The [[phenotype]] in these patients was characterized by [[hypotonia]], [[ataxia]], and developmental delay, with lack of unsupported sitting and profound mental retardation with little or no language development. Seizures and [[congenital lymphedema]] are also present. A novel [[chromosomal translocation]] causing the syndrome was described in 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17431900&quot; /&gt; The mutations affecting reelin in human are usually associated with [[Consanguinity|consanguineous marriage]].{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

=== Schizophrenia ===
Reduced expression of reelin and its [[Messenger RNA|mRNA]] levels in the brains of [[schizophrenia]] sufferers had been reported in 1998&lt;ref name=&quot;szproof1&quot; /&gt; and 2000&lt;ref name=&quot;szproof2&quot; /&gt; and independently confirmed in the postmortem studies of hippocampus,&lt;ref name=&quot;szconfirm1&quot; /&gt; [[cerebellum]],&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15560956&quot; /&gt; [[basal ganglia]],&lt;ref name=&quot;BDP_basal_ganglia_2007&quot; /&gt; and in the cortex studies.&lt;ref name=&quot;szconfirm2&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;szconfirm3&quot; /&gt; The reduction may reach up to 50% in some brain regions and is coupled with reduced expression of [[GAD-67]] [[enzyme]],&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15560956&quot; /&gt; which catalyses the transition of [[glutamate]] to [[GABA]]. [[Blood test|Blood levels]] of reelin and its [[isoform]]s are also altered in schizophrenia, along with [[mood disorder]]s, according to one study.&lt;ref name=&quot;fatemi_blood_reelin&quot; /&gt; Reduced reelin mRNA prefrontal expression in schizophrenia was found to be the most statistically relevant disturbance found in the multicenter study conducted in 14 separate laboratories in 2001 by Stanley Foundation Neuropathology Consortium.&lt;ref name=&quot;Knable_2001&quot; /&gt;

[[Epigenetics|Epigenetic]] hypermethylation of DNA in schizophrenia patients is proposed as a cause of the reduction,&lt;ref name=&quot;hypermeth&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;dong&quot; /&gt; in agreement with the observations dating from the 1960s that administration of [[methionine]] to schizophrenic patients results in a profound exacerbation of schizophrenia symptoms in sixty to seventy percent of patients.&lt;ref name=&quot;methionine1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;methionine2&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;methionine3&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;methionine4&quot; /&gt; The proposed mechanism is a part of the &quot;epigenetic hypothesis for schizophrenia pathophysiology&quot; formulated by a group of scientists in 2008 (D. Grayson; A. Guidotti; [[Erminio Costa|E. Costa]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Schizophrenia Research Forum: Current Hypotheses&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19395859&quot; /&gt; A postmortem study comparing a [[DNA methyltransferase]] ([[DNA methyltransferase#DNMT 1|DNMT1]]) and Reelin mRNA expression in cortical layers I and V of schizophrenic patients and normal controls demonstrated that in the layer V both DNMT1 and Reelin levels were normal, while in the layer I DNMT1 was threefold higher, probably leading to the twofold decrease in the Reelin expression.&lt;ref name=&quot;epigenetic2007&quot; /&gt; There is evidence that the change is selective, and DNMT1 is overexpressed in reelin-secreting GABAergic neurons but not in their glutamatergic neighbours.&lt;ref name=&quot;DNMT_inhibition_GAD67_Reelin_2004&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15684088&quot; /&gt; [[Methylation]] inhibitors and [[histone deacetylase]] inhibitors, such as [[valproic acid]], increase reelin mRNA levels,&lt;ref name=&quot;valpro&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;valproicreelin&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mitchell&quot; /&gt; while L-methionine treatment downregulates the phenotypic expression of reelin.&lt;ref name=&quot;l-meth&quot; /&gt; One study indicated the upregulation of histone deacetylase HDAC1 in the hippocampi of patients.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17553960&quot; /&gt; Histone deacetylases suppress gene promoters; hyperacetylation of hystones was shown in murine models to demethylate the promoters of both reelin and GAD67.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dong_2007&quot; /&gt; DNMT1 inhibitors in animals have been shown to increase the expression of both reelin and GAD67,&lt;ref name=&quot;DNMT_inhibition_GAD67_Reelin_2006&quot; /&gt; and both DNMT inhibitors and HDAC inhibitors shown in one study&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19029285&quot; /&gt; to activate both genes with comparable dose- and time-dependence.  As one study shows, [[S-adenosyl methionine]] (SAM) concentration in patients' prefrontal cortex is twice as high as in the cortices of non-affected people.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAM_and_DNMT1_psychosis_2007&quot; /&gt; SAM, being a methyl group donor necessary for DNMT activity, could further shift epigenetic control of gene expression.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

The factors mentioned above serve to corroborate the epigenetic hypothesis. But it is worth mentioning that in contrast with initial data, two recent studies have failed to confirm the RELN hypermethylation,&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17870056&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18319075&quot; /&gt; and psychotropic medication could in itself affect the reelin expression in the brain, as animal studies show ([[Reelin#Psychotropic medication and reelin expression|see below]]).

Other interesting findings probably linking reelin pathway to developmental hypotheses of schizophrenia are noted in the studies on mice that are either prenatally infected with [[influenza]] virus&lt;ref name=&quot;influenza1&quot; /&gt; or have their immune system activated artificially during pregnancy.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18023140&quot; /&gt; The [[Cajal-Retzius cell]]s in the newborns secrete significantly less reelin despite keeping their expression of [[calretinin]] and [[NOS1|nNos]] within normal range. These data run in parallel with the findings of increased risk of schizophrenia in humans after a prenatal infection during the second trimester.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

Chromosome region [[7q22]] that harbours the ''RELN'' gene is associated with schizophrenia,&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17684500&quot; /&gt; and the gene itself was associated with the disease in a large study that found the polymorphism [[rs7341475]] to increase the risk of the disease in women, but not in men. The women that have the [[single-nucleotide polymorphism]] (SNP) are about 1.4 times more likely to get ill, according to the study.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18282107&quot; /&gt; Allelic variations of RELN have also been correlated with working memory, memory and executive functioning in nuclear families where one of the members suffers from schizophrenia.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17684500&quot; /&gt; The association with working memory was later replicated.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19922905&quot; /&gt; In one small study, nonsynonymous polymorphism [[Val997Leu]] of the gene was associated with left and right ventricular enlargement in patients.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19054571&quot; /&gt;

One study showed that patients have decreased levels of one of reelin receptors, [[VLDLR]], in the peripheral [[lymphocyte]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17936586&quot; /&gt; After six months of [[antipsychotic]] therapy the expression went up; according to authors, peripheral VLRLR levels may serve as a reliable peripheral biomarker of schizophrenia.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17936586&quot; /&gt;

Considering the role of reelin in promoting dendritogenesis,&lt;ref name=&quot;Niu_2004&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18477607&quot; /&gt; suggestions were made that the localized dendritic spine deficit observed in schizophrenia&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18463626&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid10632234&quot; /&gt; could be in part connected with the downregulation of reelin.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid10725376&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid11592844&quot; /&gt;

Reelin pathway could also be linked to schizophrenia and other psychotic disorders through its interaction with risk genes. One example is the neuronal transcription factor [[NPAS3]], disruption of which is linked to schizophrenia&lt;ref name=&quot;Kamnasaran_2003&quot; /&gt; and learning disability. Knockout mice lacking NPAS3 or the similar protein [[NPAS1]] have significantly lower levels of reelin;&lt;ref name=&quot;Erbel-Sieler_NPAS3_deficient_mice_2004&quot; /&gt; the precise mechanism behind this is unknown. Another example is the schizophrenia-linked gene [[MTHFR]], with murine knockouts showing decreased levels of reelin in the cerebellum.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15979267&quot; /&gt; Along the same line, it is worth noting that the gene coding for the subunit [[GRIN2B|NR2B]] that is presumably affected by reelin in the process of NR2B-&gt;NR2A developmental change of NMDA receptor composition,&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17881522&quot; /&gt; stands as one of the strongest risk [[Candidate gene|gene candidates]].&lt;ref name=&quot;GRIN2B_SZ_GENE_DB&quot; /&gt; Another shared aspect between NR2B and RELN is that they both can be regulated by the [[TBR1]] transcription factor.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15066269&quot; /&gt;

The [[Zygosity|heterozygous]] reeler mouse, which is [[Haploinsufficiency|haploinsufficient]] for the RELN gene, shares several neurochemical and behavioral abnormalities with schizophrenia and bipolar disorder,&lt;ref name=&quot;HRM_shared_abnormalities_with_SZ&quot; /&gt; but is considered not suitable for use as a genetic mouse model of schizophrenia.&lt;ref name=&quot;HRM_not_SZ&quot; /&gt;

=== Bipolar disorder ===
Decrease in RELN expression with concurrent upregulation of [[DNMT1]] is typical of [[bipolar disorder]] with psychosis, but is not characteristic of patients with major depression without psychosis, which could speak of specific association of the change with psychoses.&lt;ref name=&quot;szproof2&quot; /&gt; One study suggests that unlike in schizophrenia, such changes are found only in the cortex and do not affect the deeper structures in psychotic bipolar patients, as their basal ganglia were found to have the normal levels of DNMT1 and subsequently both the reelin and GAD67 levels were within the normal range.&lt;ref name=&quot;BDP_basal_ganglia_2007&quot; /&gt;

In a genetic study conducted in 2009, preliminary evidence requiring further [[DNA replication]] suggested that variation of the RELN [[gene]] (SNP [[rs362719]]) may be associated with susceptibility to [[bipolar disorder]] in women.&lt;ref name=&quot;BipWoman09&quot; /&gt;

===Autism===
{{main article|Heritability of autism}}

[[Autism spectrum|Autism]] is a [[neurodevelopmental disorder]] that is generally believed to be caused by mutations in several locations, likely triggered by environmental factors. The role of reelin in autism is not decided yet.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

Reelin was originally in 2001 implicated in a study finding associations between autism and a [[polymorphism (biology)|polymorphic]] GGC/CGG [[repeated sequence (DNA)|repeat]] preceding the 5' ATG initiator codon of the RELN gene in an Italian population.  Longer triplet repeats in the 5’ region were associated with an increase in autism susceptibility.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid11317216&quot; /&gt;  However, another study of 125 multiple-incidence families and 68 single-incidence families from the subsequent year found no significant difference between the length of the polymorphic repeats in affected and controls.  Although, using a family based association test larger ''reelin'' alleles were found to be transmitted more frequently than expected to affected children.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid12399956&quot; /&gt; An additional study examining 158 subjects with German lineage likewise found no evidence of triplet repeat polymorphisms associated with autism.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid14515139&quot; /&gt; And a larger study from 2004 consisting of 395 families found no association between autistic subjects and the CGG triplet repeat as well as the allele size when compared to age of first word.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15048647&quot; /&gt;
In 2010 a large study using data from 4 European cohorts would find some evidence for an association between autism and the [[rs362780]] RELN polymorphism.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid20442744&quot;/&gt;

Studies of [[genetically modified organism|transgenic]] mice have been suggestive of an association, but not definitive.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17919129&quot; /&gt;

===Temporal lobe epilepsy: granule cell dispersion===
Decreased reelin expression in the hippocampal tissue samples from patients with [[temporal lobe epilepsy]] was found to be directly correlated with the extent of [[granule cell]] dispersion (GCD), a major feature of the disease that is noted in 45%–73% of patients.&lt;ref name=&quot;TLE1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TLE2&quot; /&gt; The dispersion, according to a small study, is associated with the RELN promoter hypermethylation.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19287316&quot; /&gt; According to one study, prolonged seizures in a rat model of mesial temporal lobe epilepsy have led to the loss of reelin-expressing interneurons and subsequent ectopic chain migration and aberrant integration of newborn dentate granule cells.  Without reelin, the chain-migrating neuroblasts failed to detach properly.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gonq_2007&quot; /&gt; Moreover, in a [[kainate]]-induced mouse epilepsy model, exogenous reelin had prevented GCD, according to one study.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19185570&quot; /&gt;

===Alzheimer's disease===
The Reelin receptors [[ApoER2]] and [[VLDLR]] belong to the [[LDL]] receptor gene family.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid11252768&quot; /&gt;  All members of this family are receptors for [[Apolipoprotein E]] (ApoE). Therefore, they are often synonymously referred to as 'ApoE receptors'.  ApoE occurs in 3 common isoforms (E2, E3, E4) in the human population.  [[ApoE4]] is the primary genetic risk factor for late-onset [[Alzheimer's disease]].  This strong genetic association has led to the proposal that ApoE receptors play a central role in the pathogenesis of Alzheimer's Disease.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid11252768&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17053810&quot; /&gt;  According to one study, reelin expression and [[glycosylation]] patterns are altered in [[Alzheimer's disease]]. In the cortex of the patients, reelin levels were 40% higher compared with controls, but the cerebellar levels of the protein remain normal in the same patients.&lt;ref name=&quot;alz&quot; /&gt; This finding is in agreement with an earlier study showing the presence of Reelin associated with amyloid plaques in a transgenic AD mouse model.&lt;ref name=&quot;alzmouse&quot; /&gt; A large genetic study of 2008 showed that RELN gene variation is associated with an increased risk of Alzheimer's disease in women.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18599960&quot; /&gt; The number of reelin-producing Cajal-Retzius cells is significantly decreased in the first cortical layer of patients.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid16051543&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17453452&quot; /&gt; Reelin has been shown to interact with [[amyloid precursor protein]],&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19515914&quot; /&gt; and, according to one in-vitro study, is able to counteract the Aβ-induced dampening of [[NMDA-receptor]] activity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Herz2009relnabeta&quot; /&gt;  This is modulated by ApoE isoforms, which selectively alter the recycling of ApoER2 as well as AMPA and NMDA receptors.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid20547867&quot; /&gt;

=== Cancer ===
[[DNA methylation]] patterns are often changed in tumours, and the RELN gene could be affected: according to one study, in the [[pancreatic cancer]] the expression is suppressed, along with other reelin pathway components&lt;ref name=&quot;Pancreatic_Cancer_2006&quot; /&gt; In the same study, cutting the reelin pathway in cancer cells that still expressed reelin resulted in increased motility and invasiveness. On the contrary, in [[prostate cancer]] the RELN expression is excessive and correlates with [[Gleason score]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Prostate_Cancer_2007_1&quot; /&gt;  [[Retinoblastoma]] presents another example of RELN overexpression.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17615543&quot; /&gt; This gene has also been seen recurrently mutated in cases of [[acute lymphoblastic leukaemia]].&lt;ref name=doi.10.1038/nature10725&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zhang J, Ding L, Holmfeldt L, Wu G, Heatley SL, Payne-Turner D, Easton J, Chen X, Wang J, Rusch M, Lu C, Chen SC, Wei L, Collins-Underwood JR, Ma J, Roberts KG, Pounds SB, Ulyanov A, Becksfort J, Gupta P, Huether R, Kriwacki RW, Parker M, McGoldrick DJ, Zhao D, Alford D, Espy S, Bobba KC, Song G, Pei D, Cheng C, Roberts S, Barbato MI, Campana D, Coustan-Smith E, Shurtleff SA, Raimondi SC, Kleppe M, Cools J, Shimano KA, Hermiston ML, Doulatov S, Eppert K, Laurenti E, Notta F, Dick JE, Basso G, Hunger SP, Loh ML, Devidas M, Wood B, Winter S, Dunsmore KP, Fulton RS, Fulton LL, Hong X, Harris CC, Dooling DJ, Ochoa K, Johnson KJ, Obenauer JC, Evans WE, Pui CH, Naeve CW, Ley TJ, Mardis ER, Wilson RK, Downing JR, Mullighan CG | display-authors = 6 | title = The genetic basis of early T-cell precursor acute lymphoblastic leukaemia | journal = Nature | volume = 481 | issue = 7380 | pages = 157–63 | date = Jan 2012 | pmid = 22237106 | pmc = 3267575 | doi = 10.1038/nature10725 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Other conditions ===
One [[genome-wide association study]] indicates a possible role for RELN gene variation in [[otosclerosis]], an abnormal growth of bone of the [[middle ear]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19230858&quot; /&gt; In a statistical search for the genes that are differentially expressed in the brains of cerebral malaria-resistant versus cerebral malaria-susceptible mice, Delahaye et al. detected a significant upregulation of both RELN and [[DAB1]] and speculated on possible protective effects of such over-expression.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18062806&quot; /&gt;

== Factors affecting reelin expression ==
[[File:Differential reelin levels in the cortex of adult high and low LG rats.gif|thumb|330px|Increased cortical reelin expression in the pups of &quot;High LG&quot; (licking and grooming) rats. A figure from Smit-Righter et al., 2009&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19357777&quot; /&gt;]]
The expression of reelin is controlled by a number of factors besides the sheer number of Cajal-Retzius cells. For example, [[TBR1]] transcription factor regulates RELN along with other [[T-element]]-containing genes.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15066269&quot; /&gt; On a higher level, increased maternal care was found to correlate with reelin expression in rat pups; such correlation was reported in hippocampus&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid16484373&quot; /&gt; and in the cortex.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19357777&quot; /&gt; According to one report, prolonged exposure to [[corticosterone]] significantly decreased reelin expression in murine hippocampi, a finding possibly pertinent to the hypothetical role of [[corticosteroids]] in [[Clinical depression|depression]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19477232&quot; /&gt; One small postmortem study has found increased methylation of RELN gene in the neocortex of persons past their puberty compared with those that had yet to enter the period of maturation.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19952965&quot; /&gt;

=== Psychotropic medication===
As reelin is being implicated in a number of brain disorders and its expression is usually measured posthumously, assessing the possible medication effects is important.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

According to the epigenetic hypothesis, drugs that shift the balance in favour of [[demethylation]] have a potential to alleviate the proposed methylation-caused downregulation of RELN and GAD67. In one study, clozapine and sulpiride but not haloperidol and olanzapine were shown to increase the demethylation of both genes in mice pretreated with l-methionine.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18757738&quot; /&gt; [[Valproic acid]], a [[histone deacetylase inhibitor]], when taken in combination with antipsychotics, is proposed to have some benefits. But there are studies conflicting the main premise of the epigenetic hypothesis, and a study by Fatemi et al. shows no increase in RELN expression by valproic acid; that indicates the need for further investigation.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

Fatemi et al. conducted the study in which RELN mRNA and reelin protein levels were measured in rat prefrontal cortex following a 21-day of [[intraperitoneal injection]]s of the following drugs:&lt;ref name=&quot;Reelin_book_2008&quot; /&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:125px;&quot;| Reelin expression
! style=&quot;width:85px;&quot;| [[Clozapine]]
! style=&quot;width:85px;&quot;| [[Fluoxetine]]
! style=&quot;width:85px;&quot;| [[Haloperidol]]
! style=&quot;width:85px;&quot;| [[Lithium]]
! style=&quot;width:85px;&quot;| [[Olanzapine]]
! style=&quot;width:85px;&quot;| [[Valproic Acid]]
|-
| protein || '''↓''' || '''↔''' || '''↓''' || '''↓''' || '''↑''' || '''↔'''
|-
| mRNA || '''↑''' || '''↑''' || '''↓''' || '''↑''' || '''↑''' || '''↓'''
|}
In 2009, Fatemi et al. published the more detailed work on rats using the same medication. Here, cortical expression of several participants ([[VLDLR]], [[DAB1]], [[GSK3B]]) of the signaling chain was measured besides reelin itself, and also the expression of [[GAD65]] and [[GAD67]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19359144&quot; /&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist|33em|refs=
&lt;!--not used
&lt;ref name=&quot;Assadi_2003&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Assadi AH, Zhang G, Beffert U, McNeil RS, Renfro AL, Niu S, Quattrocchi CC, Antalffy BA, Sheldon M, Armstrong DD, Wynshaw-Boris A, Herz J, D'Arcangelo G, Clark GD | title = Interaction of reelin signaling and Lis1 in brain development | journal = [[Nature Genetics]] |volume= 35|issue= 3|pages= 270–6 |date=October 2003 | doi=10.1038/ng1257 | pmid=14578885}}&lt;/ref&gt;
--&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid20442744&quot; &gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Holt R, Barnby G, Maestrini E, Bacchelli E, Brocklebank D, Sousa I, Mulder EJ, Kantojärvi K, Järvelä I, Klauck SM, Poustka F, Bailey AJ, Monaco AP | title = Linkage and candidate gene studies of autism spectrum disorders in European populations | journal = European Journal of Human Genetics | volume = 18 | issue = 9 | pages = 1013–9 | date = Sep 2010 | pmid = 20442744 | pmc = 2987412 | doi = 10.1038/ejhg.2010.69 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19952965&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lintas C, Persico AM | title = Neocortical RELN promoter methylation increases significantly after puberty | journal = NeuroReport | volume = 21 | issue = 2 | pages = 114–8 | date = Jan 2010 | pmid = 19952965 | doi = 10.1097/WNR.0b013e328334b343 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;LTP1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Weeber EJ, Beffert U, Jones C, Christian JM, Forster E, Sweatt JD, Herz J | title = Reelin and ApoE receptors cooperate to enhance hippocampal synaptic plasticity and learning | journal = The Journal of Biological Chemistry | volume = 277 | issue = 42 | pages = 39944–52 | date = Oct 2002 | pmid = 12167620 | doi = 10.1074/jbc.M205147200 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;LTP2&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = D'Arcangelo G | title = Apoer2: a reelin receptor to remember | journal = Neuron | volume = 47 | issue = 4 | pages = 471–3 | date = Aug 2005 | pmid = 16102527 | doi = 10.1016/j.neuron.2005.08.001 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Niu_2004&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Niu S, Renfro A, Quattrocchi CC, Sheldon M, D'Arcangelo G | title = Reelin promotes hippocampal dendrite development through the VLDLR/ApoER2-Dab1 pathway | journal = Neuron | volume = 41 | issue = 1 | pages = 71–84 | date = Jan 2004 | pmid = 14715136 | doi = 10.1016/S0896-6273(03)00819-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18842893&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Niu S, Yabut O, D'Arcangelo G | title = The Reelin signaling pathway promotes dendritic spine development in hippocampal neurons | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 28 | issue = 41 | pages = 10339–48 | date = Oct 2008 | pmid = 18842893 | pmc = 2572775 | doi = 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1917-08.2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Schizophrenia Research Forum: Current Hypotheses&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.schizophreniaforum.org/for/curr/grayson/default.asp | title = Current Hypotheses |vauthors=Grayson DR, Guidotti A, Costa E | date = 2008-01-17 | work = Schizophrenia Research Forum | publisher = schizophreniaforum.org | accessdate = 2008-08-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19395859&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Grayson DR, Chen Y, Dong E, Kundakovic M, Guidotti A | title = From trans-methylation to cytosine methylation: evolution of the methylation hypothesis of schizophrenia | journal = Epigenetics | volume = 4 | issue = 3 | pages = 144–9 | date = Apr 2009 | pmid = 19395859 | doi = 10.4161/epi.4.3.8534 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17870056&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Tochigi M, Iwamoto K, Bundo M, Komori A, Sasaki T, Kato N, Kato T | title = Methylation status of the reelin promoter region in the brain of schizophrenic patients | journal = Biological Psychiatry | volume = 63 | issue = 5 | pages = 530–3 | date = Mar 2008 | pmid = 17870056 | doi = 10.1016/j.biopsych.2007.07.003 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18319075&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Mill J, Tang T, Kaminsky Z, Khare T, Yazdanpanah S, Bouchard L, Jia P, Assadzadeh A, Flanagan J, Schumacher A, Wang SC, Petronis A | title = Epigenomic profiling reveals DNA-methylation changes associated with major psychosis | journal = American Journal of Human Genetics | volume = 82 | issue = 3 | pages = 696–711 | date = Mar 2008 | pmid = 18319075 | pmc = 2427301 | doi = 10.1016/j.ajhg.2008.01.008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;falconer&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal | author = Falconer DS |date=January 1951 | title = Two new mutants, 'trembler' and 'reeler', with neurological actions in the house mouse (Mus musculus L.) | journal = Journal of Genetics | volume = 50 | issue = 2 | pages = 192–201 | doi = 10.1007/BF02996215 | url = http://www.ias.ac.in/jarch/jgenet/50/192.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid16769115&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Tueting P, Doueiri MS, Guidotti A, Davis JM, Costa E | title = Reelin down-regulation in mice and psychosis endophenotypes | journal = Neuroscience and Biobehavioral Reviews | volume = 30 | issue = 8 | pages = 1065–77 | year = 2006 | pmid = 16769115 | doi = 10.1016/j.neubiorev.2006.04.001 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;hamburgh&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hamburgh M | title = Analysis of the postnatal developmental effects of &quot;reeler,&quot; a neurological mutation in mice. a study in developmental genetics | journal = Developmental Biology | volume = 8 | issue = 2 | pages = 165–85 | date = Oct 1963 | pmid = 14069672 | doi = 10.1016/0012-1606(63)90040-X }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;caviness&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Caviness VS | title = Patterns of cell and fiber distribution in the neocortex of the reeler mutant mouse | journal = The Journal of Comparative Neurology | volume = 170 | issue = 4 | pages = 435–47 | date = Dec 1976 | pmid = 1002868 | doi = 10.1002/cne.901700404 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid7972007&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Miao GG, Smeyne RJ, D'Arcangelo G, Copeland NG, Jenkins NA, Morgan JI, Curran T | title = Isolation of an allele of reeler by insertional mutagenesis | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 91 | issue = 23 | pages = 11050–4 | date = Nov 1994 | pmid = 7972007 | pmc = 45164 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.91.23.11050 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Darcan1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = D'Arcangelo G, Miao GG, Chen SC, Soares HD, Morgan JI, Curran T | title = A protein related to extracellular matrix proteins deleted in the mouse mutant reeler | journal = Nature | volume = 374 | issue = 6524 | pages = 719–23 | date = Apr 1995 | pmid = 7715726 | doi = 10.1038/374719a0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;cr50&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ogawa M, Miyata T, Nakajima K, Yagyu K, Seike M, Ikenaka K, Yamamoto H, Mikoshiba K | title = The reeler gene-associated antigen on Cajal-Retzius neurons is a crucial molecule for laminar organization of cortical neurons | journal = Neuron | volume = 14 | issue = 5 | pages = 899–912 | date = May 1995 | pmid = 7748558 | doi = 10.1016/0896-6273(95)90329-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid9837937&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Trommsdorff M, Borg JP, Margolis B, Herz J | title = Interaction of cytosolic adaptor proteins with neuronal apolipoprotein E receptors and the amyloid precursor protein | journal = The Journal of Biological Chemistry | volume = 273 | issue = 50 | pages = 33556–60 | date = Dec 1998 | pmid = 9837937 | doi = 10.1074/jbc.273.50.33556 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;receptors_discovery&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Trommsdorff M, Gotthardt M, Hiesberger T, Shelton J, Stockinger W, Nimpf J, Hammer RE, Richardson JA, Herz J | title = Reeler/Disabled-like disruption of neuronal migration in knockout mice lacking the VLDL receptor and ApoE receptor 2 | journal = Cell | volume = 97 | issue = 6 | pages = 689–701 | date = Jun 1999 | pmid = 10380922 | doi = 10.1016/S0092-8674(00)80782-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;yotari_and_scrambler&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Sheldon M, Rice DS, D'Arcangelo G, Yoneshima H, Nakajima K, Mikoshiba K, Howell BW, Cooper JA, Goldowitz D, Curran T | title = Scrambler and yotari disrupt the disabled gene and produce a reeler-like phenotype in mice | journal = Nature | volume = 389 | issue = 6652 | pages = 730–3 | date = Oct 1997 | pmid = 9338784 | doi = 10.1038/39601 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;reelin_G_scholar_search_title&quot;&gt;[https://scholar.google.com/scholar?as_q=reelin&amp;num=10&amp;btnG=Search+Scholar&amp;as_epq=&amp;as_oq=&amp;as_eq=&amp;as_occt=title&amp;as_sauthors=&amp;as_publication=&amp;as_ylo=&amp;as_yhi=&amp;as_allsubj=all&amp;hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;safe=off &quot;Reelin&quot; mentioned in the titles of scientific literature] – a search in the [[Google Scholar]]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Reelin_book_2008&quot;&gt;{{cite book | editor = Hossein S. Fatemi | title = Reelin Glycoprotein: Structure, Biology and Roles in Health and Disease | publisher = Springer | year = 2008 | doi = | page = 444 | isbn = 978-0-387-76760-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;golgi&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lacor PN, Grayson DR, Auta J, Sugaya I, Costa E, Guidotti A | title = Reelin secretion from glutamatergic neurons in culture is independent from neurotransmitter regulation | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 97 | issue = 7 | pages = 3556–61 | date = Mar 2000 | pmid = 10725375 | pmc = 16278 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.050589597 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;cr_cells&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Meyer G, Goffinet AM, Fairén A | title = What is a Cajal-Retzius cell? A reassessment of a classical cell type based on recent observations in the developing neocortex | journal = Cerebral Cortex | volume = 9 | issue = 8 | pages = 765–75 | date = Dec 1999 | pmid = 10600995 | doi = 10.1093/cercor/9.8.765 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid9671277&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Meyer G, Goffinet AM | title = Prenatal development of reelin-immunoreactive neurons in the human neocortex | journal = The Journal of Comparative Neurology | volume = 397 | issue = 1 | pages = 29–40 | date = Jul 1998 | pmid = 9671277 | doi = 10.1002/(SICI)1096-9861(19980720)397:1&lt;29::AID-CNE3&gt;3.3.CO;2-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Schiffmann&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Schiffmann SN, Bernier B, Goffinet AM | title = Reelin mRNA expression during mouse brain development | journal = The European Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 9 | issue = 5 | pages = 1055–71 | date = May 1997 | pmid = 9182958 | doi = 10.1111/j.1460-9568.1997.tb01456.x }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Interneurons&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Pesold C, Impagnatiello F, Pisu MG, Uzunov DP, Costa E, Guidotti A, Caruncho HJ | title = Reelin is preferentially expressed in neurons synthesizing gamma-aminobutyric acid in cortex and hippocampus of adult rats | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 95 | issue = 6 | pages = 3221–6 | date = Mar 1998 | pmid = 9501244 | pmc = 19723 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.95.6.3221 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Regional_patterns_1998&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Alcántara S, Ruiz M, D'Arcangelo G, Ezan F, de Lecea L, Curran T, Sotelo C, Soriano E | title = Regional and cellular patterns of reelin mRNA expression in the forebrain of the developing and adult mouse | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 18 | issue = 19 | pages = 7779–99 | date = Oct 1998 | pmid = 9742148 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;No_parvalbumin_1999&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Pesold C, Liu WS, Guidotti A, Costa E, Caruncho HJ | title = Cortical bitufted, horizontal, and Martinotti cells preferentially express and secrete reelin into perineuronal nets, nonsynaptically modulating gene expression | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 96 | issue = 6 | pages = 3217–22 | date = Mar 1999 | pmid = 10077664 | pmc = 15922 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.96.6.3217 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19543540&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Suárez-Solá ML, González-Delgado FJ, Pueyo-Morlans M, Medina-Bolívar OC, Hernández-Acosta NC, González-Gómez M, Meyer G | title = Neurons in the white matter of the adult human neocortex | journal = Frontiers in Neuroanatomy | volume = 3 | issue =  | pages = 7 | year = 2009 | pmid = 19543540 | pmc = 2697018 | doi = 10.3389/neuro.05.007.2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;bodyexpr&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Smalheiser NR, Costa E, Guidotti A, Impagnatiello F, Auta J, Lacor P, Kriho V, Pappas GD | title = Expression of reelin in adult mammalian blood, liver, pituitary pars intermedia, and adrenal chromaffin cells | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 97 | issue = 3 | pages = 1281–6 | date = Feb 2000 | pmid = 10655522 | pmc = 15597 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.97.3.1281 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;liver2&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Samama B, Boehm N | title = Reelin immunoreactivity in lymphatics and liver during development and adult life | journal = The Anatomical Record Part A: Discoveries in Molecular, Cellular, and Evolutionary Biology | volume = 285 | issue = 1 | pages = 595–9 | date = Jul 2005 | pmid = 15912522 | doi = 10.1002/ar.a.20202 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Kobold_2002_liver1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Kobold D, Grundmann A, Piscaglia F, Eisenbach C, Neubauer K, Steffgen J, Ramadori G, Knittel T | title = Expression of reelin in hepatic stellate cells and during hepatic tissue repair: a novel marker for the differentiation of HSC from other liver myofibroblasts | journal = Journal of Hepatology | volume = 36 | issue = 5 | pages = 607–13 | date = May 2002 | pmid = 11983443 | doi = 10.1016/S0168-8278(02)00050-8 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17120005&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Pulido JS, Sugaya I, Comstock J, Sugaya K | title = Reelin expression is upregulated following ocular tissue injury | journal = Graefe's Archive for Clinical and Experimental Ophthalmology = Albrecht von Graefes Archiv für Klinische und Experimentelle Ophthalmologie | volume = 245 | issue = 6 | pages = 889–93 | date = Jun 2007 | pmid = 17120005 | doi = 10.1007/s00417-006-0458-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid10980418&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Buchaille R, Couble ML, Magloire H, Bleicher F | title = A substractive PCR-based cDNA library from human odontoblast cells: identification of novel genes expressed in tooth forming cells | journal = Matrix Biology | volume = 19 | issue = 5 | pages = 421–30 | date = Sep 2000 | pmid = 10980418 | doi = 10.1016/S0945-053X(00)00091-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid16831873&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Allard B, Magloire H, Couble ML, Maurin JC, Bleicher F | title = Voltage-gated sodium channels confer excitability to human odontoblasts: possible role in tooth pain transmission | journal = The Journal of Biological Chemistry | volume = 281 | issue = 39 | pages = 29002–10 | date = Sep 2006 | pmid = 16831873 | doi = 10.1074/jbc.M601020200 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15464360&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Maurin JC, Couble ML, Didier-Bazes M, Brisson C, Magloire H, Bleicher F | title = Expression and localization of reelin in human odontoblasts | journal = Matrix Biology | volume = 23 | issue = 5 | pages = 277–85 | date = Aug 2004 | pmid = 15464360 | doi = 10.1016/j.matbio.2004.06.005 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17548821&quot;&gt;{{PDB|2E26}}; {{cite journal | vauthors = Yasui N, Nogi T, Kitao T, Nakano Y, Hattori M, Takagi J | title = Structure of a receptor-binding fragment of reelin and mutational analysis reveal a recognition mechanism similar to endocytic receptors | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 104 | issue = 24 | pages = 9988–93 | date = Jun 2007 | pmid = 17548821 | pmc = 1891246 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0700438104 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid9417911&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Royaux I, Lambert de Rouvroit C, D'Arcangelo G, Demirov D, Goffinet AM | title = Genomic organization of the mouse reelin gene | journal = Genomics | volume = 46 | issue = 2 | pages = 240–50 | date = Dec 1997 | pmid = 9417911 | doi = 10.1006/geno.1997.4983 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;reelinstructure2006japan&quot;&gt;{{PDB|2ddu}}; {{cite journal | vauthors = Nogi T, Yasui N, Hattori M, Iwasaki K, Takagi J | title = Structure of a signaling-competent reelin fragment revealed by X-ray crystallography and electron tomography | journal = The EMBO Journal | volume = 25 | issue = 15 | pages = 3675–83 | date = Aug 2006 | pmid = 16858396 | pmc = 1538547 | doi = 10.1038/sj.emboj.7601240 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Nakano_2007_CTR_1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Nakano Y, Kohno T, Hibi T, Kohno S, Baba A, Mikoshiba K, Nakajima K, Hattori M | title = The extremely conserved C-terminal region of Reelin is not necessary for secretion but is required for efficient activation of downstream signaling | journal = The Journal of Biological Chemistry | volume = 282 | issue = 28 | pages = 20544–52 | date = Jul 2007 | pmid = 17504759 | doi = 10.1074/jbc.M702300200 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;cleave&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lambert de Rouvroit C, de Bergeyck V, Cortvrindt C, Bar I, Eeckhout Y, Goffinet AM | title = Reelin, the extracellular matrix protein deficient in reeler mutant mice, is processed by a metalloproteinase | journal = Experimental Neurology | volume = 156 | issue = 1 | pages = 214–7 | date = Mar 1999 | pmid = 10192793 | doi = 10.1006/exnr.1998.7007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;centralfragment&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Jossin Y, Ignatova N, Hiesberger T, Herz J, Lambert de Rouvroit C, Goffinet AM | title = The central fragment of Reelin, generated by proteolytic processing in vivo, is critical to its function during cortical plate development | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 24 | issue = 2 | pages = 514–21 | date = Jan 2004 | pmid = 14724251 | doi = 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3408-03.2004 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17442808&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Jossin Y, Gui L, Goffinet AM | title = Processing of Reelin by embryonic neurons is important for function in tissue but not in dissociated cultured neurons | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 27 | issue = 16 | pages = 4243–52 | date = Apr 2007 | pmid = 17442808 | doi = 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0023-07.2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid14614786&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lennington JB, Yang Z, Conover JC | title = Neural stem cells and the regulation of adult neurogenesis | journal = Reproductive Biology and Endocrinology | volume = 1 | issue =  | pages = 99 | date = Nov 2003 | pmid = 14614786 | pmc = 293430 | doi = 10.1186/1477-7827-1-99 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid12925587&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hartfuss E, Förster E, Bock HH, Hack MA, Leprince P, Luque JM, Herz J, Frotscher M, Götz M | title = Reelin signaling directly affects radial glia morphology and biochemical maturation | journal = Development | volume = 130 | issue = 19 | pages = 4597–609 | date = Oct 2003 | pmid = 12925587 | doi = 10.1242/dev.00654 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18197264&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Nomura T, Takahashi M, Hara Y, Osumi N | title = Patterns of neurogenesis and amplitude of Reelin expression are essential for making a mammalian-type cortex | journal = PLOS ONE | volume = 3 | issue = 1 | pages = e1454 | year = 2008 | pmid = 18197264 | pmc = 2175532 | doi = 10.1371/journal.pone.0001454 | editor1-last = Reh | editor1-first = Thomas }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;DerRio1997&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Del Río JA, Heimrich B, Borrell V, Förster E, Drakew A, Alcántara S, Nakajima K, Miyata T, Ogawa M, Mikoshiba K, Derer P, Frotscher M, Soriano E | title = A role for Cajal-Retzius cells and reelin in the development of hippocampal connections | journal = Nature | volume = 385 | issue = 6611 | pages = 70–4 | date = Jan 1997 | pmid = 8985248 | doi = 10.1038/385070a0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Borrell1999&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Borrell V, Del Río JA, Alcántara S, Derer M, Martínez A, D'Arcangelo G, Nakajima K, Mikoshiba K, Derer P, Curran T, Soriano E | title = Reelin regulates the development and synaptogenesis of the layer-specific entorhino-hippocampal connections | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 19 | issue = 4 | pages = 1345–58 | date = Feb 1999 | pmid = 9952412 | doi =  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid16410414&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Yoshida M, Assimacopoulos S, Jones KR, Grove EA | title = Massive loss of Cajal-Retzius cells does not disrupt neocortical layer order | journal = Development | volume = 133 | issue = 3 | pages = 537–45 | date = Feb 2006 | pmid = 16410414 | doi = 10.1242/dev.02209 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19412957&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Yip YP, Mehta N, Magdaleno S, Curran T, Yip JW | title = Ectopic expression of reelin alters migration of sympathetic preganglionic neurons in the spinal cord | journal = The Journal of Comparative Neurology | volume = 515 | issue = 2 | pages = 260–8 | date = Jul 2009 | pmid = 19412957 | doi = 10.1002/cne.22044 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;roleofreelin1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hack I, Bancila M, Loulier K, Carroll P, Cremer H | title = Reelin is a detachment signal in tangential chain-migration during postnatal neurogenesis | journal = Nature Neuroscience | volume = 5 | issue = 10 | pages = 939–45 | date = Oct 2002 | pmid = 12244323 | doi = 10.1038/nn923 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17494763&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Andrade N, Komnenovic V, Blake SM, Jossin Y, Howell B, Goffinet A, Schneider WJ, Nimpf J | title = ApoER2/VLDL receptor and Dab1 in the rostral migratory stream function in postnatal neuronal migration independently of Reelin | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 104 | issue = 20 | pages = 8508–13 | date = May 2007 | pmid = 17494763 | pmc = 1895980 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0611391104 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18946489&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Blake SM, Strasser V, Andrade N, Duit S, Hofbauer R, Schneider WJ, Nimpf J | title = Thrombospondin-1 binds to ApoER2 and VLDL receptor and functions in postnatal neuronal migration | journal = The EMBO Journal | volume = 27 | issue = 22 | pages = 3069–80 | date = Nov 2008 | pmid = 18946489 | pmc = 2585172 | doi = 10.1038/emboj.2008.223 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;dentate_gyrus&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Frotscher M, Haas CA, Förster E | title = Reelin controls granule cell migration in the dentate gyrus by acting on the radial glial scaffold | journal = Cerebral Cortex | volume = 13 | issue = 6 | pages = 634–40 | date = Jun 2003 | pmid = 12764039 | doi = 10.1093/cercor/13.6.634 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;OlivierManzoni&quot;&gt;[http://www.inb.u-bordeaux2.fr/siteneuro2/pages/UniteINB/Manzoni/Manzoniavenir.htm INSERM – Olivier Manzoni – Physiopathology of Synaptic Transmission and Plasticity] – Bordo neuroscience institute.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15987942&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Sinagra M, Verrier D, Frankova D, Korwek KM, Blahos J, Weeber EJ, Manzoni OJ, Chavis P | title = Reelin, very-low-density lipoprotein receptor, and apolipoprotein E receptor 2 control somatic NMDA receptor composition during hippocampal maturation in vitro | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 25 | issue = 26 | pages = 6127–36 | date = Jun 2005 | pmid = 15987942 | doi = 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1757-05.2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17881522&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Groc L, Choquet D, Stephenson FA, Verrier D, Manzoni OJ, Chavis P | title = NMDA receptor surface trafficking and synaptic subunit composition are developmentally regulated by the extracellular matrix protein Reelin | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 27 | issue = 38 | pages = 10165–75 | date = Sep 2007 | pmid = 17881522 | doi = 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1772-07.2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15470155&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Liu XB, Murray KD, Jones EG | title = Switching of NMDA receptor 2A and 2B subunits at thalamic and cortical synapses during early postnatal development | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 24 | issue = 40 | pages = 8885–95 | date = Oct 2004 | pmid = 15470155 | doi = 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2476-04.2004 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19430527&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Campo CG, Sinagra M, Verrier D, Manzoni OJ, Chavis P | title = Reelin secreted by GABAergic neurons regulates glutamate receptor homeostasis | journal = PLOS ONE | volume = 4 | issue = 5 | pages = e5505 | year = 2009 | pmid = 19430527 | pmc = 2675077 | doi = 10.1371/journal.pone.0005505 | editor1-last = Okazawa | editor1-first = Hitoshi }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid11137154&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Bar I, Lambert de Rouvroit C, Goffinet AM | title = The evolution of cortical development. An hypothesis based on the role of the Reelin signaling pathway | journal = Trends in Neurosciences | volume = 23 | issue = 12 | pages = 633–8 | date = Dec 2000 | pmid = 11137154 | doi = 10.1016/S0166-2236(00)01675-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid16519657&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Molnár Z, Métin C, Stoykova A, Tarabykin V, Price DJ, Francis F, Meyer G, Dehay C, Kennedy H | title = Comparative aspects of cerebral cortical development | journal = The European Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 23 | issue = 4 | pages = 921–34 | date = Feb 2006 | pmid = 16519657 | pmc = 1931431 | doi = 10.1111/j.1460-9568.2006.04611.x }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid12124768&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Costagli A, Kapsimali M, Wilson SW, Mione M | title = Conserved and divergent patterns of Reelin expression in the zebrafish central nervous system | journal = The Journal of Comparative Neurology | volume = 450 | issue = 1 | pages = 73–93 | date = Aug 2002 | pmid = 12124768 | doi = 10.1002/cne.10292 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid11173219&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Pérez-García CG, González-Delgado FJ, Suárez-Solá ML, Castro-Fuentes R, Martín-Trujillo JM, Ferres-Torres R, Meyer G | title = Reelin-immunoreactive neurons in the adult vertebrate pallium | journal = Journal of Chemical Neuroanatomy | volume = 21 | issue = 1 | pages = 41–51 | date = Jan 2001 | pmid = 11173219 | doi = 10.1016/S0891-0618(00)00104-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17132178&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Goffinet AM | title = What makes us human? A biased view from the perspective of comparative embryology and mouse genetics | journal = Journal of Biomedical Discovery and Collaboration | volume = 1 | issue =  | pages = 16 | year = 2006 | pmid = 17132178 | pmc = 1769396 | doi = 10.1186/1747-5333-1-16 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid16915236&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Pollard KS, Salama SR, Lambert N, Lambot MA, Coppens S, Pedersen JS, Katzman S, King B, Onodera C, Siepel A, Kern AD, Dehay C, Igel H, Ares M, Vanderhaeghen P, Haussler D | title = An RNA gene expressed during cortical development evolved rapidly in humans | journal = Nature | volume = 443 | issue = 7108 | pages = 167–72 | date = Sep 2006 | pmid = 16915236 | doi = 10.1038/nature05113 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17542651&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Williamson SH, Hubisz MJ, Clark AG, Payseur BA, Bustamante CD, Nielsen R | title = Localizing recent adaptive evolution in the human genome | journal = PLoS Genetics | volume = 3 | issue = 6 | pages = e90 | date = Jun 2007 | pmid = 17542651 | pmc = 1885279 | doi = 10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT1&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/26/science/26human.html?pagewanted=1 | title = Humans Have Spread Globally, and Evolved Locally | author = Wade N | date = 2007-06-26 | publisher = New York Times | accessdate = 2008-08-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;integrin&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Schmid RS, Jo R, Shelton S, Kreidberg JA, Anton ES | title = Reelin, integrin and DAB1 interactions during embryonic cerebral cortical development | journal = Cerebral Cortex | volume = 15 | issue = 10 | pages = 1632–6 | date = Oct 2005 | pmid = 15703255 | doi = 10.1093/cercor/bhi041 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;cadherin&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Senzaki K, Ogawa M, Yagi T | title = Proteins of the CNR family are multiple receptors for Reelin | journal = Cell | volume = 99 | issue = 6 | pages = 635–47 | date = Dec 1999 | pmid = 10612399 | doi = 10.1016/S0092-8674(00)81552-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18077697&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Belvindrah R, Graus-Porta D, Goebbels S, Nave KA, Müller U | title = Beta1 integrins in radial glia but not in migrating neurons are essential for the formation of cell layers in the cerebral cortex | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 27 | issue = 50 | pages = 13854–65 | date = Dec 2007 | pmid = 18077697 | doi = 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4494-07.2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid9009273&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Howell BW, Gertler FB, Cooper JA | title = Mouse disabled (mDab1): a Src binding protein implicated in neuronal development | journal = The EMBO Journal | volume = 16 | issue = 1 | pages = 121–32 | date = Jan 1997 | pmid = 9009273 | pmc = 1169619 | doi = 10.1093/emboj/16.1.121 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid12526739&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Arnaud L, Ballif BA, Förster E, Cooper JA | title = Fyn tyrosine kinase is a critical regulator of disabled-1 during brain development | journal = Current Biology | volume = 13 | issue = 1 | pages = 9–17 | date = Jan 2003 | pmid = 12526739 | doi = 10.1016/S0960-9822(02)01397-0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17974915&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Feng L, Allen NS, Simo S, Cooper JA | title = Cullin 5 regulates Dab1 protein levels and neuron positioning during cortical development | journal = Genes &amp; Development | volume = 21 | issue = 21 | pages = 2717–30 | date = Nov 2007 | pmid = 17974915 | pmc = 2045127 | doi = 10.1101/gad.1604207 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18006681&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Kerjan G, Gleeson JG | title = A missed exit: Reelin sets in motion Dab1 polyubiquitination to put the break on neuronal migration | journal = Genes &amp; Development | volume = 21 | issue = 22 | pages = 2850–4 | date = Nov 2007 | pmid = 18006681 | doi = 10.1101/gad.1622907 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Zhang_2007_Pafah1b&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zhang G, Assadi AH, McNeil RS, Beffert U, Wynshaw-Boris A, Herz J, Clark GD, D'Arcangelo G | title = The Pafah1b complex interacts with the reelin receptor VLDLR | journal = PLOS ONE | volume = 2 | issue = 2 | pages = e252 | year = 2007 | pmid = 17330141 | pmc = 1800349 | doi = 10.1371/journal.pone.0000252 | editor1-last = Mueller | editor1-first = Ulrich }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17913789&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hack I, Hellwig S, Junghans D, Brunne B, Bock HH, Zhao S, Frotscher M | title = Divergent roles of ApoER2 and Vldlr in the migration of cortical neurons | journal = Development | volume = 134 | issue = 21 | pages = 3883–91 | date = Nov 2007 | pmid = 17913789 | doi = 10.1242/dev.005447 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;hugecomplex&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Utsunomiya-Tate N, Kubo K, Tate S, Kainosho M, Katayama E, Nakajima K, Mikoshiba K | title = Reelin molecules assemble together to form a large protein complex, which is inhibited by the function-blocking CR-50 antibody | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 97 | issue = 17 | pages = 9729–34 | date = Aug 2000 | pmid = 10920200 | pmc = 16933 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.160272497 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;complex&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Kubo K, Mikoshiba K, Nakajima K | title = Secreted Reelin molecules form homodimers | journal = Neuroscience Research | volume = 43 | issue = 4 | pages = 381–8 | date = Aug 2002 | pmid = 12135781 | doi = 10.1016/S0168-0102(02)00068-8 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid14729980&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Strasser V, Fasching D, Hauser C, Mayer H, Bock HH, Hiesberger T, Herz J, Weeber EJ, Sweatt JD, Pramatarova A, Howell B, Schneider WJ, Nimpf J | title = Receptor clustering is involved in Reelin signaling | journal = Molecular and Cellular Biology | volume = 24 | issue = 3 | pages = 1378–86 | date = Feb 2004 | pmid = 14729980 | pmc = 321426 | doi = 10.1128/MCB.24.3.1378-1386.2004 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid11689558&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Quattrocchi CC, Wannenes F, Persico AM, Ciafré SA, D'Arcangelo G, Farace MG, Keller F | title = Reelin is a serine protease of the extracellular matrix | journal = The Journal of Biological Chemistry | volume = 277 | issue = 1 | pages = 303–9 | date = Jan 2002 | pmid = 11689558 | doi = 10.1074/jbc.M106996200 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Reelin_ApoER2_Exon19_2005_Beffert&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Beffert U, Weeber EJ, Durudas A, Qiu S, Masiulis I, Sweatt JD, Li WP, Adelmann G, Frotscher M, Hammer RE, Herz J | title = Modulation of synaptic plasticity and memory by Reelin involves differential splicing of the lipoprotein receptor Apoer2 | journal = Neuron | volume = 47 | issue = 4 | pages = 567–79 | date = Aug 2005 | pmid = 16102539 | doi = 10.1016/j.neuron.2005.07.007 | url = http://jax.herzlab.org/Course2006/presentations/Beffert2005.pdf | format = PDF }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17359920&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Miller CA, Sweatt JD | title = Covalent modification of DNA regulates memory formation | journal = Neuron | volume = 53 | issue = 6 | pages = 857–69 | date = Mar 2007 | pmid = 17359920 | doi = 10.1016/j.neuron.2007.02.022 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18477607&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Matsuki T, Pramatarova A, Howell BW | title = Reduction of Crk and CrkL expression blocks reelin-induced dendritogenesis | journal = Journal of Cell Science | volume = 121 | issue = 11 | pages = 1869–75 | date = Jun 2008 | pmid = 18477607 | pmc = 2430739 | doi = 10.1242/jcs.027334 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15062102&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ballif BA, Arnaud L, Arthur WT, Guris D, Imamoto A, Cooper JA | title = Activation of a Dab1/CrkL/C3G/Rap1 pathway in Reelin-stimulated neurons | journal = Current Biology | volume = 14 | issue = 7 | pages = 606–10 | date = Apr 2004 | pmid = 15062102 | doi = 10.1016/j.cub.2004.03.038 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19074029&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Park TJ, Curran T | title = Crk and Crk-like play essential overlapping roles downstream of disabled-1 in the Reelin pathway | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 28 | issue = 50 | pages = 13551–62 | date = Dec 2008 | pmid = 19074029 | pmc = 2628718 | doi = 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4323-08.2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18593473&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Keilani S, Sugaya K | title = Reelin induces a radial glial phenotype in human neural progenitor cells by activation of Notch-1 | journal = BMC Developmental Biology | volume = 8 | issue = 1 | pages = 69 | date = July 2008 | pmid = 18593473 | pmc = 2447831 | doi = 10.1186/1471-213X-8-69 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid12959647&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lugli G, Krueger JM, Davis JM, Persico AM, Keller F, Smalheiser NR | title = Methodological factors influencing measurement and processing of plasma reelin in humans | journal = BMC Biochemistry | volume = 4 | issue =  | pages = 9 | date = Sep 2003 | pmid = 12959647 | pmc = 200967 | doi = 10.1186/1471-2091-4-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19303411&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hibi T, Hattori M | title = The N-terminal fragment of Reelin is generated after endocytosis and released through the pathway regulated by Rab11 | journal = FEBS Letters | volume = 583 | issue = 8 | pages = 1299–303 | date = Apr 2009 | pmid = 19303411 | doi = 10.1016/j.febslet.2009.03.024 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19366679&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Chameau P, Inta D, Vitalis T, Monyer H, Wadman WJ, van Hooft JA | title = The N-terminal region of reelin regulates postnatal dendritic maturation of cortical pyramidal neurons | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 106 | issue = 17 | pages = 7227–32 | date = Apr 2009 | pmid = 19366679 | pmc = 2678467 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0810764106 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19129405&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Chai X, Förster E, Zhao S, Bock HH, Frotscher M | title = Reelin stabilizes the actin cytoskeleton of neuronal processes by inducing n-cofilin phosphorylation at serine3 | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 29 | issue = 1 | pages = 288–99 | date = Jan 2009 | pmid = 19129405 | doi = 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2934-08.2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19396394&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Frotscher M, Chai X, Bock HH, Haas CA, Förster E, Zhao S | title = Role of Reelin in the development and maintenance of cortical lamination | journal = Journal of Neural Transmission | volume = 116 | issue = 11 | pages = 1451–5 | date = Nov 2009 | pmid = 19396394 | doi = 10.1007/s00702-009-0228-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid14645539&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Arnaud L, Ballif BA, Cooper JA | title = Regulation of protein tyrosine kinase signaling by substrate degradation during brain development | journal = Molecular and Cellular Biology | volume = 23 | issue = 24 | pages = 9293–302 | date = Dec 2003 | pmid = 14645539 | pmc = 309695 | doi = 10.1128/MCB.23.24.9293-9302.2003 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid16529723&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ohshima T, Suzuki H, Morimura T, Ogawa M, Mikoshiba K | title = Modulation of Reelin signaling by Cyclin-dependent kinase 5 | journal = Brain Research | volume = 1140 | issue =  | pages = 84–95 | date = Apr 2007 | pmid = 16529723 | doi = 10.1016/j.brainres.2006.01.121 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid12077184&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Keshvara L, Magdaleno S, Benhayon D, Curran T | title = Cyclin-dependent kinase 5 phosphorylates disabled 1 independently of Reelin signaling | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 22 | issue = 12 | pages = 4869–77 | date = Jun 2002 | pmid = 12077184 | doi =  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid8253190&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Kobayashi S, Ishiguro K, Omori A, Takamatsu M, Arioka M, Imahori K, Uchida T | title = A cdc2-related kinase PSSALRE/cdk5 is homologous with the 30 kDa subunit of tau protein kinase II, a proline-directed protein kinase associated with microtubule | journal = FEBS Letters | volume = 335 | issue = 2 | pages = 171–5 | date = Dec 1993 | pmid = 8253190 | doi = 10.1016/0014-5793(93)80723-8 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid12376533&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Beffert U, Morfini G, Bock HH, Reyna H, Brady ST, Herz J | title = Reelin-mediated signaling locally regulates protein kinase B/Akt and glycogen synthase kinase 3beta | journal = The Journal of Biological Chemistry | volume = 277 | issue = 51 | pages = 49958–64 | date = Dec 2002 | pmid = 12376533 | doi = 10.1074/jbc.M209205200 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid11163259&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Sasaki S, Shionoya A, Ishida M, Gambello MJ, Yingling J, Wynshaw-Boris A, Hirotsune S | title = A LIS1/NUDEL/cytoplasmic dynein heavy chain complex in the developing and adult nervous system | journal = Neuron | volume = 28 | issue = 3 | pages = 681–96 | date = Dec 2000 | pmid = 11163259 | doi = 10.1016/S0896-6273(00)00146-X }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid14985430&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Beffert U, Weeber EJ, Morfini G, Ko J, Brady ST, Tsai LH, Sweatt JD, Herz J | title = Reelin and cyclin-dependent kinase 5-dependent signals cooperate in regulating neuronal migration and synaptic transmission | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 24 | issue = 8 | pages = 1897–906 | date = Feb 2004 | pmid = 14985430 | doi = 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4084-03.2004 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid11226314&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ohshima T, Ogawa M, Hirasawa M, Longenecker G, Ishiguro K, Pant HC, Brady RO, Kulkarni AB, Mikoshiba K | title = Synergistic contributions of cyclin-dependant kinase 5/p35 and Reelin/Dab1 to the positioning of cortical neurons in the developing mouse brain | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 98 | issue = 5 | pages = 2764–9 | date = Feb 2001 | pmid = 11226314 | pmc = 30213 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.051628498 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;liss2000&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hong SE, Shugart YY, Huang DT, Shahwan SA, Grant PE, Hourihane JO, Martin ND, Walsh CA | title = Autosomal recessive lissencephaly with cerebellar hypoplasia is associated with human RELN mutations | journal = Nature Genetics | volume = 26 | issue = 1 | pages = 93–6 | date = Sep 2000 | pmid = 10973257 | doi = 10.1038/79246 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;liss2001&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Crino P | title = New RELN Mutation Associated with Lissencephaly and Epilepsy | journal = Epilepsy Currents / American Epilepsy Society | volume = 1 | issue = 2 | pages = 72 | date = Nov 2001 | pmid = 15309195 | pmc = 320825 | doi = 10.1046/j.1535-7597.2001.00017.x }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17431900&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zaki M, Shehab M, El-Aleem AA, Abdel-Salam G, Koeller HB, Ilkin Y, Ross ME, Dobyns WB, Gleeson JG | title = Identification of a novel recessive RELN mutation using a homozygous balanced reciprocal translocation | journal = American Journal of Medical Genetics Part A | volume = 143A | issue = 9 | pages = 939–44 | date = May 2007 | pmid = 17431900 | doi = 10.1002/ajmg.a.31667 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;szproof1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Impagnatiello F, Guidotti AR, Pesold C, Dwivedi Y, Caruncho H, Pisu MG, Uzunov DP, Smalheiser NR, Davis JM, Pandey GN, Pappas GD, Tueting P, Sharma RP, Costa E | title = A decrease of reelin expression as a putative vulnerability factor in schizophrenia | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 95 | issue = 26 | pages = 15718–23 | date = Dec 1998 | pmid = 9861036 | pmc = 28110 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.95.26.15718 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;szproof2&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Guidotti A, Auta J, Davis JM, Di-Giorgi-Gerevini V, Dwivedi Y, Grayson DR, Impagnatiello F, Pandey G, Pesold C, Sharma R, Uzunov D, Costa E, DiGiorgi Gerevini V | title = Decrease in reelin and glutamic acid decarboxylase67 (GAD67) expression in schizophrenia and bipolar disorder: a postmortem brain study | journal = Archives of General Psychiatry | volume = 57 | issue = 11 | pages = 1061–9 | date = Nov 2000 | pmid = 11074872 | doi = 10.1001/archpsyc.57.11.1061 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;szconfirm1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Fatemi SH, Earle JA, McMenomy T | title = Reduction in Reelin immunoreactivity in hippocampus of subjects with schizophrenia, bipolar disorder and major depression | journal = Molecular Psychiatry | volume = 5 | issue = 6 | pages = 654–63, 571 | date = Nov 2000 | pmid = 11126396 | doi = 10.1038/sj.mp.4000783 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;BDP_basal_ganglia_2007&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Veldic M, Kadriu B, Maloku E, Agis-Balboa RC, Guidotti A, Davis JM, Costa E | title = Epigenetic mechanisms expressed in basal ganglia GABAergic neurons differentiate schizophrenia from bipolar disorder | journal = Schizophrenia Research | volume = 91 | issue = 1-3 | pages = 51–61 | date = Mar 2007 | pmid = 17270400 | pmc = 1876737 | doi = 10.1016/j.schres.2006.11.029 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;szconfirm2&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Eastwood SL, Harrison PJ | title = Interstitial white matter neurons express less reelin and are abnormally distributed in schizophrenia: towards an integration of molecular and morphologic aspects of the neurodevelopmental hypothesis | journal = Molecular Psychiatry | volume = 8 | issue = 9 | pages = 769, 821–31 | date = Sep 2003 | pmid = 12931209 | doi = 10.1038/sj.mp.4001371 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;szconfirm3&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Abdolmaleky HM, Cheng KH, Russo A, Smith CL, Faraone SV, Wilcox M, Shafa R, Glatt SJ, Nguyen G, Ponte JF, Thiagalingam S, Tsuang MT | title = Hypermethylation of the reelin (RELN) promoter in the brain of schizophrenic patients: a preliminary report | journal = American Journal of Medical Genetics Part B | volume = 134B | issue = 1 | pages = 60–6 | date = Apr 2005 | pmid = 15717292 | doi = 10.1002/ajmg.b.30140 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15560956&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Fatemi SH, Hossein Fatemi S, Stary JM, Earle JA, Araghi-Niknam M, Eagan E | title = GABAergic dysfunction in schizophrenia and mood disorders as reflected by decreased levels of glutamic acid decarboxylase 65 and 67 kDa and Reelin proteins in cerebellum | journal = Schizophrenia Research | volume = 72 | issue = 2-3 | pages = 109–22 | date = Jan 2005 | pmid = 15560956 | doi = 10.1016/j.schres.2004.02.017 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;fatemi_blood_reelin&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Fatemi SH, Kroll JL, Stary JM | title = Altered levels of Reelin and its isoforms in schizophrenia and mood disorders | journal = NeuroReport | volume = 12 | issue = 15 | pages = 3209–15 | date = Oct 2001 | pmid = 11711858 | doi = 10.1097/00001756-200110290-00014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Knable_2001&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Knable MB, Torrey EF, Webster MJ, Bartko JJ | title = Multivariate analysis of prefrontal cortical data from the Stanley Foundation Neuropathology Consortium | journal = Brain Research Bulletin | volume = 55 | issue = 5 | pages = 651–9 | date = Jul 2001 | pmid = 11576762 | doi = 10.1016/S0361-9230(01)00521-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;hypermeth&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Grayson DR, Jia X, Chen Y, Sharma RP, Mitchell CP, Guidotti A, Costa E | title = Reelin promoter hypermethylation in schizophrenia | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 102 | issue = 26 | pages = 9341–6 | date = Jun 2005 | pmid = 15961543 | pmc = 1166626 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0503736102 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;dong&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Dong E, Agis-Balboa RC, Simonini MV, Grayson DR, Costa E, Guidotti A | title = Reelin and glutamic acid decarboxylase67 promoter remodeling in an epigenetic methionine-induced mouse model of schizophrenia | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 102 | issue = 35 | pages = 12578–83 | date = Aug 2005 | pmid = 16113080 | pmc = 1194936 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0505394102 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;methionine1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Pollin W, Cardon PV, Kety SS | title = Effects of amino acid feedings in schizophrenic patients treated with iproniazid | journal = Science | volume = 133 | issue = 3446 | pages = 104–5 | date = Jan 1961 | pmid = 13736870 | doi = 10.1126/science.133.3446.104 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;methionine2&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Brune GG, Himwich HE | title = Effects of methionine loading on the behavior of schizophrenic patients | journal = The Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease | volume = 134 | issue = 5 | pages = 447–50 | date = May 1962 | pmid = 13873983 | doi = 10.1097/00005053-196205000-00007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;methionine3&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Park LC, Baldessarini RJ, Kety SS | title = METHIONINE EFFECTS ON CHRONIC SCHIZOPHRENICS: PATIENTS TREATED WITH MONOAMINE OXIDASE INHIBITORS | journal = Archives of General Psychiatry | volume = 12 | issue = 4 | pages = 346–51 | date = Apr 1965 | pmid = 14258360 | doi = 10.1001/archpsyc.1965.01720340018003 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;methionine4&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Antun FT, Burnett GB, Cooper AJ, Daly RJ, Smythies JR, Zealley AK | title = The effects of L-methionine (without MAOI) in schizophrenia | journal = Journal of Psychiatric Research | volume = 8 | issue = 2 | pages = 63–71 | date = Jun 1971 | pmid = 4932991 | doi = 10.1016/0022-3956(71)90009-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;epigenetic2007&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ruzicka WB, Zhubi A, Veldic M, Grayson DR, Costa E, Guidotti A | title = Selective epigenetic alteration of layer I GABAergic neurons isolated from prefrontal cortex of schizophrenia patients using laser-assisted microdissection | journal = Molecular Psychiatry | volume = 12 | issue = 4 | pages = 385–97 | date = Apr 2007 | pmid = 17264840 | doi = 10.1038/sj.mp.4001954 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;DNMT_inhibition_GAD67_Reelin_2004&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Veldic M, Caruncho HJ, Liu WS, Davis J, Satta R, Grayson DR, Guidotti A, Costa E | title = DNA-methyltransferase 1 mRNA is selectively overexpressed in telencephalic GABAergic interneurons of schizophrenia brains | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 101 | issue = 1 | pages = 348–53 | date = Jan 2004 | pmid = 14684836 | pmc = 314188 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.2637013100 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15684088&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Veldic M, Guidotti A, Maloku E, Davis JM, Costa E | title = In psychosis, cortical interneurons overexpress DNA-methyltransferase 1 | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 102 | issue = 6 | pages = 2152–7 | date = Feb 2005 | pmid = 15684088 | pmc = 548582 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0409665102 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;valpro&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Tremolizzo L, Doueiri MS, Dong E, Grayson DR, Davis J, Pinna G, Tueting P, Rodriguez-Menendez V, Costa E, Guidotti A | title = Valproate corrects the schizophrenia-like epigenetic behavioral modifications induced by methionine in mice | journal = Biological Psychiatry | volume = 57 | issue = 5 | pages = 500–9 | date = Mar 2005 | pmid = 15737665 | doi = 10.1016/j.biopsych.2004.11.046 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;valproicreelin&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Chen Y, Sharma RP, Costa RH, Costa E, Grayson DR | title = On the epigenetic regulation of the human reelin promoter | journal = Nucleic Acids Research | volume = 30 | issue = 13 | pages = 2930–9 | date = Jul 2002 | pmid = 12087179 | pmc = 117056 | doi = 10.1093/nar/gkf401 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Mitchell&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Mitchell CP, Chen Y, Kundakovic M, Costa E, Grayson DR | title = Histone deacetylase inhibitors decrease reelin promoter methylation in vitro | journal = Journal of Neurochemistry | volume = 93 | issue = 2 | pages = 483–92 | date = Apr 2005 | pmid = 15816871 | doi = 10.1111/j.1471-4159.2005.03040.x }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;l-meth&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Tremolizzo L, Carboni G, Ruzicka WB, Mitchell CP, Sugaya I, Tueting P, Sharma R, Grayson DR, Costa E, Guidotti A | title = An epigenetic mouse model for molecular and behavioral neuropathologies related to schizophrenia vulnerability | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 99 | issue = 26 | pages = 17095–100 | date = Dec 2002 | pmid = 12481028 | pmc = 139275 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.262658999 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17553960&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Benes FM, Lim B, Matzilevich D, Walsh JP, Subburaju S, Minns M | title = Regulation of the GABA cell phenotype in hippocampus of schizophrenics and bipolars | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 104 | issue = 24 | pages = 10164–9 | date = Jun 2007 | pmid = 17553960 | pmc = 1888575 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0703806104 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Dong_2007&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Dong E, Guidotti A, Grayson DR, Costa E | title = Histone hyperacetylation induces demethylation of reelin and 67-kDa glutamic acid decarboxylase promoters | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 104 | issue = 11 | pages = 4676–81 | date = Mar 2007 | pmid = 17360583 | pmc = 1815468 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0700529104 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;DNMT_inhibition_GAD67_Reelin_2006&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Kundakovic M, Chen Y, Costa E, Grayson DR | title = DNA methyltransferase inhibitors coordinately induce expression of the human reelin and glutamic acid decarboxylase 67 genes | journal = Molecular Pharmacology | volume = 71 | issue = 3 | pages = 644–53 | date = Mar 2007 | pmid = 17065238 | doi = 10.1124/mol.106.030635 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19029285&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Kundakovic M, Chen Y, Guidotti A, Grayson DR | title = The reelin and GAD67 promoters are activated by epigenetic drugs that facilitate the disruption of local repressor complexes | journal = Molecular Pharmacology | volume = 75 | issue = 2 | pages = 342–54 | date = Feb 2009 | pmid = 19029285 | pmc = 2684898 | doi = 10.1124/mol.108.051763 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;SAM_and_DNMT1_psychosis_2007&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Guidotti A, Ruzicka W, Grayson DR, Veldic M, Pinna G, Davis JM, Costa E | title = S-adenosyl methionine and DNA methyltransferase-1 mRNA overexpression in psychosis | journal = NeuroReport | volume = 18 | issue = 1 | pages = 57–60 | date = Jan 2007 | pmid = 17259861 | doi = 10.1097/WNR.0b013e32800fefd7 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;influenza1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Fatemi SH, Emamian ES, Kist D, Sidwell RW, Nakajima K, Akhter P, Shier A, Sheikh S, Bailey K | title = Defective corticogenesis and reduction in Reelin immunoreactivity in cortex and hippocampus of prenatally infected neonatal mice | journal = Molecular Psychiatry | volume = 4 | issue = 2 | pages = 145–54 | date = Mar 1999 | pmid = 10208446 | doi = 10.1038/sj.mp.4000520 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18023140&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Meyer U, Nyffeler M, Yee BK, Knuesel I, Feldon J | title = Adult brain and behavioral pathological markers of prenatal immune challenge during early/middle and late fetal development in mice | journal = Brain, Behavior, and Immunity | volume = 22 | issue = 4 | pages = 469–86 | date = May 2008 | pmid = 18023140 | doi = 10.1016/j.bbi.2007.09.012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17684500&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Wedenoja J, Loukola A, Tuulio-Henriksson A, Paunio T, Ekelund J, Silander K, Varilo T, Heikkilä K, Suvisaari J, Partonen T, Lönnqvist J, Peltonen L | title = Replication of linkage on chromosome 7q22 and association of the regional Reelin gene with working memory in schizophrenia families | journal = Molecular Psychiatry | volume = 13 | issue = 7 | pages = 673–84 | date = Jul 2008 | pmid = 17684500 | doi = 10.1038/sj.mp.4002047 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18282107&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Shifman S, Johannesson M, Bronstein M, Chen SX, Collier DA, Craddock NJ, Kendler KS, Li T, O'Donovan M, O'Neill FA, Owen MJ, Walsh D, Weinberger DR, Sun C, Flint J, Darvasi A | title = Genome-wide association identifies a common variant in the reelin gene that increases the risk of schizophrenia only in women | journal = PLoS Genetics | volume = 4 | issue = 2 | pages = e28 | date = Feb 2008 | pmid = 18282107 | pmc = 2242812 | doi = 10.1371/journal.pgen.0040028 }} [http://genetics.plosjournals.org/perlserv/?request=get-document&amp;doi=10.1371/journal.pgen.0040028 free full text]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19054571&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Gregório SP, Sallet PC, Do KA, Lin E, Gattaz WF, Dias-Neto E | title = Polymorphisms in genes involved in neurodevelopment may be associated with altered brain morphology in schizophrenia: preliminary evidence | journal = Psychiatry Research | volume = 165 | issue = 1-2 | pages = 1–9 | date = Jan 2009 | pmid = 19054571 | doi = 10.1016/j.psychres.2007.08.011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17936586&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Suzuki K, Nakamura K, Iwata Y, Sekine Y, Kawai M, Sugihara G, Tsuchiya KJ, Suda S, Matsuzaki H, Takei N, Hashimoto K, Mori N | title = Decreased expression of reelin receptor VLDLR in peripheral lymphocytes of drug-naive schizophrenic patients | journal = Schizophrenia Research | volume = 98 | issue = 1-3 | pages = 148–56 | date = Jan 2008 | pmid = 17936586 | doi = 10.1016/j.schres.2007.09.029 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18463626&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Sweet RA, Henteleff RA, Zhang W, Sampson AR, Lewis DA | title = Reduced dendritic spine density in auditory cortex of subjects with schizophrenia | journal = Neuropsychopharmacology | volume = 34 | issue = 2 | pages = 374–89 | date = Jan 2009 | pmid = 18463626 | pmc = 2775717 | doi = 10.1038/npp.2008.67 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid10632234&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Glantz LA, Lewis DA | title = Decreased dendritic spine density on prefrontal cortical pyramidal neurons in schizophrenia | journal = Archives of General Psychiatry | volume = 57 | issue = 1 | pages = 65–73 | date = Jan 2000 | pmid = 10632234 | doi = 10.1001/archpsyc.57.1.65 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid10725376&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Rodriguez MA, Pesold C, Liu WS, Kriho V, Guidotti A, Pappas GD, Costa E | title = Colocalization of integrin receptors and reelin in dendritic spine postsynaptic densities of adult nonhuman primate cortex | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 97 | issue = 7 | pages = 3550–5 | date = Mar 2000 | pmid = 10725376 | pmc = 16277 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.050589797 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid11592844&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Costa E, Davis J, Grayson DR, Guidotti A, Pappas GD, Pesold C | title = Dendritic spine hypoplasticity and downregulation of reelin and GABAergic tone in schizophrenia vulnerability | journal = Neurobiology of Disease | volume = 8 | issue = 5 | pages = 723–42 | date = Oct 2001 | pmid = 11592844 | doi = 10.1006/nbdi.2001.0436 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Kamnasaran_2003&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Kamnasaran D, Muir WJ, Ferguson-Smith MA, Cox DW | title = Disruption of the neuronal PAS3 gene in a family affected with schizophrenia | journal = Journal of Medical Genetics | volume = 40 | issue = 5 | pages = 325–32 | date = May 2003 | pmid = 12746393 | pmc = 1735455 | doi = 10.1136/jmg.40.5.325 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Erbel-Sieler_NPAS3_deficient_mice_2004&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Erbel-Sieler C, Dudley C, Zhou Y, Wu X, Estill SJ, Han T, Diaz-Arrastia R, Brunskill EW, Potter SS, McKnight SL | title = Behavioral and regulatory abnormalities in mice deficient in the NPAS1 and NPAS3 transcription factors | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 101 | issue = 37 | pages = 13648–53 | date = Sep 2004 | pmid = 15347806 | pmc = 518807 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0405310101 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15979267&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Chen Z, Schwahn BC, Wu Q, He X, Rozen R | title = Postnatal cerebellar defects in mice deficient in methylenetetrahydrofolate reductase | journal = International Journal of Developmental Neuroscience | volume = 23 | issue = 5 | pages = 465–74 | date = Aug 2005 | pmid = 15979267 | doi = 10.1016/j.ijdevneu.2005.05.007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;GRIN2B_SZ_GENE_DB&quot;&gt;[http://www.schizophreniaforum.org/res/sczgene/geneoverview.asp?geneid=135 Gene Overview of All Published Schizophrenia-Association Studies for GRIN2B] – Schizophrenia Gene Database.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;HRM_shared_abnormalities_with_SZ&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Pappas GD, Kriho V, Pesold C | title = Reelin in the extracellular matrix and dendritic spines of the cortex and hippocampus: a comparison between wild type and heterozygous reeler mice by immunoelectron microscopy | journal = Journal of Neurocytology | volume = 30 | issue = 5 | pages = 413–25 | date = May 2001 | pmid = 11951052 | doi = 10.1023/A:1015017710332 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;HRM_not_SZ&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Podhorna J, Didriksen M | title = The heterozygous reeler mouse: behavioural phenotype | journal = Behavioural Brain Research | volume = 153 | issue = 1 | pages = 43–54 | date = Aug 2004 | pmid = 15219705 | doi = 10.1016/j.bbr.2003.10.033 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;BipWoman09&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Goes FS, Willour VL, Zandi PP, Belmonte PL, MacKinnon DF, Mondimore FM, Schweizer B, DePaulo JR, Gershon ES, McMahon FJ, Potash JB | title = Sex-specific association of the Reelin gene with bipolar disorder | journal = American Journal of Medical Genetics Part B | volume = 153B | issue = 2 | pages = 549–53 | date = Mar 2010 | pmid = 19691043 | pmc = 3032172 | doi = 10.1002/ajmg.b.31018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid11317216&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Persico AM, D'Agruma L, Maiorano N, Totaro A, Militerni R, Bravaccio C, Wassink TH, Schneider C, Melmed R, Trillo S, Montecchi F, Palermo M, Pascucci T, Puglisi-Allegra S, Reichelt KL, Conciatori M, Marino R, Quattrocchi CC, Baldi A, Zelante L, Gasparini P, Keller F | title = Reelin gene alleles and haplotypes as a factor predisposing to autistic disorder | journal = Molecular Psychiatry | volume = 6 | issue = 2 | pages = 150–9 | date = Mar 2001 | pmid = 11317216 | doi = 10.1038/sj.mp.4000850 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid12399956&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zhang H, Liu X, Zhang C, Mundo E, Macciardi F, Grayson DR, Guidotti AR, Holden JJ | title = Reelin gene alleles and susceptibility to autism spectrum disorders | journal = Molecular Psychiatry | volume = 7 | issue = 9 | pages = 1012–7 | year = 2002 | pmid = 12399956 | doi = 10.1038/sj.mp.4001124 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid14515139&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Bonora E, Beyer KS, Lamb JA, Parr JR, Klauck SM, Benner A, Paolucci M, Abbott A, Ragoussis I, Poustka A, Bailey AJ, Monaco AP | title = Analysis of reelin as a candidate gene for autism | journal = Molecular Psychiatry | volume = 8 | issue = 10 | pages = 885–92 | date = Oct 2003 | pmid = 14515139 | doi = 10.1038/sj.mp.4001310 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15048647&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Devlin B, Bennett P, Dawson G, Figlewicz DA, Grigorenko EL, McMahon W, Minshew N, Pauls D, Smith M, Spence MA, Rodier PM, Stodgell C, Schellenberg GD | title = Alleles of a reelin CGG repeat do not convey liability to autism in a sample from the CPEA network | journal = American Journal of Medical Genetics Part B | volume = 126B | issue = 1 | pages = 46–50 | date = Apr 2004 | pmid = 15048647 | doi = 10.1002/ajmg.b.20125 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17919129&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Pardo CA, Eberhart CG | title = The neurobiology of autism | journal = Brain Pathology | volume = 17 | issue = 4 | pages = 434–47 | date = Oct 2007 | pmid = 17919129 | doi = 10.1111/j.1750-3639.2007.00102.x }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;TLE1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Haas CA, Dudeck O, Kirsch M, Huszka C, Kann G, Pollak S, Zentner J, Frotscher M | title = Role for reelin in the development of granule cell dispersion in temporal lobe epilepsy | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 22 | issue = 14 | pages = 5797–802 | date = Jul 2002 | pmid = 12122039 | doi = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;TLE2&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Heinrich C, Nitta N, Flubacher A, Müller M, Fahrner A, Kirsch M, Freiman T, Suzuki F, Depaulis A, Frotscher M, Haas CA | title = Reelin deficiency and displacement of mature neurons, but not neurogenesis, underlie the formation of granule cell dispersion in the epileptic hippocampus | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 26 | issue = 17 | pages = 4701–13 | date = Apr 2006 | pmid = 16641251 | doi = 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5516-05.2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19287316&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Kobow K, Jeske I, Hildebrandt M, Hauke J, Hahnen E, Buslei R, Buchfelder M, Weigel D, Stefan H, Kasper B, Pauli E, Blümcke I | title = Increased reelin promoter methylation is associated with granule cell dispersion in human temporal lobe epilepsy | journal = Journal of Neuropathology and Experimental Neurology | volume = 68 | issue = 4 | pages = 356–64 | date = Apr 2009 | pmid = 19287316 | doi = 10.1097/NEN.0b013e31819ba737 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Gonq_2007&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Gong C, Wang TW, Huang HS, Parent JM | title = Reelin regulates neuronal progenitor migration in intact and epileptic hippocampus | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 27 | issue = 8 | pages = 1803–11 | date = Feb 2007 | pmid = 17314278 | doi = 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3111-06.2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19185570&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Müller MC, Osswald M, Tinnes S, Häussler U, Jacobi A, Förster E, Frotscher M, Haas CA | title = Exogenous reelin prevents granule cell dispersion in experimental epilepsy | journal = Experimental Neurology | volume = 216 | issue = 2 | pages = 390–7 | date = Apr 2009 | pmid = 19185570 | doi = 10.1016/j.expneurol.2008.12.029 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;alz&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Botella-López A, Burgaya F, Gavín R, García-Ayllón MS, Gómez-Tortosa E, Peña-Casanova J, Ureña JM, Del Río JA, Blesa R, Soriano E, Sáez-Valero J | title = Reelin expression and glycosylation patterns are altered in Alzheimer's disease | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 103 | issue = 14 | pages = 5573–8 | date = Apr 2006 | pmid = 16567613 | pmc = 1414634 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0601279103 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;alzmouse&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Wirths O, Multhaup G, Czech C, Blanchard V, Tremp G, Pradier L, Beyreuther K, Bayer TA | title = Reelin in plaques of beta-amyloid precursor protein and presenilin-1 double-transgenic mice | journal = Neuroscience Letters | volume = 316 | issue = 3 | pages = 145–8 | date = Dec 2001 | pmid = 11744223 | doi = 10.1016/S0304-3940(01)02399-0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18599960&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Seripa D, Matera MG, Franceschi M, Daniele A, Bizzarro A, Rinaldi M, Panza F, Fazio VM, Gravina C, D'Onofrio G, Solfrizzi V, Masullo C, Pilotto A | title = The RELN locus in Alzheimer's disease | journal = Journal of Alzheimer's Disease | volume = 14 | issue = 3 | pages = 335–44 | date = Jul 2008 | pmid = 18599960 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid16051543&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Baloyannis SJ | title = Morphological and morphometric alterations of Cajal-Retzius cells in early cases of Alzheimer's disease: a Golgi and electron microscope study | journal = The International Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 115 | issue = 7 | pages = 965–80 | date = Jul 2005 | pmid = 16051543 | doi = 10.1080/00207450590901396 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17453452&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Baloyannis SJ, Costa V, Mauroudis I, Psaroulis D, Manolides SL, Manolides LS | title = Dendritic and spinal pathology in the acoustic cortex in Alzheimer's disease: morphological and morphometric estimation by Golgi technique and electron microscopy | journal = Acta Oto-Laryngologica | volume = 127 | issue = 4 | pages = 351–4 | date = Apr 2007 | pmid = 17453452 | doi = 10.1080/00016480601126986 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19515914&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hoe HS, Lee KJ, Carney RS, Lee J, Markova A, Lee JY, Howell BW, Hyman BT, Pak DT, Bu G, Rebeck GW | title = Interaction of reelin with amyloid precursor protein promotes neurite outgrowth | journal = The Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 29 | issue = 23 | pages = 7459–73 | date = Jun 2009 | pmid = 19515914 | pmc = 2759694 | doi = 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4872-08.2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Herz2009relnabeta&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Durakoglugil MS, Chen Y, White CL, Kavalali ET, Herz J | title = Reelin signaling antagonizes beta-amyloid at the synapse | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 106 | issue = 37 | pages = 15938–43 | date = Sep 2009 | pmid = 19805234 | pmc = 2747222 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0908176106 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pancreatic_Cancer_2006&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Sato N, Fukushima N, Chang R, Matsubayashi H, Goggins M | title = Differential and epigenetic gene expression profiling identifies frequent disruption of the RELN pathway in pancreatic cancers | journal = Gastroenterology | volume = 130 | issue = 2 | pages = 548–65 | date = Feb 2006 | pmid = 16472607 | doi = 10.1053/j.gastro.2005.11.008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Prostate_Cancer_2007_1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Perrone G, Vincenzi B, Zagami M, Santini D, Panteri R, Flammia G, Verzi A, Lepanto D, Morini S, Russo A, Bazan V, Tomasino RM, Morello V, Tonini G, Rabitti C | year = 2007 | title = Reelin expression in human prostate cancer: a marker of tumor aggressiveness based on correlation with grade. | url = | journal = Modern Pathology | volume =  20| issue = | pages =  344–51| doi = 10.1038/modpathol.3800743 | pmid = 17277764 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17615543&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Seigel GM, Hackam AS, Ganguly A, Mandell LM, Gonzalez-Fernandez F | title = Human embryonic and neuronal stem cell markers in retinoblastoma | journal = Molecular Vision | volume = 13 | issue =  | pages = 823–32 | year = 2007 | pmid = 17615543 | pmc = 2768758 | url = http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v13/a90/ }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19230858&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Schrauwen I, Ealy M, Huentelman MJ, Thys M, Homer N, Vanderstraeten K, Fransen E, Corneveaux JJ, Craig DW, Claustres M, Cremers CW, Dhooge I, Van de Heyning P, Vincent R, Offeciers E, Smith RJ, Van Camp G | title = A genome-wide analysis identifies genetic variants in the RELN gene associated with otosclerosis | journal = American Journal of Human Genetics | volume = 84 | issue = 3 | pages = 328–38 | date = Mar 2009 | pmid = 19230858 | pmc = 2667982 | doi = 10.1016/j.ajhg.2009.01.023 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18062806&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Delahaye NF, Coltel N, Puthier D, Barbier M, Benech P, Joly F, Iraqi FA, Grau GE, Nguyen C, Rihet P | title = Gene expression analysis reveals early changes in several molecular pathways in cerebral malaria-susceptible mice versus cerebral malaria-resistant mice | journal = BMC Genomics | volume = 8 | issue =  | pages = 452 | year = 2007 | pmid = 18062806 | pmc = 2246131 | doi = 10.1186/1471-2164-8-452 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15066269&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Wang GS, Hong CJ, Yen TY, Huang HY, Ou Y, Huang TN, Jung WG, Kuo TY, Sheng M, Wang TF, Hsueh YP | title = Transcriptional modification by a CASK-interacting nucleosome assembly protein | journal = Neuron | volume = 42 | issue = 1 | pages = 113–28 | date = Apr 2004 | pmid = 15066269 | doi = 10.1016/S0896-6273(04)00139-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid16484373&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Weaver IC, Meaney MJ, Szyf M | title = Maternal care effects on the hippocampal transcriptome and anxiety-mediated behaviors in the offspring that are reversible in adulthood | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 103 | issue = 9 | pages = 3480–5 | date = Feb 2006 | pmid = 16484373 | pmc = 1413873 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0507526103 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19357777&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Smit-Rigter LA, Champagne DL, van Hooft JA | title = Lifelong impact of variations in maternal care on dendritic structure and function of cortical layer 2/3 pyramidal neurons in rat offspring | journal = PLOS ONE | volume = 4 | issue = 4 | pages = e5167 | year = 2009 | pmid = 19357777 | pmc = 2663818 | doi = 10.1371/journal.pone.0005167 | editor1-last = Linden | editor1-first = Rafael }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19477232&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lussier AL, Caruncho HJ, Kalynchuk LE | title = Repeated exposure to corticosterone, but not restraint, decreases the number of reelin-positive cells in the adult rat hippocampus | journal = Neuroscience Letters | volume = 460 | issue = 2 | pages = 170–4 | date = Aug 2009 | pmid = 19477232 | doi = 10.1016/j.neulet.2009.05.050 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18757738&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Dong E, Nelson M, Grayson DR, Costa E, Guidotti A | title = Clozapine and sulpiride but not haloperidol or olanzapine activate brain DNA demethylation | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 105 | issue = 36 | pages = 13614–9 | date = Sep 2008 | pmid = 18757738 | pmc = 2533238 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0805493105 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19359144&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Fatemi SH, Reutiman TJ, Folsom TD | title = Chronic psychotropic drug treatment causes differential expression of Reelin signaling system in frontal cortex of rats | journal = Schizophrenia Research | volume = 111 | issue = 1-3 | pages = 138–52 | date = Jun 2009 | pmid = 19359144 | doi = 10.1016/j.schres.2009.03.002 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid12899622&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Andersen OM, Benhayon D, Curran T, Willnow TE | title = Differential binding of ligands to the apolipoprotein E receptor 2 | journal = Biochemistry | volume = 42 | issue = 31 | pages = 9355–64 | date = Aug 2003 | pmid = 12899622 | doi = 10.1021/bi034475p }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid12670700&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Benhayon D, Magdaleno S, Curran T | title = Binding of purified Reelin to ApoER2 and VLDLR mediates tyrosine phosphorylation of Disabled-1 | journal = Brain Research. Molecular Brain Research | volume = 112 | issue = 1-2 | pages = 33–45 | date = Apr 2003 | pmid = 12670700 | doi = 10.1016/S0169-328X(03)00032-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19922905&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Wedenoja J, Tuulio-Henriksson A, Suvisaari J, Loukola A, Paunio T, Partonen T, Varilo T, Lönnqvist J, Peltonen L | title = Replication of association between working memory and Reelin, a potential modifier gene in schizophrenia | journal = Biological Psychiatry | volume = 67 | issue = 10 | pages = 983–91 | date = May 2010 | pmid = 19922905 | pmc = 3083525 | doi = 10.1016/j.biopsych.2009.09.026 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid11252768&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Herz J, Beffert U | title = Apolipoprotein E receptors: linking brain development and Alzheimer's disease | journal = Nature Reviews. Neuroscience | volume = 1 | issue = 1 | pages = 51–8 | date = Oct 2000 | pmid = 11252768 | doi = 10.1038/35036221 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17053810&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Herz J, Chen Y | title = Reelin, lipoprotein receptors and synaptic plasticity | journal = Nature Reviews. Neuroscience | volume = 7 | issue = 11 | pages = 850–9 | date = Nov 2006 | pmid = 17053810 | doi = 10.1038/nrn2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid20547867&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Chen Y, Durakoglugil MS, Xian X, Herz J | title = ApoE4 reduces glutamate receptor function and synaptic plasticity by selectively impairing ApoE receptor recycling | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 107 | issue = 26 | pages = 12011–6 | date = Jun 2010 | pmid = 20547867 | pmc = 2900641 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0914984107 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid10571241&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hiesberger T, Trommsdorff M, Howell BW, Goffinet A, Mumby MC, Cooper JA, Herz J | title = Direct binding of Reelin to VLDL receptor and ApoE receptor 2 induces tyrosine phosphorylation of disabled-1 and modulates tau phosphorylation | journal = Neuron | volume = 24 | issue = 2 | pages = 481–9 | date = Oct 1999 | pmid = 10571241 | doi = 10.1016/S0896-6273(00)80861-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid10571240&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = D'Arcangelo G, Homayouni R, Keshvara L, Rice DS, Sheldon M, Curran T | title = Reelin is a ligand for lipoprotein receptors | journal = Neuron | volume = 24 | issue = 2 | pages = 471–9 | date = Oct 1999 | pmid = 10571240 | doi = 10.1016/S0896-6273(00)80860-0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

== Recommended reading ==
{{Commons category}}
* The book: {{cite book | author = Fatemi, S. Hossein | title = Reelin Glycoprotein: Structure, Biology and Roles in Health and Disease | publisher = Springer | location = Berlin | year = 2008 | pages = 444 pages | isbn = 978-0-387-76760-4 }}
* A review: {{cite journal | vauthors = Förster E, Jossin Y, Zhao S, Chai X, Frotscher M, Goffinet AM | title = Recent progress in understanding the role of Reelin in radial neuronal migration, with specific emphasis on the dentate gyrus | journal = The European Journal of Neuroscience | volume = 23 | issue = 4 | pages = 901–9 | date = Feb 2006 | pmid = 16519655 | doi = 10.1111/j.1460-9568.2006.04612.x }}

== External links ==
{{wiktionary}}

=== Articles, publications, webpages ===
* {{cite web | url = http://lifesci.rutgers.edu/~molbiosci/faculty/darcangelo.html | title = Gabriella D'Arcangelo | work = | publisher = Rutgers University | pages = | archiveurl = | archivedate = | quote = the scientist who discovered the reelin gene and protein | accessdate = 2008-08-23}}
* [http://www.wikigenes.org/e/gene/e/5649.html Human RELN at WikiGenes]

=== Figures and images ===
{{refbegin|33em}}
* {{cite web | url = http://www.stjudebgem.org/web/view/probe/viewProbeDetails.php?id=404 | title = Reelin gene expression in mice | work = Brain Gene Expression Map | publisher = St. Jude Children’s Research Hospital | accessdate = 2008-08-23}}
* {{cite web | url = http://www.jlr.org/cgi/contnt-nw/full/45/3/403/FIG4 | title = Schematic representation of signaling through the LDLR family members apoER2 and VLDL receptor | accessdate = 2008-08-23}} – A figure from {{cite journal | vauthors = Beffert U, Stolt PC, Herz J | title = Functions of lipoprotein receptors in neurons | journal = Journal of Lipid Research | volume = 45 | issue = 3 | pages = 403–9 | date = Mar 2004 | pmid = 14657206 | doi = 10.1194/jlr.R300017-JLR200 }}
* {{cite web | url = http://www.pnas.org/cgi/content-nw/full/102/35/12578/FIG5 | title = Proposed mechanism by which mouse RELN promoter regulate reelin gene expression | publisher = Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA | accessdate = 2008-08-23}} – A figure from {{cite journal | vauthors = Dong E, Agis-Balboa RC, Simonini MV, Grayson DR, Costa E, Guidotti A | title = Reelin and glutamic acid decarboxylase67 promoter remodeling in an epigenetic methionine-induced mouse model of schizophrenia | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 102 | issue = 35 | pages = 12578–83 | date = Aug 2005 | pmid = 16113080 | pmc = 1194936 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0505394102 }}
* {{cite journal | url = http://www.sciencedirect.com/science?_ob=MiamiCaptionURL&amp;_method=retrieve&amp;_udi=B6VRT-44PC6R0-G&amp;_image=fig2&amp;_ba=2&amp;_user=10&amp;_coverDate=12%2F11%2F2001&amp;_fmt=full&amp;_orig=search&amp;_cdi=6243&amp;_qd=1&amp;view=c&amp;_acct=C000050221&amp;_version=1&amp;_urlVersion=0&amp;_userid=10&amp;md5=61889242c72086d56e74e498ceadd958 | title = Corticogenesis in wild-type, reeler mutant and β1 deficient mice| quote = Pictorial rendition of the difference that the lack of reelin brings to the cortical structure | accessdate = 2008-08-23}} – A figure from {{cite journal | vauthors = Magdaleno SM, Curran T | title = Brain development: integrins and the Reelin pathway | journal = Current Biology | volume = 11 | issue = 24 | pages = R1032-5 | date = Dec 2001 | pmid = 11747842 | doi = 10.1016/S0960-9822(01)00618-2 }}
* {{cite web | url = http://www.nature.com/ng/journal/v26/n1/fig_tab/ng0900_93_F5.html | title = Effects of human and naturally occurring mouse RELN mutations on the predicted protein | work = Nature Genetics | accessdate = 2008-08-23}} A figure from {{cite journal | vauthors = Hong SE, Shugart YY, Huang DT, Shahwan SA, Grant PE, Hourihane JO, Martin ND, Walsh CA | title = Autosomal recessive lissencephaly with cerebellar hypoplasia is associated with human RELN mutations | journal = Nature Genetics | volume = 26 | issue = 1 | pages = 93–6 | date = Sep 2000 | pmid = 10973257 | doi = 10.1038/79246 }}
* {{cite web | url = http://www.nature.com/ng/journal/v26/n1/fig_tab/ng0900_93_F2.html | title = MRI analysis of chromosome 7q22-linked lissencephaly with cerebellar hypoplasia |work= Nature Genetics | accessdate = 2008-08-23}} – A figure from Hong et al.
{{refend}}

{{PDB Gallery|geneid=5649}}
{{Medicine}}
{{Proteases}}
{{Serine endopeptidases}}
{{Enzymes}}
{{Portal bar|Molecular and Cellular Biology|border=no}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2010}}

[[Category:EC 3.4.21|*]]
[[Category:Molecular neuroscience]]
[[Category:Neurology]]
[[Category:Glycoproteins]]
[[Category:Biology of bipolar disorder]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Genes on human chromosome 7]]</text>
      <sha1>9u10h3d0clbg6x8wo57eubjgmnslumg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
