<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.28.0-wmf.17</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2600" case="first-letter">Topic</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>The Dawn of Love (painting)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>47501643</id>
    <revision>
      <id>733374525</id>
      <parentid>733241806</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-07T10:48:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>FACBot</username>
        <id>22689343</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Promoting 'The Dawn of Love (painting)' to Featured Article status</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21306">{{featured article}}
{{italic title}}
[[Image:Etty – The Dawn of Love.jpg|right|300px|thumb|''The Dawn of Love'', 1828,  {{convert|88.8|by|96|cm|in|abbr=on}}|alt=Naked woman sitting beside a sleeping man]]
'''''The Dawn of Love''''', also known as '''''Venus Now Wakes, and Wakens Love''''', is an [[oil painting]] on canvas by English artist [[William Etty]], first exhibited in 1828 and currently in the [[Russell-Cotes Art Gallery &amp; Museum]] in [[Bournemouth]]. Loosely based on a passage from [[John Milton]]'s 1634 [[masque]] ''[[Comus (John Milton)|Comus]]'', it shows a [[nude (art)|nude]] [[Venus (mythology)|Venus]] leaning across to wake the sleeping Love by stroking his wings. While Etty often included nude figures in his work he rarely depicted physical intimacy, and owing to this ''The Dawn of Love'' is one of his more unusual paintings. The open sensuality of the work was intended to present a challenge to the viewer mirroring the plot of ''Comus'', in which the heroine is tempted by desire but remains rational and detached.

While a few critics praised elements of its composition and execution, ''The Dawn of Love'' was very poorly received when first exhibited. Etty had developed a reputation for painting realistic figures, and his stylised Venus was thought unduly influenced by foreign artists such as [[Rubens]] as well as being overly voluptuous and unrealistically coloured, while the painting as a whole was considered tasteless and obscene. ''The Dawn of Love'' was not among the 133 paintings exhibited in the major 1849 [[retrospective exhibition]] of Etty's works, and its exhibition in Glasgow in 1899 drew complaints for its supposed obscenity. In 1889 it was bought by [[Merton Russell-Cotes|Sir Merton Russell-Cotes]], and has remained in the collection of the Russell-Cotes Art Gallery &amp; Museum ever since.

==Background==
[[File:William Etty - Pandora Crowned by the Seasons, 1824.jpg|thumb|''Pandora Crowned by the Seasons'' (1824). Following the success of ''Cleopatra'', Etty tried to replicate its success with further history paintings containing nude figures.|alt=Standing naked woman, surrounded by naked people, being crowned by four scantily dressed figures]]
[[William Etty]] was born in 1787, the son of a [[York]] baker and miller.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODNB&quot;&gt;{{Cite ODNB|id=8925|title=William Etty}}&lt;/ref&gt; He began as an apprentice printer in [[Kingston upon Hull|Hull]].{{sfn|Gilchrist|1855|p=23}} On completing his seven-year apprenticeship he moved at the age of 18 to London &quot;with a few pieces of chalk crayons&quot;,{{sfn|Burnage|2011a|p=157}} with the intention of becoming a [[history painting|history painter]] in the tradition of the [[Old Masters]].{{sfn|Smith|1996|p=86}} He enrolled at the [[Royal Academy]], and after a year spent studying under renowned portrait painter [[Thomas Lawrence]],{{sfn|Farr|1958|p=15}} Etty returned to the Royal Academy, drawing at the [[life class]] and copying other paintings.{{sfn|Farr|1958|p=15}}{{sfn|Green|2011|p=61}} A follower of [[John Opie]], who promoted the unfashionable painting style of [[Titian]] and [[Peter Paul Rubens|Rubens]] over the then-prevalent formal style of [[Joshua Reynolds]],{{sfn|Farr|1958|p=12}} Etty was unsuccessful in all the Academy's competitions and every work he submitted to the [[Royal Academy Summer Exhibition]] in the 1810s was rejected.{{sfn|Farr|1958|p=15}} In 1821 the Royal Academy accepted and exhibited one of Etty's works in the Summer Exhibition, ''[[The Arrival of Cleopatra in Cilicia]]'' (also known as ''The Triumph of Cleopatra'').{{sfn|Burnage|2011d|p=31}} This painting was extremely well received, and many of Etty's fellow artists greatly admired him.{{sfn|Burnage|2011b|p=118}} He became well respected for his ability to capture flesh tones accurately in painting, and for his fascination with contrasts in skin tones.{{sfn|Burnage|2011c|p=198}} Following the exhibition of ''Cleopatra'', over the next decade Etty tried to replicate its success by painting [[Nude (art)|&lt;!-- Normally this would be overlinking, but in this context readers are likely to want to learn more about the tradition of nude art --&gt;nude figures]] in biblical, literary and mythological settings.&lt;ref name=&quot;MAG Etty&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.manchestergalleries.org/salvaged/the-painting/about-the-artist/index.html|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150211024806/http://www.manchestergalleries.org/salvaged/the-painting/about-the-artist/index.html|archivedate=11 February 2015|title=About the artist|publisher=Manchester Art Gallery|accessdate=10 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While some nudes by foreign artists were held in private English collections, the country had no tradition of nude painting and the display and distribution of nude material to the public had been suppressed since the 1787 [[Society for the Suppression of Vice|Proclamation for the Discouragement of Vice]].{{sfn|Smith|2001b|p=53}} Etty was the first British artist to specialise in the nude, and the reaction of the lower classes to these paintings caused concern throughout the 19th century.{{sfn|Smith|2001b|p=55}} Many critics condemned his repeated depictions of female nudity as indecent, although his portraits of male nudes were generally well received.{{sfn|Smith|2001a|p = 54}}{{efn-ua|Etty's male nude portraits were primarily of mythological heroes and classical combat, genres in which the depiction of male nudity was considered acceptable in England.{{sfn|Burnage|2011d|pp=32–33}}}}

==Composition==
{{Quote box|width=21em|align=right|salign=right|quote=&lt;poem&gt;
And on the tawny sands and shelves
Trip the pert fairies and the dapper elves
By dimpled brook and fountain-brim
The wood-nymphs, decked with daisies trim
Their merry wakes and pastimes keep;
What hath night to do with sleep?
Night hath better sweets to prove,
Venus now wakes, and wakens Love.
Come, let us our rites begin;
'Tis only day-light that makes sin
Which these dun shades will ne'er report.
Hail! Goddess of nocturnal sport.
&lt;/poem&gt;|source=''[[Comus (John Milton)|Comus]]'', lines 117–28}}
''The Dawn of Love'' illustrates an early passage from ''[[Comus (John Milton)|Comus]]'', a 1634 [[masque]] by [[John Milton]]. ''Comus'' is a morality tale in which the female protagonist, referred to only as &quot;The Lady&quot;, becomes separated from her family. She encounters the debauched magician [[Comus]] who captures and imprisons her, and uses all the means at his disposal to try to inflame her sexual desires. The Lady resists all temptation, and using her reason and sense of morals resists Comus's efforts to draw her into intemperance or surrender to desire.{{sfn|Burnage|2011b|p=116}}

Etty's painting is not a direct illustration of a scene from ''Comus''. Instead, it is inspired by an early passage in which Comus, prior to his meeting with The Lady, muses on the notion that sin is only problematic if others become aware of it, and thus that it is right and natural to surrender to base desires while under cover of darkness, arguing that &quot;What hath night to do with sleep? Night hath better sweets to prove, Venus now wakes, and wakens Love&quot;.{{sfn|Burnage|2011b|p=116}} Etty's painting shows the nude [[Venus (mythology)|Venus]], as &quot;Goddess of nocturnal sport&quot;, reaching across to wake the sleeping Love by stroking his wings.{{sfn|Burnage|2011b|p=116}}&lt;ref name=&quot;NMM&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|date=1 April 1828|title=Fine Arts|publisher=Henry Colburn|location=London|volume=III|page=157}}&lt;/ref&gt; While Etty had built his reputation on his renowned ability to paint realistic human figures, Venus in ''The Dawn of Love'' is highly stylised, and painted in a deliberate pastiche of the style of Rubens.{{sfn|Burnage|2011b|p=116}}

''The Dawn of Love'' intentionally presents a moral dilemma to viewers. By his open depiction of nudity and sensuality, Etty makes the same argument as that presented by Comus, that it is rational for the viewer to succumb to their lustful thoughts while in private. The picture presents the same moral challenge to the viewer as that which Comus presents to The Lady, that of remaining true to her better, moral and rational, nature, despite there being no apparent disadvantage in surrendering to desire.{{sfn|Burnage|2011b|p=116}}

While Etty regularly painted nudity, he rarely depicted physical intimacy other than in combat, and ''The Dawn of Love'' is unusual among his works; Etty's biographer Leonard Robinson commented in 2007 that ''The Dawn of Love'' &quot;is a subject so untypical of Etty that one finds difficulty in understanding why he painted it&quot;.{{sfn|Robinson|2007|p=259}}

==Reception==
[[Image:Etty - The World Before the Flood (Southampton).jpg|right|thumb|Etty's ''[[The World Before the Flood]]'', exhibited later in 1828, also illustrated Milton, in this case ''[[Paradise Lost]]''.{{sfn|Burnage|2011b|p=113}}|alt=Large number of semi-naked people]]
Etty exhibited the painting in February 1828 at the [[British Institution]] under the title of ''Venus Now Wakes, and Wakens Love''.{{sfn|Burnage|2011b|p=116}}{{sfn|Burnage|Bertram|2011|p=23}} It immediately met with a storm of derision from critics for the style in which Venus was painted;{{sfn|Burnage|2011b|p=116}} one of the few positive reviews was that of ''[[The New Monthly Magazine]]'', whose critic considered &quot;the figure of Venus is delightfully drawn and most voluptuously coloured; and the way in which she awakens love, by ruffling the feathers of his wings, is exquisitely imagined and executed&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;NMM&quot; /&gt; ''[[The Times]]'' commented that &quot;the drawing is free and flowing&quot; and &quot;the colouring, though rich, is perfectly natural&quot;, but felt that &quot;the subject is, however, handled in a way entirely too luscious (we might, with great propriety, use a harsher term) for the public eye&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite newspaper The Times |articlename=British Institution |day_of_week=Monday |date=4 February 1828 |page_number=3 |issue=13506 |column=A }}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The Literary Gazette]]'' conceded that the painting was &quot;very attractive, especially in colour&quot;, but considered the painting's &quot;voluptuousness&quot; as &quot;one of the most unpardonable sins against taste&quot;, and chided Etty's &quot;careless&quot; drawing, observing that &quot;it is impossible that an artist who has for so many years, and so unremittingly, studied the living model, can err in that respect from want of knowledge&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|date=9 February 1828|title=Fine Arts: British Institution|journal=The Literary Gazette|publisher=W. A. Scripps|location=London|issue=577|page=90}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[Monthly Magazine]]'' complained of Venus's &quot;sullen colour and corpulent shape&quot;, as well as Etty's &quot;excessive exposure of [Venus's] figure&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Fine Arts Exhibitions|journal=The Monthly Magazine|publisher=Richard Phillips|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[La Belle Assemblée]]'', meanwhile, felt that Etty's representation of Venus &quot;though a fine voluptuous woman, is not, either in supremacy of beauty, or according to any received description of the love-inspiring goddess, a Venus&quot;, and complained that &quot;the colouring of the flesh is chalky&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|date=March 1828|title=Fine Arts Exhibitions, &amp;c: British Institution|journal=La Belle Assemblée|publisher=Shackell and Baylis|location=London|volume=7|issue=39|page=133}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The harshest criticism came from an anonymous reviewer in ''[[The London Magazine]]'':
{{quote|text=This small picture&amp;nbsp;... we utterly condemn, not for the nudity or indecency of which some have complained, but because there is a total want of beauty, grace, and expression, to clothe the nakedness and abstract the mind from it. Mr.&amp;nbsp;Etty seems conscious of the coldness of his flesh-colour, and atones for it by the flabbiness of his figures. They are {{not a typo|any thing}} but voluptuous or alluring. We would recommend to our artist to leave these small unfinished vignettes, these little doughy Rubenses as &quot;toys of desperation&quot; to others. His firm, broad, manly pencil, requires wider scope and a different subject.|sign=''The London Magazine'', April 1828&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|date=April 1828|title=Notes on Art|journal=The London Magazine|publisher=Henry Hooper|location=London|volume=I|issue=1|page=27}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
An anonymous reviewer in the same publication later that year returned to the theme, chiding Etty for his imitation of foreign artists rather than attempting to develop a new and unique style of his own, observing that &quot;we cannot imitate the voice or the actions of another, without exaggerating or caricaturing them&quot;, complaining that there is &quot;[no] propriety in seeing the Venuses of Titian, the fables of heathenism, or the base occupations of Dutch boors, placed in parallel with those subjects which form the basis [of] all our future hopes&quot;, and observing that &quot;surely, Rubens ought here [in England] to be held up as rock to avoid, not a light to follow&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|date=July 1828|title=The British Institution|journal=The London Magazine|publisher=Henry Hooper|location=London|volume=I|issue=2|page=395}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
[[Image:Etty – Musidora- The Bather 'At the Doubtful Breeze Alarmed'.jpg|right|upright|thumb|''[[Musidora: The Bather 'At the Doubtful Breeze Alarmed']]'' (exh.&amp;nbsp;1846). Etty continued to paint nudes throughout his career, but rarely again depicted physical intimacy.|alt=Naked woman standing in a stream]]
In February 1828, shortly after the exhibition of ''The Dawn of Love'', Etty defeated [[John Constable]] by 18 votes to five to become a full [[Royal Academician]],{{sfn|Farr|1958|p=52}} at the time the highest honour available to an artist.{{sfn|Robinson|2007|p=135}}{{efn-ua|In Etty's time, honours such as knighthoods were only bestowed on presidents of major institutions, not on even the most well respected artists.{{sfn|Robinson|2007|p=135}}}} From 1832 onwards, needled by repeated attacks from the press on his supposed indecency and tastelessness, Etty continued to be a prominent painter of nudes but began to make conscious efforts to reflect moral teachings in his work.{{sfn|Burnage|2011d|p=42}} He died in 1849,{{sfn|Robinson|2007|p=440}} working and exhibiting up until his death{{sfn|Burnage|2011e|p=243}} and remained well-regarded as an artist despite being regarded by many as a pornographer. [[Charles Robert Leslie]] observed shortly after Etty's death that {{nowrap|&quot;[Etty]}} himself, thinking and meaning no evil, was not aware of the manner in which his works were regarded by grosser minds&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Leslie|first=Charles Robert|date=30 March 1850|title=Lecture on the Works of the late W. Etty, Esq, R.A., by Professor Leslie|journal=The Athenæum|location=London|issue=1170|page=352}}&lt;/ref&gt; Interest in his work declined as [[Victorian painting|new movements]] came to characterise painting in Britain, and by the end of the 19th century the cost of all his paintings had fallen below their original prices.{{sfn|Robinson|2007|p=440}}

''The Dawn of Love'' (under its original title of ''Venus Now Wakes, and Wakens Love'') was exhibited in 1829 at the [[Royal Birmingham Society of Artists|Birmingham Society of Arts]], but other than that its history during Etty's lifetime is not recorded. No record of its original sale exists, and it was not among the 133 paintings included in the major [[retrospective exhibition]] of Etty's works at the [[Royal Society of Arts]] in 1849.{{sfn|Farr|1958|p=157}} It is known that in 1835 it was in the collection of textile entrepreneur [[Joseph Strutt (philanthropist)|Joseph Strutt]], but it was not among the paintings sold on his death in 1844.{{sfn|Farr|1958|p=157}} In June 1889 it was bought from an unknown buyer for an unknown sum by [[Merton Russell-Cotes|Sir Merton Russell-Cotes]],{{sfn|Farr|1958|p=157}} and has remained in the collection of the [[Russell-Cotes Art Gallery &amp; Museum]] in [[Bournemouth]] ever since.{{sfn|Smith|2001b|p=56}} It was shown at an 1899 exhibition of works from Russell-Cotes's collection at the [[Glasgow Corporation Gallery]].{{sfn|Smith|2001b|p=56}} This exhibition caused some controversy owing to its supposed obscene nature; in 1894 a number of supposedly obscene [[Printmaking|prints]] of works by major artists had been removed from a Glasgow shop by police and magistrates, and it was felt inappropriate for a publicly funded educational body to be displaying a work of equal obscenity.{{sfn|Smith|2001b|p=57}} Several luminaries of the art world such as [[Frederic Leighton, 1st Baron Leighton|Frederic Leighton]] intervened, and the exhibition went ahead.{{sfn|Smith|2001b|p=58}} ''The Dawn of Love'' was also exhibited at a 1955 [[Arts Council]] exhibition,{{sfn|Farr|1958|p=157}} and was one of the works exhibited in a major retrospective of Etty's works at the [[York Art Gallery]] in 2011–12.{{sfn|Burnage|2011b|p=117}}

== Footnotes ==
{{notelist-ua}}

== References ==

=== Notes ===
{{Reflist|colwidth=25em}}

=== Bibliography ===
* {{cite book|last1=Burnage|first1=Sarah|editor-last1=Burnage|editor-first1 =Sarah|editor-last2=Hallett|editor-first2=Mark|editor-last3 = Turner |editor-first3=Laura|title= William Etty: Art &amp; Controversy | year = 2011a |chapter=Etty and the Masters|pages=154–97|publisher = Philip Wilson Publishers |location=London|isbn=978-0-85667-701-4|oclc = 800599710 | ref = harv}}&lt;!-- This is not an error—the book contains two different chapters called &quot;Etty and the Masters&quot;, by two different people --&gt;
* {{cite book|last1=Burnage|first1=Sarah|editor-last1=Burnage| editor-first1 =Sarah|editor-last2=Hallett|editor-first2=Mark|editor-last3 = Turner |editor-first3=Laura|title= William Etty: Art &amp; Controversy | year = 2011b|chapter=History Painting and the Critics|pages=106–54 | publisher = Philip Wilson Publishers|location=London|isbn = 978-0-85667-701-4 |oclc=800599710|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last1=Burnage|first1=Sarah|editor-last1=Burnage| editor-first1 =Sarah|editor-last2=Hallett|editor-first2=Mark|editor-last3 = Turner |editor-first3=Laura|title= William Etty: Art &amp; Controversy | year = 2011c|chapter=The Life Class|pages=198–227|publisher= Philip Wilson Publishers |location=London|isbn=978-0-85667-701-4|oclc = 800599710 | ref =harv}}
* {{cite book|last1=Burnage|first1=Sarah|editor-last1=Burnage| editor-first1 =Sarah|editor-last2=Hallett|editor-first2=Mark|editor-last3 = Turner |editor-first3=Laura|title= William Etty: Art &amp; Controversy | year = 2011d| chapter = Painting the Nude and 'Inflicting Divine Vengeance on the Wicked'|pages= 31–46|publisher= Philip Wilson Publishers | location=London|isbn= 978-0-85667-701-4|oclc= 800599710 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book|last1=Burnage|first1=Sarah|editor-last1=Burnage| editor-first1=Sarah|editor-last2=Hallett|editor-first2=Mark|editor-last3 = Turner |editor-first3=Laura|title= William Etty: Art &amp; Controversy | year =2011e|chapter=Portraiture|pages=228–50|publisher=Philip Wilson Publishers |location=London|isbn=978-0-85667-701-4|oclc=800599710|ref =harv}}
* {{cite book|last1=Burnage|first1=Sarah|last2=Bertram| first2 = Beatrice | editor-last1=Burnage|editor-first1=Sarah|editor-last2 = Hallett |editor-first2=Mark|editor-last3=Turner|editor-first3=Laura | title = William Etty: Art &amp; Controversy| year= 2011| chapter = Chronology | pages= 20–30| publisher= Philip Wilson Publishers | location =London|isbn=978-0-85667-701-4|oclc=800599710|ref= harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Farr|first=Dennis|title=William Etty|year= 1958 | publisher =Routledge and Kegan Paul| location= London|oclc= 2470159 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Gilchrist|first=Alexander|authorlink=Alexander Gilchrist |title=Life of William Etty, R.A.|volume=1|year=1855 | publisher =David Bogue|location=London|oclc= 2135826 |ref = {{harvid | Gilchrist | 1855}}}}
* {{cite book|last1=Green|first1=Richard|editor-last1=Burnage|editor-first1=Sarah|editor-last2=Hallett|editor-first2=Mark|editor-last3=Turner|editor-first3=Laura|title=William Etty: Art &amp; Controversy|year=2011|chapter=Etty and the Masters|pages=61–74|publisher=Philip Wilson Publishers|location=London|isbn=978-0-85667-701-4|oclc=800599710|ref={{harvid|Green|2011}}}}&lt;!-- This is not an error—the book contains two different chapters called &quot;Etty and the Masters&quot;, by two different people --&gt;
* {{cite book|last=Robinson|first=Leonard|title=William Etty: The Life and Art|year=2007|publisher=McFarland &amp; Company|location=Jefferson, NC|isbn=978-0-7864-2531-0|oclc= 751047871|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Smith|first=Alison|title=Exposed: The Victorian Nude|year=2001a|publisher=Tate Publishing|location=London|isbn=978-1-85437-372-4|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Smith|first=Alison|editor-last=Bills|editor-first=Mark|title=Art in the Age of Queen Victoria: A Wealth of Depictions|year=2001b|chapter=Private Pleasures?|pages=53–67|publisher=Russell–Cotes Art Gallery and Museum|location=Bournemouth|isbn=978-0-905173-65-8|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Smith|first=Alison|title=The Victorian Nude|year=1996|publisher=Manchester University Press|location=Manchester|isbn=978-0-7190-4403-8|ref=harv}}

{{William Etty}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dawn of Love}}
[[Category:Paintings by William Etty]]
[[Category:1828 paintings]]
[[Category:John Milton]]
[[Category:Nude art]]
[[Category:Paintings in South West England]]
[[Category:Paintings of Venus]]</text>
      <sha1>5q611xlx9i59v1ne5hv3s2p1h1z0m9i</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
