<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Lettuce</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1624058</id>
    <revision>
      <id>693263424</id>
      <parentid>693259489</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-12-01T12:48:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>William Avery</username>
        <id>1398</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/27.114.177.197|27.114.177.197]] ([[User talk:27.114.177.197|talk]]) to last version by ERAGON</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="30067">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=21:21, 20 April 2012
|action1link=Talk:Lettuce/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=488393971

|action2=PR
|action2date=23:32, 29 May 2012
|action2link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Lettuce/archive1
|action2result=reviewed
|action2oldid=495037607

|action3=FAC
|action3date=09:37, 29 July 2012
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Lettuce/archive1
|action3result=promoted
|action3oldid=504313960

|topic=Natural science
|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=September 26, 2012
}}
{{Vital article|level=4|topic=Science|class=FA|subpage=Biology}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Agriculture|class=FA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Food and drink|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Plants|class=FA|importance=High}}}}
{{WPCD}}

== Reconciling the lettuce map and 'facts and figures'==
From the trivia section at the bottom: &quot;In the United States, 95% of all head lettuce is grown in California and Arizona.&quot; Yet, the map shows lettuce being grown on the east coast of the US. My first thought was that the map shows which countries grow the lettuce, but then why would there be multiple dots within a single country (like the US)? Any ideas on how we could make this more clear? --[[User:Revaaron|Revaaron]] 17:59, 26 July 2007 (UTC)

==Distinguishing members of the asterales from species that are not really lettuce==
I wonder whether this article should mention that &quot;Lamb's lettuce&quot; is not, strictly speaking, a true lettuce, as it belongs to a totally different plant family to familiar varieties such as iceberg? Also, is Chinese leaf really a form of lettuce? I would be interested to hear whether any one can clarify for me whether this, as with other lettuces, is a member of the asterale family (compositae), or belongs (as I seem to recall hearing) to the family of crucifers.[[User:ACEO|ACEO]] 20:52, 16 March 2006 (UTC)

This article should include germination of the lettuce plant from a young age and more information on what lettuces are and how they grow not irellirant information on species and subspecies.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:202.137.246.190|202.137.246.190]] ([[User talk:202.137.246.190|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/202.137.246.190|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;
:Please keep in mind that not everyone considers taxonomic information irrelevant.  As for adding information that isn't in the article now, please [[WP:BOLD|be bold]] if you know where to find good information on lettuce development.  --[[User:Amcbride|Allen]] 16:06, 16 July 2006 (UTC)

also, oakleaf (or oak-leaf) lettuce seems to be missing from wikipedia entirely.... [[User:84.97.154.181|84.97.154.181]] 19:04, 27 March 2007 (UTC)

== Images ==
I'm moving this image here, because the page seems crowded with images, and there is already an image of Iceberg in the taxobox. [[Image:Iceberg lettuce.jpg|thumb|120px|Iceberg lettuce]] [[User:Pekinensis|Pekinensis]] 21:02, 19 Mar 2005 (UTC)

== World record ==
Do we need a reference for the world record inserted by [[User:69.139.227.87|69.139.227.87]]?  I haven't been able to confirm the information. [[User:Pekinensis|Pekinensis]] 21:16, 19 Mar 2005 (UTC)

== Vandalism? ==
Do you think the second paragraph of &quot;History&quot; was vandalized?    Either way, without the citation it should probably be removed. [[User:63.252.64.106|63.252.64.106]] 03:45, 3 June 2006 (UTC)

Why the hell would someone vandalize an article on lettuce? --[[User:71.112.104.213|71.112.104.213]] 04:44, 19 November 2006 (UTC)
:Maybe he got attacked by a lettuce as a child LOL - after being around here a while - I still fail to understand why people vandalize. The ones I expect are immature kids vandalizing &quot;dirty word&quot; articles, or adding &quot;dirty words&quot; to articles, or messing up the school page, or making nasty remarks about their teachers, or defaming their friends. But there are others where people spend a lot of time writing intricate articles full of nonsense. They usually get deleted within a couple of minutes - so why bother. --[[User:ArmadilloFromHell|&lt;font color=&quot;#0000FF&quot;&gt;'''Armadillo'''&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#000000&quot;&gt;'''From'''&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#FF0000&quot;&gt;'''Hell'''&lt;/font&gt;]] 05:01, 19 November 2006 (UTC)

I will admit, the ClueBot OS is a fine piece of programming for sorting out vandalism, i've seen a fair share of it myself coming from this IP address over a few months and stepped in when I realised there was a block warning in place for any more, but kids will be kids, however strict the school is there will still be the occassional rebellious person. The best we can do is undo the damage that they do and if it's possible try and find out which student did it.
On the matter of Lettuce I don't really know much so if this gets removed by ClueBot OS as not contributing then it makes sense to me, I just wanted to give my opinion on this matter. [[Special:Contributions/82.33.215.26|82.33.215.26]] ([[User talk:82.33.215.26|talk]]) 10:58, 26 September 2012 (UTC)

== Nutrition Comparison ==
Does anyone have any information about comparing the nutritional value for different types of lettuces (in particular, is Iceberg lettuce anywhere near as nutritional)? &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:68.249.203.206|68.249.203.206]] ([[User talk:68.249.203.206|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/68.249.203.206|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;
:There are small differences, but in general, the nutritional value of lettuces is so low that it doesn't make much of a difference. It's 96% water! [[User:Hankwang|Han-Kwang]] 13:05, 9 August 2006 (UTC)

This is not true at all.  Head lettuce is worthless nutritionally, while Romaine lettuce is full of vitamins.  Three cups of Romaine lettuce contains 87% RDA of Vitamin A an 10% RDA of iron. ([[User:Cashew|Cashew]] 23:48, 28 October 2006 (UTC))
:I confess that I only checked 2 or 3 types of lettuce before I made that remark, but after comparing butterhead and Romaine side-by-side I'm not really convinced. The vit A content in butterhead lettuce isn't so bad either, although indeed lower than in romaine. [[User:Hankwang|Han-Kwang]] 01:09, 29 October 2006 (UTC)

== Citation needed ? == 
What sort of citation would you need for this?  A citation of someone describing 
bolted lettuce or a citation of someone associating it with verility?

&quot;As any vegetable gardener will know the lettuce can bolt or surge vertically upwards. This combined with a milky substance they can exude when cut could have been seen as a symbol of the male phallus ejaculating [citation needed].&quot;

:The citation is asking for the second one, but that doesn't mean that the first one isn't needed. Everything should be cited, there is just a focus on less obviously &quot;right&quot; statements to start with. [[User:Notinasnaid|Notinasnaid]] 08:23, 22 November 2006 (UTC)

== Lettuce opium ==
The article mentions [[lactucarium]], an opium-like substance found in lettuce. Is this in common (I'm in the US) salad lettuce like Romaine and iceberg or only a few species? &amp;mdash; [[User:Samuella|Sam]] 23:36, 26 March 2007 (UTC)

:I think this is found in &quot;wild lettuce&quot; (''[[Lactuca virosa]]'') not the same as commercially available lettuce. It grows as a weed in North America. [[User:Badagnani|Badagnani]] 21:07, 18 May 2007 (UTC)

==From?==
I read in World Book that lettuce comes from Iran. &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[Special:Contributions/67.110.221.182|67.110.221.182]] ([[User talk:67.110.221.182|talk]]) 06:51, 6 April 2007 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;

== Red leaf ==
Red leaf lettuce should be describe in the list of varieties. [[User:Badagnani|Badagnani]] 21:08, 18 May 2007 (UTC)

==History section - copyvio==
I have removed the History section as copyvio - it is a lift from [http://www.selfsufficientish.com/lettuce.htm here]. [[User:Bridgeplayer|Bridgeplayer]] 15:34, 24 June 2007 (UTC)

== Layout ==

I inserted a  great new picture into the article, which necessitated a wholesale change in the layout.  Feel free to shuffle around further if it still doesn't look good.--[[User:Slashme|Slashme]] 11:04, 17 October 2007 (UTC)

==Article needs more information==
Specifically, it should mention what climate lettuce grows in.[[Special:Contributions/128.95.141.35|128.95.141.35]] ([[User talk:128.95.141.35|talk]]) 19:52, 22 May 2008 (UTC)

== Sativa ==

Lactuce Sativa is the official name of lettuce, Cannabis Sativa of weed. is there something the same about these two?  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/84.85.130.72|84.85.130.72]] ([[User talk:84.85.130.72|talk]]) 23:19, 6 July 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

i beilieve that alettuce helps dijest your food as a suplimentary laxidive  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/74.62.87.26|74.62.87.26]] ([[User talk:74.62.87.26|talk]]) 17:28, 20 May 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:sativa is the latin word for cultivated or useful and is used for many unrelated species. They are not at all the same.--[[User:Charlesdrakew|Charles]] ([[User talk:Charlesdrakew|talk]]) 18:10, 28 October 2009 (UTC)

== Article on Wikibooks Horticulture? ==

As Wikipedia is not a how-to manual the growing instructions on the page should really go to Wikibooks Horticulture.--[[User:Charlesdrakew|Charles]] ([[User talk:Charlesdrakew|talk]]) 18:17, 28 October 2009 (UTC)

== &quot;Green leaf&quot; lettuce ==
I know this is a place to discuss the article, not the subject, so I guess I'm skirting on the edge of both here, but: I came here to find out what the &quot;green leaf lettuce&quot; I see in American supermarkets is, and discovered that this article mentions nothing about it. Google has provided me with only very vague results (nutritional information, but not whether it is different from or the same as Romaine, and so on), so I'm wondering if anyone more educated than me could clarify this, and perhaps take the opportunity to improve the article? [[User:Matt S.|Matt S.]] ([[User talk:Matt S.|talk]]) 17:45, 10 November 2009 (UTC)

==Romans and Egyptians==
Added a Dubious tag to the claim &quot;Both the Romans and Egyptians took advantage of this property by eating lettuce at the end of a meal to induce sleep&quot;, until someone comes up with a stronger reference than an organic food and lifestyle website.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/157.155.224.6|157.155.224.6]] ([[User talk:157.155.224.6|talk]]) 04:20, 16 January 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Hardiness? ==

The article says that lettuce is &quot;hardy to zone 6&quot;. Since lettuce can be grown in much colder zones, I assume that this refers to winter hardiness. Since the plant is almost invariably grown as an annual (does it even have perennial behavior?) is this relevant, and is it important enough to be so high in the article? I'm deciding not and moving this fact lower in the article, but wanted to ask the question.  [[User:RamblingChicken|RamblingChicken]] ([[User talk:RamblingChicken|talk]]) 23:29, 4 June 2011 (UTC)
:The criterion for inclusion on WP is verifiability by reliable secondary sources rather than truth. We have to go with what the sources say even if we personally disagree. In the absense of reliable sources it should just be left out. I hope this helps.--[[User:Charlesdrakew|Charles]] ([[User talk:Charlesdrakew|talk]]) 10:00, 5 June 2011 (UTC)

A belated response: It's not that I disagree, the question is about relevance and/or meaning. To me, &quot;hardy&quot; usually means that the plant can survive a winter and be alive the next spring. Since lettuce finishes its life in two or three months, that definition doesn't seem relevant, so I don't know what &quot;hardiness&quot; means in this context. [[User:RamblingChicken|RamblingChicken]] ([[User talk:RamblingChicken|talk]]) 07:21, 24 June 2011 (UTC)

:RC has a point. The term is vague because it is used in different contexts. According to my childhood instruction, it means that the plant can survive frost; &quot;half hardy&quot; would mean that it can survive frost as a mature plant, but not as a seedling. This should be clarified in text, or it would amount to hand-waving. [[User:JonRichfield|JonRichfield]] ([[User talk:JonRichfield|talk]]) 15:13, 10 January 2012 (UTC)

==Iceberg lettuce==

Why does the section on cultivars not mention iceberg lettuce? While I am here, I could also point out that it does not mention curly
leaf or little gem. [[User:ACEOREVIVED|ACEOREVIVED]] ([[User talk:ACEOREVIVED|talk]]) 20:47, 23 August 2011 (UTC)

== In 1492 Columbus sailed the ocean blue. In 1493 Columbus sailed the deep blue sea==
I have removed the claim that &quot;Christopher Columbus introduced lettuce to the [[New World]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.fruitsandveggiesmatter.gov/month/lettuce.html |title=Fruits &amp; Veggies Matter: Fruit &amp; Vegetable of the Month: Lettuce &amp;#124; CDC |work=fruitsandveggiesmatter.gov |year=2008 [last update] |accessdate=20 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It seemed suspicious and the source is lightweight to say the least. I found hardly better sources claiming (without support) that he did so on his second voyage. I found nothing to support the idea that if he did, the crop was established from that point on. I have no access to primary sources or even to authoritative secondary sources, but in searching online, I found nothing pre-twentieth century, and nothing substantial post 19th. To my mind this spells Urban Legend and I reckon we need something better than that.  [[User:JonRichfield|JonRichfield]] ([[User talk:JonRichfield|talk]]) 15:21, 10 January 2012 (UTC)

{{Talk:Lettuce/GA1}}

==Comments from EauOo==

Lettuce contains several defensive compounds, including sesquiterpene lactones, and other natural phenolics such as flavonol and glycosides, which help to protect it against pests; certain varieties contain more than others, and some selective breeding and genetic modification studies ''have focused on identifying and producing varieties with larger amounts'' of these compounds for increased pest resistance.[36]

:Can you quote me from the report where it says they are attempting to produce varieties with larger amounts? Thanks. [[User:EauOo|Eau]] ([[User talk:EauOo|talk]]) 05:54, 7 September 2012 (UTC)

::The source says &quot;The resistance seems to reside in the latex. If this resistance can be characterized and transferred to horticulturally acceptable varieties of romaine lettuce, the need for insecticide applications would be greatly diminished.&quot; [[User:Dana boomer|Dana boomer]] ([[User talk:Dana boomer|talk]]) 22:47, 8 September 2012 (UTC)

:::Yes, this is all I could find also. It says does not say &quot;larger amounts,&quot; so please change. [[User:EauOo|Eau]] ([[User talk:EauOo|talk]]) 23:04, 8 September 2012 (UTC)

::::If they're trying to transfer this to commercial varieties, they're trying to produce commercial varieties with larger amounts. I've tweaked the sentence a bit. [[User:Dana boomer|Dana boomer]] ([[User talk:Dana boomer|talk]]) 14:08, 9 September 2012 (UTC)
:::::No, that is not the only means of increasing the resistance, adding larger amounts, the scientists.could, as in the cases of other plants, add the generic resistance to different locations, tweak the molecule to make it more powerful and add lesser amounts, this is original research on your part, an assumptiom that increased insect resistance is always due to larger volumes of insecticides. That is not how it works, and it is not how it is always done for very obvious reasons. [[User:EauOo|Eau]] ([[User talk:EauOo|talk]]) 15:33, 9 September 2012 (UTC) 


Please return the first fact tag. What you call the florets are the flowers, this is the correct term for a Asteraceae flower. However, what you and the source call a flower is an inflorescence, please find a orrect source. [[User:EauOo|Eau]] ([[User talk:EauOo|talk]]) 13:05, 7 September 2012 (UTC)
:If you want information changed that is currently sourced to a reliable source, the duty is upon you to find a &quot;correct&quot; source. [[User:Dana boomer|Dana boomer]] ([[User talk:Dana boomer|talk]]) 22:47, 8 September 2012 (UTC)
::I will just add a disputed tag, maybe there is also a contradictory tag to warn readers your information contradicts everything else in Wikipedia on the topic. And, I am a volunteer, please don't insert &quot;the earth is the center of the universe,&quot; declare the source reliable, then command me the duty to replace your error. The duty does not exist. [[User:EauOo|Eau]] ([[User talk:|talk]]) 23:04, 8 September 2012 (UTC)
:::First, your dictatorial manner does not make for a collegial editing environment. Second, please don't add major cleanup banners to featured articles when you only have an issue with one word in the entire article. The cycle is [[WP:BRD|bold, revert, discuss]], not bold, revert, slap an even bigger tag on the article. The [[Asteraceae]] article itself says that the inflorescence is &quot;generally referred to as flower head&quot; - if you would like to change &quot;flower&quot; to &quot;flower head&quot;, that's fine, but I see no reason to use a term that many readers won't understand - especially when the source doesn't use that term. And yes, when an editor wants to change information that is already reliably sourced, it is upon them to find new sourcing, not to demand that others do so. [[User:Dana boomer|Dana boomer]] ([[User talk:Dana boomer|talk]]) 14:08, 9 September 2012 (UTC)
You're the one dictating my duties. And you miss the point: if the source gives false information, it is not reliable. And your fight to keep an unreliable source suggests your other sources in this article will be faulty also. I don't demand that you find new sourcing, I simply demand you remove unreliable sourcing, but I will remove it myself. And, I will add a statement to the request for mainpage that I dispute the factual accuracy of this article, and a notice here that I dispute the factual accuracy, you agree it is inaccurate, but refuse to allow the factual inaccuracy to be noted for the reader. [[User:EauOo|Eau]] ([[User talk:EauOo|talk]]) 15:33, 9 September 2012 (UTC)

Okay, I added a disputed tag for the original botany. The Wikipedia article on the [[Asteraceae]] would be a helpful starting point for anyone who wants to correct the information. [[User:EauOo|Eau]] ([[User talk:EauOo|talk]]) 23:23, 8 September 2012 (UTC)

== Disputed accuracy, original research, unreliable sources ==

This article contains inaccuracies, and it is based upon sources that contain factual inaccuracies, a source that is being promoted as reliable, when it is clearly not. This, plus the original research discussed above suggest to me that this article should not have been promoted to featured article. There is no mission of an encyclopedia that includes dumbing down the facts to the level of wrong to spair the reader's brain.

While this misinformation remains in the article, the disputed tag should remain on the article.

Featured articles do not have a free pass on spreading misinformation.

[[User:EauOo|Eau]] ([[User talk:EauOo|talk]]) 15:50, 9 September 2012 (UTC)

:Eau, could you separate out the different issues that are concerning you here? I'm uncertain if this is just about the sentence of the article that runs &quot;have focused on identifying and producing commercial varieties with larger amounts of these compounds&quot; or if there you have additional concerns as well. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 16:15, 9 September 2012 (UTC)
::So far, the sentence that says the flowers are composed of florets, since floret is a synonym for flower in the Aster family, this sentence reads as nonsense. One can dumb down the science without creating nonsense. The source contains this information which suggests the source is not reliable. In the insecticides source, the source does not say to increase the quantity, in fact, that is often a problematic genetic solution, what the scientists work the hardest on, but Dana jumped to a conclusion about it. Dana also, althouh maybe in the cabbage article, stated research studies from 7 years ago were ongoing and initially ignored my comment and did not change that.
:::I am concerned about these problems, and I feel the nature of the problems, and the editor's aggressive protection of the content, requires all sources to be checked.
:::I also believe that readers ''must'' be alerted when articles contain protected factual inaccuracies such as this one does, and I would like the disputed tag to go back up to alert the thousands of readers who come to this article while we discuss the issue. [[User:EauOo|Eau]] ([[User talk:EauOo|talk]]) 16:57, 9 September 2012 (UTC)
::::Dear Lord. Eau, I'm having a hard time believing that you're having this much of a problem over a handful of words. I've done some additional tweaking on the article, and added in a new source - hopefully this satisfy you. So far, you've accused me of original research, aggressiveness, misuse of sources, and generally being a bad editor. Not a word about how I've almost single-handedly re-written (to a much higher standard) two major food articles that you apparently had no interest in before I started working on them. Adding in a new source and making a few wording tweaks yourself would probably have been much easier than tag bombing a featured article and making demands of other editors on the talk page (something which you have asked me not to do to you, but continue to do to me). [[User:Dana boomer|Dana boomer]] ([[User talk:Dana boomer|talk]]) 21:30, 9 September 2012 (UTC)
::::Cut out the name calling. I brought these to your attention. I am not obliged to praise your work, and, when faulty, I will not. You argued with me when I pointed out factual inaccuracies and you fought to keep the inaccuracies in.
::::There are more problems with the science you want praises for adding to this article, but I resign, and leave it to your angry self to correct the issues before it lands on the main page.
:::::[[User:EauOo|Eau]] ([[User talk:EauOo|talk]]) 22:57, 9 September 2012 (UTC)
:::::: Hi, I am Dianna, and I am the person who nominated the article for a main page appearance. If there's factual inaccuracies in the article it should definitely not be on the main page until corrections are made. I will withdraw the nomination. -- [[User:Diannaa|Dianna]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 14:37, 10 September 2012 (UTC)
:::::::Hi Diannaa! I hadn't realized that you had nominated it for a main page appearance... As far as I know, there are no further inaccuracies in the article (I think I have fixed the places that Eau was concerned about, although he is apparently unwilling to acknowledge this). This article has been thoroughly checked by several of WP's top biology editors, so I highly doubt that there are major factual inaccuracies in it, as alleged by Eau. A few minor wording issues do not rise to the level of gross misuse of sources, IMO. [[User:Dana boomer|Dana boomer]] ([[User talk:Dana boomer|talk]]) 14:53, 10 September 2012 (UTC)
So, from what I've drawn from the above, the two concerns are:
:*Over how &quot;have focused on identifying and producing commercial varieties with larger amounts of these compounds&quot; has been interpreted;
:*And over &quot;Lettuce inflorescences (known colloquially as &quot;flower heads&quot;) are composed of multiple florets&quot;, and the meaning of the word floret?
If so, although I'm not a specialist in lettuces, I'm not convinced this should prevent a front-page appearance; they seem fairly minor issues to me. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 16:45, 10 September 2012 (UTC)
:Hi Hchc! Regarding the first point, I have reworked that sentence. Regarding the second point, that is the rewritten version (it previously read &quot;Lettuce flowers are composed of multiple florets&quot; and the discussion was regarding the meaning of the word flower). Eau has yet to comment on either of these changes, or to identify additional issues with the article. [[User:Dana boomer|Dana boomer]] ([[User talk:Dana boomer|talk]]) 17:05, 10 September 2012 (UTC)
::Agreed. Nice article by the way! [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 17:15, 10 September 2012 (UTC)
:FWIW, I agree with EauOo on the first point, not sure about the second (no botanical expertise here), but I think Dana's fixes are satisfactory (and were easy to make... seems to be much ado about minor changes). Would welcome further input from EauOo as to whether additional fixes are needed. [[User:Sasata|Sasata]] ([[User talk:Sasata|talk]]) 17:30, 10 September 2012 (UTC)
:: Thank you for checking this out. I am restoring my nomination, and hopefully the article will soon be selected for an appearance on the main page. - [[User:Diannaa|Dianna]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 18:40, 10 September 2012 (UTC)

I was asked to examine the issues here (not by Eau), and there are some remaining ones:
#'Greeks and Romans, who gave it the name &quot;lactuca&quot;': Later it makes it abundantly clear that it was the Romans that called it ''lactuca''.
#''Sativa'' means &quot;cultivated&quot;, not &quot;common&quot;
#'Mature lettuce flower and fruits' (illustration) should be 'Mature lettuce inflorescence in fruit'
#'Lettuce inflorescences (known colloquially as &quot;flower heads&quot;)' It's not colloquial--&quot;flower head&quot; is an accepted alternative term. Some people misunderstand it to mean a flower that is a head, rather than a head made up of flowers, but people misunderstand a lot of things. An even better term for the inflorescence is &quot;capitulum&quot;.
#'each containing a ligulate petal and reproductive system.' This is way oversimplified to the extent of being wrong. The ligule is composed of five petals all fused together (you can count their tips), and the flower also contains the pappus, which makes the parachute of the fruit.
#'stigma-containing style' is nonsense; the style and stigma are separate parts (it would be the equivalent of saying &quot;pastern-containing cannon&quot;)
#'The flowers form compressed, obovate (teardrop-shaped) dry fruits' The fruits come from a specific part of the flower, the ovary.

I'd be happy to suggest alternative wording if anyone is interested, and look at the rest of the article, but I'm rather cynical about Wikipedia now, so if you're resistant, please let me know up front and I'll go elsewhere.--[[User:Curtis Clark|Curtis Clark]] ([[User talk:Curtis Clark|talk]]) 01:47, 20 September 2012 (UTC)
:Hi Curtis, and thanks for your comments! The technical botany part of the article is obviously the weakest - if you have suggested rewordings (or perhaps new sources?) it would be fantastic - please feel free to simply edit the article yourself, as well (not that I need to give you permission, I'm just trying to make it doubly obvious that I know I don't &quot;own&quot; the article). My background is much stronger in the cultivation/production/culinary uses area. I'll begin working on your comments above (especially the first two, which are quite easy to rectify) in the morning. Thanks again, [[User:Dana boomer|Dana boomer]] ([[User talk:Dana boomer|talk]]) 01:59, 20 September 2012 (UTC)
::I made some changes; you might want to tweak the wording to make it fit better. Also, what I wrote is correct, but it may not be 100% included in the reference. If you see any issues, I can look for an additional reference.--[[User:Curtis Clark|Curtis Clark]] ([[User talk:Curtis Clark|talk]]) 18:03, 20 September 2012 (UTC)
:::Thanks Curtis, and I hope the changes I made earlier addressed the rest of your comments above. The new wording is unfortunately not supported by the sources I have in there (I think they are both available to the public?), so if you have a better source to supplement/supplant what is currently there, I would be grateful. Thanks again, [[User:Dana boomer|Dana boomer]] ([[User talk:Dana boomer|talk]]) 20:29, 20 September 2012 (UTC)
::::[http://www.efloras.org/florataxon.aspx?flora_id=1&amp;taxon_id=20701 Here's a reference] for the floral stuff; I'd add it, but you'd just have to correct my &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt; syntax. I've modified the text so that the connection to the reference, which is about the entire tribe [[Cichorieae]], is clear.--[[User:Curtis Clark|Curtis Clark]] ([[User talk:Curtis Clark|talk]]) 23:36, 21 September 2012 (UTC)
:::::OK, I've added the new ref in. My apologies for taking a few days to do so - I saw your post about the source and then completely forgot about taking action on it :( Thanks again for your help, and if you have any further comments, I'd love to hear them, [[User:Dana boomer|Dana boomer]] ([[User talk:Dana boomer|talk]]) 13:55, 24 September 2012 (UTC)

== Weaver Source ==

Quite a bit of the info in this article is cited from &quot;Weaver,&quot; who I presume is the author of a book, but I can't find a title of the book or anything else about this source.  Who is Weaver?  And how is it OK to cite him/her so heavily in this article without even proving that he/she (or the source authored by him/her) even exists?  Am I missing something?  I'm not a regular Wikipedia editor, but I use Wikipedia every day, and if I'm having trouble locating this source, I'm sure many others are, too. [[Special:Contributions/24.252.90.73|24.252.90.73]] ([[User talk:24.252.90.73|talk]]) 16:50, 13 May 2015 (UTC)

==Worthy of Note?==

Lettuce is now the first foodstuff to be grown and consumed in space. [http://www.theguardian.com/science/2015/aug/10/nasa-astronauts-lettuce-vegetables-grown-space?CMP=fb_gu] --[[User:ERAGON|ERAGON]] ([[User talk:ERAGON|talk]]) 12:47, 11 August 2015 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>taafcfog2zdm32b00wqck10in3gxcld</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
