<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:James Nesbitt</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>6438113</id>
    <revision>
      <id>722395905</id>
      <parentid>722395806</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-05-27T20:49:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>86.181.148.223</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13276">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=15:37, 17 July 2008
|action1link=Talk:James Nesbitt/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=226258233

|action2=PR
|action2date=01:51, 1 March 2009
|action2link=Wikipedia:Peer review/James Nesbitt/archive1
|action2result=reviewed
|action2oldid=274019441

|action3=FAC
|action3date=23:13, 18 April 2009
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/James Nesbitt/archive1
|action3result=not promoted
|action3oldid=283588420

|action4=PR
|action4date=14:58, 12 July 2009
|action4link=Wikipedia:Peer review/James Nesbitt/archive2
|action4result=reviewed
|action4oldid=301701366

|action5=FAC
|action5date=19:36, 22 August 2009
|action5link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/James Nesbitt/archive2
|action5result=promoted
|action5oldid=309457605

|topic=film
|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=January 22, 2012}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|blp=yes|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=yes|class=FA|filmbio-priority=mid|listas=Nesbitt, James|filmbio-work-group=yes}}
{{WikiProject Ireland |class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Northern Ireland|class=FA|importance=low}}}}

== Sarcastic comment? ==
The opening comment &quot;an actor and presenter from Northern Ireland known for his extensive range of accents all from Northern Ireland&quot; is obviously sarcastic and does not have a place here.

== Native of which town? ==
Nesbitt didn't actually grow up in Coleraine, from what I remember my uncle (another actor) telling me. He comes from a nearby town, and I forget the name of it. If anyone knows the town, please replace Coleraine with it. --[[User:Setanta747|Mal]] 20:09, 2 September 2006 (UTC)

Have now changed it to Bruogshone
I love you James Nesbitt your hot really hot even if your old no Afence

== James Nesbitt next Doctor who? ==

Look at the link I've provided.  It seems to suggest that James Nesbitt may be the next [[Doctor (Doctor Who)|Doctor Who]] when [[David Tennant]] steps down.  Would this be worth including in the article?

http://uk.tv.yahoo.com/02082007/21/nesbitt-new.html

[[User:Looneyman|Looneyman]] 20:35, 2 August 2007 (UTC)
:The rumour appears to stem from ''The Sun'', so I've sourced that. Please remember that newspapers &quot;know&quot; who the next Dr Who will be every time the current one looks like quitting. This should be treated as a rumour until confirmed or denied by the BBC (albeit a notable rumour). [[User:Brad|Brad]] 07:47, 3 August 2007 (UTC)

It's a rumour started by a comedian on a forum.

{{Talk:James Nesbitt/GA1}}

== Source ==

*{{cite news|author= Smith, Lynn|title= Should he stay or should he go Hollywood?|url= http://articles.latimes.com/2005/jan/23/entertainment/ca-murphy23|work= [[Los Angeles Times]]|publisher= Tribune Company|date= 2005-01-23}}
[[User:Bradley0110|Bradley0110]] ([[User talk:Bradley0110|talk]]) 20:32, 5 August 2008 (UTC)
*Egan, Barry (1 March 2009). &quot;[http://www.independent.ie/entertainment/film-cinema/its-good-to-talk-james-1657678.html It's good to talk, James]&quot;. ''Irish Independent'' (Independent News &amp; Media).
[[User:Bradley0110|Bradley0110]] ([[User talk:Bradley0110|talk]]) 12:43, 1 March 2009 (UTC)
*Tinney, Aaron (14 June 2009). &quot;[http://www.belfasttelegraph.co.uk/sunday-life/jimmyrsquos-pain-for-mum-may-14338487.html Jimmy's pain for mum May]&quot;. ''Belfast Telegraph'' (Independent News &amp; Media (Northern Ireland)).
[[User:Bradley0110|Bradley0110]] ([[User talk:Bradley0110|talk]]) 07:46, 15 June 2009 (UTC)

== PR checklist of individual comments ==

For my benefit so I don't have to keep returning to the PR [[User:Bradley0110|Bradley0110]] ([[User talk:Bradley0110|talk]]) 22:28, 21 March 2009 (UTC)
{{hide|Hidden |
* You need to clarify that Colin Bateman is a writer {{Y}}
* The parenthetical note is not grammatical, and in any event &quot;latter&quot; can't be used when the list has more than two items. I suggest you lose the parentheses and rephrase: &quot;...Stephen Moffat's Jekyll, the last of which gained him a Golden Globe award nomination.&quot; {{Y}} (sentence removed)
* &quot;Comedic roles are still offered him&quot; - when is &quot;still&quot;? You then refer to a 2003 BBC series, which is hardly &quot;still&quot;. I suggest you reword along the lines: &quot;He has continued to accept offers of comedic roles, appearing with...&quot; etc {{Y}} (sentence reworded)
* Having given his full birth date in the lead, is it necessary to include &quot;in 1985&quot; in the section opening? [[WP:Lead]] allows for both, though I prefer to repeat for completion's sake.
* Suggest simplify to &quot;attended his father's local primary school&quot; {{Y}} (sentence reworded)
* &quot;...the audition for which his parents 'dragged' him to&quot; is very clumsy prose. Prepositional endings should always be avoided. Try &quot;...his parents having dragged him to the audition&quot;. {{Y}} (sentence reworded)
* &quot;He continued to appear in Christmas productions, and received his Equity card...&quot; First, we have no prior information of his appearing in &quot;Christmas productions&quot;, and haven't been told what they are. Secondly, the and combines unrelated clauses in a single sentence. I suggest you rephrase the first clause, then divide the sentence. {{Y}} (sentence reworded)
* Despite enjoying...&quot; would sound better as &quot;Although he enjoyed...&quot; {{Y}} (sentence expanded)
* &quot;His part was critically praised...&quot; - his performance, rather than his part? {{Y}} (sentence reworded)
* Which performance did the NYT find &quot;jaunty and bemused&quot;? {{Y}} (sentence expanded)
* He is suddenly in America. When did he go there? Information already present
* You need to say what &quot;Central&quot; is, rather than suddenly introduce this short form of the name.  {{Y}} (&quot;CSSD&quot; abbrev introduced at first instance)
* He seems to be back in the UK. Again, some date informatio would help us follow this satge of his career. {{Y}}
* Breakthrough: Last line - you should insert [Claudia] before &quot;Harrison&quot;, so we know who's being talked about without having to use the link. {{Y}}
* &quot;The events of Bloody Sunday passd him by...&quot; etc. Did he say this? It requires some verification. Information already present
* &quot;Aside, the film and Nesbitt...&quot; etc. &quot;Aside&quot; is not a word to use in isolation like this. The sense is &quot;nevertheless&quot;, and I suggest you use this word instead. {{Y}} (sentence reworded)
* Unnecessary quote marks around &quot;household name&quot; and &quot;celebrity status&quot; {{Y}}
* Can you reword, to avoid &quot;...ITV. ITV...&quot;? {{Y}}
* &quot;The accent was discarded after a chat between Nesbitt and the director, and when Nesbitt tried it out on co-star Daniela Nardini.&quot; Discarded twice? {{Y}}
* &quot;...putting a distance between his previous work&quot; doesn't make grammatical sense. &quot;Distancing himself from his previous work&quot; is the meaning required. {{Y}}
* BBC One is normally written &quot;BBC 1&quot; {{N}} No it isn't
* Try to avoid phrases that will rapidly become out of date, like &quot;In 2009 he will appear...&quot; Something like &quot;His 2009 plans included...&quot; will save you having to repeatedly revisit the article to update it. 
* In the &quot;Other projects&quot; section, &quot;...three consecutive occasions between 2002 and 2005&quot; - which three consecutive years? {{Y}}
* Same section: &quot;He will present the 2nd National Movie Awards in September 2008&quot;. That has to be past tense now, but his sort of thing illustrates one of the main problems in an article describing an on-going career. {{Y}}

* A LARGE number of your web sources don't have last access dates. They need them. {{N}} Hard-copy sources with convenience links to respective websites do not require access dates.
|}}

== Nationality ==

Why is his nationality listed as Northern Irish, which is itself, a part of the United Kingdom? I realise being from Northern Ireland part of the UK he can choose to be called Irish or British, but if you read his biography in newspapers such as the Guardian, the Telegraph, on IMDB and even on the Northern Ireland.gov website, he is regarded as British. Why are wikipedia editors other than British ones, obsessed with supporting separatist and republican movements, albeit non-vocally. I realise Americans are pretty obsessed with the whole independence thing but it's too far when an actor even regards himself as British and you don't allow it.
:Do you have a reference that &quot;[he] regards himself as British&quot;? [[User:RashersTierney|RashersTierney]] ([[User talk:RashersTierney|talk]]) 14:01, 26 December 2012 (UTC)

:http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9d_AFzqoIMc and http://www.filmclub.org/behind-the-scenes/details/313/james-nesbitt-and-aidan-turner
::In neither of these 'refs' does Nesbitt say he is British. Checking them out proved to be a waste of time. [[User:RashersTierney|RashersTierney]] ([[User talk:RashersTierney|talk]]) 20:16, 26 December 2012 (UTC)
Furthermore I have to add, if someone doesn't say they are British but also doesn't say they're not, are we now to assume every British Citizen isn't British until they say they are? Or every person is a supporter of Irish Nationalism until they say otherwise? That's a bad precedent to set. He has never said he supports a United Ireland or Irish Nationalism, under the Good Friday agreement he can identify himself as Irish or British [not Northern Irish]. It's utter tosh frankly that he is being displayed as a nationality that doesn't exist simply so as not to upset the few nationalists that haunt these boards.  [[User:Son of the Isles|Son of the Isles]] ([[User talk:Son of the Isles|talk]]) 16:40, 28 December 2012 (UTC)

:Please note this page is [[WP:NOTFORUM|not 'a board']]. [[User:RashersTierney|RashersTierney]] ([[User talk:RashersTierney|talk]]) 20:16, 26 December 2012 (UTC)

:If that's the one thing you pick out of my above post I'm seriously starting to worry about the preservation of sense on this website. It's clearly slipping when we start referring to people as nationalities that don't exist, and calling cities such as Londonderry by names that aren't even legally certified in the countries they're a part of.  [[User:Son of the Isles|Son of the Isles]] ([[User talk:Son of the Isles|talk]]) 16:40, 28 December 2012 (UTC)
:::Unless you draw some legalistic distinction between 'nationality' and 'national identity', then a significant proportion of the population of Northern Ireland ''do'' give their nationality as 'Northern Irish', according to the [http://www.nisra.gov.uk/Census/key_stats_bulletin_2011.pdf recent census release]. [[User:RashersTierney|RashersTierney]] ([[User talk:RashersTierney|talk]]) 17:52, 28 December 2012 (UTC)
::Further to the above, the article does not and has never stated his ''nationality'' as Northern Irish. With the exception of politicians and people who explicitly describe themselves as &quot;British&quot;, any article about someone from the UK refers to them being of their constituent country, be that England, Scotland, Wales or Northern Ireland. [[User:Bradley0110|Bradley0110]] ([[User talk:Bradley0110|talk]]) 16:29, 27 December 2012 (UTC)
::::It most certainly has, [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=James_Nesbitt&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=173750155 since 2007], notwithstanding the [[Northern Irish|redirect]] to 'Northern Ireland'. [[User:RashersTierney|RashersTierney]] ([[User talk:RashersTierney|talk]]) 17:52, 28 December 2012 (UTC)
:::::Oh, it looks like I've skewered my own argument, in that it was me who changed it from &quot;from Northern Ireland&quot; to &quot;Northern Irish&quot;. However, it did go back to &quot;from Northern Ireland&quot;, probably in mid-2008. My statement above though referred to &quot;Northern Irish&quot; being interpreted as a nationality instead of simply an adjective. [[User:Bradley0110|Bradley0110]] ([[User talk:Bradley0110|talk]]) 21:40, 28 December 2012 (UTC)
::::::In the absence of a definite self-identification of some kind, I think a return to 'from Northern Ireland' is probably best, particularly since the new census considers 'Northern Irish' as a statement of national identity. [[User:RashersTierney|RashersTierney]] ([[User talk:RashersTierney|talk]]) 21:54, 28 December 2012 (UTC)
:http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emma_Thompson  Care to explain Emma Thompson, among others, who is cited quite clearly by the true Nationality, which is British, even though she is from the English constituent country? [[User:Son of the Isles|Son of the Isles]] ([[User talk:Son of the Isles|talk]]) 16:40, 28 December 2012 (UTC)
::No. It was discussed on the relevant TP. Take it up there if you wish. [[User:RashersTierney|RashersTierney]] ([[User talk:RashersTierney|talk]]) 17:52, 28 December 2012 (UTC)
http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FyGYnBsQYxs Irish tricolours at 01:45 and green, white and orange streamers decorate his trailer along with other things to &quot;remind him of home&quot; http://uk.movies.yahoo.com/nesbitt-makes-home-100959432.html. Unless he explicitly states he is Irish, British or both then I agree that the article is fine as it is by stating the fact that he is from Northern Ireland. [[User:TTWSYFree|TTWSYFree]] ([[User talk:TTWSYFree|talk]]) 03:19, 5 January 2013 (UTC)

== Advertising roles. ==

I believe Nesbitt is currently &quot;starring&quot; in 2x advertising rolls, one for Thomas Cook (in person) and another for an insurance (voice)...thing. Damn it, now I'm hearing his voice everywhere. Dat accent. Anyway, can this be added to other projects? --[[User:Somchai Sun|Somchai Sun]] ([[User talk:Somchai Sun|talk]]) 08:25, 10 August 2013 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>s8h3la5blws39b7ay0b5xaeb19d0kld</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
