<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Wife selling (English custom)</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>9540400</id>
    <revision>
      <id>556215929</id>
      <parentid>556107800</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-05-22T04:50:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MiszaBot I</username>
        <id>3797869</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot: Archiving 2 threads (older than 30d) to [[Talk:Wife selling (English custom)/Archive 4]].</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11526">{{skip to talk}}
{{talk header|search=yes}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=FAC
|action1date=23:20, 10 January 2010
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Wife selling/archive1
|action1result=promoted
|action1oldid=337048242

|action2=AFD
|action2date=1 April 2010
|action2link=Wikipedia:Articles for deletion/Wife selling
|action2result=speedily kept
|action2oldid=353448563

|dykdate=21 December 2009
|maindate=1 April 2010
|currentstatus=FA
}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 4
|minthreadsleft = 4
|algo = old(30d)
|archive = Talk:Wife selling (English custom)/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Auto archiving notice |bot=MiszaBot I |age=1 |units=month }}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Business &amp; Economics|class=FA|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject England|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Feminism|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Women's History|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
}}

{{press
|author=Anon|date=1 April 2010|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/technology/news/7543967/April-Fools-Best-jokes-from-the-tech-world.html|title=April Fools: Best jokes from the tech world|org=''Daily Telegraph''|section=Technology News| author2=Anon| title2=The best April Fools day jokes on the web| org2=''The Independent''|url2=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/media/the-best-april-fools-day-jokes-on-the-web-1933414.html| date2=1 April 2010| author3=Anon| title3=Top 10 April Fools' Day Fake News Items for 2010| org3=[[PC World (magazine)|PC World]]|url3=http://www.pcworld.com/article/193113/top_10_april_fools_day_fake_news_items_for_2010.html| date3=1 April 2010
|title4=April Fools 2010: The Definitive List |url4=http://techcrunch.com/april-fools-shenanigans/ |org4=[[TechCrunch]] |date4=March 31, 2010 |author4=Anon
}}
{{British-English}}

== An account of wife selling in 1787 ==

I found [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=z2b8jCQ0PtkC&amp;pg=PA15#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false this] while looking for something else (honest!), middle column, about two thirds of the way down, beginning &quot;A correspondent who may be relied on...&quot;. I had a quick look but couldn't see any reference to it here, so I thought I'd pass it on, in case it was useful. No worries if not! I've posted this to [[User talk:Malleus Fatuorum#Wife selling anyone...?|Malleus Fatuorum's talk page]] too. Cheers. [[User:Nortonius|Nortonius]] ([[User talk:Nortonius|talk]]) 18:29, 13 January 2012 (UTC) p.s. Scroll up to page 13 in the Google Books preview linked above for clear reference to a publication date for this on 11 January 1787. The intervening page 14 is missing from the preview - or, it is for me at any rate!

== See Also - Organ Trade ==

I created a see also section and added the link to [[organ trade]].   ‎Malleus Fatuorum undid my edit with the following explanation: &quot;I hate stupid arseholes who don't understand the purpose of a See also section&quot;.  So...what's the purpose of the see also section?  From my perspective...the topic of selling organs is more than just peripherally relevant to the topic of selling wives.  --[[User:Xerographica|Xerographica]] ([[User talk:Xerographica|talk]]) 01:19, 13 November 2012 (UTC)

:Let's have the full story Xerographica, not just your edited highlights. You added that daft link with the explanation that &quot;I hate pages without see also sections&quot;. Don't you agree that's pretty dumb? [[User:Malleus Fatuorum|Malleus]] [[User_talk:Malleus_Fatuorum|Fatuorum]] 01:27, 13 November 2012 (UTC)

::What difference does my explanation make?  Either selling organs is...or it isn't...peripherally relevant to selling people.  How would my explanation possibly alter the relevance?  My explanation was '''additional''' information.  I am a browser...which means that from my perspective, a page without a see also section is an educational dead end.  If people aren't interested in peripherally relevant topics then the see also section does them absolutely no harm.  But if people are interested in peripherally relevant topics...then the existence of a see also section might benefit them.  Therefore, it is our responsibility, as editors, to provide readers with topics in the see also section that are at least peripherally relevant.  --[[User:Xerographica|Xerographica]] ([[User talk:Xerographica|talk]]) 01:44, 13 November 2012 (UTC)
:::Xerographica, your personal preferences aside, see [[WP:SEEALSO]]: &quot;The links in the &quot;See also&quot; section should be relevant, should reflect the links that would be present in a comprehensive article on the topic, and should be limited to a reasonable number...Thus, many high-quality, comprehensive articles do not have a &quot;See also&quot; section.&quot; This tells us two things: first, that topics that are only peripherally relevant should not be included; and second, that an article which is comprehensive (a requirement for [[WP:FA|featured]] status, which this article has) need not have any such section. [[User:Nikkimaria|Nikkimaria]] ([[User talk:Nikkimaria|talk]]) 05:03, 13 November 2012 (UTC)
::::Perhaps you should have continued reading...&quot;The links in the &quot;See also&quot; section do not have to be directly related to the topic of the article, because one purpose of the &quot;See also&quot; links is to enable readers to explore topics that are only peripherally relevant.&quot;  --[[User:Xerographica|Xerographica]] ([[User talk:Xerographica|talk]]) 07:08, 13 November 2012 (UTC)
:::::The edit summary was unfortunate, but I agree completely that it's a not a link that would belong in a see also section on this topic. I don't even see how it's peripherally related. --[[User:Onorem|Onorem]][[Special:Contributions/Onorem|♠]][[User talk:Onorem|Dil]] 07:26, 13 November 2012 (UTC)
::::::1st batter up didn't understand the point of the see also section.  2nd batter up didn't understand the point of reading the entire see also policy.  And here you are...the 3rd batter up...and you need me to explain why selling body parts is relevant to selling entire bodies.  Forget it...there's no way I can explain it without sounding extremely condescending.  --[[User:Xerographica|Xerographica]] ([[User talk:Xerographica|talk]]) 08:05, 13 November 2012 (UTC)

:::::::There is no relationship between a form of divorce and the trade in organs.  Your addition was irrelevant. &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:grey 0.2em 0.2em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;[[User:Parrot of Doom|Parrot]] [[User talk:Parrot of Doom|of Doom]]&lt;/span&gt; 10:48, 13 November 2012 (UTC)

::::::::If it's merely a form of divorce then [[put your money where your mouth is]] and remove this article from the [[Portal:Economics|business/economics portal]].  --[[User:Xerographica|Xerographica]] ([[User talk:Xerographica|talk]]) 12:15, 13 November 2012 (UTC)

:::::::::You're just making yourself look foolish.  I couldn't care less about portals - as, I suspect, is the case for about 99.9% of people who visit Wikipedia.  By the way, do you often create articles with absolutely no citations or sources? &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:grey 0.2em 0.2em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;[[User:Parrot of Doom|Parrot]] [[User talk:Parrot of Doom|of Doom]]&lt;/span&gt; 13:39, 13 November 2012 (UTC)

:::::::::Like Parrot of Doom, I couldn't care less about portals. I didn't add this article to the Economics/business portal, so why not ask whoever did? I didn't even know there ''was'' such a portal. But you've still to explain the similarity of organ selling to a form of divorce. Should be interesting to see what you manage to come up with, or more what likely you don't manage to come up with. If you consider wife selling to be a sale of bodies, which I don't, then surely a more obvious link would be to slavery? I'd be particularly interested to hear from you of any cases in which someone succeeded in setting up a business to sell wives in 18th or 19th-century England.  [[User:Malleus Fatuorum|Malleus]] [[User_talk:Malleus_Fatuorum|Fatuorum]] 14:31, 13 November 2012 (UTC)

:::No, a page without wikilinks would be an &quot;educational dead end&quot;. [[User:Malleus Fatuorum|Malleus]] [[User_talk:Malleus_Fatuorum|Fatuorum]] 14:35, 13 November 2012 (UTC)
I can't see that [[Organ trade]] is &quot;peripherally relevant&quot;. It's more like &quot;extremely tenuously relevant&quot;. --[[User:Dweller|Dweller]] ([[User talk:Dweller|talk]]) 15:19, 13 November 2012 (UTC)
:What about the concept of [[self ownership]]?  Is it...A. &quot;relevant&quot; or B. &quot;peripherally relevant&quot; or C. &quot;extremely tenuously relevant&quot;?  --[[User:Xerographica|Xerographica]] ([[User talk:Xerographica|talk]]) 21:06, 13 November 2012 (UTC)

::How about D. &quot;completely irrelevant&quot;? &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:grey 0.2em 0.2em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;[[User:Parrot of Doom|Parrot]] [[User talk:Parrot of Doom|of Doom]]&lt;/span&gt; 21:35, 13 November 2012 (UTC)

:::So women being the property of their husbands is &quot;completely irrelevant&quot; to the concept of [[self ownership]]?  Here's what it says in the article...
::::Women were completely subordinated to their husbands after marriage, the husband and wife becoming one legal entity, a legal status known as coverture. As the eminent English judge Sir William Blackstone wrote in 1753: &quot;the very being, or legal existence of the woman, is suspended during the marriage, or at least is consolidated and incorporated into that of her husband: under whose wing, protection and cover, she performs everything&quot;. Married women could not own property in their own right, and were indeed themselves the property of their husbands. 
:::The idea of women being property of their husbands, the idea of people being slaves, the idea of a fetus being the property of a woman, the idea of being able to sell your own organs...they are all relevant to the concept of [[self-ownership]]...and as such, they are all at least peripherally relevant to each other.  --[[User:Xerographica|Xerographica]] ([[User talk:Xerographica|talk]]) 22:01, 13 November 2012 (UTC)

::::As relevant as an arse is to an elbow. &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:grey 0.2em 0.2em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;[[User:Parrot of Doom|Parrot]] [[User talk:Parrot of Doom|of Doom]]&lt;/span&gt; 23:41, 13 November 2012 (UTC)

== þ vs y ==

Per [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Wife_selling_(English_custom)&amp;diff=556070064&amp;oldid=556035451 this diff], where the letter &quot;þ&quot;, or thorn, was swapped back to a &quot;y&quot;, I thought that's probably right for a 17th century source – it would presumably have been &quot;þ&quot; in a much earlier source – but noticed that the sentence isn't supported by a ref. Nor is the information there supported by the reffed source for the next sentence, which I've checked online. D'oh! Though, that 17th century source does use a &quot;y&quot; instead of a &quot;þ&quot;. Btw I found another instance of historical wife selling in a book I was looking at the other night, I'll dig it out in a bit and post details here. [[User:Nortonius|Nortonius]] ([[User talk:Nortonius|talk]]) 09:41, 21 May 2013 (UTC)

== Another example, FWIW… ==

I found this in Murphy, S. (ed.), ''Cox's Fragmenta An Historical Miscellany'', History Press, Stroud, 2011, ISBN 978-0-7524-6329-2, p. 125:

&lt;blockquote&gt;''DISGRACEFUL TRANSACTION''&lt;br&gt;A man, a few days since, sold his wife, in a halter, for 1s. 6d. in the public market, at Wellington, and allowed the purchaser a quart of ale to drink his health.&lt;br&gt;''Jackson's Oxford Journal'', Saturday 8 February 1817 (v.34, p.8)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Maybe it's already covered in an existing ref or something, but I thought it might be useful. [[User:Nortonius|Nortonius]] ([[User talk:Nortonius|talk]]) 14:08, 21 May 2013 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>rgpqnpmeab210mkg2l3kxxxhuvy2kir</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
