<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Action Park</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>4107397</id>
    <revision>
      <id>742424028</id>
      <parentid>740985702</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-03T16:46:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot (v1.2.4)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="72212">{{WikiProject New Jersey|importance=mid|class=B}}
{{WikiProject Amusement Parks|importance=mid|class=B}}
{{high traffic|date=June 26, 2012|site=Longform.org|url=http://longform.org/2012/06/26/action-park/}}
== Discrepancy? ==

The article lists both the Alpine Slide and the Kayak Experience as resulting in the first patron deaths.  I have no idea which, if either, of these are correct, but I'm sure that somebody does.&lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment was added by [[User:70.174.180.183|70.174.180.183]] ([[User talk:70.174.180.183|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/70.174.180.183|contribs]]){{#if:{{{2|}}}|&amp;#32;{{{2}}}|}}.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

:The Alpine Slide resulted in the first death, but it was an ''employee'' who got killed. The first dead patron was on the Kayak Experience. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] 05:42, 7 May 2006 (UTC)
::Look at the &quot;Fatalities&quot; section. The first patron death was in the wave pool, according to that section (which at least gives dates). I've corrected the &quot;Kayak Experience&quot; section to conform with &quot;Fatalities.&quot; --[[User:Tkynerd|Tkynerd]] 00:50, 27 August 2006 (UTC)

== Citation Needed / Neutrality Dispute  ==

Where is all of this information coming from? Can we have a citation?

Also, this article is written in the tone of an partisan editorial, and not as a neutral information source. (E.g. &quot;...underaged, underpaid and sometimes under-the-influence employees...&quot;)&lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[User:Mynamejonascuomo|Mynamejonascuomo]] ([[User talk:Mynamejonascuom|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Mynamejonascuom|contribs]]) {{{2|}}}.&lt;/small&gt;


This needs change.

:Agreed.  I see a number of loaded phrases such as &quot;shady business dealings&quot;.  I think this article should be flagged POV.  --[[User:Dmuth|Douglas Muth]] 13:45, 21 August 2006 (UTC)

::Well, a lot of this does come with the references section. I should put the footnotes in. But it is pretty much accepted and reported fact that the employees of the park were as described. And Gene Mulvihill's company ''did'' get in trouble with the SEC.&lt;br&gt;Of course, some of the wording could be changed. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] 00:54, 27 August 2006 (UTC)
:::One thing I would like to see is some documentation of the statement, early in the article, that increasing numbers of personal-injury lawsuits forced the closing of more and more rides and eventually the park itself. Since I became fascinated with this article yesterday (I'd never even heard of the park before!), I've been looking at information about it on the Web, but haven't seen much detail about lawsuits at all. --[[User:Tkynerd|Tkynerd]] 02:42, 27 August 2006 (UTC)
::::A great deal of the facts in the article come from the two ''Weird NJ'' articles. I did mean to sit down and put in refs but I just fell asleep for a couple of hours.
::::One thing that should be clarified about that is that not so much the actual lawsuits, but merely quick settlements at the mere threat of one, were instrumental in sapping the park's financial resources in its later years. Someone ''did'' look and found very few actual lawsuits (But Action Park's well-deserved reputation probably led its insurance company to just settle for costs and a little extra, knowing that it would be hard to win with juries ore judges). [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] 05:45, 27 August 2006 (UTC)
::::OK, I just did some of the footnoting. Good thing ... I found my main source for the corporate history of GAR had been our own article on [[Mountain Creek]], which I've long suspected of being written by someone on the inside of Intrawest (since the pics originally in it were copyvio). I found sourcing which holds the part of GAR up better. They were investigated not by the federal government but the state; Mulvihill did in fact take a plea in late 1984. I also changed &quot;shady&quot; to &quot;questionable&quot;, a bit less POV.
::::However, I'm getting tired and I can't stay up all night doing this. More tomorrow. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] 06:42, 27 August 2006 (UTC)

I agree. It needs to be toned down and the many errors corrected. 
[[User:69.255.59.191|69.255.59.191]] 02:32, 16 February 2007 (UTC) Chris Ish

:The article cites the ''Weird NJ'' coverage, which is about the only extensive coverage there is out there (until I get to the ''Herald'' articles Joanne Austin seemed to be using as source material for her main article) that meets our [[WP:RS|reliable source]] guidelines (coverage which is in two issues of the magazine and the book ''Weird NJ, Vol. 2''. I saw your recently reverted edit; certainly, [[WP:AGF|assuming good faith]], you have your point of view and are probably telling the truth as you believe it to be.&lt;p&gt;But &quot;[[WP:OR|I was there, so trust me]]&quot; is ''not'' a standard we accept for including information in articles as it's not [[WP:V|verifiable]] independently. Anyone can go look up the two issues of ''Weird NJ'' and see that the cited facts are as reported in the magazine (which is why it does not go over well to remove cited facts from an article, unless you have serious questions about the reliability of the source and ''not'' the accuracy of the facts themselves). All we do here is reflect the world, not report it.&lt;p&gt;Chris, if you have your version to compete with Fergus's and DeSaye's, and want to see it reflected here, what I strongly suggest you do is write it up and send it to ''Weird NJ'', attn: Joanne Austin. Once it's published there, it can be referenced here. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] 03:12, 16 February 2007 (UTC)

I'll consider doing that. I would point out that you do mention personal comments from someone named Tom Fergus (he must have been after my time) as a source for some material so I must admit to being a little confused about what is acceptable as a reference. I have my doubts about how willing to print corrections so long after the fact a publication will be. Some of the erros are so glaring and obvious that I doubt you will find them in print anywhere - such as the fact that the Kayak ride was in Motor World, not Water World, and that the Tarzan swing pool was so cold because it was a fresh spring and certainly not stagnant (stagment water would have been warm - think about it). As a long time employee who was working in the frist aid department when several of the accidents and deaths occured (inlcuding the kayak fatality) and was the cliffs supervisor the year after the drowning occured there you must admit that I would know a lot of these things. I would be willing to be a named source on par with Mr. Fergus. 
[[User:162.129.236.43|162.129.236.43]] 18:22, 16 February 2007 (UTC)Chris Ish

:The Tom Fergus quotes are in the ''Weird NJ'' articles that Daniel used as major [[WP:RS|sources]], which is why they can be used. --[[User:Tkynerd|Tkynerd]] 19:01, 16 February 2007 (UTC)

:It ''does'' make sense if the Tarzan Spring was cold (as indeed I remember it being) by virtue of being a spring. But that can't just be in the article because we sort of agree on it here. It needs to be in a published source. We had a brief discussion about the reliability of ''[[Weird NJ]]'' [[Wikipedia talk:Reliable_sources/archive10#The Devil.'s Tree and related questionsa about Weird NJ|here]]; we seem to have accepted it (If you think the stuff in the article is questionable, you should see what I take out every now and then). Also, remember their article was largely compiled from ''New Jersey Herald'' stories, which may have made the errors originally and which I'd like to see myself at some point. &quot;Reliability&quot; on Wikipedia means &quot;if it's wrong, it's their fault, not ours&quot;.&lt;p&gt;Don't worry about ''Weird NJ'' not publishing your letter ... they are always publishing letters and new articles about things they first covered long ago. Based on what they've published in the past about Action Park, I think they'd be delighted to include a long letter by a former employee willing to sign his own name to it. The next issue isn't due till May or so ... you might get it in even by then.&lt;p&gt;Also, if you're not familiar with the magazine and you want copies of the two articles, I'd be delighted to make a PDF and email it to you. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] 22:46, 16 February 2007 (UTC)

I tried to find the artciles on-line. It looks like they archive the tables of contents on their site but not the full articles - so I think I will take you up on that. It looks like you can e-mail them through their website but if you have more specific contact info that would be helpful. &quot;The New Jersey Herald&quot; was the local paper (that name brings back memories). It was/is very small with a circulation largely restricted to Sussex County NJ. They are small enough that I am mentioned in it many times for one thing or another - they had extensive coverage of high school sports and other local events. As you can imagine the writers tried their best but were not all of the calibre that readers of &quot;The Times&quot; are accustomed. The articles often did have more &quot;color&quot; than you usually find in newspapers. As I said before, it is a small operation. If I have a list of references I'll bet I could help get the original articles either directly from them or possiby from one of the local libraries. I'm sure many of them used to archive The Herald on microfiche and may still have it going back that far. I live in Maryland now and all of my relatives have left the area so I would have to persuade people to do it through mail and e-mail, not in person. [[User:69.255.59.191|69.255.59.191]] 13:50, 17 February 2007 (UTC)Chris Ish c_ish@comcast.net

This article seems awfully biased. It is not an article about Action Park itself, but about how dangerous the park was. For instance, the first sentence in the Alpine slide section barely describes what the ride is before it derails into negative commentary. I think information about injuries can be appropriate, but it should not be the focus of the whole article (or the title should be changed to reflect the angle of the article). And I am not an expert on Action Park, but I did go there a few times and I think this article would definitely present a skewed picture of what the park is like to anyone who did not visit it.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/216.15.62.202|216.15.62.202]] ([[User talk:216.15.62.202|talk]]) 22:50, 8 August 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:The history of Action Park is largely the history of its rides and the grief they created. I don't think you need to go into too much detail to describe an alpine slide. I decided to group the sourced reports on injuries on specific rides with the rides themselves because otherwise the article would and could be fragmented ... you'd have to keep flipping back and forth to understand what the ride was. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] ([[User talk:Daniel Case|talk]]) 13:56, 9 August 2008 (UTC)

== 1984 death? ==

I've added a footnote linking to a NYT article about the 1984 death at Action Park. That NYT article, which is very short, doesn't mention a heart attack or the Tarzan Swing. Can anyone confirm that the NYT article refers to the same incident as our article? --[[User:Tkynerd|Tkynerd]] 03:12, 27 August 2006 (UTC)

:Apparently, it does not ... my source for the 1984 incident related to the heart attack is the ''Weird NJ'' article (which does not in turn enumerate its own sources the way we are supposed to, although it suggests extensive research through the archives of the ''New Jersey Herald''). While it doesn't say so, it clearly indicates that death happened in ... The Grave Pool!, whereas the heart attack was connected to the Tarzan Swing.&lt;br&gt;It looks like that Times article is yet another death related to Action Park, and we can update the body count to six. Congratulations Tkynerd for some effective research! [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] 19:28, 27 August 2006 (UTC)
::Thanks, Daniel! :-) This leaves me wondering what DID happen with that case noted in the NYT. It's clear that wasn't the Grave Pool, which was larger than the pool the Times article describes. I guess I was wondering if this might actually be the Tarzan Swing case, and maybe the Times just didn't have many details about the case when they wrote that item. In any case, 300 swimmers and 20 lifeguards sounds like a hell of a lot for a 110- by 50-foot pool...or am I wrong? --[[User:Tkynerd|Tkynerd]] 22:11, 27 August 2006 (UTC)

:::Or the Times (the AP, rather, or whoever filed the story before it hit the wire) got the details wrong. Believe me, it was (and is) the only really large pool there. The only pool most people go swimming in. But I'll want more details. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] 01:08, 28 August 2006 (UTC)

Actually, you are either missing a death or maybe one was misattributed as being in the wavepool (I'm pretty sure it is the former). One person drowned in the cliff diving area. I'm pretty sure it was in the summer of 1985. I was the supervisor of the cliffs in 1987, a lifeguard there in 1986 and I think it was the year before that. I was working as a first-aider there in 1985 (I did that from 1983-1986) and recall that it happened while I was there but on one of my days off. That area is still open and pictures of it can be seen on the Mountain Creek website (http://www.mountaincreekwaterpark.com/pages/attr_et.html). The &quot;air slide&quot; (they list under &quot;bombs away&quot; - the first thumbnial) and the cliffs (big and little moe - which is what we used to call them too - the third thumbnail) all let out into a 20 foot deep pool. At the time of the drowning the bottom was left unpainted in order to preserve the natural feel of a jungle watering hole. Someone went in (I forget from which ride) and didn't come up. The guardes noted it immediately but despite forming a standard search line were not able to find him. The currents took the body into a corner right under where the search line started (under the air slide) and as they took the first descent at the usual angle they swam right over him and then spent a long time searching the rest of the pool. After that the bottom was painted white - just as it is pictured now. I've searched the web and can't find any mention of it. I just sent an e-mail to the NJ Herald asking of they can give some assistance with this. I'll let you know if they help me out.

== YouTube links ==
[[Image:Information_icon.svg|left|30px]] This article is one of [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Special:Linksearch&amp;target=%2A.youtube.com&amp;limit=500&amp;offset=10000 thousands] on Wikipedia that have a link to YouTube in it.  Based on the [[WP:EL|External links]] policy, most of these should probably be removed.  I'm putting this message here, on this talk page, to request the regular editors take a look at the link and make sure it doesn't violate policy.  In short: 1. '''99% of the time YouTube should not be used as a [[WP:V|source]]'''. 2. '''[[WP:C#Linking_to_copyrighted_works|We must not link to material that violates someones copyright]]'''.  If you are not sure if the link on this article should be removed, feel free to ask me on my talk page and I'll review it personally.  Thanks. ---[[User:J.smith|J.S]] ([[User_talk:J.smith|t]]|[[Special:Contributions/J.smith|c]]) 07:22, 7 November 2006 (UTC)

== There are some errors in the deaths/ references.  ==

I'm not sure how to edit the text without screwing up the references so I will point it out to you here: 

The sentence that reads; &quot;On August 27 of that year, an 18-year-old from Brooklyn drowned in the Wave Pool.[22],&quot; should say:

&quot;On August 27 of that year, an 20-year-old from Brooklyn drowned in a pool.[21]&quot; 

I agree with what you said in the other discussion that the description of this pool doesn't sound big enough to be the wave pool, which was much larger than 110x50 feet. This might be the cliff diving pool incident that I have been talking about. [[User:69.255.59.191|69.255.59.191]] 20:46, 17 February 2007 (UTC)Chris Ish

==Comments==
Hi everyone, Chris Ish ([[User:69.255.59.191|69.255.59.191]]) asked me to take a look at the article because he (I'm assuming &quot;he&quot; because of the name, if I'm wrong correct me and accept my appologies) had some concerns about NPOV issues.  He seems like a reasonable person and willing to compromise, and has expressed a desire not to have this disagreement turn into a bigger deal with formal dispute resolution and all that, so this is good.  I think we'll be able to settle on something mutually satisfactory.  I feel I'm a neutral party in this dispute, never having heard of the park before now.  I've looked over the comments here and on Chris's talk page, as well as the article itself (and did some copy editing, but left alone more complex content issues).  Here are some comments:
*''Its popularity, however, went hand in hand with a reputation for poorly-designed, unsafe rides; inattentive, underaged, underpaid and sometimes under-the-influence employees; equally intoxicated and underprepared visitors — and the poor safety record that followed from this perfect storm of circumstances''
**&lt;s&gt;This requires a source.&lt;/s&gt;

***I should put it in quotes because that's pretty much taken word-for-word from ''Weird NJ''.

**This sentence does strike me as having some NPOV problems.  As I understand it, &lt;s&gt;&quot;however&quot; is a [[Wikipedia:words to avoid|word to be avoided]] in this context.&lt;/s&gt;  However, (heh) the facts, if they can be referenced, should remain.  
**The sentence strikes me as having some interpretation on the part of the writer.  I'd encourage a rewrite of the sentence that merely states the bare facts.  If it had a reputation, find a source where someone says this.  List the events that happened.  So, for example, rather than saying &quot;underpaid and sometimes under-the-influence employees&quot;, say something like, &quot;employees were paid below-average wages for the type of work, and there were seven reports of employees being intoxicated on the job.&lt;ref&gt;bluh&lt;/ref&gt;&quot;  I realise this is the lead for more information, a lot of which is really well referenced and specific, but I still think the &quot;show don't tell&quot; thing is important here.
*''Things started to darken, however, with two deaths in summer 1984 and the legal and financial problems that stemmed from the lawsuits''
**This sounds POV.  I'd suggest, &quot;Then, in the summer of [[1984]], two deaths occured at the park, causing legal and financial difficulties for the park due to lawsuits.&quot; &lt;s&gt;Or something less crappily worded.&lt;/s&gt;

***Will do.

*''for some visitors, the park's reputation merely added to the thrill''
**I'm not sure how we can state this confidently.  Is there some source that says this?

***''Weird NJ'', and some of the cited blogs, again.

*Hate to say this, but I'm concerned that the weird NJ article might not be a reliable source.  From looking at its website and wp entry, it looks like a sensationalist magazine, perhaps not the biggest stickler for the bare facts.  Also, if I understand the above discussion correctly, it doesn't cite its sources after specific facts.  If it is decided that the magazine is not a reliable source, we'll have to find other references for potentially controversial information, or remove it if we can't. :(  An exception to this, though, is the source for the statement that it's been nicknamed traction park: the fact that the magazine itself is using that nickname is enough for me.


**We already discussed that at the [[WP:RS|reliable sources]] talk page (is that the one you're referring to?). In the many articles  I've done here about things that have been heavily discussed in its pages, are part of the two books compiled from the magazine's pages and are part of New Jersey culture ([[The Devil's Tree]] and [[Clinton Road]], primarily but not exclusively), I have only included things discussed in extensive articles that often show signs of being heavily researched through local historical archives and newspaper records, which are often credited in the text. If you saw the print editions of the magazine (I repeat my offer to Chris to privately email you PDFs of the two articles), you'd understand it is not like the website (after all, they want you to buy it, not read the website for free).&lt;p&gt;They don't list their sources after articles? Neither does ''[[The New York Times]]'', but we use them as a source. Remember, &quot;reliable&quot; is about getting us off the hook here. We don't and can't vouch for every source we reprint material from.
  
*In 1992, five people died in a bus accident on the way there.[7] While for once the park and its rides were not responsible for deaths associated with it, this began to taint it.
**I'm not sure how this is relevant, or what &quot;taint it&quot; means here.

***Again this is from the article. This led to a decline in attendance.

**&lt;s&gt;I'd at least suggest taking out &quot;for once&quot;&lt;/s&gt;.  Aside from the POV sound of the wording, surely there were other times where deaths occured related to going to or coming from the park and the park wasn't responsible.
*''Action Park's alpine slide descended the mountain roughly below the ski area's [[Gondola lift|gondola]], resulting in much verbal harassment and sometimes [[expectoration|spitting]] from passengers going up for their turn, who would often be entertained by the accidents they witnessed while at the same time hoping to avoid similar fates.''
**&lt;s&gt;Cite a source or remove&lt;/s&gt;

***Will do. I thought I had.

*''But the real safety problem was the [[sled]]s themselves''
**Editorializing and interpreting.  &lt;s&gt;Just state what dangers existed.&lt;/s&gt;
*''This was [[black humor|a very dark joke]], as the slide led to the first fatality at the park''
**&lt;s&gt;Remove dark joke clause: editorializing&lt;/s&gt;
*''In contrast to other rides, this attraction was fairly safe''
**Editorializing
*The article does have lots of neutral, well-referenced info, which is great.  
*The article uses vague words like &quot;many&quot;, &quot;frequent&quot;, &quot;numerous&quot;, etc., uh, frequently.  &lt;s&gt;I'd suggest being more specific&lt;/s&gt;, since this is both a POV and a factual problem.
*For example: ''Many visitors weren't aware that the pool depth increased as one got closer to the far end, and only remembered or realized that they couldn't [[swimming|swim]] when they were in over their heads and the waves were going full blast''
**In addition to the vague &quot;many&quot; problem, I have a concern about how we can confidently state this, without a citation.  
*''It was cold enough, in fact, that the lifeguards had to rescue people on some occasions who went into shock from the sudden chill and couldn't swim out''
**Shock is a medical term referring to an inadequately full circulatory system.  I think this is a colloquial use of the term, but I'm concerned that the claim is not medically accurate.
***Wording changed so &quot;shock&quot; isn't used. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] 14:57, 2 March 2007 (UTC)  
*''incredibly steep slopes''
**&lt;s&gt;Just say how steep they are (i.e. what angle).&lt;/s&gt;
*Overall, I feel that the article focuses heavily on the dangers of the park and might be seen as biased due to that.  To me, it reads like the writer has an agenda: to convince us that the park was unsafe.  
*I also feel like the tone of the article is sometimes too informal, written in a style similar to what I imagine the Weird NJ article is written in: kind of sensationalist.  In many cases, I think wording could be changed to help this: &quot;Sudden turns would send the rafts careening&quot;, &quot;slammed into&quot;, etc.
*Chris, unfortunately I must discourage you from editing the article directly, because of your past involvement with the park (see [[WP:COI]] for the guideline on conflict of interest).  However, you can propose changes here and I or another editor can review them and determine whether they should be added in.  
*Also, the other editors that have mentioned above that personal experience can't be used are right.  Of course we believe you are who you say you are and don't think you're making stuff up, but since it's theoretically possible for someone to fake it, there has to be a reliable published source in order to comply with the [[WP:V|verifiability]] policy.
I stopped looking through the article at &quot;Other attractions&quot;; I felt I have too much here already.  Let's discuss this far and work on more later.  I'm suggesting a large pruning of the article: removal of unsourcable info.  Thoughts? [[user:delldot|delldot]] | &lt;small&gt;[[user talk:delldot|talk]]&lt;/small&gt; 21:57, 18 February 2007 (UTC)

:A lot of what you cite can be addressed simply by putting more footnotes in. To a certain extent, the tone was influenced slightly by working from the article as I was putting it together a year ago.&lt;p&gt;It's not POV, it's a fact: the park ''was'' unsafe. I didn't get hurt when I went there, probably because I just looked at certain rides and said &quot;you gotta be kidding me&quot;. But not everyone did.&lt;p&gt;I'm glad you saw how much I ''did'' try to source; I knew the article would never fly without it. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] 03:06, 19 February 2007 (UTC)

Than-you for your time, interest and comments. I agree that my not editting it directly is reasonable. I appreciate Dan's willingness to send me the articles from Wierd NJ and repeat my desire that he do so. I have found Dan to reasonable throughout this and am confident that if given other sources that he will update the article appropriately. If I may be so bold to make one more editorial comment: how dengerous the park was depends on what you compare it to. It was not a traditional type of passive - strap you in and toss you about - park. The rides required active participation and some physical ability from the patrons. It would be more appropriate to compare it to other similar activities than to the more common amusement parks (which also report deaths and injuries).&lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment was added by [[User:69.255.59.191|69.255.59.191]] ([[User talk:69.255.59.191|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/69.255.59.191|contribs]]){{#if:{{{2|}}}|&amp;#32;{{{2}}}|}}.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

:OK, but it won't be tonight ... I'm working on some road articles and it's getting late. I'll scan the pages tomorrow. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] 06:00, 19 February 2007 (UTC)

::Great, I'm glad everyone's willing to work together on this. I commend you both for your mature approach to this. Thanks for being willing to send Chris a PDF of the article, Daniel.  I appreciate your offer to send me a copy and would like to take you up on it.   Some of your responses to my comments suggest to me that the article may be too similar to the source, and could be a problem under [[WP:CV]] (which I assume you're familiar with).  As you probably know, even if it's not copied word-for-word, a copyright problem will exist if the material is too closely paraphrased.  If you email me a copy of the article, I can look to determine whether I think the wording is too close.  Again, I think the article uses too much material from the Wierd NJ source, and some should be removed.  A theme park as popular and unsafe as this one certainly seems to have been would surely have received more media attention that we can use.  Is [[Wikipedia talk:Reliable sources/archive10#The Devil's Tree and related questionsa about Weird NJ|this]] the discussion at [[WT:RS]] you're referring to, Daniel?  If not could you link to it?  Thanks very much, sorry to put you to all this work! Oh, one last minor thing: Chris, please sign your posts on the page using four tildes (&lt;nowiki&gt;~~~~&lt;/nowiki&gt;) so subsequent readers can know who posted what.  Also, Daniel, I'm not really sure how to deal with this, but it makes it a little confusing if you reply right under my comments, and it may look to subsequent readers like I posted it all myself and am just schizophrenic ;)  Maybe in the future you could copy and paste parts of my comments with replies to them?  Or I could number my comments in the future so you can just be like, &quot;in response to #1...&quot; Have other ideas?  Anyway, thanks guys, sorry to be so nitpicky.  [[user:delldot|delldot]] | &lt;small&gt;[[user talk:delldot|talk]]&lt;/small&gt; 04:25, 20 February 2007 (UTC)

:::Rereading them as I was scanning them, it doesn't seem like there would be copyright issues (Really, I'm not that sloppy). If anything migrated, it was the ''tone'' of the article, which your suggested changes go a long way to addressing.&lt;p&gt;There ''is'' more media; but it's not really available online (The ''Herald'', as I said, doesn't put its arhives online (and in any case I doubt they'd digitize clips that old) and the ''[[Newark Star-Ledger]] has the same issue). It would at present take a nice day trip down to [[Newton, New Jersey|Newton]] to go look at the latter; I don't think I have the time yet.&lt;p&gt;I'll change my replying style for your posts in the future. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] 06:40, 20 February 2007 (UTC)

::::I have the WeirdNJ article now, and some time on my hands, so I'd like to go through the article and make the changes I suggested as well as others, which will involve trimming some out.  Are there objections to this?  If you're ok with me having a go at this, you can undo specific changes I make or we can discuss it here afterwards if you don't like it.  [[user:delldot|delldot]] | &lt;small&gt;[[user talk:delldot|talk]]&lt;/small&gt; 23:36, 24 February 2007 (UTC)

::::::Yeah, I was going to do some of them later tonight. As I said, a lot of it is just putting in references. If we do, can we keep that &quot;sometimes under-the-influence employees&quot; bit since it can be cited? [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] 23:59, 24 February 2007 (UTC)

:::::::Well, the more specific the better (e.g. number of times...), but if we find a source that says &quot;sometimes under the influence&quot; I guess I wouldn't object to that.  Why don't you have a crack at it then I'll have a go and we can discuss the results later.  Peace, [[user:delldot|delldot]] | &lt;small&gt;[[user talk:delldot|talk]]&lt;/small&gt; 02:12, 26 February 2007 (UTC)

Sorry for the delay, I've been busy.  I'm starting to make [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Action_Park&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=112109342 changes], I'm being very bold since I know we can discuss anything there's a problem with.  [[user:delldot|&lt;font color=&quot;#990066&quot;&gt;delldot&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;[[user talk:delldot|&lt;font color=&quot;#8B00FF&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/small&gt; 17:22, 2 March 2007 (UTC)

:OK so far. As I often do, I sort of hunched up when I clicked the difflink, but it wasn't as far-reaching as I thought it might be.&lt;p&gt;I still think, though, we need to make the point that the major cause of injuries on the Alpine Slide was not so much the falls as the poorly maintained sleds. As edited, it now sounds like it was a combination of both factors, but it seems in retrospect it was more the sleds.&lt;p&gt;I had thought of some wording for this, but it has slipped my mind ... temporarily, I hope. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] 03:46, 3 March 2007 (UTC)
{{Reflist talk}}

== My but that section was getting long... ==

Sorry for the absense, I've been doing other things and kind of forgot about this.  I think it's cool if you want to add facts back in, but we should remember not to interpret facts, only to state them (so not &quot;poorly maintained&quot;, just state how it was maintained or not).  I'm uncomfortable about the idea of trying to convey either one conclusion or another to the reader.  We should just be presenting facts and letting the reader come to their own conclusion, as voiced by [[User:Karada|Karada]] at [[WP:NPOV#Let the facts speak for themselves]] (not that this is as extreme a situation!).  Anyway, I ramble on. I only got partway down the other time, so I'm going to do another bit now.  Peace, [[user:delldot|&lt;font color=&quot;#990066&quot;&gt;delldot&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;[[user talk:delldot|&lt;font color=&quot;#8B00FF&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/small&gt; 15:55, 7 March 2007 (UTC)

:A concern about this: 
:&lt;blockquote&gt;an otherwise standard small-engine car ride became a chance to play [[bumper cars]] at 50 mph (80 km/h), and many injuries resulted from [[head-on collision]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Traction Park21-22&quot;&gt;Austin, ''op. cit.'', 21-22.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
:I find the claim highly dubious.  Having worked as an EMT, I believe the standards for any collision, head on or not, is that a collision at 40 mph merits an automatic trip to a [[trauma center]].  I believe that a head on collision at 50 mph even in a regular car would usually produce fatalities or very serious traumas.  The idea that head on collisions at 50 mph could happen in bumper cars, &quot;many&quot; times, and not cause massive amounts of carnage, seems highly dubious to me.  The park's death rate would be a lot higher than that reported here.  Now I gotta admit though, I (cough) haven't yet read the weird NJ article, so I can't talk.  But I strongly suggest that we find an additional source for this or get rid of it.  It would also be good to be more specific than &quot;many&quot; here. [[user:delldot|&lt;font color=&quot;#990066&quot;&gt;delldot&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;[[user talk:delldot|&lt;font color=&quot;#8B00FF&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/small&gt; 16:43, 7 March 2007 (UTC)
::OK, finished with this set of [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Action_Park&amp;diff=113350196&amp;oldid=113349723 tweaks], mostly rewording and removing bits.  I got as far as [[Action Park#Waterworld]].  I reworded the Alpine Slide bit, Daniel, so you may find it better, otherwise you can tweak it.  I also took out &quot;vandalism will not be tolerated&quot;: is there some reason why vandalism to this article is less tolerated than to others?  [[user:delldot|&lt;font color=&quot;#990066&quot;&gt;delldot&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;[[user talk:delldot|&lt;font color=&quot;#8B00FF&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/small&gt; 17:12, 7 March 2007 (UTC)

:::I also checked the source on the Go-Karts and rewrote the section ... the head-ons mostly happened at the intended operating speed, it seems (although I wouldn't be surprised if some happened with the governors hacked). I was unable to chekc out your edits due to an edit conflict.&lt;p&gt;As for the vandalism warning in the comments, I put it there because some months ago there was a lot of it for some reason I don't totally understand. Since most of it came from anons who I doubt read any of our vandalism policies, I put it where I'm sure they'd read it. I guess it worked, but what do I know? [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] 17:17, 7 March 2007 (UTC)

::::Nice catches to my spelling and italicization errors.  I just finished another small set of tweaks.  Sorry about the edit conflict!  (I'm writing illicitly from work so I'm saving often, and I didn't notice you were working on it today).  [[user:delldot|&lt;font color=&quot;#990066&quot;&gt;delldot&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;[[user talk:delldot|&lt;font color=&quot;#8B00FF&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/small&gt; 18:37, 7 March 2007 (UTC)
{{Reflist talk}}

== [[Shellac (band)|Shellac]] ==

* Anyone know if this is the source of the [[Shellac (band)|Shellac]] album title ''[[At Action Park]]''? [[User:W guice|W guice]] 13:04, 5 April 2007 (UTC)

** I think it is ... it was recorded in the park's declining years, when they began staging concerts to keep the revenue stream up, and the article about that album describes text on the back of the cover on resuscitating victims of electric shock, which might be an allusion to the Kayak Experience fatality. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] 15:54, 5 April 2007 (UTC)

** Reportedly no, the CD liner notes apparently contain a map of a different 'Action Park': [http://thecenteroftheaction.blogspot.com/2007/04/debunking-steve-albini-connection.html] [[User:Mathtinder|Mathtinder]] 06:09, 9 July 2007 (UTC)

== another photo of the looping waterslide ==

Another picture of the Cannonball Loop can be found on Center of the Action: [http://thecenteroftheaction.blogspot.com/2007/04/ride-that-spawned-thousand-legends.html] [[User:Mathtinder|Mathtinder]] 06:07, 9 July 2007 (UTC)

== Needs complete rewrite--wrong focus, sensational, serious POV issues ==

I see that some of this has been pointed out before, but this article has many issues and needs a complete rewrite.  It's a fascinating article but doesn't at all represent a good example of Wikipedia editing:

First, it purports to be an article about Action Park yet the text in every section seems focused first on the safety issues at Action Park; perhaps it should be split into a brief descriptive main article and a detailed safety issues article.

Second (and even if the safety issues are moved to a subordinate article), it's littered with text written in an extremely sensationalist style.  Simply placing a footnote at the end of each paragraph does not alleviate the responsibility to conform to the Wikipedia policy for Neutral Point of View.

[[User:Babaronwheels|Babaronwheels]] 11:21, 11 October 2007 (UTC)
:The safety issues are what Action Park is best known for, so it seems to me that moving the focus of the article away from them would itself be POV. --[[User:Tkynerd|Tkynerd]] 11:25, 11 October 2007 (UTC)

:I don't agree.  If the article claims to be about Action Park, it should describe what Action Park was, give an NPOV history (including brief NPOV references to the safety issues that led to its reputation and eventual shutdown).  But a detailed listing of each ride's hazards along with detailed visitor and employee perceptions of the park belongs in a separate article or at the very least in a separate section.  (And even so, virtually all of that text needs to be rewritten in a less sensational style.)  --[[User:Babaronwheels|Babaronwheels]] 11:43, 11 October 2007 (UTC)

:::A separate article would probably be deleted as an [[WP:POVFORK|unacceptable POV fork]] in any event. The language of your proposal would, in fact, make that hard to argue against. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] 15:08, 11 October 2007 (UTC)

::While it probably could be reorganized a little bit (I hadn't expected people to add so many tidbits about the rides, a few of which are not really notable in the context of Action Park or any other amusement park), I agree with Tkynerd, who's been very helpful in the past in developing this article, that trying to pretend safety problems are a side issue would be an instance in which an attempt to be more NPOV winds up becoming more POV.&lt;p&gt;Well before this article was written, &quot;Action Park&quot; was almost synonmymous with &quot;concerns about unsafe amusement park ride design and actual liability issues&quot;. You ''cannot'' discuss Action Park without making that central to such a discussion.&lt;p&gt;I initially tried to deal with the individual rides' safety issues within the history section but that was taking too long and resulting in too many digressions to be considered an effective narrative.&lt;p&gt;As for &quot;sensational&quot; style, could you provide some specific examples? Most editors with more than, say, ten edits to their credit would do that. Using language like &quot;virtually all&quot; is not the best way to get people to work with you on fixing issues. If you're going to tag an article with {{tl|rewrite}}, you better be willing to go into depth and detail on the talk page to get the issues fixed. This wasn't copied text ... a lot of research and work has gone into this, and [[WP:OWN]] notwithstanding people who have done most of the work in question have to really bite their lips when a very very new editor makes sweeping, blanket, unsupported statements about the problems he or she perceives in an article without simultaneously [[WP:BITE|biting the newcomer]]. (You might have done better with {{tl|inappropriate tone}} and/or {{tl|confusing}} instead, perhaps at the section heds rather than the whole article, based on your comments above). [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] 14:57, 11 October 2007 (UTC)

One more complaint: the article's structure is confusing in places.  It states that Action Park closed in 1996 but in several places there are references to rides being used in later years.  While the article does describe the change in ownership that occurred, it still doesn't read well; either the article should be restructured and/or renamed to accommodate the change of ownership, or the references to later years should be moved to a separate article focused on the subsequent incarnation(s).  --[[User:Babaronwheels|Babaronwheels]] 11:43, 11 October 2007 (UTC)

:That problem could be remedied by a hatnote {{tl|see}} link to [[Mountain Creek Waterpark]], which is what's meant by most of the &quot;later years&quot;. That's the separate article on the current park using many of the same facilities that I think you're looking for. Action Park and MCWP are entitled to separate articles because they were two legally distinct entities which offer(ed) an overlapping set of attractions, even if they do use the same property and water rides initially developed for the former. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] 14:58, 11 October 2007 (UTC)

This is absolutely hilarious. I appreciate the concern to keep articles on Wiki concise and accurate, but this is an undeniable masterpiece. I regret that I never made it to Action Park, and in spite of anything written here, I would have tried all of the attractions out. Unfortunately I think this country suffers from too much finger pointing. Most of these injuries were probably due to lack of common sense. It is similar to law suits over hot coffee, or slipping through the Gap on the Long Island Railroad. Some common sense is required here. Next set of lawsuits will revolve around someone who tripped over a curb and is suing because the curb was 7 inches high instead of the regulation 6 inches high. Come on America, take some responsibility for your own actions. This is the real world. I can't believe we are spraying to kill mosquitos because they carry West Nile, a relatively mild virus that the body develops immunity to after contracting it for the first time. We can't live in a world without bugs. They are a mandatory part of the propagation of all life on earth. The mosquito spray kills beneficial insects, animals, and damages sea life when rain washes into the surrounding water bodies. A little less miopic perspective on our world is required if our species is to survive the next 100 years. [[User:Galinor|Galinor]] ([[User talk:Galinor|talk]]) 20:44, 22 June 2009 (UTC)

This article is probably the most entertaining page I've ever seen on Wikipedia. It's unfortunate that it is so un-encyclopedic, in another context this would be a great article. [[Special:Contributions/68.197.163.69|68.197.163.69]] ([[User talk:68.197.163.69|talk]]) 04:41, 7 July 2009 (UTC)

:I agree. The article is hilarious, and it's surprisingly well-sourced, too. I would prefer to see it left the way it is, with a little bit of fat-trimming here and there. Apparently, most Wikipedians agree, because the article is still going strong after four and a half years. I commend [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] for all of his hard work in writing, sourcing, and maintaining this masterpiece. [[User:Uncle Dick|Uncle Dick]] ([[User talk:Uncle Dick|talk]]) 23:09, 8 June 2010 (UTC)

'''RIP Action Park'''
~~ Comment / Opinion ~~
Ok folks... I agree that ironing out details like times, names, ages, etc. is called for in any fact-based reference, but this article/listing is vividly accurate as I remember the place.  I have told people about it for 3 decades now and just learned of it's demise today (RIP AP).  I am an amusement park/boardwalk/etc junkie (now 50 and still doing them), lived a few miles from a Six Flags, a few blocks from a boardwalk, etc. and Action Park was THE most fun I've EVER had at one.  Action Park is exactly as was described on the wiki page. 

For example, after our last visit, we had so much fun that I had nothing left on but torn-up sneakers &amp; shorts hanging on by 3 threads, and took my friend to the hospital when it closed as he refused to go UNTIL it closed. The injury that solidified the ER visit was that his Alpine sled (on our 4th run) shot off the tracks and he flew through the trees several yards off the ground and ended up dangling from a branch.  We may have gotten beat up there, but that's because we were allowed to actually have FUN and we HAD FUN (as opposed to waiting in line for 2 hours to sit on boring-ass 'It's A Small World'... puh-leez).  

Ok, in retrospect, there were some management issues as does anywhere, but AP was THE best, there were REAL exciting things to do &amp; patrons were free to 'go for it' if they wanted to, and many of us did.  I will never ever forget Action Park for as long as I live!!!

== Missing Ride Description - WaterPark ==

Action Park was one of my favorite places to go as a kid. I regret that it is gone.  One of the favorite rides that is not fully described was one comprised of two side by side enclosed waterslide tubes, apparently of concrete construction buried under soil, completely coated on the inside with a smooth, slick, but somewhat soft foam padding their entire length.  Water was sprayed at the top of the tubes, and one slid down these two tubes 50-100' or so, without a mat, completely in the dark, until released 6-10' in the air or so above a pool of water.  I think it was the same pool that the tarzan swing was on.

The only mention of these on the page is in passing regarding the enclosed &quot;loop waterslide&quot; with the picture.  These two enclosed waterslides were effectively of the same design, excepting the loop.

&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/64.211.77.162|64.211.77.162]] ([[User talk:64.211.77.162|talk]]) 18:34, 27 December 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:I stick with what's in the sources, per WP policy. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] ([[User talk:Daniel Case|talk]]) 05:24, 28 December 2010 (UTC)

== Names for the deceased? ==

Is the lack of names for the people whom died in the wave pool and Kayak Experience rides done out of not knowing, or out of respect?
:Largely not knowing, but I also don't think they're encyclopedic enough. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] ([[User talk:Daniel Case|talk]]) 05:20, 7 January 2011 (UTC)  

If the latter, I understand the idea but surely documenting the facts about something - especially a place like Action Park where information [especially greater details] can be difficult to find to begin with, involves all the facts?

If the former, the names ARE known:

- Jeffrey Nathan was the guy who was shocked on the Kayak Experience ride in 1982.
- Gregory Grandchamps, and Donald DePass drowned in the Wave Pool

ALSO found an article abstract mentioning a death at another park related to a prototype ride being designed for Action Park [location [and park?] of where the ride being designed was going to be implemented] - maybe I could post it here?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Travelsonic|Travelsonic]] ([[User talk:Travelsonic|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Travelsonic|contribs]]) 04:12, 7 January 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Sounds great. Post it. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] ([[User talk:Daniel Case|talk]]) 05:20, 7 January 2011 (UTC)

== Space Tower death ==

It seems like even the rides being designed, built, and tested for Action Park were cursed. ~_~

In July of 1994, Jason Ricks was testing a prototype ride for Action Park that was &quot;designed to take eight passengers at high rates of speed up and down a 165-foot vertical shaft.&quot;  While riding in the car to the top at a speed of 3MPH, the ride sped up inexplicably to 10MPH causing him to lose his footing and fall to his death.

[http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=EONHAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=kewDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6734,5840621&amp;hl=en  [ARTICLE: State Probing Deadly Fall Of Benson Man&lt;nowiki&gt;]&lt;/nowiki&gt;]  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Travelsonic|Travelsonic]] ([[User talk:Travelsonic|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Travelsonic|contribs]]) 18:45, 7 January 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Post-Intrewet/Return of the Original Owners ==

Would it be worth mentioning some of the changes to Mountain Creek with the return of Mulhivil etc, the original owners?

Like that Surf Hill is back, in its original location [especially since it was the fans of the ride that, I think, got it to succeed], the building of a new lodge where the old Hexagon lodge is, the building of the new Alpine Coaster, etc? [[User:Travelsonic|Travelsonic]] ([[User talk:Travelsonic|talk]])  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|undated]] comment added 15:48, 16 June 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!--Template:Undated--&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:I saw where you went and added it. Can you give the URL of the park's Facebook page so we make it a proper reference? [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] ([[User talk:Daniel Case|talk]]) 20:26, 16 June 2012 (UTC)

==Longform==
This article was [http://longform.org/category/editors-pick/ today's Editor's Pick] on longform.org. Nice work here.[[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] ([[User talk:IvoShandor|talk]]) 00:34, 27 June 2012 (UTC)
:Wow. Didn't notice. Actually, it's in northern New Jersey. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] ([[User talk:Daniel Case|talk]]) 04:02, 27 June 2012 (UTC)

== Watercraft ==

In the watercraft section, the paragraphs for Super Speedboats and Bumper Boats should be the other way around, with Super Speedboats first.[[Special:Contributions/190.42.151.105|190.42.151.105]] ([[User talk:190.42.151.105|talk]]) 08:07, 21 July 2012 (UTC)
:I see you [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Action_Park&amp;curid=3679118&amp;diff=503791701&amp;oldid=503714045 did this]. Thanks. I think it happened because some editor was convinced they should go in alphabetical order (which they still could, if we were willing to rewrite them a little bit). [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] ([[User talk:Daniel Case|talk]]) 17:34, 23 July 2012 (UTC)

== Pocono Action Park ==

Anybody have information about this place, or at least enough to add a section to the article on it [or create its own sub-article, or whatever]?

Apparently another Action Park - same company [GAR, Great American Recreation], in the Poconos, in PA, instead of in Vernon, NJ, modeled after the Vernon, NJ location offering **SOME OF **  the same types of attractions [a couple of water slides, a &quot;motorworld&quot; section w/ the same go-karts, mini racecars, etc]... no idea at all when it opened, or shut down, seems there is an outlet mall where it once stood.

http://articles.philly.com/1986-06-20/entertainment/26045927_1_pocono-mountains-mount-pocono-heart-shaped - article with a LITTLE mention, possible info
http://i.ebayimg.com/t/Vintage-POCONO-ACTION-PARK-and-Motor-World-1980s-F203-/00/s/MTIwMFgxNjAw/z/b6oAAOxyOa9R41vF/$T2eC16F,!)!E9s2f!G5GBR41vFRiBQ~~60_57.JPG?rt=nc - image to brochure.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Travelsonic|Travelsonic]] ([[User talk:Travelsonic|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Travelsonic|contribs]]) 19:15, 3 September 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Interesting ... wouldn't surprise me that they tried to spin it off. Not sure the Ebay photo will stay up forever ... can we save a copy of it somewhere else? [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] ([[User talk:Daniel Case|talk]]) 03:25, 4 September 2013 (UTC)
::It'd be a good idea - I already went and saved every image from that brochure - spanning 2 e-bay auctions, one complete the other not, to my external hard drive that I could find, just to be safe, as this is really a lesser known aspect of Action Park... too bad the only info I've found out aside from the brochure, so far, is little snippets from various message board posts on Action Park, a couple of old news articles, and a couple of pictures on Flickr.  I've posted on Weird NJ, and plan a little later today, to post in the comments section of the DoD3 article on the park, as well as on some of the bigger Facebook groups on Action Park, hoping SOMEBODY will either have gone there, or knows somebody who went there, and can hook me up with information. [[User:Travelsonic|Travelsonic]] ([[User talk:Travelsonic|talk]]) 13:19, 4 September 2013 (UTC)

== Any exceptions to rules regarding Youtube links? ==

I found a video was uploaded to Youtube very recently that is from Pocono Action Park, and was wondering... if I do finally make a section on the Pocono Action Park offshoot, is there any way I can satisfy rules regarding sources and still use the video?  I mean, considering how little information there actually is on this offshoot of Action Park and all...
:Per [[WP:YOUTUBE]], any video link is OK per the [[Digital Millenium Copyright Act|DMCA]] as long it's one uploaded by the copyright holder or a designee. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] ([[User talk:Daniel Case|talk]]) 04:15, 14 September 2013 (UTC)

== Regarding Incidents at Action Park ==

Hello - I had *moved* the content that was already present in this article to the compilation list article of Amusement Park Incidents [[Incidents at independent amusement parks]]. In that location, the incidents - gathered together in one well-cited, documented location - give greater weight to notable amusement park injuries and deaths than they do listed on each individual park's page. It also makes long-term editing/monitoring easier to keep that similar content in one location rather than sharing the same content in multiple places, as editors are not always aware of branched content that needs to be addressed in more than one location. Plan was to expand/rewrite into format/fix citations... and also to further research and document any other notable incidents that took place at Action Park, as we have done for other amusement park incidents that have been merged into the assorted master pages. [[User:SpikeJones|SpikeJones]] ([[User talk:SpikeJones|talk]]) 03:38, 4 October 2013 (UTC)
:I don't see what limits us to having to have that information in only one place. Particularly with this park. The fatalities are a big part of Action Park's lore, and having an accurate sourced enumeration here can only help the article.&lt;p&gt;We handle branched content quite well in other areas (like [[WP:NRHP]] lists ... I don't see why we can't here. And lastly, since the park has been closed for 17 years, there's not going to be much in the way of new information to add, is there? [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] ([[User talk:Daniel Case|talk]]) 05:25, 4 October 2013 (UTC)
::No offense intended, just being bold and incorporating notable Amusement Park incidents into the single location, regardless of timeframe they occurred. By moving/referencing the incidents, keeps the consistency that has been in place in all other similar articles of other notable parks. Doesn't diminish that they happened by relocating that specific content, other than adding additional emphasis on deaths/injuries that occur in amusement parks.  On a side note, perhaps see how the Great Adventure haunted house fire was handled between the two (three?) articles. [[User:SpikeJones|SpikeJones]] ([[User talk:SpikeJones|talk]]) 03:30, 7 October 2013 (UTC)

== Wow, so basically there were 2 spinoffs of Action Park, all owned by GAR,... ==

http://downthepike.courierpostonline.com/blog/2012/09/12/skiing-in-south-jersey-yes-and-not-so-long-ago/
That's cool - I wish I had a damn time machine so I could go back in time to visit this one, which was in Pine Hill, NJ, the one in Tannersville, PA, AND the original Vernon, NJ location.

Gotta find out more, I so plan on adding sections to this article on the Tannersville location as well as this one eventually. [[User:Travelsonic|Travelsonic]] ([[User talk:Travelsonic|talk]]) 14:30, 11 October 2013 (UTC)

== Edited part on motorworld ==

Edited
&quot;The park also had a section called Motorworld. It had powered vehicles and boats on the west side of Route 94. These closed with Action Park in 1996. They have been replaced with a condominium housing development, a mini golf course, a restaurant, and additional parking for the Mountain Creek ski resort. Several types of vehicles were used in this area.&quot;

And struck out the mini golf course from that list on the assumption that the course was always there [seen in a 1986 commercial for Action Park] - do edit it back in if in fact they removed the old one and replaced it outright, but I'm pretty sure it is the exact same course from the Action Park days that is there now.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Travelsonic|Travelsonic]] ([[User talk:Travelsonic|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Travelsonic|contribs]]) 14:46, 14 October 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Pardon my French, but this is getting really fucking annoying [w/ edits] ==

Some of the revisions are getting annoying, especially when inaccurate info is being passed around.

The section on the spinoff locations is needlessly getting changed.  More readable?  Whoever edited it removed a lot of information and left something that was shorter [with some minor facual errors].  Just because it is longer than a couple of sentences doesn't make it more or less readable - if anything, you made it less to read, which is not the same [and detrimental in this case since the information is now not entirely correct].

The people behind Action Mountain/Action Park of Pine Hill were AFFILIATED with GAR [which could, admittedly, mean anything - after all, there were rumors that Eugene Mulvihil operated his own insurance gig for the Vernon, NJ park... hehe...]... and they were spinoffs of Action Park.  They used the same logos, trademarks [well, Action Mountain did for the first year - before being renamed to Action Mountain], Pocono Action Park was in fact a better example of a DIRECT SPINOFF, having a Motorworld section with a lot of the same attractions, water rides of the same design [and similar ones], being operated by GAR, AS WELL AS having the same trademarks/logos and advertising the Vernon, NJ as &quot;Our Vernon, NJ location&quot;.  

WHOEVER KEEPS reverting to what it is now [since I can't [at the time of posting this I couldn't, at least] revert - STOP messing with these areas so far as the actual content at least until we have more factually provable evidence - articles, maps, etc with DATES that contradict what the current evidence shows.  It was fine the way it was.  EDIT: Screw it, adding in the paragraph on the spinoffs again w/ some sentence structure changes that actually make it clearer without sacrificing content.

== Merger proposal ==

I propose that [[Mountain Creek Waterpark]] be merged into [[Action Park]]. Both articles cover the same place, and would be better explained in a single article. Also, the Mountain Creek article does not cite any sources, and (to me) reads like an advertisement. [[User:Hooky-i-vanisher|Hooky-i-vanisher]] ([[User talk:Hooky-i-vanisher|talk]]) 01:10, 5 April 2014 (UTC)

Also, I forgot to mention that the park's name is being reverted back to Action Park. [[User:Hooky-i-vanisher|Hooky-i-vanisher]] ([[User talk:Hooky-i-vanisher|talk]]) 01:16, 5 April 2014 (UTC)

:I have no objection; I never understood the justification for a separate article anyway. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] ([[User talk:Daniel Case|talk]]) 02:06, 5 April 2014 (UTC)

:: I actually was pondering this idea since I heard about them going and re-naming the park back to Action Park, and think it'd be a good idea to merge Mountain Creek Waterpark's article and this one, given that they both talk about the same piece of property, just different stages in its life.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Travelsonic|Travelsonic]] ([[User talk:Travelsonic|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Travelsonic|contribs]]) 02:13, 5 April 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:::Makes sense to me. [[User:Doniago|DonIago]] ([[User talk:Doniago|talk]]) 12:50, 7 April 2014 (UTC)

No issue with merging. We're going to have to redo the tense in some areas though. Just glad that us who were only five or six when the place closed get to see it now. :) &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Poor Richard;color:red;&quot;&gt;Mitch&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Georgia;color:black;&quot;&gt;&lt;big&gt;'''32'''&lt;/big&gt;&lt;sup&gt;([[User:Mitchazenia|Any fool can make a rule]], [[User talk:Mitchazenia|And any fool will mind it.]])&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 22:23, 25 April 2014 (UTC)

Action Park deserves its own article considering its history and [http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2673751/It-like-just-crazy-guys-yard-Six-deaths-countless-injuries-criminal-fraud-charges-worlds-dangerous-theme-park-making-return-fortunately-adjustments.html international] coverage.  The name Mountain Creek was the change in ownership after the closing and the obvious disassociation from Action Park.--[[User:Bf2002]] ([[User talk:Bf2002|talk]]) 14:34, 29 June 2014 (UTC)
::Agreed. Mountain Creek was a different entity under different management, and I think they should remain separate articles. I grew up in Vernon, NJ, and I worked several summers at Action Park. It closed and opened under new ownership as Mountain Creek, in order to dissociate itself from the reputation of Action Park. The two are linked for obvious reasons and could remain so - they should reference one another, however,as they are historically linked. [[User:Rachel.dicerbo|Rachel.dicerbo]] ([[User talk:Rachel.dicerbo|talk]]) 22:19, 15 July 2014 (UTC)

== Mini versions of rides ==

Do we have any information about the miniature versions of Cannonball Falls and Surf Hill that existed - except what can be ascertained from the maps of the park, which is that the mini Surf Hill probably didn't use mats like the full version did, and that they were located on the hill surrounded by Surf Hill, the Serpentine Slides, and a few of the Speed Slides by Kamikaze?

I do recall going on the miniature version of Surf Hill when I went there in 1996, but rather than put in what I recall without verifying the accuracy, I'd rather find out more, and see if that is at all accurate &amp; put in factually verifiable information more preferably.
:I wish there was something out there more than this, but ... I can recall them being there in 1987. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] ([[User talk:Daniel Case|talk]]) 02:20, 8 May 2014 (UTC)
:: Someone on the Mountain Creek Facebook page posted pictures from a large 1983 map of the park he had framed sitting around, showing not just little graphics indicating the ride like the maps patrons got at the park, but showing like the full rides as they stood... and am trying to get pictures of that particular part of the park amongst others - especially since the map seems to depict the park perfectly for 1983 especially, and it could fill in a LOT of gaps so far as attraction ride names, what they were like, sorta, and even rides we may not have at least listed.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Travelsonic|Travelsonic]] ([[User talk:Travelsonic|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Travelsonic|contribs]]) 14:05, 9 May 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== The Article's Layout ==

Feels a bit messy, gonna take a lot of work, but I wanna redo it, properly do the sections of the park - the Alpine Center, Waterworld + Roaring Springs, Motorworld, and put the ride info in the proper sections, because it feels like bits and pieces are out of place.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Travelsonic|Travelsonic]] ([[User talk:Travelsonic|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Travelsonic|contribs]]) 16:37, 7 May 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:The heavy editing the article has recently undergone is probably the reason for that. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] ([[User talk:Daniel Case|talk]]) 02:19, 8 May 2014 (UTC)
:: I'm working on - and sandbox testing, of course, a page dedicated to just the rides.  When done it shall contain the attractions, when they were opened roughly, when they closed, information about them - all on their own page instead of cluttering up the main page, kinda like how TV show wiki articles have a separate page for episodes listed by season, or music/rhythm game wiki articles have separate pages for their soundtracks, etc.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Travelsonic|Travelsonic]] ([[User talk:Travelsonic|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Travelsonic|contribs]]) 12:16, 12 May 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
::: Hmm ... interesting idea. Have we done this in any other amusement-park articles? It's justifiable but having some precedent would be better. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] ([[User talk:Daniel Case|talk]]) 12:20, 12 May 2014 (UTC)
:::: I dunno, but is setting a precedence s bad thing here?  I mean, given the amount of information on the sttra tions the history, AS WELL AS the number, how the were laid out in the park...  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Travelsonic|Travelsonic]] ([[User talk:Travelsonic|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Travelsonic|contribs]]) 23:42, 13 May 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:::: Hey Daniel, got pictures of a 1983 park map poster - I must say, the idea of having a separate page for all the attractions, info about them, when they opened/closed, etc, is looking even more tempting now.  :D  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Travelsonic|Travelsonic]] ([[User talk:Travelsonic|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Travelsonic|contribs]]) 21:19, 20 June 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Action Park]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=699765323 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20071222234456/http://www.northjersey.com:80/page.php?qstr=eXJpcnk3ZjcxN2Y3dnFlZUVFeXkyJmZnYmVsN2Y3dnFlZUVFeXk2NjkyNjgy to http://www.northjersey.com/page.php?qstr=eXJpcnk3ZjcxN2Y3dnFlZUVFeXkyJmZnYmVsN2Y3dnFlZUVFeXk2NjkyNjgy

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=true}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 09:37, 14 January 2016 (UTC)

== Discussion over disagreement over if something can be counted as a source [regarding the Tidal Wave Pool] ==

So there has been disagreement over the use of a Facebook post, with an aerial photograph of the park, as a source for statements about how the park was open with baseball fields that were replaced with the wave pool.  Rather than bicker back and forth in the editing/undoing of each others edits, I think we should civilly discuss it here.

The statements this image (and Facebook post encapsulating it) were supposed to cover as a source: &quot;The early 1980s saw more slides along with a huge wavepool that replaced the softball field.&quot;
[https://www.facebook.com/MountainCreekNJ/photos/a.156936411937.119746.8641466937/10152124195411938/?type=3&amp;theater The image can be seen here.]

The image itself seems to be from 1978 at the earliest, 1980 or MAYBE 1981 at the latest.  I come to that conclusion because the Jr. Rapids, Green Mat Slide, and a swimming pool are the only water attractions here.  The Blue Mat Slide and adjacent Kamikaze slide would not appear until some time in the early 80s, the Super Speed Slide tower was under construction some time in 1982, and the Tidal Wave Pool came sometime in 1982, or 1983.

Even without words on a page to go by, however, you can inference that the softball fields in the image were replaced by the Tidal Wave Pool, since there are a number of geographical features, things like paths, as well as rides that remain unchanged enough to recognize what should be there, was there, and whatnot  I guess one question is, however how much can/should be left to inference?  Not everyone can recognize the geography, and the features that stayed relatively unchanged during the last 38 years, and thus might not be able to easily see that the softball fields in the picture were where the Tidal Wave Pool would eventually go.  

Part of my frustration is that getting information about Action Park at this stage in its life (from 1978 to the very early 80s) is so goddammed difficult.  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Travelsonic|Travelsonic]] ([[User talk:Travelsonic|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Travelsonic|contribs]]) 17:23, 30 June 2016 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:I can understand this frustration, but the problem is that, since nothing on Facebook is subject to editorial oversight, we cannot accept that this picture is authentic. I don't mean to say it's fake—I don't think it is—just that by virtue of being published on Facebook it does not come under [[WP:IRS|RS]]. If we find it somewhere else, that might be different. [[User:Daniel Case|Daniel Case]] ([[User talk:Daniel Case|talk]]) 20:30, 30 June 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:3|one external link|3 external links}} on [[Action Park]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=742424026 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added {{tlx|dead link}} tag to http://soli.inav.net/~catalyst/Humor/jersey.htm
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/19961227075424/http://www.actionpark.com/ to http://www.actionpark.com/
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/19961227075424/http://www.actionpark.com/ to http://www.actionpark.com/
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20061103102741/http://lifeinabungalo.com/2006/02/21/an-interview-with-an-action-park-employee/ to http://lifeinabungalo.com/2006/02/21/an-interview-with-an-action-park-employee/

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 16:46, 3 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>jnmnjmjflkitrnvcgwbuwtrgbztoyu3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
