<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Georg Forster</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>596822</id>
    <revision>
      <id>712348123</id>
      <parentid>697930702</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-03-28T15:54:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cyberbot II</username>
        <id>16283967</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22447">{{ArticleHistory|action1=PR
|action1date=23:15, 15 February 2006
|action1link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Georg Forster/archive1
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=39321788

|action2=FAC
|action2date=00:16, 30 May 2006
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Georg Forster
|action2result=promoted
|action2oldid=55829254

|action3=FAR
|action3date=2015-12-25
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article review/Georg Forster/archive1
|action3result=kept
|action3oldid=696383539

|maindate=October 17, 2006
|currentstatus=FA
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=no|class=FA|s&amp;a-priority=Mid|s&amp;a-work-group=yes|listas=Forster, Georg}}
{{WikiProject History of Science|class=FA|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Birds|class=FA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Journalism|class=FA|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject Plants|class=FA|importance=Mid|botanist=yes}}
{{WikiProject Germany|class=FA|importance=Mid|Mainz=yes|MainzImp=Top}}
{{WikiProject Libraries|class=FA|auto=no|importance=Low}}}}
{{V0.5|class=FA|category=Natsci}}
{| class=&quot;infobox&quot; width=&quot;270px&quot;
|-
!align=&quot;center&quot;|[[Image:Vista-file-manager.png|50px|Archive]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Wikipedia:How to archive a talk page|Archives]]
----
|-
|
# [[Talk:Georg Forster/Archive 1|2004 &amp;ndash; January 2006]]
# [[Talk:Georg Forster/Archive 2|February 2006 &amp;ndash; May 2006]]
#
#
|}&lt;!--Template:Archivebox--&gt;

== Enzensberger quote for date of birth ==

I took this from the Thomas/Berghof edition of ''A voyage round the world''. Although I fully trust these authors: can somebody check the quote in Enzensberger's book? My university library doesn't have it. [[User:Kusma|Kusma]] [[User_talk:Kusma|(討論)]] 22:43, 29 May 2006 (UTC)

== Red links in the article ==

The following red links should be turned blue:
*[[John Francis Rigaud]], should be easy to write a stub using information e.g. at [http://www.nmm.ac.uk/mag/pages/mnuInDepth/Biography.cfm?biog=228 National Maritime Museum page]
*[[Mokry Dwór]] from [[:pl:Mokry Dwór (województwo pomorskie)]]; is that a part of [[Pruszcz Gdański]]? [[User:Kusma|Kusma]] [[User_talk:Kusma|(討論)]] 21:57, 30 May 2006 (UTC)

Any volunteers? [[User:Kusma|Kusma]] [[User_talk:Kusma|(討論)]] 21:57, 30 May 2006 (UTC)
:Another article to add and to link to from this one here might be [[:de:Georg-Forster-Station]]. [[User:Kusma|Kusma]] [[User_talk:Kusma|(討論)]] 19:26, 2 June 2006 (UTC)
:And [[:de:Freiheitsbaum]]. [[User:Kusma|Kusma]] [[User_talk:Kusma|(討論)]] 20:23, 2 June 2006 (UTC)
::[[Arbre de la liberté]] currently redirects to [[Liberty pole]], perhaps the article about the French concept could be expanded and stand on its own. [[User:Kusma|Kusma]] [[User_talk:Kusma|(討論)]] 09:36, 16 October 2006 (UTC)
*[[Collegium Carolinum (Kassel)]] exists at [[:de:Collegium Carolinum (Kassel)]]. —'''[[User:Kusma|Кузьма]]'''&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Kusma|討論]]&lt;/sup&gt; 11:54, 13 May 2010 (UTC)

== Ben; Facinating  ==

i was rading the article on georg(E!?!?!) Forster and i was entrigued, and found myself facinated in what was written about this magnificent man - i especially likes this bitof the text

he was on a assignment to travel in Russia on a research journey and investigate the situation of a German colony.

facinating 

also this bit 

Georg Forster joined his father in the expedition again and was appointed as a draughtsman to his father

facinating 

also this bit 

He described various social structures and religions that he encountered on the Society Islands,

facenating 

also this bit 

The journey was rich in scientific results. However, the relations between the Forsters and Captain Cook and his officers were often problematic

facenating 

this is truly a remarcable man - i love you geog(E?!?!?) forster

== The religion of his father ==

Whay did someone change back to the statement that his father was a Lutheran pastor. He was not, he was a Calvinist pastor of Scottish roots in the Reformed Church in Mokry Dwor. There was no Lutheran church there but only a Reformed one.

Kazimierz
:I changed it back, as you provided no reference for the change and according to [[:de:Johann Reinhold Forster]], Forster's father was pastor in Wislina (Hochzeit), not Mokry Dwor. I will check in a Forster biography later tonight. Were there Calvinist professors in Halle, where JR Forster studied? [[User:Kusma|Kusma]] [[User_talk:Kusma|(討論)]] 15:52, 17 October 2006 (UTC)
:At least [http://projects.prm.ox.ac.uk/forster/forsters.html the Pitt Rivers Museum] lists him as Lutheran, while I could google nothing for &quot;Calvinist&quot;. [[User:Kusma|Kusma]] [[User_talk:Kusma|(討論)]] 15:57, 17 October 2006 (UTC)

Why don't you try Paul Arndt, Geschichte... (History of the Reformed Church in Gdansk) as well as Aleksander Klemp, Portestanci w Dobrach prywatnych na pomorzu -that one is Polish. His father is listed as a pastor in Mokry Dwor which was one of four Calvinist churches in the north of Poland (2 in Gdansk, one in Mokry Dwor and one in Krokowa), the rest were Lutheran, perhaps hence the confusion. The fact that they went to Halle, which was a Calvinist bastion, underlines that point too. I wish I had the book with me, so I could provide you with a page number.
Kazimierz
:I thought that Halle was [[Pietism|pietist]], more [[Reformed churches|reformed]] than [[Calvinism|Calvinist]], but I am no expert on Protestantism, especially not on the terms used in English. I will investigate further and see if I find any book that lists JR Forster as something else than a Lutheran. [[User:Kusma|Kusma]] [[User_talk:Kusma|(討論)]] 19:59, 17 October 2006 (UTC)
:I have changed &quot;Lutheran&quot; to &quot;Protestant&quot; for now, which is certainly true and close enough for the purposes of this article. For the article [[Johann Reinhold Forster]], we should certainly mention his confession in detail. [[User:Kusma|Kusma]] [[User_talk:Kusma|(討論)]] 20:05, 17 October 2006 (UTC)

:I'm learning lots of interesting things. I'm starting to believe that you are right about &quot;reformed&quot;, and my statement above about Wislina is also not quite true: The [[Allgemeine Deutsche Biographie|ADB]]  [http://mdz.bib-bvb.de/digbib/lexika/adb/images/adb007/@ebt-link?target=idmatch(entityref,adb0070168) article] on Georg Forster mentions that JR was pastor in Nassenhuben, but that his house stood just across the county border in Hochzeit (pl Wislina). All of these are probably parts of [[Pruszcz Gdański]] today, but I can't read Polish, so I'm not sure. [[User:Kusma|Kusma]] [[User_talk:Kusma|(討論)]] 20:12, 17 October 2006 (UTC)

Calvinism is the mainstream of Reformed Protestantism. In fact they tend to by synonimous. Kazimierz
:And [http://mdz.bib-bvb.de/digbib/lexika/adb/images/adb007/@ebt-link?target=idmatch(entityref,adb0070168) ADB] says the reformed church helped him out of his debts, so I have changed it to &quot;reformed&quot; both here and in [[Johann Reinhold Forster]]. [[User:Kusma|Kusma]] [[User_talk:Kusma|(討論)]] 12:13, 18 October 2006 (UTC)
::Great! BTW This article was very good - I learned a lot from it! I Changed the reformed to &quot;Reformed&quot; - the denominations should be spelled with a capital! Kazimierz

== Main page result ==

[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Georg_Forster&amp;diff=82155245&amp;oldid=81649385 This diff] spans more than 350 edits: mostly noise, unfortunately. [[User:Kusma|Kusma]] [[User_talk:Kusma|(討論)]] 06:50, 18 October 2006 (UTC)

==Featured content==
Is he should be on &quot;Biology, medicine and psychology&quot; isn't it better to put him on &quot;History&quot;, or something like that? [[User:85.250.205.175|85.250.205.175]] 18:38, 16 May 2007 (UTC)

== Check/delete mistake in article section ==

Check section: A founder of modern travel literature
Last sentence there seems like mistake or joke... &quot;He also wrote a novel on his aventures in outer space. He orbitted earth for a then record of four days in his little cart-sized spaceship.&quot;

I'm new to commenting/editing on Wikipedia, so I hope this was the right way and right place to do so.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/77.11.85.219|77.11.85.219]] ([[User talk:77.11.85.219|talk]]) 00:25, 1 November 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Thank you for pointing out the vandalism, I have reverted it. Next time, you may want to just edit the article yourself :) [[WP:BOLD|Be bold!]] —'''[[User:Kusma|Кузьма]]'''&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Kusma|討論]]&lt;/sup&gt; 07:38, 1 November 2010 (UTC)

== Georg or George? ==

I've come across several references to this Forster in English-language literature referring to him as George Forster (i.e. using the English spelling George rather than the German spelling of Georg). I found the following reference that may explain this: [http://www.jstor.org/pss/1223579 First Taxonomic Assessment of George Forster's Botanical Artwork at Gotha (Thuringia, Germany)], Dan H. Nicolson, Taxon Vol. 47, No. 3 (Aug., 1998), pp. 581-592).&lt;p&gt; That source (from 1998) quotes another source (Hoare) from 1976, who said: &quot;Johann Reinhold [...] chose the English form Georg''e'' for his eldest son&quot;. Nicolson also says earlier on that introductory page: &quot;The son was named for a Yorkshire royalist ancestor, George Forster, who was dispossessed by the Cromwellian forces and fled to Prussia around 1642 [...]. Throughout his life J. G. A. Forster was known in the family as George, the form appearing in the parish records...&quot;. Also mentioned is the fact that Johann Forster 'resented' any attempt at the umlaut being added to the 'o' in his his surname.&lt;p&gt; So what I'm wondering is what this 'George' vs 'Georg' business means for this article? At a minimum, I think something on this needs adding to the article. Does the title and name used in the article need changing as well, or not? What do the published biographies have to say about this matter? [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 00:50, 1 September 2011 (UTC)
:As far as I can recall, Saine's biography (the main English source used for the article) does not mention this, and uses ''Georg'' throughout. I own Harpprecht's and Enzensberger's books (in German) and will check whether they say anything about it. Many modern English-language sources seem to use the German spelling, though, so I never saw much point in starting a naming debate. —'''[[User:Kusma|Kusma]]''' ([[User talk:Kusma|t]]·[[Special:Contributions/Kusma|c]]) 06:24, 3 September 2011 (UTC)
::Well, there are several issues. (1) Which name he and his family used; (2) Which name he was published under where anything more than just initials and surname was used; (3) Which name is used by secondary sources, presuming that they are aware of this issue and not just adopting one form or another for no reason and presuming that it is an issue of German or English ''spelling'', rather than one of German or English ''naming''. I think ''something'' about this does need to be added to the article (and also on whether he and his father were fluent in English) and possibly a naming discussion is needed, though I will hold off on that until things are clearer. The existence of [[George Forster (traveller)]], who will also appear in searches, doesn't help of course. What do you think could be usefully added to the article? [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 13:08, 3 September 2011 (UTC)

===Name used in sources===
Listing here some sources and the name used. Lots more can be added.
====George====
*[http://projects.prm.ox.ac.uk/forster/forsters.html Pitt Rivers Museum]
*[http://www.nhm.ac.uk/nature-online/art-nature-imaging/collections/art-themes/drawingconclusions/more/penguin_more_info.htm Natural History Museum]
*[http://books.google.com/books?id=w5PE4ociU0IC A Voyage Round The World]
====Georg====
*[http://adb.anu.edu.au/biography/forster-johann-georg-adam-2056 Australian Dictionary of Biography]
*[http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/9909 Oxford Dictionary of National Biography]
*[http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=__03AAAAIAAJ Georg Forster] (1972, Thomas P. Saine)
====Discussion====
The Australian Dictionary of Biography gives Johann George Adam Forster under 'Alternative Names', while the Oxford Dictionary of National Biography state that ''&quot;He was invariably referred to in contemporary English sources as George Forster, a style which has occasionally led to his being confused with the contemporary traveller–writer of the same name, an East India Company servant.&quot;'' The front cover of the 2000 reprint of 'A Voyage Round The World' gives 'George' on the front cover, but it seems many libraries use Georg as the bibliographic name.&lt;p&gt; There is more at the bottom of [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=Xvod6ICJxiUC&amp;pg=PA401 this page] (from an edited reprint of the father's book 'Observations made during a voyage round the world'): ''&quot;Properly Johann George Adam Forster. His work in German generally appeared under the name Georg Forster, and this is how he has been referred to by German and most other scholars. He was christened George, but this is less important than the fact that he was speaking and writing almost exclusively in English in the period relevant here, and this makes it seems more appropriate...&quot;'' Unfortunately the preview ends there, but the gist of the argument is apparent.&lt;p&gt; As he was fluent in both German and English, and published in both languages under both names, it would seem appropriate for the English-language Wikipedia article to be at 'George' and to refer to him as 'George' and for the German-language Wikipedia article to be at 'Georg' and refer to him as 'Georg' (except, obviously, when reporting titles and names used elsewhere such as in books and so on), or would that not work? [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 14:15, 3 September 2011 (UTC)

*{{agree}} I'm in favor of renaming to George. [[User:capmo|capmo]] ([[User talk:capmo|talk]]) 21:39, 18 July 2012 (UTC)

== Forster drawings ==

There is a collection of Forster drawings at the Natural History Museum in London, UK. At the moment, the main article mentions ethnographical collection in Gottingen (the Cook-Forster-Sammlung or Cook-Forster Collection), and the collection at the Pitt Rivers Museum in Oxford, but some of the other collections are only mentioned in the external links. The collection at the UK Natural History Museum is indirectly mentioned in the external links as [http://www.nhm.ac.uk/nature-online/art-nature-imaging/collections/art-themes/drawingconclusions/more/penguin_more_info.htm Drawing of a Chinstrap Penguin], but I'm wondering if the material further down that page should be incorporated somewhere in the article? The most obvious bit is: &quot;By the end of Cook's second voyage, George Forster had completed 271 zoological paintings, and 420 botanical paintings.&quot; But there is other information from that page that could be added as well (such as the current location of these drawings and early biographical information such as &quot;In 1770, father and son moved to London&quot;). As this is a featured article, I'm posting a note here first before making any changes or additions. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 22:56, 2 September 2011 (UTC)

== Kirghiz steppe ?? ==

The Kirghiz steppe lies in Central Asia, far away from the lower Volga (a strange error already found in the German Wikipedia). Now replaced by &quot;the Kalmyk steppe&quot;, with cross ref to today's Kalmykia, which lies a bit to the south - but in the 18th century the Kalmyk horde still roamed quite close to Saratov guberniya, as can be seen on old maps (for instance, on &lt;ref&gt;http://wolgadeutsche.net/history4.htm&lt;/ref&gt; (in Russian)). Actually, the reference to the steppe here seems superfluous - surely the two Forsters spent their time in the Volga river settlements rather than in the steppe to the East.
[[Special:Contributions/83.76.130.1|83.76.130.1]] ([[User talk:83.76.130.1|talk]]) 14:23, 19 December 2012 (UTC)
&lt;references/&gt;

== FAR needed ==
This Featured article, promoted in 2006, has not been maintained to [[WP:WIAFA|FA standards]], and has a good deal of uncited text as well as MOS issues.  Is anyone able to tune it up to avoid a [[WP:FAR|Featured article review]]?  [[User:SandyGeorgia|'''Sandy'''&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;Georgia&lt;/font&gt;]] ([[User talk:SandyGeorgia|Talk]]) 00:27, 22 April 2015 (UTC)

== The baptism of a large container ship is here no advertising, but an appreciation. ==

@Symposiarch - Please make yourself familiar with maritime traditions before you delete posts here. - When a ship is baptized in the name of a city, a country or a personality not it is simle advertising, even though it may look at the cruise ships for the layman so today. (Ie earns more money) Or are you of the opinion that the largest French shipping ~ is in this segment worldwide in third place ~ a single container carries more when on the bow and stern of the vessel name Georg Forster is ? - G. F. was an outstanding naturalist and world traveler who has traveled with the famous James Cook for years the world's oceans. Fits not it be excellent and it is evident that a well-known shipping company their newest, largest and most modern ship baptizing them in the name of Georg Forster and hence the name &quot;the world bears&quot;? Just to be documented in the GF-Wikipedia contribution and nothing else! - Just as an example, at the Wikipedia entries on the cities Solingen, Dresden, Marburg and Coburg was correctly identified and proceed accordingly. - Why did the post Georg Forster not above also equal to the special postage stamp with away? The stands rather for the word Advertising ~ in the case for the post which has thus probably sold more brands of collectors. -. Buonasera (talk) 16:33, 13 Jul 2015 (CEST)

:What about advertising on this assessment, I also do not understand .-- Mr. Froude (talk) 17:18, 13 July 2015 (UTC)

::Even me is completely incomprehensible, what should be advertising on this assessment, because Buonasera has nevertheless expressed very clear what is meant by a (maritime) Findings .-- Semi Versus (Talk) 12:50, 14 July 2015 ( CEST)

:::This clear appreciation has really nothing to do with &quot;advertising&quot;. Too often, here is a hasty view, often well-meaning, in fact, implemented immediately and the &quot;eraser&quot; is set to work. Please inform correctly once. Endrick (Discussion) 05:50 July 14 2015 (CEST) (05:59, 15 July 2015 (CEST), date / time added later, see Help: Signature)

&lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Buonasera2|Buonasera2]] ([[User talk:Buonasera2|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Buonasera2|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

:Hello {{ping|Buonasera2}}, thanks for bringing this disagreement to the talk page, a few comments:
:*de-Wiki decisions have no influence on en-Wiki as separate project with own policies (no offense meant: de-Wiki editors would say exactly the same in the opposite case).
:*Translating and copy/pasting ''others' comments from de-Wiki'' is not a good idea imo - see above, these are 2 separate projects.
:But aside from that, I disagree with the inclusion in general: Compare this &quot;appreciation&quot; with the GDR stamp. The stamp is an offical, notable recognition on national level. The logistics company is just a single company, giving their carrier a good name with some history. Of course that's a nice gesture, but nowhere near the same level as a national stamp, official memorial or other kinds of recognition for his legacy. In short: that kind of appreciation is not a significant, notable part of his legacy (even if it may not be promotional per se). A few more quick points, only incase the fact is kept: 1) The information would need a reliable source for an article on FA level. 2) The image is obsolete: it only shows a standard container ship and adds nothing to the article (readers know, how a container ship looks like). 3) The fact does not need a separate header, short sections are discouraged by MOS. The information could be simply included in &quot;Legacy&quot; (in a broader sense of the term). [[User:GermanJoe|GermanJoe]] ([[User talk:GermanJoe|talk]]) 18:38, 27 July 2015 (UTC)
:I think the fact that some company names some ship after him is essentially trivia and not encyclopaedic information about the person. [[Albert Einstein]] should not include a list of all schools ever named after Albert Einstein, and I don't think this is a very different case. —'''[[User:Kusma|Kusma]]''' ([[User talk:Kusma|t]]·[[Special:Contributions/Kusma|c]]) 09:48, 28 July 2015 (UTC)
::Hello [[User:Kusma|Kusma]], I thank you that you have taken the time to tell me your opinion on the matter. -  I have made myself unfortunately too easy. -  I should have put up for discussion the problem in the English Wikipedia. - Maybe the result would be similar to the failed in the German Wikipedia. - We are in this specific case disagree and leave things as they are now. -- [[User:Buonasera2|Buonasera2]] ([[User talk:Buonasera2|talk]]) 20:05, 31 July 2015 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Georg Forster]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=712348116 my edit]. You may add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it, if I keep adding bad data, but formatting bugs should be reported instead. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether, but should be used as a last resort. I made the following changes:
*Attempted to fix sourcing for http://www.filosofie.leidenuniv.nl/content_docs/publicaties/Kleingeld/six_varieties_of_cosmopolitanism.pdf

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 15:54, 28 March 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>tpjx22etn711mujlyvcniq9f43wt307</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
