<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Dartmouth College</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>8568</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746365756</id>
      <parentid>746316019</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-27T00:03:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lowercase sigmabot III</username>
        <id>17518500</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Archiving 2 discussion(s) to [[Talk:Dartmouth College/Archive 3]]) (bot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21397">{{article history
|action1=PR
|action1date=06:09, 6 Jun 2005
|action1link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Dartmouth College/archive1
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=14802515

|action2=GAN
|action2date=14:39, 9 February 2006
|action2link=
|action2result=listed
|action2oldid=38919564

|action3=PR
|action3date=15:25, 6 March 2007
|action3link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Dartmouth College/archive2
|action3result=reviewed
|action3oldid=112940535

|action4=FAC
|action4date=17:53, 31 August 2007
|action4link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Dartmouth College/archive1
|action4result=not promoted
|action4oldid=154842774

|action5=FAC
|action5date=17:40, 30 September 2007
|action5link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Dartmouth College
|action5result=promoted
|action5oldid=161199477

|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=August 31, 2008
|otddate=2007-12-13
|otdoldid=177380902
|otd2date=2008-12-13
|otd2oldid=257220582
|otd3date=2009-12-13
|otd3oldid=331010005
|otd4date=2010-12-13
|otd4oldid=402177372
|otd5date=2015-12-13
|otd5oldid=695073941
|topic=Socsci
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject United States|class=FA|importance=High|Dartmouth=yes|Dartmouth-importance=Top|NH=yes|NH-importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Universities| class = FA}}
}}
{{Archive box|
* [[Talk:Dartmouth College/Archive 1|Archive 1]]: 2006–07
* [[/Archive 2|Archive 2]]: 2008– —
}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{talkarchivenav|noredlinks=y}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 3
|minthreadsleft = 5
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Dartmouth College/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Auto archiving notice|bot=MiszaBot I |age=90 |small=yes |dounreplied=yes}}
{{Wikipedia:WikiProject Dartmouth College/userboxy}}
&lt;!-- Please comment below this line --&gt;

== Image of [[Dartmouth Conferences (peace)]] ==

Can anyone find an image for that article? The series of conferences seems to have taken part at least partially in this College. If no image from a conference is forthcoming, perhaps we could at least identify a building which hosted one of the conferences? If anyone has any suggestions, please cc them to [[Talk:Dartmouth_Conferences_(peace)]]. Cheers, --&lt;sub style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus]]&amp;#124;[[User talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt; reply here&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sub&gt; 05:25, 19 October 2015 (UTC)

== Where does rape at Dartmouth belong? ==

[[User:NFLisAwesome|NFLisAwesome]], regarding your edit https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Dartmouth_College&amp;diff=724510826&amp;oldid=724494824
with the comment:
&quot;While this very well may merit reference in this article, this particular placement, especially before student groups, seems inappropriate&quot;

The edit was in the Student Life section under the heading Campus Safety. 
What section do you think it should go in?
[[User:Formulairis990|Formulairis990]] ([[User talk:Formulairis990|talk]]) 21:12, 9 June 2016 (UTC)
:{{ping|Formulairis990}} For your information, I was ''not'' the one who reverted it. That would be {{u|2602:30a:2ef0:81c0:c151:582c:200e:abaf}}. All I did was change the hyphen to a dash. '''&lt;span&gt;[[User:NFLisAwesome|&lt;font color=&quot;#03202F&quot;&gt;NFL&lt;/font&gt;]][[Special:Contributions/NFLisAwesome|&lt;font color=&quot;#A5ACAF&quot;&gt;is&lt;/font&gt;]][[User talk:ZappaOMati|&lt;font color=&quot;#DD4814&quot;&gt;Awesome&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;''' &lt;small&gt;([[User:ZappaOMati|ZappaOMati]])&lt;/small&gt; 00:13, 10 June 2016 (UTC)
::[[User:NFLisAwesome|NFLisAwesome]], my sincere apologies, I was confused by the way the anonymous editor is identified in the edit attribution.[[User:Formulairis990|Formulairis990]] ([[User talk:Formulairis990|talk]]) 16:19, 10 June 2016 (UTC)

Hi [[User:Formulairis990|Formulairis990]]. Sorry for all the confusion. I just want to reiterate: I have no problems with the inclusion of this info. I'm not sure it should be assigned priority above &quot;student groups&quot; and &quot;athletics&quot;, though. I'd recommend placing it above &quot;Native Americans at Dartmouth&quot; or below &quot;Traditions&quot;. Plus, the paucity of information makes it seem even more out of place than it otherwise would be. So maybe augment that section with a bit more information, perhaps additional sources or commentary. I hope that helps.[[User:2602:30a:2ef0:81c0:c151:582c:200e:abaf]]
:::Please indent your responses by prefixing it with a colon for each indentation.
:::Why do you take issue with source by demanding &quot;additional sources&quot;? 
:::The federal data is collected directly from Dartmouth, which it is must provide under federal law. It is hard to see how any other source would not in itself rely on this data, unless Dartmouth is falsifying the data it is reporting. The edit cites a Washington Post article which did an objective ranking analysis of this data. 
:::The federal law was recently enacted to create this data because there was no such publicly available data. The Washington Post is a preeminent investigative journalistic institution.
:::Could you explain your rational for your priority ordering. Student safety is pertinent to all students, but you give higher priority to &quot;athletics&quot;, a recreational pursuit, of interest to some, in an Ivy League school which can not even provide athletic scholarships. 
:::If you wish to see &quot;commentary&quot; added, please make edits as you see fit, or bring up your edits for discussion.[[User:Formulairis990|Formulairis990]] ([[User talk:Formulairis990|talk]]) 16:45, 13 June 2016 (UTC)
:::I copied existing content on police raids, hazing, and sexual harassment accusations from the section Student Groups that immediately follows Student Safety. This adds additional sources and commentary. The content previously preceded Athletics and all the other sections.[[User:Formulairis990|Formulairis990]] ([[User talk:Formulairis990|talk]]) 17:01, 15 June 2016 (UTC)

== What doesn't belong in the Dartmouth article introduction? What does? Why? ==

[[User:Nomoskedasticity|Nomoskedasticity]], in fulfillment of your request (https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Dartmouth_College&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=725688782&amp;oldid=725649850), I've contrived a space below for discussion on recent alterations of the Dartmouth article. From what I can glean, the introductory section suffices the requirements stipulated in the Wikipedia [[Wikipedia:Manual of Style/Lead section|Manual of Style]]. In my opinion, there is no undue specificity, no critical omission, and no overt or subtle subjectivity. Moreover, none of the statements seem to conflate the institution beyond what is well-known or substantiated. The only facet of the introduction that might cause any reasonable concern is the &quot;It is consistently ranked among the best and most selective institutions of higher learning in the United States&quot; bit. 
Now, the Wikipedia [[Wikipedia:Manual of Style/Lead section|Manual of Style]] ''does'' state in the &quot;Giving 'equal validity' can create a false balance&quot; section that not &quot;every minority view or extraordinary claim needs to be presented along with commonly accepted mainstream scholarship as if they were of equal validity.&quot; However, the notion that Dartmouth is &quot;among the best and most selective institutions&quot; in the U.S. is well-supported and additional sources can certainly be added to further evidence this reality. It is also &quot;commonly accepted&quot; among &quot;mainstream scholarship&quot;. Rankings including but not limited to the [[U.S. News &amp; World Report]], [[Forbes]], [[Princeton Review ]], and [[Business Insider]] place Dartmouth in the top 15 universities in the United States. The [[Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching]] and [[U.S. News &amp; World Report]] deem the university &quot;most selective&quot;, and [[Princeton Review ]] gave Dartmouth a selectivity rating of 99 out of 99. There is no doubt, thus, that Dartmouth is &quot;consistently ranked among the best and most selective institutions of higher learning in the United States&quot; (Note: only the U.S. is mentioned, not the world). The only other possible contentions I can conceive of regard the university's &quot;extensive research enterprise&quot; and &quot;numerous community outreach and study abroad programs&quot;. The source cited may not be sufficient enough, and certainly more can be augmented, but again, I'm hard-pressed to see how this lacks a &quot;neutral point of view&quot;, is not &quot;commonly accepted&quot; among &quot;mainstream scholarship&quot;, or is unworthy of inclusion in the summary. Precedent is also a guiding principle here. The [[Princeton University|Princeton]] article states that &quot;It is consistently ranked as one of the best universities in the world&quot;. The [[Harvard University|Harvard]] article reads: &quot;[Harvard's] history, influence and wealth have made it one of the world's most prestigious universities&quot;. The [[Brown University|Brown]] article maintains that &quot;admissions is very selective&quot;. The [[Stanford University|Stanford]] page says the school is &quot;one of the world's most prestigious institutions.&quot; Finally, the [[University of Pennsylvania|U Penn]] article mentions its &quot;broad range of academic departments&quot;, &quot;extensive research enterprise&quot;, and &quot;number of community outreach and public service programs.&quot; The quality and amount of evidence given to support these claims are equal to what's presented in the Dartmouth article. Interestingly, in observing the edit histories of those pieces, arguments against the inclusion of such assertions aren't raised. In fact, not only are the repudiations and need for &quot;consensus&quot; raised here scarce elsewhere, the editors who challenge these statements here find no issue with like sentiments about institutions in the same &quot;Ivy League&quot; echelon as Dartmouth. My question is: why is Dartmouth different? Either nothing is wrong with this article or a lot is wrong with this one and similar ones. Which one is it? Maintaining uniformity among these Wikipedia articles ''is'' important to ensuring no favor is bestowed to some institutions and not to others. So please advise [[User:Nomoskedasticity|Nomoskedasticity]] or anyone else who takes issue with this article as it stands or with my justifications in favor of its present state. [[User:128.252.33.1]]
:&lt;small&gt;I removed the material you noted in the intro of the Princeton article.  The two citations provided don't come anywhere close to supporting the statement. [[User:ElKevbo|ElKevbo]] ([[User talk:ElKevbo|talk]]) 16:23, 17 June 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
:From what I recall, the most extensive discussion about whether to include broad statements about quality in the lead of an article occurred, appropriately enough, at the Harvard article.  You can probably get a good sense of where the discussion ended up by looking at the broad range of sources that support the current statement.  As noted above, I oppose the inclusion of broad statement of quality that don't have an equally broad set of supporting references.  Simply having one year's worth of rankings don't come anywhere close to supporting such an assertion.  Even multiple years of rankings don't support a broad assertion of quality; in fact, that might raise concerns about [[WP:SYN|inappropriate synthesis]].  (Note that a very valid and workable around some of these issues is to narrow one's focus e.g., reputation, rankings.)  So I'm not opposed to these kinds of statements but it's clear that few institutions can support them with the numerous high quality sources that such statements require.
:I don't feel as strongly about the selectivity issue except that I'll note that selectivity is often used as a proxy for quality which (a) raises issue of [[WP:OR]] for any editor trying to make that connection him or herself and (b) leads us right back to the preceding discussion about quality.  Selectivity and other admissions data, possibly excluding yield, are also very easy to misunderstand and misuse.  Finally, take care not to attribute qualitative judgments of ranking data to organizations that don't actually assign their own judgments but simply use categories created by others.  For example, I don't think that the [[Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching]] (actually Indiana University's Center for Postsecondary Research now since the classifications have been transferred to them) actually categorizes admissions selectivity but instead they, like many others, simply rely on Barron's. [[User:ElKevbo|ElKevbo]] ([[User talk:ElKevbo|talk]]) 16:33, 17 June 2016 (UTC)
::Thanks for instilling some clarity, [[User:ElKevbo|ElKevbo]]. Am I wrong in assuming that the central thrust of your reply is in favor of retaining what's already there? Or, are you recommending complete deletion of that statement or that more sources be added to support it? Additionally, you mentioned that &quot;having one year's worth of rankings [doesn't] come anywhere close to supporting&quot; qualitative assessments. I have to reject the premise of this, though. The article is not declaring that Dartmouth ''is'', in fact, one of the &quot;best&quot; schools in the country. It states: &quot;It is ''consistently'' ''ranked'' among the best and most selective institutions of higher learning in the United States&quot;. This isn't directly qualitative at all, it's stating a fact. The operative word here that may raise issues is &quot;consistently&quot;. Now I understand your point that reliance on merely one year's worth of rankings is tenuous; but I'm confused. Is it the quality of the rankings provided that is problematic? If not, how many years is enough? 2 years? 3 years? 5? 10? 15? All the rankings rendered by a given publication, ''ever''? And, since these ranking systems accrete reputability over time, citing the years when the publication was in its nascent state could be deemed less legitimate. My point is: where does it end? What exactly is the limiting principle? (This is [[User:128.252.33.1]] in a different network)
:::I don't feel strongly about retaining or removing the material; I only feel strongly that what is included is well-supported by high quality, reliable sources. You're correct that the primary focus of my attention right now is on the word &quot;consistently.&quot; You've asked good questions but my response would be that an editor who wishes to include that statement should provide sources that explicitly make that claim; to do otherwise (e.g., selecting one's own personal favorite rankings and determining how many years count as &quot;consistent&quot;) would be [[WP:OR|original research]]. Please remember that if you can't find high quality, independent sources that make that claim then it probably doesn't belong in an encyclopedia article. [[User:ElKevbo|ElKevbo]] ([[User talk:ElKevbo|talk]]) 19:39, 17 June 2016 (UTC)
::::Gotcha, [[User:ElKevbo|ElKevbo]]. Thanks for making all that clear! (This is [[User:128.252.33.1]] in a different network)
:First things first: stop trying to edit-war this material into the article.  (Well, as it happens, you now don't have that option...)  Second: the sources you are using are primary sources in this context.  Third: the terms are specific to an American cultural trope of &quot;selectivity&quot;; they do not make sense to readers who haven't been fed from birth on USNWR.  Finally, there's no requirement of uniformity; perhaps there should be (and then we could decide whether other articles should perhaps exclude this sort of information from the first paragraph), but there isn't.  [[User:Nomoskedasticity|Nomoskedasticity]] ([[User talk:Nomoskedasticity|talk]]) 08:49, 18 June 2016 (UTC)
::At the risk of giving this reply more heed than it deserves, let me clear a few things up for you, [[User:Nomoskedasticity|Nomoskedasticity]]. I'm not insistent on including this information, first off. In fact, if you'd notice: I didn't even write the sentence in question (https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Dartmouth_College&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=725408324&amp;oldid=725333360). I am, however, eager to contrive a solution (notice: I created this Talk section to resolve the issue and &quot;describe the best practices...clarify principles, resolve conflicts, and otherwise further our goals&quot; as [[Help:Editing|Wikipedia editing procedure]] prescribes). I'm also adamant about counteracting obstinate Wikipedia editors who unilaterally delete material without cogent justification (or in your case, no explanation at all), then tout the need for &quot;consensus&quot;, and in an act of blithe inattention, fail to realize that the material they've reverted to contains the exact same information (unless you're dispute is over ''where'' the material is placed, which again, no one could possibly know since you've explained nothing). Secondly, the notion that the &quot;cultural trope&quot; of admissions selectivity, being specific to America in this context, is beyond what readers are capable of understanding doesn't make a single iota of sense. One can cite ARWU, QS, Times Higher Education, CWTS Leiden, Telegraph, Mastersportal, Ukun, and a surfeit of other non-U.S. based [[College and university rankings|global and country-specific rankings]] that use similar metrics. As you can see, the entire developed world revels in this ranking obsession. Why do you think institutions in the top 20 spots on the USNWR receive over 200 percent more applications from international students than the next 20? It would seem that those from without are as much &quot;fed from birth on USNWR&quot; as those within. Thus, these &quot;American terms&quot; as you call them, which are pervasively employed nearly everywhere, are not specific to this country or any other; they're universal. Attempting to use the Dartmouth Wikipedia article—of all places!—as a forum for advancing your weak crusade on American ranking systems, which many find valuable in assessing institutional quality (although I personally don't), is inappropriate by any measure and is proof of your subjectivity.  Finally, I concede there is no requirement of uniformity among Wikipedia articles, but that's certainly no reason to condone the obvious disparities between them, nor does it justify imposing a double-standard by &quot;edit warring&quot; for an unspecified reason in one piece and failing to do so in others. Again, the central question here bears repetition: What doesn't belong in the Dartmouth article introduction? What does? ''Why?'' There's no need to comment in this section if you have nothing substantive to contribute beyond assigning false blame. Thanks. (This is [[User:128.252.33.1]] in a different network)

Please advise on recent changes. (This is [[User:128.252.33.1]] in a different network)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:6|one external link|6 external links}} on [[Dartmouth College]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=738913983 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20150929223025/https://thedartmouth.com/2015/09/18/college-ends-need-blind-admission-for-international-students/ to http://thedartmouth.com/2015/09/18/college-ends-need-blind-admission-for-international-students/
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20150103024149/https://thedartmouth.com/2014/04/10/club-fencing-takes-first-national-title/ to http://thedartmouth.com/2014/04/10/club-fencing-takes-first-national-title/
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://foxnews.com/story/0,2933,1255,00.html
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.bates.edu/oren-cheney.xml
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.politicalstudies.org/pdf/psr/hix.pdf
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.tuck.dartmouth.edu/about/campus/index.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 19:18, 11 September 2016 (UTC)

== Could someone clear up confusion, on Mathew Brady ==

Mathew Brady, US Secretary of the Treasury, is listed as a Dartmouth graduate, with a link to Mathew B. Brady (May 18, 1822 – January 15, 1896) the American photographer known for his scenes of the US Civil War.  No mention made in that linked article that Mathew B. Brady the photographer was ever US Secretary of the Treasury.
https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mathew_Brady#Later_years_and_death
...
The disambiguation page does not help.  
https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthew_Brady_(disambiguation)
Can't find an article about Mathew Brady, US Secretary of the Treasury.
Can any experts clear this up?

[[Special:Contributions/68.35.173.107|68.35.173.107]] ([[User talk:68.35.173.107|talk]]) 16:31, 26 October 2016 (UTC)

:It seems the picture is mislabeled: it's of [[Salmon Chase]], TAKEN by Mathew Brady.  See https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Mathew_Brady,_Portrait_of_Secretary_of_the_Treasury_Salmon_P._Chase,_officer_of_the_United_States_government_(1860%E2%80%931865,_full_version).jpg.  I'm going to change the picture's title in the article. [[User:Contributor321|Contributor321]] ([[User talk:Contributor321|talk]]) 16:55, 26 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>fd56fkeiswsq5v5bcjieyedlj9hl8x8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
