<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Nebula Award</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>7615219</id>
    <revision>
      <id>699963166</id>
      <parentid>699962381</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-01-15T14:44:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>PresN</username>
        <id>1712026</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9308">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Science Fiction |class=GA |importance=High |type=Article |listas=Nebula Award}}
{{WikiProject Literature |class=GA |importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Awards and prizes |class=GA |importance=mid}}
}}{{ArticleHistory|action1=GAN
|action1date=21:15, 4 September 2012
|action1link=Talk:Nebula Award/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=508244778
|action2=FTC
|action2date=15:07, 23 October 2012 (UTC)
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured topic candidates/Nebula Award/archive1
|action2result=promoted
|ftname=Nebula Award
|ftmain=yes

|currentstatus=GA
|topic=literature
}}

==Photo request==
A picture of the actual award would be nice... --[[User:JollyRogerz|JollyRogerz]] 13:31, 25 October 2006 (UTC)

==Notes and suggestions==
Word within SFWA from numerous sources is that the award has no bearing on sales, and can, in fact, reduce advances and sales of an author who isn't already an established name.  Both the Hugo and Nebula are seen as being &quot;literary&quot; and pretentious by many readers.  It's entirely dependent upon how the author's existing market is perceived. [[User:209.43.8.69|209.43.8.69]] 00:51, 25 January 2007 (UTC) Michael Z. Williamson

Changed &quot;award is handed out&quot; to &quot;Award is presented&quot; since the former seems to belittle it. [[User:209.43.8.69|209.43.8.69]] 00:56, 25 January 2007 (UTC) Michael Z. Williamson

== List of Notable Recipients ==

I've shortened and ordered the list of notable Nebula winners.  In the interest of scannability and conciseness, I cut down the list to anyone who has won the award three times or more.  Without wanting to exclude anyone in particular, the list must be short enough to read well in paragraph form, so it cannot include every Nebula winner who some wikipedian thinks is notable enough to add to this list--I assume that's how this list grew so monstrous in the first place.

Also, how do we list a reference for this?  The [[Nebula Award for Best Novel]] and related pages have references--can someone come up with a concise way of noting the source for this information?  [[User:Tdimhcs|Tdimhcs]] ([[User talk:Tdimhcs|talk]]) 20:54, 20 July 2012 (UTC)

{{Talk:Nebula Award/GA1}}

Something is off here. On the list there is no mention of Samuel R. Delany's winning the Nebula Award for &quot;Ye, and Gomorrah&quot; for Short Story, the same year he won it for &quot;The Einstien Intersection&quot; as best SF novel. I know he won it for the short story, because I am looking at the twelve(?) pound block of lucite with the sparkly things inside which he/I was presented with that evening in New York in 1968 right now. Beset wishes. (SRD)  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/108.52.140.190|108.52.140.190]] ([[User talk:108.52.140.190|talk]]) 14:37, 15 January 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:The winners themselves (and the nominees) are listed at the various award category lists- in this case [[Nebula Award for Best Short Story]] and [[Nebula Award for Best Novel]], where he/you are listed as the winner in 1968 for both categories. This article doesn't go into winner statistics like you winning twice in the same year, though perhaps it should. --'''[[User:PresN|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Pres&lt;/span&gt;]][[User talk:PresN|&lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;N&lt;/span&gt;]]''' 14:44, 15 January 2016 (UTC)

== Awards tables ==

The individual article pages, [[Nebula Award for Best Script|best script]], [[Nebula Award for Best Short Story|best short story]], [[Nebula Award for Best Novelette|best novelette]], [[Nebula Award for Best Novella|nest novella]] and [[Nebula Award for Best Novel|best novel]], the tables need some serious work. Most awards tables use rowspans for the year only to make it easier to read and separate the different nominees and winners. Examples: [[Academy Award for Best Writing (Original Screenplay)]], [[Golden Globe Award for Best Screenplay]]. Also, they all include this little tidbit:

::''&quot;In the following table, the years correspond to the date of the ceremony, rather than when the work was first released. Entries with a blue background and an asterisk (*) next to the writer's name have won the award; those with a white background are the other nominees on the shortlist. Entries with a gray background and a plus sign (+) mark a year when &quot;no award&quot; was selected as the winner.&quot;''

It's completely unnecessary to have the winners &quot;*&quot; when they are already highlighted within the table and the &quot;+&quot; is also redundant if the &quot;no award&quot; is highlighted gray. [[User:Lady Lotus|Lady Lotus]] ([[User talk:Lady Lotus|talk]]) 17:30, 5 November 2012 (UTC)
:I knew before looking that your two examples weren't going to be featured lists. Know how? Because it's completely impossible nowadays (i.e. at least the past 2 years) to get a list featured if it doesn't follow the [[WP:ACCESS]] parts of the MOS. Part of that doc is that you can't just use color to highlight specific rows that mean something special- like winners. Because if you use a screen-reader, then there's no way to tell the difference. You're not going to get anywhere with removing the &quot;*&quot; signs.
:As far as the rowspans go, I'm not totally against you. They would be nice, if I can figure out a good way to do them (rowpans for the ref column won't work, btw.) The issue, though, is again that MOS- I have no idea if it works right for WP:ACCESS, and didn't get a clear answer last time I asked.
:You really want rowspans? Go to [[WT:FLC]] or [[WT:ACCESS]], and pin somebody down on if they're okay for use in featured lists. You do that, and I'll even help you change all the Hugo/Nebula award lists to use them. I'm not as against it as you seem to be in favor of it, so I'll go along. But since we're talking about 22 lists at minimum, I'm not going to put in that massive amount of effort only to get blocked for it on my next FLC or have it all be reverted. --'''[[User:PresN|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Pres&lt;/span&gt;]][[User talk:PresN|&lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;N&lt;/span&gt;]]''' 21:09, 5 November 2012 (UTC)

:::OK that seems fair enough, and I really wasn't changing things to make them worse or just to be a brat, just trying to make the pages look nicer. The only thing I'm really looking for is the change in the years, it's just a jumbled mess and I totally understand about the accessibility aspect bc i remove rowspans on most pages but when it's things like this, it just makes more sense and looks nicer. So i'll try to get an answer from someone but if not, I'll be ok with it. Thank you for responding nicely :) [[User:Lady Lotus|Lady Lotus]] ([[User talk:Lady Lotus|talk]]) 17:24, 6 November 2012 (UTC)

== Award year ==

We say in the lead that the 2012 Awards were presented in Washington DC, May 2012.

The sponsor SFWA at [http://www.sfwa.org/2011/05/nebula-award-winners-announced/ &quot;Nebula Awards Winners&quot; (announced)] calls those the 2011 winners --and that dating convention holds back to &quot;2000 Nebula Award Winners&quot; at the bottom of the same page.

I don't know who consistently we or they follow the pattern reported here. --[[User:P64|P64]] ([[User talk:P64|talk]]) 18:35, 3 April 2013 (UTC)

:The standard used to be that we went by the year that the award ceremony was in, to maintain consistency with other awards (such as the Hugo)- they all got moved over to the SFWA counting scheme a few months ago, though, and I guess this page didn't get updated. Now done. --'''[[User:PresN|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Pres&lt;/span&gt;]][[User talk:PresN|&lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;N&lt;/span&gt;]]''' 18:51, 3 April 2013 (UTC)

:: Regarding {{c|SFWA Grand Masters}}, now created by the practically annual Damon Knight Award, the association has been inconsistent during the last year: [http://www.sfwa.org/nebula-awards/nebula-weekend/events-program/grandmaster/ Connie Willis listed for 2012] [http://www.sfwa.org/2012/12/2012-damon-knight-memorial-grand-master-awarded-to-gene-wolfe/ Gene Wolfe announced for 2012]
:: Continued at [[Talk: Damon Knight Memorial Grand Master Award]]. --[[User:P64|P64]] ([[User talk:P64|talk]]) 20:42, 3 April 2013 (UTC)

::: In rewriting the paragraph on other awards beside Nebulas, I changed 1976/1996/2007 to 1975/1995/2006 (because our outside source SFE gives those dates) and neglected to change Bradbury's 2010 to 2009. 
::: As I noted above, SFWA is not consistent. I doubt that either SFE or Locus is consistent. On SFE's part, shouldn't that be Norton Awards from 2005 --the year established and the first eligible publication year? (I can't imagine where we got 2007, maybe a simple typo.)
::: Locus refers to Nebula rules changes early in 2009[http://www.locusmag.com/SFAwards/Db/Nebula.html], first governing awards presented in 2010. I don't know whether that is the most recent rule change we date 2010. Elsewhere (EN.wikipedia, not SF) I have used &quot;in 2009&quot; and &quot;for 2010&quot; regarding rule changes in 2009 that first bear on the 2009/2010 or 2010 awards. Unfortunately that suggests &quot;in 2010&quot; and &quot;for 2009&quot; regarding awards official dated 2010 for works published in 2009.
::: Anyway, I don't know whether those Locus 2009 rules changes are our changes &quot;most recently in 2010&quot;. --[[User:P64|P64]] ([[User talk:P64|talk]]) 20:32, 27 April 2013 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>q7uuyu3tvj9k0pnroqb6jjyajcpvlh6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
