<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Addition</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>163868</id>
    <revision>
      <id>717700603</id>
      <parentid>700449060</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-04-29T06:41:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JJMC89 bot</username>
        <id>27446209</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>subst /Comments to [[WP:DCS|discontinue comments subpage]]) ([[Project:AWB|AWB]] [12009]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="58543">{{Vital article|level=3|topic=Mathematics|class=GA}}
{{Article history
|currentstatus=GA
|topic=math

|action1=GAN
|action1date=15:51, 27 December 2014 (UTC)
|action1link=Talk:Addition/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=639821710

|action2=FAC
|action2date=2015-04-24
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Addition/archive1
|action2result=failed
|action2oldid=655829071
}}
{{To do|3}}

{{maths rating|frequentlyviewed=yes|vital=Y|class=GA|importance=top|field=basics}}
{{WP1.0|class=GA|category=category|VA=yes}}

==Split?==

I think this article should deal only with the binary (dyadic) operation x+y, and arbitrary sums should be moved to a separate page, possibly named [[Summation]] or [[Sigma notation]] or both. [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 05:42, 28 November 2005 (UTC)
:Also, once the split is done, we might want to merge [[Addition of natural numbers]] into [[Addition]], where someone might read it. [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 05:50, 28 November 2005 (UTC)

:Strongly support splitting off [[Summation]]. Support merging [[Addition of natural numbers]]. --[[User:KSmrq|KSmrq]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:KSmrq|T]]&lt;/sup&gt; 00:55, 29 November 2005 (UTC)

:I agree, it seems like a good idea. My only worry is that [[Addition of natural numbers]] is technical in places, but I trust you can handle that. -- [[User:Jitse Niesen|Jitse Niesen]] ([[User talk:Jitse Niesen|talk]]) 12:48, 29 November 2005 (UTC)
:I agree with a split. Also a reference to [[Series (mathematics)]], including the Taylor and Fourier series should be added.([[User:Igny|Igny]] 18:14, 29 November 2005 (UTC))

Okay, thanks for your suggestions! I'll probably do it on Friday. [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 18:57, 29 November 2005 (UTC)

:I agree that you should outsource the sigmas, but I strongly '''disagree''' with &quot;[[Addition of natural numbers]]&quot; being incorporated into this article.  That seems overly Bourbakist.  The content of the article &quot;''Addition of natural numbers''&quot; certainly needs a better home, but it isn't here.  Check out &lt;nowiki&gt;[[Category:Set theory]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;.  [[User:Silly rabbit|Silly rabbit]] 20:48, 29 November 2005 (UTC)

::Well, then I won't do the merger yet, or perhaps at all; we'll see how [[Addition]] looks after the split to [[Summation]] and go from there. We'll still need to do ''something'' about [[Addition of natural numbers]], possibly taking a hard look at [[Natural number]] itself. (Too many math articles seem to have catchall sections named &quot;Properties&quot;...) And [[Addition]] will still need a bit more discussion on its most fundamental example.
::Oh, and for those of us (me) who aren't cultured enough, what do you mean by &quot;Bourbakist&quot;? [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 22:38, 29 November 2005 (UTC)
:::See [[Nicolas Bourbaki]]  ;-)  [[User:Silly rabbit|Silly rabbit]] 23:03, 7 December 2005 (UTC)
::::Holy crap, I always thought it was some person! [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 23:37, 7 December 2005 (UTC)

==Split.==
Okay, I've done the split. See [[Summation]] and [[Talk:Summation]]. As I write this, however, the dust has yet to clear... [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 02:13, 3 December 2005 (UTC)

Still to do, possibly for someone else:
*&lt;strike&gt;Chainsaw &quot;In music&quot; section. I like music theory as much as anyone else, but come on.&lt;/strike&gt;
*&lt;strike&gt;Determine where interlang links are appropriate in [[Summation]].&lt;/strike&gt;
*Add more explanation of what addition ''is''.
[[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 02:28, 3 December 2005 (UTC)

:Come on what? [[User:Hyacinth|Hyacinth]] 08:18, 3 December 2005 (UTC)

::Come on, as in the example I moved to [[Musical_set_theory#Addition]] was an overgrown example of arithmetic modulo 12. I replaced it with the comment, &quot;In [[modular arithmetic]], the set of integers modulo 12 has twelve elements; it inherits an addition operation from the integers that is central to [[musical set theory]].&quot; which now appears in the Generalizations section. I hope that the Generalizations section makes it clear that there are countless different versions of addition indispensible to all kinds of fields.
::In fact, I'm more than a little uneasy that you've linked to it from the top of [[Addition]].
::#The notion of addition in musical set theory doesn't have its own article, and
::#the material linked to never defines addition,
::#nor does it use the word &quot;addition&quot; except in the heading you added, and
::#the word &quot;sum&quot; is ''just a link back to &lt;strike&gt;here&lt;/strike&gt;''. (''now a link back to [[summation]] after re-redirect of [[sum]])
::Along with the mention in Generalizations, would you be happy with a See also link? [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 18:29, 3 December 2005 (UTC)

::Looks like you agree. Thanks! [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 18:19, 4 December 2005 (UTC)

Of the four interlang links I found, two are pretty respectable. It looks like the German and Russian Wikipedias had the idea of separate articles a long time ago! [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 07:56, 5 December 2005 (UTC)

== More needed material ==

&lt;strike&gt;I've indicated where I think sections on history and algorithms might go.&lt;/strike&gt; I hope I'm not defying [[Wikipedia:Don't disrupt Wikipedia to illustrate a point|this guideline]]. [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 22:06, 3 December 2005 (UTC)
:Never mind... [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 00:57, 8 December 2005 (UTC)

Oh, and someone with a reference on combinatorics ought to have a look at what I've written in Related operations. [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 22:07, 4 December 2005 (UTC)

test test [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 19:33, 9 December 2005 (UTC)

== Etymology ==

Does the source state that &quot;addere&quot; means &quot;to give to&quot;? Certainly, &quot;ad&quot; can mean &quot;to&quot; and &quot;dare&quot; means &quot;to give&quot;, but that doesn't imply that &quot;addere&quot; means &quot;to give to&quot;. Charlton T. Lewis, An Elementary Latin Dictionary, lists &quot;to put to, place upon, lay on, join, attach&quot; as meanings [http://perseus.mpiwg-berlin.mpg.de/cgi-bin/ptext?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0060%3Aentry%3D%23305]. Furthermore, the form &quot;addend&quot; does not exist in Latin. As you say, the word is inflected; the canonical form &quot;addendus&quot;, which is the masculine singular nominative. -- [[User:Jitse Niesen|Jitse Niesen]] ([[User talk:Jitse Niesen|talk]]) 02:37, 14 January 2006 (UTC)

:Well, I know virtually nothing about Latin (Does it show?), so let me just quote. Schwartzman says:
::'''add''' (verb), '''addition''' (noun), '''additive''' (adjective): from the Latin verb ''addere'', itself a compound of ''ad'' (''q.v.'') &quot;to&quot; and ''dare'' &quot;to give.&quot; When you add an amount to something, you &quot;give more to&quot; that something. The Indo-European root is ''do-'' &quot;to give.&quot; Related borrowings from Latin include ''donate'' and ''condone'' &quot;to give sanction or approval.&quot; A related borrowing from Greek is the ''dose'' of medicine given to a patient. In arithmetic, the &quot;+&quot; symbol...
:He seems pretty confident about the giving. I originally wrote &quot;give more to&quot; to follow the source, but I decided the &quot;more&quot; wasn't justified without speaking of &quot;an amount&quot;, so I deleted it, leaving &quot;give to&quot;.
:I guess I shouldn't be too surprised that ''addere'' has other meanings; if you'd like to add Lewis' list, be my guest.
:As for ''addend'' not actually being a Latin word, I wasn't sure about that, so I kind of hedged. How should we put it? [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 02:58, 14 January 2006 (UTC)

:Actually, as long as I'm quoting, I should quote this entry:
::'''addend''' (noun): from Latin ''addere'' &quot;to add&quot; (''q.v.''), with the suffix ''-nd'', which creates a type of passive causative, so that Latin ''numerus addendus'' meant &quot;the number to be added.&quot; In the statement 3 + 4 = 7, many Renaissance writers...
:What the heck is a &quot;passive causative&quot;? Is it just a gerundive, or am I missing something? [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 03:06, 14 January 2006 (UTC)

Well, I think I've fixed the passages in question. [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 09:25, 28 January 2006 (UTC)

:It is fine now, thanks; you're doing great on the article by the way (sorry for the late reaction) -- [[User:Jitse Niesen|Jitse Niesen]] ([[User talk:Jitse Niesen|talk]]) 14:46, 31 January 2006 (UTC)
::Thanks! [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 20:48, 31 January 2006 (UTC)

== Commutativity ==

Would it be good to mention under commutativity that addition is only commutative for a finite number of terms or an [[absolutely convergent]] [[infinite series]], but not that it is not commutative for a [[conditional convergence|conditionaly convergent]] infinite series?  --[[User:FurciferRNB|FurciferRNB]] 1 March 2006
:Hmm... I think that's beyond the scope of the main body of the article, which deals with addition of two terms. Perhaps you could add a note under ''Other ways to add: Summation'' towards the bottom? I'm not sure how to phrase it. [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 20:51, 1 March 2006 (UTC)

== conjugations ==

Under the section Notation and terminology, addition and add are said to be conjugations of the latin verb addere.  They are more properly derivatives...  A conjugation is a changed form of a verb indicating aspect, person, number, etc like it says in [[grammatical conjugation]], but a nonal form or a reuse of a verb stem in another language is a [[Derivative_%28disambiguation%29|derivative]].  Verily, the Romans had a regularized form additio, from which we get addition.--[[User:Josh Rocchio|Josh Rocchio]] 22:07, 20 March 2006 (UTC)
:Hmm... interesting. Well, I guess I'll go fix it; natually, you're welcome to clean up any more mistakes you see! [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 22:19, 20 March 2006 (UTC)
::Sorry, I didn't see your edit. But I'm not sure [[derivation (linguistics)]] is the correct term either. I settled on &quot;loanword derived from the Latin&quot;. -- [[User:Jitse Niesen|Jitse Niesen]] ([[User talk:Jitse Niesen|talk]]) 22:58, 20 March 2006 (UTC)
::Well, I'm not sure that [[loanword]] is correct either, so I changed it to &quot;word derived from the Latin&quot;, which echoes the second sentence of [[etymology]] (&quot;Some words have been derived from other languages &amp;hellip;&quot;). Conclusion: it's dangerous to write about things one does not know. -- [[User:Jitse Niesen|Jitse Niesen]] ([[User talk:Jitse Niesen|talk]]) 23:05, 20 March 2006 (UTC)
:::Amen. When the article is good enough to send to peer review, I'm going to have to advertise it on quite a few WikiProjects for help. [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 23:40, 20 March 2006 (UTC)
::::Sorry to be so late in checking back on this.  Yes, a loan word is more like ''cologne'' or ''bologna''. Addition is most certainly in the realm of linguistics considered to be a derivation of the Latin verb ''addere'', though it seems the [[derivation (linguistics)]] needs another definition or a dismbiguation page, or perhaps I should, more concisely, start the [[derivation (philology)]] page. Thanks for fixing the error so quickly, fellas.--[[User:Josh Rocchio|Josh Rocchio]] 04:38, 31 March 2006 (UTC)


==Addition in analog computers==
I would question the assertion that &quot;Addition is not tremendously important to analog computers, whose essential function is integration.[23]&quot; Analog computes are generally used to solve differential equations, not simple integration, and the RHS of most DE's of interest include the sum of more than one term. So  addition is tremendously important. --[[User:ArnoldReinhold|agr]] 22:34, 18 August 2006 (UTC)

:That makes sense. All I really meant by that sentence was to contrast with digital computers. I guess we could take it out, but then how do we transition from analog to digital? [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 02:35, 19 August 2006 (UTC)

:...okay! Is there anything else fishy in there? [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 04:30, 20 August 2006 (UTC)

::I'm not real happy with the sentence on adding machines. An analogy might be &quot;plowing was so important that the earliest farm tool was called a plow.&quot; I'll try an edit.--[[User:ArnoldReinhold|agr]] 16:24, 21 August 2006 (UTC)

:::Fair enough. I was trying to make a point beyond naming, though, so I'll give that another shot. [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 16:55, 21 August 2006 (UTC)
:::Oh, and I'll also restore &quot;earliest automatic, digital computers&quot;, which is a stronger statement than &quot;earliest mechanical calculators&quot;. My memory is a little hazy, but I believe this assertion is covered by the citation at the end of the paragraph. [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 16:58, 21 August 2006 (UTC)

== The madness of Addition ==

OK, now that I've been pointed to this article by another editor (whose [[User:Salix alba|good name]] I shall not sully by mentioning), I'm going to offer an opinion before even attempting to work on it. (Caveat: I am not a math person. I am a writer and editor outside of Wikipedia; those are the skills and perspective I'm bringing here.)

#This article covers too much territory. It needs to be pared down to basics. Ideally, I think it should provide such a basic level of information that it can be used as a reference term elsewhere without overwhelming people when they click through to it.
#I actually think '''non'''-mathematicians need to work on this article. I think this '''may''' be a case where too much knowledge is a bad thing. There's too much information and detail.
#Addition is one of the most basic building blocks of math as I understand it. This article should reflect that. It should be simple, straightforward. At a glance, I'd say 80% of the content could be tossed, broken into separate articles, or reduced to &quot;see also&quot; or wikilinks. 

I realize this is going against what people have created here. This is why I'm putting this on the talk page before getting all [[WP:BOLD|bold]] on it. I'd like some input on whether people think I'm balmy for this view. I'm not an innumerate person and yet I glaze over reading this article. Thoughts? --[[User:Paul_Pigman|'''&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;Pig&lt;/font&gt;'''&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;man&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;sub&gt;[[User talk:Paul_Pigman|dialogue]]&lt;/sub&gt; 00:34, 17 March 2007 (UTC)

:I'm all for creating summary-style daughter articles. (But plain deletion is Bad and &quot;see also&quot; is a cry for expansion all over again.) [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 00:54, 17 March 2007 (UTC)

::Here's my thinking: When an article gets as large as this, it's a cry to be divided into discrete parts which can concentrate on explaining the specifics. I realize that, because of the very foundational nature of &quot;addition&quot;, there is a desire to enumerate these many mathematical and scientific connections in the same article. However, the drawback to this approach is the reader may be overwhelmed with detail.

::I believe the language in the article needs to be vastly simplified. 

::For example, I have to concentrate to understand the '''first sentence''' of the article. I have to '''really''' concentrate to understand the second sentence. It's not a brag to say I am fairly literate and well versed in the English language. And I '''already''' understand the concept of addition and the use of symbolic representative letters in math. Why is it so difficult? Perhaps it's a problem of translating math, a precise symbolic system, into less precise words. Beyond that point in the article there is an almost unremitting stream of specialized mathematical jargon/cant and terminology. (I'm using &quot;jargon&quot; in a non-pejorative manner here.) When a term is explained/defined with words whose specific contextual meaning is ''also'' difficult to understand, there's a problem. I suppose the many wikilinks are intended to provide additional clarification but it feels like a weak alternative to clearer original text.

::I'm not even sure I could do a better job on the article but I feel these are valid concerns so I'm expressing them. I'm a writer, a wordsmith, if you will. I'm certainly not an advocate of writing to an overly simplistic, grade-school level. But if I'm having trouble comprehending the text, I've found this is a good indication that a large majority of other readers will also have trouble. I ''know'' my points above are radical. However, I also know there comes a point when line editing and tweaking sentences will not noticeably improve the readability of the article. I believe this is one of those times.

::I have no intention of unilaterally making large changes to the article. I just think these are things to consider. --[[User:Paul_Pigman|'''&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;Pig&lt;/font&gt;'''&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;man&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;sub&gt;[[User talk:Paul_Pigman|dialogue]]&lt;/sub&gt; 02:57, 17 March 2007 (UTC)

:::You raise valid points that are equally applicable to many introductory-level math articles. It is unfortunately often true that the prose is too difficult or proceeds too quickly for the intended reader.  I hope that you will consider making at least a few changes to illustrate how you would like to see the prose improved.  Typically, the reason that things are phrased the way they are is that the original author didn't, or couldn't, think of a better way to say them.  So some editing by a nonspecialist might inspire the rest of us in how to write the rest more clearly.  Perhaps you could rewrite just the first paragraph - you almost certainly understand the material. [[User:CMummert|CMummert]] · &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:CMummert|talk]]&lt;/small&gt; 03:08, 17 March 2007 (UTC)

:::Yeah, writing a good first sentence is especially hard. I was amused by Mathworld's solution: [http://mathworld.wolfram.com/Addition.html Addition] is &quot;The combining of two or more quantities using the [[plus]] operator&quot;, whereas [http://mathworld.wolfram.com/Plus.html Plus] is &quot;The [[addition]] of two quantities, i.e., a plus b.&quot; I was shooting for something a little more meaningful here! [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 06:13, 17 March 2007 (UTC)

::::Indeed, first paragraphs in maths articles are always hard, I'm somewhat suprised that thiss has proved the case even for something as simple as addition.
::::Encarta has ''The arithmetic operation of addition is indicated by the plus sign (+) and is a means of counting by increments greater than 1. For example, four apples and five apples could be added by putting them together and then counting them individually from 1 to 9. Addition, however, makes it possible to add, or compute, sums more readily.''
::::Britannica ''Combining two sets of objects together, which contain a and b elements, a new set is formed that contains a + b = c objects. The number c is called the sum of a and b''
::::[[simple:Addition|Simple English wikipedia]] has ''In arithmetic, addition is putting two or more numbers together. The sign for addition is &quot;+&quot;. The name for this sign &quot;+&quot; is &quot;plus&quot;.''
::::As to whether its too long, ther is some very advanced material here, especially in the Addition of natural and real numbers, which makes many references to set-theoretic quantities. These could possibly be split off to [[formal definitions of addition]]. Its worth also comparing with [[Subtraction]] and [[Multiplication]] which are both too short and don't come close to comprehensive. --[[User:Salix alba|Salix alba]] ([[User talk:Salix alba|talk]]) 08:51, 17 March 2007 (UTC)

::::I realize the difficulty of explaining addition in plain prose. I think that's why I ranted a bit on the talk page rather than just attempting some changes and providing an example of clearer language. I'll take a whack at the opening para and see if I can make it better. For the record, I think the whole intro should be reduced to a plain para or two on the '''basic''' concept of addition. Info currently in paras three and four shouldn't be in an intro at all. My basic mantra for an intro is '''basic and simple'''. Despite what I said above about not writing to a grade school level, I believe an intro needs to be written as simply as possible without misrepresenting the subject. If there are wikilinked words/phrases in the intro, they themselves need to be easily understood '''without''' clicking through. I'm speaking only of the intro here, not the rest of the article. Ugh. I'm sorry if I appear to be speaking condescendingly to an undoubtedly intelligent group here. It's not my intent to insult anyone. Oh, and thanks for the other examples, Salix and Melchoir. It's very helpful to see how others define the term. --[[User:Paul_Pigman|'''&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;Pig&lt;/font&gt;'''&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;man&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;sub&gt;[[User talk:Paul_Pigman|dialogue]]&lt;/sub&gt; 19:23, 17 March 2007 (UTC)

== Comment ==

If this is true (quoted from [[Addition]]):
:''Performing addition is one of the simplest numerical tasks, accessible to infants as young as five months and even some animals.''
then why can't a person with too many college degrees understand the first paragraph without great effort?  [[User:Mattisse|Anonymous]] 16:57, 18 March 2007 (UTC)

::Musing philosophically (after edit conflit with paul below) -
::[[Piaget]] 1965 - ''it is a great mistake to suppose that a child acquires the notion of number and other mathematical concepts just from teaching. On the contrary, to a remarkable degree he develops them himself, independantly and spontaneously. When an adult try to impose mathematical concepts on a child prematurely, his learning is mearly verbal; true understanding of them come only with mental growth''. 
::My interpretation of this is that it is actually a hard thing to explain in words. When I've taught children basic arathmatic I've primarally used methods other than english paragraphs to explain the concepts - lots of manipulative materials like lego brick, and activities like counting squares and many many examples slowly leading up to a general theory. Bairly a word is written on the page. 
::The other problem is that mathematics is priamilly a constructive field, everything in mathematics builds on a simpler concept, hence addition first requires the idea of counting, 1,2,3,4... Then the idea of counting on hold up four fingers then raise 1,2,3 more fingers, now count how many fingers there are 1,2,3,4,5,6,7. We see reference to other concepts in the other intro paragraphs above, [[set]] is mentioned by Britannica.
::Then we have the fact that addition covers several related things, addition of counting numbers is subitly different to addition of lengths. 
::So I posit that there is an intrinsic dificulty with plain english sentances which do not refer to other concepts and cover the range of things which addition covers. None of the other intro paragraphs above is entirely satisfactory. But then I am a child of [[New Math]] so my education was probably messed up! --[[User:Salix alba|Salix alba]] ([[User talk:Salix alba|talk]]) 19:08, 18 March 2007 (UTC)
:::I was thinking the very same thing! That is, that you were probably a child of [[New Math]] and that could account for the problem. [[User:Mattisse|Anonymouse]] 14:39, 19 March 2007 (UTC)

== Intro paragraph rewrite ==

OK, this is, of course, not as easy as I hoped. I feel a bit like a ass coming in and blustering about the difficulty in reading it and then struggling ''much'' more than I usually do in rewriting such a small section. Before anyone screams about the important points I eliminated, please consider that I attempted to focus solely on the very '''basic''' qualities of addition. I believe almost everything I took out was far too complicated for an intro. I also haven't looked carefully in the body of the article for the supporting documentation for the children and animals statement. I sure hope that's supported. Why would I leave something so peripherally related to addition like that in the intro and get rid of so much other info? Because it's human interest. &quot;Oh, my child may know how to add before speaking? Wow, that's strange!&quot; This is intended to draw people into the body of the article. It's called a teaser in print and TV. So let loose the slings and arrows of discontent if you've got them. Cheers, --[[User:Paul_Pigman|'''&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;Pig&lt;/font&gt;'''&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;man&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;sub&gt;[[User talk:Paul_Pigman|dialogue]]&lt;/sub&gt; 18:56, 18 March 2007 (UTC)
:I admit I've got a few slings…
:*I don't think it's a good idea to introduce &quot;adding&quot; and &quot;total&quot; in the first sentence along with &quot;addition&quot;. The main danger is that they're read as parts of the definition, which would make it circular. Maybe putting them in italics would help clarify their role?
:*&quot;Combining&quot; is vague. All binary operations could be described as combining two numbers — some quite meaningfully. My question is, ''how'' does addition combine its inputs in a way that distinguishes it from MAX, or subtraction, or averaging, or multiplication, or the Pythagorean sum…?
:*&quot;Equal simple amount&quot;?
:As for taking out things that are too complicated for an intro, just remember that the [[Wikipedia:Lead section|manual of style]] advises us that the lead should reflect the whole article — and I agree, and so do the folks at [[WP:FAC]]. So in the long term, some more work is going to have to be done there. [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 19:45, 18 March 2007 (UTC)

:By the way, the children and animals bit refers to [[Addition#Innate ability]]. Of course, you can't ask a five-month-old to compute 1 + 1 using symbols or even English words; the question has to be acted out. [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] 19:50, 18 March 2007 (UTC)

::First para is actually readable now, even interesting. In fact I was lured into venturing down a few more paras for the first time and my brain didn't explode.  [[User:Mattisse|Anonymouse]] 11:39, 20 March 2007 (UTC)

::Sorry for the lateness getting back here on this. Life intrudes. I acknowledge the things you pointed out, Melchoir. Most of your critique comes down to the difficulty I have in translating a symbolic and number based transaction into a simple English phrasing. While I should not argue with the WP manual of style, I still contend that if people can't make it through the lead section easily, they are highly unlikely to go further into the article. That's what I think the target is for a lead section: to include enough of the complexity of the full article but without overwhelming the casual reader. You'll have to excuse me if I say the overload threshold for most general readers of the maths articles is going to be lower than many other types of articles. I'm basing this on mostly on my own perceptions but I believe it holds true.
::Every one of your points is well taken: the circular nature of using &quot;adding&quot; to describe addition, &quot;combining&quot; is a poor substitute for what was originally &quot;increasing&quot; I believe, and &quot;equal simple amount&quot; was a paraphrase from a ''Merriam-Webster's Collegiate Dictionary'' definition (and a stunning failure of a phrase in my opinion.) I'm trying to think my way through to another way of expressing it. Argh. Perhaps I'm not as flash as I like to think. This is easily one of the most difficult tasks I've attempted on WP, requiring exceptional precision in the choice of words and phrasing. Thinking now, I'll be back. --[[User:Paul_Pigman|'''&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;Pig&lt;/font&gt;'''&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;man&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;sub&gt;[[User talk:Paul_Pigman|dialogue]]&lt;/sub&gt; 03:24, 21 March 2007 (UTC)

:::I think the children and animals statement probably over states the case. From what I can tell these experiments do something like: put one object behind a screen, then put another object behind it. Finally the screen is removed and the child is suprised if there is not two objects behind it. This ability is far removed from a complete ability for addition, even for low numbers like 3+5. Indeed there are counter experiments where children between 4-7 have problems with inclusion of sets, given a set of 3 boys and 5 girls the child will answer incorrectly when asked if there are more children than girls.

:::Just found an interesting example of a definition. ''Addition of numbers does not mean to increase but to group, join or rename a pair of numbers as a single number. The number idea is the same whether expressed as 3+2 or 5. ...'' (Richard Copeland - How children learn mathematics, p133) --[[User:Salix alba|Salix alba]] ([[User talk:Salix alba|talk]]) 10:29, 21 March 2007 (UTC)

::::Salix, the def in your last para is interesting and seems really quite accurate to me. It covers a range of possible examples. Any other people's opinions on it? Of course the problem is finding a way to paraphrase it in just as clear language without plagiarizing it. --[[User:Paul_Pigman|'''&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;Pig&lt;/font&gt;'''&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;man&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;sub&gt;[[User talk:Paul_Pigman|dialogue]]&lt;/sub&gt; 18:37, 21 March 2007 (UTC)

Folks, I'm going to bow out of this discussion. Please do whatever you think appropriate to the intro. This re-write is easily one of the more stressful experiences in my recent Wikipedia participation (and that's saying something!) Perhaps it's my own lack of ease with the broader math subjects but I can't seem to adequately grasp the best English expression of these concepts. I feel that I'm just poking at it without having a firm vision of outcome. For me, this is very unusual. Be assured my backing off has nothing to do with the company discussing it here. I just have to back off for my own well-being. --[[User:Pigman|'''&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;Pig&lt;/font&gt;'''&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;man&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;sub&gt;[[User talk:Pigman|dialogue]]&lt;/sub&gt; 18:09, 23 March 2007 (UTC)

Wow. The attempt to make the intro accessible has clearly gone too far. I came here by way of the Pages Needing Attention place, and yes, this does need attention. I read the first sentence of the article and fell of my chair. I'd argue that someone who can read the word &quot;addition&quot; knows what it is already. &quot;For example, in the picture on the right, there are 3 + 2 apples — meaning three apples and two other apples — which is the same as five apples, since 3 + 2 = 5.&quot; should not be the second sentence of the article. I urge each to simply read the first paragraph, and judge whether the writing is encyclopedic or not. 

I do see the problem, however - I can't think of a satisfactory solution.
[[User:Leon math|Leon math]] ([[User talk:Leon math|talk]]) 04:27, 13 December 2008 (UTC)

:...Well, feedback noted, but that's not very helpful...
:I missed Salix alba's suggestion above; I suppose you could say something like &quot;Addition means to group, join, or rename a pair of numbers as a single number.&quot; It's not perfect, though -- a good introductory definition would distinguish addition from other operations, while avoiding confusion between numbers and the objects whose size they measure. [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] ([[User talk:Melchoir|talk]]) 05:37, 13 December 2008 (UTC)

== Addition of algebraic numbers ==

I think some attention should be paid to intuitionistic addition of [[algebraic number]]s.  There is a method, due to [[Kronecker]], for adding such numbers by forming a common [[primitive element theorem|primitive element]] for the [[extension field]]s.  There are other methods, using Newton's theorem on [[symmetric function]]s and the [[resultant]].  The most sophisticated approach (that I know of) is [[Trager's algorithm]] used in modern [[symbolic computation]].  I'll try to source these and include them in the article. [[User:Silly rabbit|Silly rabbit]] 15:48, 10 May 2007 (UTC)

== Notation ==

In the [[Addition#Notation_and_terminology|Notation and Terminology]] section, it says that 
:&quot;A column of numbers, with the last number in the column underlined, usually indicates that the :numbers in the column are to be added, with the sum written below the underlined number.&quot;
However, I've always been told that this means ''multiplication'', not addition. [[User:Foxjwill|Foxjwill]] 01:28, 10 September 2007 (UTC)

== Associativity ==

I don't think that &quot;one can add more than two numbers&quot; is a good way to describe associativity.  On the other hand, I'm not sure how to concisely describe it in laymen's terms.  Thoughts?  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/67.204.0.186|67.204.0.186]] ([[User talk:67.204.0.186|talk]]) 03:08, 19 May 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;



== Deffinition on Mathematical logics ==

In the field of mathematical logics you can define all aritmetrics by creating a language with the normal things Natural, Rational, Real or complex numbers, +,-,*,/ and anything else you need. I would like to know how such a definition of + (and everything else looks) it should be on this page or on the general aritmetriks page.

Thank you for your time!  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/83.176.244.189|83.176.244.189]] ([[User talk:83.176.244.189|talk]]) 21:32, 16 March 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Qualification ==

I am not entirely sure what this paragraph is intended to address, but it seems to include ideas that aren't present anywhere else in the article. Kundip, can you please clarify exactly what you are trying to add? [[User:Publicly Visible|Publicly Visible]] ([[User talk:Publicly Visible|talk]]) 05:57, 4 September 2009 (UTC)

It is intended to directly addresses the process of addition. No matter what you increase the size of, put together, join, combine - whether numbers or even ingredients and so on - there is '''qualification'''. In all the definitions of addition this fundamental, this basic - is missing. There is no ´trying to add' there is actual addition because qualification is included. The word qualification should be in the primary definition. I have modified mine to reflect the main definition as my first one was deleted and I put my second attempt under the first definition so as not to put any noses out of joint. Even in old dictionary definitions this was missed. You cannot add a dog and a cat and call it two spoons or two cars or two dogs. You would automatically know itś two animals. You do not add one plus two and call it three ants. The answer is three numbers of the value one we shorten it and say three. kundip [[User:Kundip|Kundip]] ([[User talk:Kundip|talk]]) 11:09, 14 September 2009 (UTC)

:Where are these ideas coming from? [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] ([[User talk:Melchoir|talk]]) 17:30, 14 September 2009 (UTC)



''Addition is the [[mathematics|mathematical]] process of combining quantities.''

This definition does not state that there is an increase in size or quantity.

If one &quot;combines&quot; something - it may actually decrease in size which is subtraction.

It must state &quot;so as to increase the size or quantity&quot; to be addition.

The issue of &quot;how&quot; you combine is not addressed at all.

It just says &quot;process of&quot;.

The prerequisite for addition is '''qualification'''.

'' It is signified by the [[plus sign]] (+). For example, in the picture on the right, there are 3 + 2 apples—meaning three apples and two other apples—which is the same as five apples. Therefore, 3 + 2 = 5.''

This is not a definition it is an example.

In one edit of my definition I was referred to &quot;Identical particles&quot;. I have pointed out that there is no such thing. Even '''if''' they were the same at some point in their growth or decay - you still have the problem that they occupy different spaces. If they occupy different spaces - they are not the same. There would be a minuscule difference in temperature between them - I could go on. I understand the usefulness of such concepts as explained previously. Mathematics would not work without it. [[User:Kundip|Kundip]] ([[User talk:Kundip|talk]]) 08:26, 15 February 2010 (UTC)

:Please provide a citation to a reliable source that makes this claim. [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] ([[User talk:Melchoir|talk]]) 08:37, 15 February 2010 (UTC)

:Re your latest edit, I don't see any references in [http://books.google.com/books?q=addition+%22first+qualifying%22 this search] (I also tried various permutations of the words.) [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] ([[User talk:Melchoir|talk]]) 17:56, 15 February 2010 (UTC)

Addition (mathematics) is the process or action of '''first qualifying''' then joining or combining under a common heading so as to increase in size.

The primary definition of addition (mathematics) https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Addition

States that it is ''the the mathematical process of combining quantities''.

The first step in adding anything is qualification. &quot;We are going to add some '''numbers'''&quot;. We are going to count the '''fruit'''. How many '''items''' are there?.

Qualification is the first step carried out by anyone adding. You quickly correct anyone that has not qualified properly. e.g. &quot;two cars plus a truck is three cars&quot;. Immediately you say &quot;three vehicles&quot;. Test this out on almost anyone. Why do you do this? - The person has not added it correctly. How have they not added correctly? Qualification!

I defy you to let anyone add incorrectly: &quot;Two apples plus an orange equals three apples&quot;. This immediately catches your attention. &quot;Three pieces of fruit&quot;.

Addition is the mathematical process of qualifying then combining quantities. Is that a better definition?  [[User:Kundip|Kundip]] ([[User talk:Kundip|talk]]) 07:03, 16 February 2010 (UTC)

:No, because no dictionary or textbook I've seen contains it. One can find plenty of definitions of &quot;addition&quot; that mention [http://books.google.com/books?q=%22addition+is+the+operation%22+combining combining] but none for [http://books.google.com/books?q=%22addition+is+the+operation%22+qualifying qualifying].
:I think the root issue here is that you're confusing numbers with the collections they measure. Suppose I hold two apples in my left hand and one orange in my right hand. It occurs to me that I have three pieces of fruit in my hands. I might say to myself: okay, that makes sense, because 2 + 1 = 3.
:However, I wouldn't say to myself: &quot;2 apples + 1 orange = 3 pieces of fruit&quot;. That sentence would commit me to concluding that 1 apple = 1 orange, which for most purposes is untrue. The mistake is in overextending the words &quot;plus&quot; and &quot;equals&quot;. If I really want to express the relationship between the sizes and types of the sets, I might say: &quot;the union of a set of 2 apples with a set of 1 orange is a set of 3 pieces of fruit.&quot; Or: &quot;2 apples and 1 orange are altogether 3 pieces of fruit&quot;.
:In other words, if you're given two sets and you want to use the arithmetic operation of addition to learn something about how they join together, the first step you do isn't to &quot;qualify&quot; them. Instead, you take the cardinality of both sets, stripping them of all information about their individual elements.
:Now, I'll admit that the sentence &quot;Addition is the mathematical process of combining quantities&quot; glosses over the distinction between numbers and sets. That's partly by design; we don't want to get too technical in the introduction. But if you prefer, we could make the distinction explicit with something like &quot;Addition is a mathematical operation that represents combining collections of objects together into a larger collection&quot;. [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] ([[User talk:Melchoir|talk]]) 08:00, 16 February 2010 (UTC)

The &quot;into a larger collection&quot; piece is much better.

For the first part your argument fails, to me, on two counts. First even your own sentence above &quot;''It occurs to me that I have three pieces of fruit''&quot; is an immediate qualification before you have completed the action of addition. One cannot help oneself. Secondly the numbers have a qualification: 1 + 1 in mathematics is understood to be the joining or combining of two theoretical quantities that are the same in every possible way. As no two items are exactly the same this qualification is critical to make the wonder of mathematics work. The article you referred me to ''&quot;Identical particles&quot;'' admits that Identical particles &quot;''are particles that cannot be distinguished from one another''&quot; There are two names listed &quot;identical particles&quot; and &quot;indistinguishable particles&quot;. This all means that they cannot see any differences at this stage in their research hence the two names. The article goes on to say &quot;''The fact that particles can be identical has important consequences in statistical mechanics''&quot; Again this is a critical element in making this area of science work. By stating that they are the same for the purpose for which you are using them gives one a stable platform to work off.

I thank you for taking the time to write a reply. I hope my work stays on this page as a matter of record. In any case I appreciate the immense work you do here. [[User:Kundip|Kundip]] ([[User talk:Kundip|talk]]) 13:21, 16 February 2010 (UTC)

:Thanks, and you're welcome! But I have to ask: you wrote &quot;1 + 1 in mathematics is understood to be the joining or combining of two theoretical quantities that are the same in every possible way&quot;. Where in the world did you get that idea? [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] ([[User talk:Melchoir|talk]]) 00:39, 17 February 2010 (UTC)

OK 1=1 https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/%3D ''&quot;The equality sign, equals sign, or &quot;=&quot; is a mathematical symbol used to indicate equality. It was invented in 1557 by Welshman Robert Recorde. The equals sign is placed between the things stated to be exactly the same, as in an equation.&quot;'' I added (maybe incorrectly) &quot;in every way&quot; to emphasize the point. I added &quot;theoretical&quot; because there is no such thing as two identical particles.   At the top of this page, https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Identical_particles it says &quot;T''his article does not cite any references or sources.''&quot; [[User:Kundip|Kundip]] ([[User talk:Kundip|talk]]) 01:46, 17 February 2010 (UTC)

:Oh, you're referring to the number 1. Yes, 1 = 1. Again, it is helpful to consider the difference between the numbers and the sets they measure. In the expression 1 + 1, both addends are identical; yet this expression can be interpreted as the number of elements in the union of two one-element sets, in which the elements are not identical, and indeed may have nothing at all in common. [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] ([[User talk:Melchoir|talk]]) 03:16, 17 February 2010 (UTC)

Firstly here is the qualification: &quot;both addends are ''identical''&quot;. Identical being the key word.
Secondly &quot;indeed may have nothing at all in '''common'''&quot; adds strength to the part of my my definition &quot;''under a common heading''&quot;. One finds a way to join or unite. The more precise the better. &quot;Two brad nails&quot; is better than &quot;two nails&quot; is better than &quot;two thin pieces of metal&quot; is better than &quot;two items&quot;. [[User:Kundip|Kundip]] ([[User talk:Kundip|talk]]) 04:37, 17 February 2010 (UTC)

:Let's take your intuition that it's useful to precisely describe groups of objects, and follow that intuition to its logical conclusion.
:Given a nail ''x'' and a nail ''y'', they are not just any two nails. Perhaps they are both brad nails. But they aren't just any two brad nails either. They will have something else in common: their lengths will both be less than 1 meter, they will both be made of a substance other than chesse, and so on. So they are two non-cheese, sub-meter, brad nails. It never ends. No amount of adjectives can completely specify the two of them. Ultimately, the most exclusive heading shared by ''x'' and ''y'' is simply that they are the elements of the set {''x'', ''y''}.
:Likewise a screw ''a'', a screw ''b'', and a screw ''c'' are not just any three screws; they are the elements of the set {''a'', ''b'', ''c''}.
:If we put our nails and screws together, we get five thin pieces of metal. They are not five nails, nor are they five screws. But they aren't just any five thin pieces of metal, either... they are the elements of the set {''x'', ''y'', ''a'', ''b'', ''c''}.
:The relationship between these sets has a name. It is called the [[Union (set theory)|union of sets]]. One writes
::&lt;math&gt;\{x,y\} \cup \{a,b,c\} = \{x,y,a,b,c\}.&lt;/math&gt;
:The union operation is the mathematical tool whose job it is to join sets of objects under an perfectly precise common heading. Do you understand so far? [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] ([[User talk:Melchoir|talk]]) 07:22, 17 February 2010 (UTC)

Yes, I get that clearly. [[User:Kundip|Kundip]] ([[User talk:Kundip|talk]]) 14:10, 17 February 2010 (UTC)

:Okay, on to numbers. The operation that measures the size of a set is called the [[cardinality]]; it takes a set and produces a number. For example, |{''x'', ''y''}| = 2. Taking the cardinality of a set is an intentionally destructive action; we throw away all information about the set except its size.
:Roughly speaking, taking cardinalities turns set union into addition. By that I mean, given disjoint sets ''S'' and ''T'', we have |''S'' U ''T''| = |''S''| + |''T''|. Applying cardinality to the above equation, we derive the equation
::&lt;math&gt;2 + 3 = 5.\ &lt;/math&gt;
:So addition of numbers and union of sets are two different, although closely related, operations. And they ''are'' both ''operations'': given two numbers, there is a unique number which we call their sum, and given two sets, there is a unique set which we call their union. Okay? [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] ([[User talk:Melchoir|talk]]) 01:54, 18 February 2010 (UTC)

OK, I understand that. I am not lost yet. [[User:Kundip|Kundip]] ([[User talk:Kundip|talk]]) 11:54, 18 February 2010 (UTC)

:So which operation are you interested in? [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] ([[User talk:Melchoir|talk]]) 21:48, 18 February 2010 (UTC)

Was away for a week. Either operation is OK. As I understand it we are talking about some sort of increase. If I have to choose - I pick the harder to defend. Union of sets? [[User:Kundip|Kundip]] ([[User talk:Kundip|talk]]) 13:40, 25 February 2010 (UTC)

Re the: &quot;union of sets&quot;. &quot;union&quot;  Comes from unite or unit or one. This points out that one is trying to join something. If the result is more it is addition, less - subtraction.How does one unite? Give it a quality. i.e. Qualification. Any unity has some sort of name.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Kundip|Kundip]] ([[User talk:Kundip|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Kundip|contribs]]) 01:53, 26 February 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== example of columnar addition ==

I think the example of columnar addition would be more interesting if there was a &quot;carry&quot; in the operation. &amp;mdash; [[User:MFH|MFH]]:[[User talk:MFH|Talk]] 07:41, 23 June 2011 (UTC)

== Addition in group theory ==

Can we have a setion on addition in group theory please? Akin to the section in multiplication [[Multiplication#Multiplication_in_group_theory|here]]. Explaining which sets forms groups under addition.
Thanks [[User:PointOfPresence|PointOfPresence]] ([[User talk:PointOfPresence|talk]]) 09:40, 5 September 2011 (UTC)
:Well, there's already a section on abstract algebra. Currently the last paragraph says this:
:*The general theory of abstract algebra allows an &quot;addition&quot; operation to be any [[associative]] and [[commutative]] operation on a set. Basic [[algebraic structure]]s with such an addition operation include [[commutative monoid]]s and [[abelian group]]s.''
:I suppose you're saying it should be expanded? [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] ([[User talk:Melchoir|talk]]) 01:15, 6 September 2011 (UTC)

:::Sure, but I do think we ought to add a section to the addition article, just for completeness and for consistency with multiplication. [[User:PointOfPresence|PointOfPresence]] ([[User talk:PointOfPresence|talk]]) 11:43, 8 September 2011 (UTC)
::::Oh, that's sort of what I meant: expanding this article. Completeness and consistentency are good, but I'm not convinced that consistency with multiplication requires an exact analogy here. When we're talking about addition, groups aren't the most natural setting. It would make more sense to focus on modules and vector spaces as generalizations of real addition, and maybe commutative monoids and semirings as generalizations of cardinal addition. Perhaps in an article on subtraction, I'd expect to see more on abelian groups. In an article on multiplication, I'd expect to see groups but also monoids and rings and algebras. [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] ([[User talk:Melchoir|talk]]) 20:12, 8 September 2011 (UTC)

== This article illustrates the problem with math articles on Wikipedia ==

Too much information, often presented in an esoteric fashion.  Yes, the purpose of Wikipedia is information, but that information is pointless if the reader cannot understand it.  I learned addition in first grade and now at 40 with a degree in mathematics, and I find this article challenging.  Lets define information...information is defined as knowledge transferred or communicated.  The word information is based on the word &quot;inform&quot;, which is a verb that can be defined as &quot;transfer knowledge&quot;.  This is in contrast to the definition of &quot;data&quot; or &quot;facts&quot;, which requires &quot;processing&quot;, or &quot;refinement&quot; to become useful information.  If Wikipedia is to truly be a knowledge base, we must take care to present our data and facts so that it is truly informative.  I am not suggesting that we &quot;dumb it down&quot;....indeed, Einstein can be quoted as saying &quot;You do not really understand something unless you can explain it to your grandmother.&quot;  We can and should do better.
:Tsk tsk, that's far too simplistic a view of imformation, it is measured by

::&lt;math&gt;-\sum_{x \in \mathbb{X}} p(x) \log p(x).&lt;/math&gt;

: ;-) I must admit on having a look at it the lead immediately would be a put off for anyone not a maths graduate. I think the [[Multiplication]] article is a bit better but not by a long shot. [[User:Dmcq|Dmcq]] ([[User talk:Dmcq|talk]]) 16:44, 19 July 2012 (UTC)

== Carry ==

The [[Addition#Computers|Computers]] section describes &quot;carry&quot;. That should be called [[Arithmetic_overflow|Arithmetic overflow]] with a reference to that. Perhaps some of the description of &quot;carry&quot; should be merged into the Arithmetic overflow article.
[[User:Sam Tomato|Sam Tomato]] ([[User talk:Sam Tomato|talk]]) 16:35, 15 November 2012 (UTC)
: Carries are also mentioned in section &quot;Decimal system&quot;. It is very strange that this notion that is fundamental for the practice of addition is not clearly defined in this article, and there is no link to the relevant WP article [[carry (arithmetic)]]. About your suggestion, note that &quot;carry&quot; and &quot;overflow&quot; are very different concepts: a carry is a piece of information that is kept to be used later in another place; carries are 0 or 1 when adding two numbers, but may be larger when adding several numbers of multiplying a number of several digits by a number of one digit. On the other hand, &quot;overflows&quot; occur because computer arithmetic deals with integers of a fixed number of digits; overflow occurs when the result may not be represented with the fixed number of digits. The fact that the overflow bit may be, and is, used to store carries in multiple precision addition is an interesting property; it does not makes the notions identical. Thus I am against the suggested merge. [[User:D.Lazard|D.Lazard]] ([[User talk:D.Lazard|talk]]) 18:34, 15 November 2012 (UTC)

== symbols for four operations ==

AT the bottom of the article, there is a colorful box with symbols for the four operations.  The problem is that both the plus and the  multiplication  signs are two line segments set at right angles, AND the plus sign is tilted, so that it looks almost like a multiplication sign.  Can this be fixed/[[User:Kdammers|Kdammers]] ([[User talk:Kdammers|talk]]) 02:58, 9 January 2013 (UTC)

:This problem still plagues the math pages.[[User:Kdammers|Kdammers]] ([[User talk:Kdammers|talk]]) 00:08, 6 March 2015 (UTC)
::All the image signs are slightly rotated; I really don't think it will confuse anyone (especially with the + sign below the word &quot;Addition&quot;), but I can see your point and if you would like to make/find an image we can use instead of the current green + sign, go ahead. But your problem is with the template ({{t|Elementary arithmetic}}), not this article, so your comments might be more suited to [[Template talk:Elementary arithmetic]]. — '''[[User:Bilorv|Bilorv]]'''&lt;sub&gt;'''[[User talk:Bilorv|(talk)]]'''&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Bilorv|(c)]][[Special:EmailUser/Bilorv|(e)]]&lt;/sup&gt; 13:15, 7 March 2015 (UTC)

== Simple animation? ==

[[file:Eqn balance addition subtraction negation.gif|thumb|Animation of the equation balance analogy showing: addition, subtraction, negation, collecting like terms.]]

This article is cluttered with a million images, how about one animation for a simple equation? Probably not. Feel free to take or leave... [[user:Maschen|'''M&amp;and;''Ŝ''''']][[special:contributions/Maschen|''c''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;''ħ''ε]][[user talk:maschen|''И&lt;sub&gt;τlk&lt;/sub&gt;'']] 22:21, 18 May 2013 (UTC)

:I took six semesters as a math major (admittedly, I didn't do that well), and I cannot figure out what this animation is supposed to be showing (maybe it's the flashing that makes it impossible for me -- I did not grow up on television or computer games).  So, from my perspective, this would be a terrible &quot;addition&quot; to the article. [[Special:Contributions/211.225.33.104|211.225.33.104]] ([[User talk:211.225.33.104|talk]]) 03:56, 10 June 2013 (UTC)

== Definition ==

The current lede says additionis the operation that &quot;represents....&quot;  Is that correct, or is it the operation that &quot;produces...&quot; or &quot;results in...&quot;? [[User:Kdammers|Kdammers]] ([[User talk:Kdammers|talk]]) 09:29, 18 June 2013 (UTC)
: I agree. Moreover the article continue with &quot;It is signified by the plus sign ...&quot;, when &quot;it is represented by ...&quot; seems more appropriate. [[User:D.Lazard|D.Lazard]] ([[User talk:D.Lazard|talk]]) 09:47, 18 June 2013 (UTC)

== Adding 0-10 ==

The graphic about adding 0-10 has the numbers and colors in the legend in exact opposite order of their order on the graphic proper.  This is confusing.[[User:Kdammers|Kdammers]] ([[User talk:Kdammers|talk]]) 13:08, 9 December 2013 (UTC)

== modular addition ==

One or two examples of modular addition would be quite helpful. [[User:Kdammers|Kdammers]] ([[User talk:Kdammers|talk]]) 13:09, 9 December 2013 (UTC)

== Patterns ==

When referring to association etc., the article says addition follows patterns.  This sounds pretty loose.  Wouldn't it be better to call them properties or laws (as I was taught in high school)?[[User:Kdammers|Kdammers]] ([[User talk:Kdammers|talk]]) 00:51, 4 July 2014 (UTC)

== References ==

Is there a better way to source the references?  I tried to find a source listed in a footnote on learning (#33).  It was in fact listed under cognitive.  Maybe this is the best place for this particular source, which has a number of references to it -- I don't know.  But why make it hard to find for some-one coming from the educational aspect of addition?  For all I know, there are other cases,'' mutatis mutandis''.[[User:Kdammers|Kdammers]] ([[User talk:Kdammers|talk]]) 00:55, 4 July 2014 (UTC)

==GA1==
{{Talk:Addition/GA1}}
[[User:Bilorv|Bilorv]]&amp;nbsp;([[User talk:Bilorv|talk]] '''·''' [[Special:Contributions/Bilorv|contribs]]) 21:09, 22 December 2014 (UTC)

==&quot;{{noredirect|Sum}}&quot;==
This usage of {{la|sum}} , a redirect, is under dispute. A prior discussion exists at [[Talk:Sum (disambiguation)]], however it is mostly proceeding in the edit summaries of &quot;sum&quot;. -- [[Special:Contributions/65.94.40.137|65.94.40.137]] ([[User talk:65.94.40.137|talk]]) 11:05, 26 January 2015 (UTC)
:Further discussion is occurring at [[talk:summation]] -- [[Special:Contributions/65.94.40.137|65.94.40.137]] ([[User talk:65.94.40.137|talk]]) 11:05, 26 January 2015 (UTC)

[[File:Information.svg|40px|left]]
An editor has asked for a discussion to address the redirect [[Sum]]. Please participate in [[Wikipedia:Redirects for discussion/Log/2015 January 26#Sum|the redirect discussion]] if you have not already done so. &lt;!-- from Template:RFDNote --&gt; 
[[Special:Contributions/65.94.40.137|65.94.40.137]] ([[User talk:65.94.40.137|talk]]) 08:31, 27 January 2015 (UTC)

== addition on computers ==

I have removed the C code aimed to simulate hardware addition. Its explanation was placed too far from the piece of code for being useful. Moreover, this is too technical here, as the reader of this section is not supposed to be able to read C code. A pseudo-code version could be useful, for expliciting the algorithm, if the shift, OR and AND operation would be given with their full name (without any C abbreviation that may be cryptic for the layman). [[User:D.Lazard|D.Lazard]] ([[User talk:D.Lazard|talk]]) 13:35, 16 September 2015 (UTC)

:Agree with the removal. In fact, even if it's in pseudo-code, I think [[Adder (electronics)]] would be a more appropriate home for this level of detail than [[Addition]]. [[User:Melchoir|Melchoir]] ([[User talk:Melchoir|talk]]) 18:42, 16 September 2015 (UTC)

== 5.5 Complex numbers ==

Quotation:

&quot;Using the '''visualization''' of complex numbers in the complex plane, the addition has the following geometric interpretation: the sum of two complex numbers A and B, interpreted as points of the complex plane, is the point X obtained by building a parallelogram three of whose vertices are O, A and B. Equivalently, X is the point such that the triangles with vertices O, A, B, and X, B, A, are congruent.&quot;

It is not very comfortable to read this passage without any real visualization of these vertices O, A and B :( -- [[User:AKA MBG|Andrew Krizhanovsky]] ([[User talk:AKA MBG|talk]]) 14:57, 18 January 2016 (UTC)
:But there is an image there: [[:File:Vector Addition.svg]]. There are a few images in that section in quick succession, so the image may be a bit below section 5.5 on your screen, but it is there. Admittedly, it doesn't label O, A or B, but it does show the vector addition being described. &lt;span class=&quot;nowrap&quot;&gt;— '''[[User:Bilorv|Bilorv]]'''&lt;sub&gt;'''[[User talk:Bilorv|(talk)]]'''&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[Special:Contribs/Bilorv|(c)]][[Special:EmailUser/Bilorv|(e)]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 15:52, 18 January 2016 (UTC)

==Assessment comment==
{{Substituted comment|length=264|lastedit=20070609195628|comment=Potential GA candidate. [[User:Salix alba|Salix alba]] ([[User talk:Salix alba|talk]]) 19:14, 29 September 2006 (UTC)

A longer lead would help, as would some broader context: history, education, society. [[User:Geometry guy|Geometry guy]] 19:56, 9 June 2007 (UTC)}}
Substituted at 06:41, 29 April 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>6pb8pol51or0kr1rsqwh4k5eersu9ib</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
