<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:University of California, Riverside</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>706745</id>
    <revision>
      <id>707312713</id>
      <parentid>703859863</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-02-28T03:21:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cyberbot II</username>
        <id>16283967</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="28315">{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target= Talk:University of California, Riverside/Archive index
|mask= Talk:University of California, Riverside/Archive &lt;#&gt; 
|leading_zeros=0 |indexhere=yes |template= 
}}{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=8 August 2007
|action1link=Talk:University of California, Riverside#GA fail
|action1result=failed
|action1oldid=150003214

|action2=GAN
|action2date=20 August 2007
|action2link=Talk:University of California, Riverside#GA Review
|action2result=listed
|action2oldid=152624440

|action3=PR
|action3date=15:27, 11 October 2007
|action3link=Wikipedia:Peer review/University of California, Riverside/archive1
|action3result=reviewed
|action3oldid=163669736

|action4=FAC
|action4date=22:39, 7 January 2008
|action4link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/University of California, Riverside/archive1
|action4result=not promoted
|action4oldid=182813405

|action5=FAC
|action5date=00:47, 26 March 2008
|action5link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/University of California, Riverside
|action5result=promoted
|action5oldid=200700655

|topic=Socsci
|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=February 21, 2009
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell
|1=
{{WikiProject University of California|class=FA|importance=Top|UCR=yes|UCR-importance = top}}
{{WikiProject California|class=FA|importance=High|unref=no|southerncalifornia=yes|southerncalifornia-importance=High|selected-article=yes|inland-empire=yes|inland-empire-importance=top}}
{{WikiProject Universities|class=FA|importance=High|unref=no}}
{{WikiProject Education|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject University of California Riverside Libraries|class=FA |importance=High }}
}}
{{LOCErequest|small=yes}}
{{todo|small=yes}}
{{archive box|auto=long}}
{{connected contributor|Stevenmg|declared=yes|editedhere=yes}}

== AAU ==

Should we write about UCR's attempt at AAU membership under Chan. White? 

http://strategicplan.ucr.edu/pdf/ucr2020.pdf  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.232.206.173|76.232.206.173]] ([[User talk:76.232.206.173|talk]]) 04:16, 15 January 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Noted Alum section ==

Yes, [[James Eagan Holmes|James Holmes]] is a &quot;notable&quot; alumnus. We have a [[List of University of California, Riverside people]] and his name is on that list.  Accordingly, I've pared down the section in this article to include only the ''very most'' notable alums. Holmes himself is [[WP:BLP1E]] and [[WP:BLPCRIME]], so I see little justification for including him in the [[WP:FA]] which covers the entire U, not [[WP:RECENTISM]].--[[User:Srich32977|S. Rich]] ([[User talk:Srich32977|talk]]) 17:31, 23 July 2012 (UTC)

:I agree. I'm fine with his name appearing on [[List of University of California, Riverside people]], but not in this article, especially per [[WP:BLP1E]] and the need to keep the article on topic. &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;[[User:Szyslak|szyslak]]&lt;/font&gt; (&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Szyslak|t]]&lt;/font&gt;) 06:03, 24 July 2012 (UTC)

::Hello. I disagree. You mention &quot;very most&quot; as your criteria for inclusion of such persons in this list. The question is what does &quot;very most&quot; mean. Does it mean only notable in a positive sense? If so, then I think only naming those people would degrade the encyclopedic value of this article. However, if you mean &quot;very most notable&quot; to mean at face value then Mr. Holmes should be included, since Mr. Holmes is probably now the most notable alumnus now from UC Riverside, more than anyone else! If one were to ask a random person on the street if they have Mr. James Holmes or Dr. Richard R. Schrock-- who would they know better??? I would like to know what others think about this.[[User:AxonPatch|AxonPatch]] ([[User talk:AxonPatch|talk]]) 23:17, 24 July 2012 (UTC)
:::Oh, I quite agree that defining &quot;very most&quot; is difficult, but those people now listed (pared down from a less selective list) are quite notable -- the Nobel Prize, Poet Laurate, Pulitizers, etc. are very rare/distinctive measures of qualification.  As you say, Holmes has notability ''for now''. So putting limits on this section is more than just name recognition. (So what if people recognize his name right now? What were the names of the guys that shot up Columbine, Virginia Tech, Fort Hood?) This is a [[WP:FA|featured article]] and FA criteria calls for article stability. Adding his name now, because of his temporary notability, goes against the FA guidelines.  I ask you -- ''why'' should be be included? How does his name fit [[WP:UNIGUIDE#Article structure]] guidelines?  Again, Holmes is listed in the People of UCR article.  That should work for all concerned.  --[[User:Srich32977|S. Rich]] ([[User talk:Srich32977|talk]]) 23:52, 24 July 2012 (UTC)

::::I think it's a foregone conclusion that this individual is of lasting infamy.  I don't like the edit warring that has occurred around this edit but it's pretty clear that the perpetrator of such a widely-reported, heinous crime is notable by our standards.  He's clearly notable and I think fairness demands we include him in this article, not least so we avoid the appearance of keeping this article unduly positive. [[User:ElKevbo|ElKevbo]] ([[User talk:ElKevbo|talk]]) 01:56, 25 July 2012 (UTC)

Hi. I'm actually a graduate of UC Riverside. At first, I was shocked to see that the Aurora killer was a graduate of UCR, but looking back at my college days, there were quite a few weirdos that remind me of him. I added his name to the alumni list as a reminder that UCR, given its &quot;inland&quot; location, can tend to attract students like James Holmes. In this one club I was in, there was one particular guy would show up at our meetings dressed in a black trenchcoat. Anyway, let's be honest here. Are any of the alumni listed really that notable? Colleges have graduates who win the Nobel Prize all the time! A Nobel laureate may be a big deal for UCR (because there aren't that many), but it's seriousl not &quot;that&quot; notable. Same with Pulitzer Prize winners, especially for a cartoonist. I don't even know what a poet laureate is (for that Billy Collins person). And listing someone who discovered some fossils and was named an influential person by Time, a newsmedia magazine? James Holmes shocked the nation with his crime. He is far more notable and recognizable than any of the other &quot;notable alumni,&quot; and it is particularly noteworthy that he was a &quot;top student&quot; from UCR as well. I don't think there needs to be a whole section devoted to James Holmes, but he definitely belongs on that front page, just like the lesser known alumni. I agree with Axonpitch. [[User:Wikimaster415|Wikimaster415]] ([[User talk:Wikimaster415|talk]]) 01:38, 25 July 2012 (UTC)

Hi. I agree with Wikimaster and ElKevbo. I have included Holmes in the article for now. I feel that those who exclude Holmes from the article is a violation of NPOV, and (may) just be wanting to bolster their personal grandeur view of the school. [[User:AxonPatch|AxonPatch]] ([[User talk:AxonPatch|talk]]) 02:45, 25 July 2012 (UTC)
:Edit warring isn't the way to go about it, though. (And it is quite a coincidence that several brand new editors have popped up to make the same edits at the same time, no?)  [[User:ElKevbo|ElKevbo]] ([[User talk:ElKevbo|talk]]) 04:02, 25 July 2012 (UTC)
::The current influx of single-purpose editors is one reason I have started an RFC below. &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;[[User:Szyslak|szyslak]]&lt;/font&gt; (&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Szyslak|t]]&lt;/font&gt;) 04:25, 25 July 2012 (UTC)
{{od}}
&lt;s&gt;I'll suggest then that we leave him on the List of UCR Alum article ''and'' remove ''all'' of the names (including the Nobel Prize winner what's-his-name) from the alum subsection of the UCR article.&lt;s&gt;--[[User:Srich32977|S. Rich]] ([[User talk:Srich32977|talk]]) 18:49, 25 July 2012 (UTC)15:14, 31 July 2012 (UTC)

== Page protected ==

The article has been page protected for a week due to continued edit warring. Please take advantage of the current discussion and attempt to come to an informed consensus. Thank you [[User:Calmer Waters|&lt;span style=&quot;color:black&quot;&gt;'''''Calmer'''''&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Calmer Waters|&lt;span style=&quot;color:Blue&quot;&gt;'''''Waters'''''&lt;/span&gt;]] 03:05, 25 July 2012 (UTC)

== RFC: James Eagan Holmes ==
{{archivetop|result = General consensus not to include James Eagan Holmes in the main article. He is currently included in [[List of University of California, Riverside people]]. &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;[[User:Szyslak|szyslak]]&lt;/font&gt; (&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Szyslak|t]]&lt;/font&gt;) 08:18, 10 August 2012 (UTC)}}
Should the article mention that [[James Eagan Holmes]], the suspect in the [[2012 Aurora shooting]], attended the university? &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;[[User:Szyslak|szyslak]]&lt;/font&gt; (&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Szyslak|t]]&lt;/font&gt;) 04:23, 25 July 2012 (UTC)

===Threaded discussion===

'''No.'''    That would be [[WP:UNDUE]] in spades.   There are four alumni listed, and no other former students.   The four alumni are presumably notable for having done something worthwhile with their education.   The gunman is notable for having gone off the rails, which seems unlikely to have anything to do with his education.   This could only be construed as guilt by association.   This article would have to get much larger before a mention of the gunman would swim into focus without being unduly emphasized. [[User:Abhayakara|Abhayakara]] ([[User talk:Abhayakara|talk]]) 20:34, 28 July 2012 (UTC)

'''No.''' Would most reliable sources, such as the Encyclopaedia Britannica, note that UC Riverside was the alleged gunman's alma mater in describing notable points about the university? Doubtful. Mentioning that he attended UC Riverside would be appropriate for a biographical entry ''on him'', but mentioning him in the university's entry would be a violation of [[WP:UNDUE]].  [[User:Dezastru|Dezastru]] ([[User talk:Dezastru|talk]]) 07:22, 31 July 2012 (UTC)

'''No''': the shooting happened outside university and no connection between his education and university was ever found. This proposal to me is equal to mentioning him in articles about all the places he attended: fast food restaurants, hospitals, streets, etc. — [[User:Czarkoff|Dmitrij D. Czarkoff]] ([[User talk:Czarkoff|talk]]) 15:02, 31 July 2012 (UTC)

'''No''': As per my original comments (above), inclusion is not appropriate. As consensus is turning towards non-inclusion, I've stricken my earlier suggestion that we leave all names out of the particular subsection.--[[User:Srich32977|S. Rich]] ([[User talk:Srich32977|talk]]) 15:14, 31 July 2012 (UTC)

'''Yes''': This is no different than listing other notable alumni in university articles.  The value judgments being placed on this are highly inappropriate, particularly if those judgments are being made to protect the reputation of this university.  If editors want to say that this individual is not notable enough, then that may be in line with our practices.  But to say that &quot;the university shouldn't be associated with him&quot; or anything along those lines is misplaced and a blatant insertion of [[WP:NPOV|a point of view]].  And if you're going to go down the road of &quot;what he did isn't related to the university&quot; then you have a lot of work to do in other articles removing all of the artists, musicians, politicians, etc. whose notability isn't directly linked to their academic work. [[User:ElKevbo|ElKevbo]] ([[User talk:ElKevbo|talk]]) 05:33, 1 August 2012 (UTC)

'''Weak No''': Clearly every alumnus with a Wikipedia article is notable per Wikipedia standards, or else they wouldn't have articles. The notion of only selecting the &quot;very most notable&quot; alumni in the main article leaves a ''lot'' of room for value judgments and thus edit wars. That said, it seems to me that someone who is only notable in his own right under [[WP:BLP1E]] cannot be seen as &quot;very most notable&quot; in any context at present. Billy Collins, by contrast, is notable for a long and very public career as a major contemporary poet. Still, I find the argument compelling that excluding an alum because his notability is based on a bad act ''may'' constitute a bit of boosterism and (good-faith) violation of NPOV. -- [[User:Danielklotz|DanielKlotz]] ([[User talk:Danielklotz|talk]] ·  [[Special:Contributions/Danielklotz|contribs]]) 10:20, 1 August 2012 (UTC)

'''No, with caveat''' Typically, I would !say yes in a situation like this, but the list of alumni at [[University of California, Riverside#Alumni]] is only 4 entries long, and I would say that Holmes isn't among the top 4 most notable alumni at this university. However, if that section were to be re-written to have a longer list of example alumni, say top 10 or more, then Holmes would definitely be on that list.  He should definitely be listed at [[List of University of California, Riverside people]].--[[User:GrapedApe|GrapedApe]] ([[User talk:GrapedApe|talk]]) 12:22, 1 August 2012 (UTC)

:Reply -- Holmes ''is'' included in the [[List of University of California, Riverside people|list article]], so his connection to UCR is ''not excluded''. That leads to the issue of whether he should be included on this page. Editorial (and value) judgment judgment comes into play in any editing discussion/decision. For example, it's common to list Nobel-prise-laurates (or other super-notable people) placed at the top of various lists.  So the question is whether to include him here, on the main UCR page.  To answer that question we should consider weather including him here is UNDUE (a value judgment) in light of his [[WP:NTEMP|temporary]] notability for this single event.--[[User:Srich32977|S. Rich]] ([[User talk:Srich32977|talk]]) 14:26, 1 August 2012 (UTC)

::I think the meta-question of exactly why a person would be included on this page is interesting, but it seems very clear to me that if a person is included on this page merely because he or she is notable, and went to UCR, that's a poor criterion for inclusion.   There ought to be a stronger connection than that—the fact that the person went to UCR ought to have been somehow instrumental in their becoming notable.   It seems to me that by listing the person in the article, you are making the statement that this is the case—that their notability is connected to UCR.   So the statement should be true.   If it is ''not'' true for the people currently listed, then they shouldn't be listed either.   I think it's pretty clearly not true for the gunman. [[User:Abhayakara|Abhayakara]] ([[User talk:Abhayakara|talk]]) 18:48, 1 August 2012 (UTC)

:::That's a reasonable opinion but it's very far out of line with current practice.  You have a lot of articles to edit if that is the standard you believe we should enforce in college and university articles!
:::And that is the problem I have with this discussion: Everyone is content to look the other way as alumni are added to this and other articles when those alumni have (a) trivial notability and (b) a tenuous connection to the institution.  But now that an alumnus who reflects poorly on the university has been added to this article, a group of editors emerges from the woodwork to create a new, POV-based standard that has not been and will not be enforced anywhere else.  [[User:ElKevbo|ElKevbo]] ([[User talk:ElKevbo|talk]]) 18:00, 8 August 2012 (UTC)
::::The existence of an article where something is done badly is no justification for doing the same thing in a different article. I think this case and, e.g., the case of Ted Bundy are excellent examples to show that the status quo that you report, if it in fact exists, is wrong and should not be Wikipedia policy. [[User:Abhayakara|Abhayakara]] ([[User talk:Abhayakara|talk]]) 03:52, 9 August 2012 (UTC)
:::::I look forward to you joining those of us who regularly edit college and university articles where you can help us remove all other non-academic alumni from those articles.  That will go over really well! [[User:ElKevbo|ElKevbo]] ([[User talk:ElKevbo|talk]]) 04:07, 10 August 2012 (UTC)

'''No''': Notable implies distinguished - and for the well reasoned opinions above. [[User:Mcusa|Mcusa]] ([[User talk:Mcusa|talk]]) 15:15, 8 August 2012 (UTC)
:&quot;Notable implies distinguished.&quot;  Huh?  Are you arguing that we should only write about &quot;distinguished&quot; people in this encyclopedia, omitting criminals and others who have made an impact on the world simply because they aren't &quot;distinguished?&quot; [[User:ElKevbo|ElKevbo]] ([[User talk:ElKevbo|talk]]) 18:00, 8 August 2012 (UTC)
::This is not the case at all. ''Holmes (and a lot of others) is in the UCR list article.'' Besides, he has his own article. In any event, WP does look at [[WP:SCHOLAR]] in the academic environment, and does so in the context of that environment. --[[User:Srich32977|S. Rich]] ([[User talk:Srich32977|talk]]) 18:38, 8 August 2012 (UTC)
:::Sorry but I still don't get it.  Are you advancing the idea that only those who meet [[WP:SCHOLAR]] should be included in this and other articles about colleges and universities?  Setting aside the fundamental issue that the notability guidelines apply only to article subjects and not to the content of articles, that seems extremely problematic since that would omit all non-academics completely.
:::I'm really not trying to be argumentative.  But I simply don't see a workable principle underlying the decision to omit this individual from this article, especially if you accept the view that our guidelines are descriptive and not prescriptive.  The widely accepted and rarely (?) challenged practice in college and university articles is to include notable alumni without regard to their status as academics, how closely linked they are to the college or university, and whether their notability is positive or negative.  If we are going to change our practices then let's do so.  Ignoring them to carve out an exception for this one individual in this one article simply because his notability is derived from negative circumstances is a huge mistake.  We need to operate from sound principles, not immediate emotions. [[User:ElKevbo|ElKevbo]] ([[User talk:ElKevbo|talk]]) 19:35, 8 August 2012 (UTC)

'''No''' as per Dezastru's comments above. Similarly, Ted Bundy is not listed in the notable alumni section of his alma maters but is listed in the pages of ____ university people as Holmes is. That seems to be the norm. [[User:Ayzmo|Ayzmo]] ([[User talk:Ayzmo|talk]]) 19:24, 8 August 2012 (UTC)

'''Comment''' Holmes is an '''allegedly''' notable criminal. Otherwise he's nobody. If Wikipedia has him on this list by virtue of notability, it presumes his guilt (in a subtle way). Some BLP problems there, possibly. '''Oppose''', I suppose. [[User:InedibleHulk|InedibleHulk]] ([[User talk:InedibleHulk|talk]]) 00:46, 10 August 2012 (UTC)
*Wow.  This isn't a court of law.  We all know that he did it.--[[User:GrapedApe|GrapedApe]] ([[User talk:GrapedApe|talk]]) 01:46, 10 August 2012 (UTC)
{{od}}
As the discussion does not seem to have any new points forthcoming, I suggest we close it with a decision to keep Holmes out of the UCR article.--[[User:Srich32977|S. Rich]] ([[User talk:Srich32977|talk]]) 02:35, 10 August 2012 (UTC)
:Agreed. -- [[User:Danielklotz|DanielKlotz]] ([[User talk:Danielklotz|talk]] ·  [[Special:Contributions/Danielklotz|contribs]]) 02:45, 10 August 2012 (UTC)
:Agreed. You're all dead set on making the wrong decision for reasons that run contrary to some our foundational principles but I know when I'm in the minority.  Let's move on. [[User:ElKevbo|ElKevbo]] ([[User talk:ElKevbo|talk]]) 04:09, 10 August 2012 (UTC)
::I agree that it's time to close. &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;[[User:Szyslak|szyslak]]&lt;/font&gt; (&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Szyslak|t]]&lt;/font&gt;) 08:09, 10 August 2012 (UTC)
{{archivebottom}}

== Endowment ==

NACUBO is a very useful source because it standardizes endowment data, but I believe it should only be the &quot;official&quot; source for private colleges and universities and should be used with caution for public universities. In the case of the University of California system, NACUBO seems to report only the endowments managed by the UC schools' Foundations, and does not include the endowments managed on behalf of the UC schools by the UC Regents (see p.4 of http://www.ucop.edu/treasurer/_files/report/UC_Annual_Endowment_Report_FY2011-2012.pdf for details). Therefore, I believe the UC endowment data reported by the UC Treasurer's Office is relevant and should be shown in Wikipedia articles for UC schools instead of NACUBO's.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Contributor321|Contributor321]] ([[User talk:Contributor321|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Contributor321|contribs]]) 17:27, 5 June 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:3|one external link|3 external links}} on [[University of California, Riverside]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=686163853 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20090215160026/http://www.pe.com:80/localnews/rivcounty/stories/PE_News_Local_D_hinderaker25.4033be3.html to http://www.pe.com/localnews/rivcounty/stories/PE_News_Local_D_hinderaker25.4033be3.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20090214121034/http://www.pe.com:80/localnews/environment/stories/PE_News_Local_S_china17.3e41f93.html to http://www.pe.com/localnews/environment/stories/PE_News_Local_S_china17.3e41f93.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20070309091424/http://www.pe.com:80/sports/college/ucr/stories/PE_Sports_Local_D_percival_ucr.1dc3b54.html to http://www.pe.com/sports/college/ucr/stories/PE_Sports_Local_D_percival_ucr.1dc3b54.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers. —[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 12:18, 17 October 2015 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:2|one external link|2 external links}} on [[University of California, Riverside]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=698304434 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20090214112740/http://www.pe.com:80/localnews/inland/stories/PE_News_Local_D_patent27.1834716.html to http://www.pe.com/localnews/inland/stories/PE_News_Local_D_patent27.1834716.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20090213202440/http://www.pe.com:80/sports/college/local/stories/PE_Sports_Local_D_locals_20.32e0a2c.html to http://www.pe.com/sports/college/local/stories/PE_Sports_Local_D_locals_20.32e0a2c.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 07:33, 5 January 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:9|one external link|9 external links}} on [[University of California, Riverside]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=703859849 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20090213202355/http://www.pe.com:80/localnews/inland/stories/PE_News_Local_D_medskl23.368812d.html to http://www.pe.com/localnews/inland/stories/PE_News_Local_D_medskl23.368812d.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20090215162213/http://www.pe.com:80/lifestyles/stories/PE_Fea_Daily_D_dbltrk1128.1e28499.html to http://www.pe.com/lifestyles/stories/PE_Fea_Daily_D_dbltrk1128.1e28499.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20100615054559/http://www.pe.com:80/localnews/highereducation/stories/PE_News_Local_S_hiednotes11.468022b.html to http://www.pe.com/localnews/highereducation/stories/PE_News_Local_S_hiednotes11.468022b.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20090214111809/http://www.pe.com:80/sports/college/ucr/stories/PE_Sports_Local_D_ucr_women_prev_07.3e82722.html to http://www.pe.com/sports/college/ucr/stories/PE_Sports_Local_D_ucr_women_prev_07.3e82722.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20100615054012/http://www.pe.com:80/sports/college/ucr/stories/PE_Sports_Local_W_ucr_women_22.466fbef.html to http://www.pe.com/sports/college/ucr/stories/PE_Sports_Local_W_ucr_women_22.466fbef.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20100615054001/http://www.pe.com:80/sports/college/local/stories/PE_Sports_Local_W_ucr_women_07.46bb515.html to http://www.pe.com/sports/college/local/stories/PE_Sports_Local_W_ucr_women_07.46bb515.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20100615055523/http://www.pe.com:80/sports/college/ucr/stories/PE_Sports_Local_D_ucr_base_05.3f2ca3f.html to http://www.pe.com/sports/college/ucr/stories/PE_Sports_Local_D_ucr_base_05.3f2ca3f.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20090215162551/http://www.pe.com:80/columns/jimalexander/stories/PE_Sports_Local_D_jacol24.411f3dd.html to http://www.pe.com/columns/jimalexander/stories/PE_Sports_Local_D_jacol24.411f3dd.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20100615055533/http://www.pe.com:80/sports/college/ucr/stories/PE_Sports_Local_D_ucr_notes_30.3e43232.html to http://www.pe.com/sports/college/ucr/stories/PE_Sports_Local_D_ucr_notes_30.3e43232.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 02:21, 8 February 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[University of California, Riverside]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=707312706 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20080517002201/http://www.pe.com/localnews/riverside/stories/PE_News_Local_D_bagpipes11.3ab535f.html to http://www.pe.com/localnews/riverside/stories/PE_News_Local_D_bagpipes11.3ab535f.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tl|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 03:21, 28 February 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>9xzk1l87k3biab5w4xz3h4mfvegb919</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
