<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Tulsa, Oklahoma</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>15281624</id>
    <revision>
      <id>739382507</id>
      <parentid>725025429</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-14T10:31:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot (v1.2.4)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25503">{{Talk header|search=yes}}
{{User:WildBot/m04|sect={{User:WildBot/m03|1|Race and ethnicity in the United States Census#Race|other races}}, {{User:WildBot/m03|1|mayor-council government#Executive or Strong Mayor Form|strong mayoral system}}|m04}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=FAC
|action1date=00:11, 12 May 2007
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Tulsa, Oklahoma
|action1result=promoted
|action1oldid=130210798
|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=10 August 2010
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Oklahoma|class=FA|importance=Top|tulsa-task-force=yes|tulsa-importance=top}}
{{WikiProject Cities|class=FA|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject United States|class=FA|importance=High|USOldwest=Yes|USOldwest-importance=High}}
}}
{{todo}}

== Photo ==

[[:Image:Downtown Tulsa, 1908.jpg|Image:Downtown Tulsa, 1908.jpg]]

Hi, does anyone think that this photo of early Tulsa should be added or replace another photo? Mabye in the history section, there are no old photos of the city and I think a FA should have at least one.--[[User:CPacker|CPacker]] ([[User talk:CPacker|talk]]) 19:29, 23 February 2008 (UTC)
:It would be nice, but we shouldn't include it due to licensing issues with this particular picture. I'm not sure of the copyright status of the pictures from the Tulsa Historical Society, but we could email and ask them. If the current license is correct, we cannot use it. There were pictures with the &quot;published before 1923&quot; license when this article became a featured candidate, but reviewers wanted them removed since the tag only necessarily applies to the United States, possibly excluding its legal status in other countries. No one would probably care about it being on [[History of Tulsa, Oklahoma]], but featured articles must set a higher standard for viewing around the world. Pictures are really a tricky thing if they're not taken personally and released to public domain by the photographer. Feature article candidates often have problems with picture licensing. [[User:Okiefromokla|Okiefromokla]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Okiefromokla|questions?]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 20:31, 23 February 2008 (UTC)

==Revert of Feb. 23==

Per implied request by anonymous user [[User talk:81.76.73.250|81.76.73.250]], I'll explain further my edit of February 23, and again today. &quot;Buckle of the Bible Belt&quot; is not a [[nickname]] of Tulsa (a word that is synonymous with &quot;Tulsa&quot;). Tulsa is merely considered one of the many [[Bible_belt#.22Buckle.22_of_the_Bible_Belt|buckles of the Bible Belt]]. &quot;America's Most Beautiful City&quot; does not meet the definition of a nickname, either. In other words, who would consider &quot;America's Most Beautiful City&quot; interchangeable with the word &quot;Tulsa&quot;? &quot;Oil Capital of the World&quot; has the deeply-entrenched historical basis and wide recognition to be considered a nickname. I'm willing to keep &quot;T-Town&quot;, although this is not really a nickname, and doesn't have recognition outside of Tulsa. It's borderline.

As far as my changes to the lead, it was merely a matter of keeping things objective. Calling Tulsa an &quot;important town in the history of popular music&quot; somewhat violates [[WP:SYNTH]], as there's no need to make this opinion-based generalization if a source does not make it for us. Simply talking about the prominent artists from Tulsa and the two musical styles from Tulsa is enough, and readers will come to a conclusion based on that information, rather than being told a conclusion by this article. I don't like this generalization to be in the body either, but it most certainly shouldn't be in the lead. 

Additionally, Tulsa was not the &quot;start&quot; of Route 66 &amp;mdash; that implies the geographical start, which it is/was not. [[The Tulsa Sound]] should remain out of the lead for the sake of a concise, summary style per [[WP:LEAD]]. It was not a prominent musical genre like [[Western Swing]]. Furthermore, omitting details like Cain’s Ballroom also helps meet WP:LEAD standards. The mention of Tulsa being the birthplace of Western Swing is enough, there is no reason to go into specific points as to ''why'' it's the birthplace.[[User:Okiefromokla|Okiefromokla]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Okiefromokla|questions?]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 21:10, 24 February 2008 (UTC)

==popular music edit==

shouldn't david cook, the winner of american idol 08 be added to popular music?  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/122.161.23.168|122.161.23.168]] ([[User talk:122.161.23.168|talk]]) 09:04, 22 May 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Is he from Tulsa?  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/72.192.94.145|72.192.94.145]] ([[User talk:72.192.94.145|talk]]) 03:33, 2 July 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;


==[[S.E. Hinton]]==

Probably noteworthy that she's from there.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/71.63.88.111|71.63.88.111]] ([[User talk:71.63.88.111|talk]]) 03:33, 24 August 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Y'know what Tulsa is backwards? A slut. Y'know what A slut backwards is? 20$  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/173.88.189.176|173.88.189.176]] ([[User talk:173.88.189.176|talk]]) 19:09, 10 August 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!--             Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Tulsa is the Paris of Oklahoma ==

Don't you people ever watch Friends?  [http://www.univie.ac.at/Anglistik/aaas/route66/class/oklahoma/friends.htm http://www.univie.ac.at/Anglistik/aaas/route66/class/oklahoma/friends.htm] [[Special:Contributions/68.224.92.165|68.224.92.165]] ([[User talk:68.224.92.165|talk]]) 16:43, 1 July 2008 (UTC)

He was being sarcastic [[User:Sweetie candykim|Sweetie candykim]] ([[User talk:Sweetie candykim|talk]]) 17:52, 25 April 2011 (UTC)

== Who has &quot;control&quot; ==

With wikipedia being community driven, who is the individual who has the final say as to what appears on Tulsa's Wiki page?  I ask because there have been numerous attempts to get certain non-profit organizations listed on the page and everytime they're added they get removed.  Seems a bit odd, considering the media, press, and even the Mayor supports the project.  So who's deciding -- I'd really like to find a justifiable answer.  

Whoever is &quot;modding this&quot; Wiki page:  If you feel as though you're contributing to the city through the Wiki, thanks -- but share credit to those who are contributing outside of the Wiki and in the community we live and play.

Thanks

Justin (want to get at me, google &quot;Tulsa Justin&quot; and find the article about inadequate bloggers and you'll find me)  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/129.244.24.75|129.244.24.75]] ([[User talk:129.244.24.75|talk]]) 22:35, 27 August 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:There is an evil group of totalitarian users who mercilessly patrol and dictate the happenings of this article. ... :) Heh, sorry, that's a [[WP:CABAL|running gag]] on Wikipedia. Actually, there are many [[WP:POLICY|policies and guidelines]] on Wikipedia that dictate what should and should not be in articles (you can find a list of such policies and guidelines at the bottom on my user page). I believe you are referring to a link to a blog that was removed several times. Wikipedia has a special set of guidelines that tell when it is appropriate for external links to be added to certain articles, and in most cases, blogs are not allowed (see [[Wikipedia:External links]]). These policies and guidelines have been determined by anyone and everyone through discussion and [[WP:CONSENSUS|consensus forming]], and at any time they can be changed if there is consensus to do so through discussion on the corresponding talk page. Also, any changes that are disputed on the article can be discussed here (such as the inclusion of a particular link) as long as policy is not broken. I know it's a lot to take in, but no one will look down on you for suggesting something here that policy covers. Trust me, many regular Wikipedia editors aren't entirely clear on what policies there are &amp;mdash; it's confusing. So don't be afraid to ask anything at all. [[User:Okiefromokla|Okiefromokla]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Okiefromokla|questions?]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 22:55, 27 August 2008 (UTC)

::In addition to the excellent answer already provided by ''Okiefromokla'', I would also add that part of Wikipedia's official policy on [[WP:NOT|What Wikipedia is not]] is the notion that it [[WP:NOTDIRECTORY|is not a directory]].  --[[User:Kralizec!|Kralizec!]] ([[User talk:Kralizec!|talk]]) 23:47, 27 August 2008 (UTC)

==Bias?==
Does anyone else notice that this article sounds like it was written by someone on the board of trustees at ORU?  Either the man or the University is mentioned 12 times in the article.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/70.234.180.25|70.234.180.25]] ([[User talk:70.234.180.25|talk]]) 05:30, 31 December 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Well, think about it. It's a pretty big part of Tulsa's education, architecture, sports, and religion. But word for word (including in captions), the phrase &quot;University of Tulsa&quot; is used 10 times and &quot;Oral Roberts University&quot; also 10 times. Sounds pretty even to me. [[User:Okiefromokla|Okiefromokla]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Okiefromokla|questions?]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 05:59, 1 January 2009 (UTC)

Dude, yeah! ORU is so much a part of Tulsa's history that it has its own zip-code, which AFAIK, is not shared by another property. It's kinda crazy. [[Special:Contributions/170.225.12.33|170.225.12.33]] ([[User talk:170.225.12.33|talk]]) 19:28, 12 April 2016 (UTC)

==Whitewash?==
I was born in Tulsa, and there are many Tulsa-related articles that seem to be rather whitewashed to me (in every sense of the word).  They avoid all of the things that are negative about Tulsa and the surrounding counties.  Example:  North Tulsa is Skid Row -- I should know, my parents lived there when I was born.  It's got good stuff there (airport, zoo etc), but Tulsa does have a dark side.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.121.134.253|76.121.134.253]] ([[User talk:76.121.134.253|talk]]) 18:05, 14 September 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:As do most cities. --[[Special:Contributions/70.128.123.6|70.128.123.6]] ([[User talk:70.128.123.6|talk]]) 16:27, 23 October 2009 (UTC)
::True, but I agree with the above.  I can't read anything about Tulsa that is negative, even peripherally.  I moved away because of the large &quot;white supremacy sympathizer&quot; population in the greater Tulsa area and haven't been back to visit in 5+ years.  Too many bad memories.  I don't expect someone to be a jerk about the town, but I would like to see more even-handed reporting.[[Special:Contributions/98.225.230.65|98.225.230.65]] ([[User talk:98.225.230.65|talk]]) 06:59, 22 November 2009 (UTC)
:: Tulsa happens to have the largest [[American Indian]] population of any U.S. metro area. The city should be proud to explore its past and celebrate its ethnic/racial diversity. The [[Greenwood]] section recovered from the race riots in the 1920's and experiences urban revitalization, while the number of Hispanic and Asian immigrants in the West and East sides of town is a reminder of where the American dream can be found. But, despite a history of oil wealth (i.e. Southern Hills), Tulsa lies in one of the 10 least prosperous US states. [[Special:Contributions/71.102.1.101|71.102.1.101]] ([[User talk:71.102.1.101|talk]]) 14:30, 16 July 2011 (UTC)

==Question regarding Tulsa Mayoral elections==
I thought that the term that a mayor was supposed to serve was four years, so why was there a mayoral election in 2009 if the one prior to it was held in 2006, a span of three years? Was there a provision in the city law that required special elections in the event that the incumbent mayor failed to complete a term? [[User:Fuelsaver|Fuelsaver]] ([[User talk:Fuelsaver|talk]]) 03:11, 2 January 2010 (UTC)

== Sister cities ==

Someone keeps adding [[Ploesti]] to the sister city list.  Neither [http://www.sister-cities.org/directory/index.cfm Sister Cities International] nor [http://www.tulsaglobalalliance.org/SisterCity.aspx Tulsa Global Alliance] list Ploesti in this quality. --[[Special:Contributions/71.153.137.46|71.153.137.46]] ([[User talk:71.153.137.46|talk]]) 17:00, 22 May 2010 (UTC)

== Nicknames: The918 ==

I removed &quot;The918&quot; from the list of nicknames and added &quot;Tulsey Town&quot; in its place. I'll work to find a verifiable source. In the meantime, who the hell calls Tulsa &quot;The918&quot; and where is the source for this? This isn't The OC or gangstaland.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Cassidydr|Cassidydr]] ([[User talk:Cassidydr|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Cassidydr|contribs]]) 14:54, 21 July 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:I don't have a strong opinion about including it or leaving it out, but I have seen variants of &quot;the 918&quot; (''with'' a space) used here and there in reliable sources.  Examples: [http://www.tulsaworld.com/scene/article.aspx?subjectid=269&amp;articleid=20090922_371_0_Planah309485 'Rock the 918' to raise money for Tulsa charities], [http://www.cityoftulsa.org/environmental-programs/office-of-sustainability/city-of-tulsa-initiatives/greening-the-918-series.aspx Greening the (918) Series] (City of Tulsa seminar), [http://kotv.com/news/local/story/?id=135790 Don't Hate The 918] ([[KOTV]]).--[[User:Arxiloxos|Arxiloxos]] ([[User talk:Arxiloxos|talk]]) 16:14, 21 July 2010 (UTC)

== Songs about Tulsa ==

There are two songs of consideration regarding Tulsa. The first one &quot;[[Tulsa Time]]&quot; by [[Don Williams]] and later, [[Eric Clapton]] while the second is &quot;[[Take Me Back to Tulsa]]&quot; by [[George Strait]] I think. [[User:Miller17CU94|Chris]] ([[User talk:Miller17CU94|talk]]) 02:12, 10 August 2010 (UTC)
:There are ''lots'' of songs that mention Tulsa. A bunch of them are mentioned at [[List of songs about Oklahoma]].  I don't know that there'd be any compelling reason to add a list of these songs to this article, though.--[[User:Arxiloxos|Arxiloxos]] ([[User talk:Arxiloxos|talk]]) 20:34, 10 August 2010 (UTC)
::Oh, by the way, &quot;[[Take Me Back to Tulsa]]&quot; was popularized by [[Bob Wills]], who ''is'' an important figure in Tulsa cultural history, but I think he's already mentioned enough times in this article.--[[User:Arxiloxos|Arxiloxos]] ([[User talk:Arxiloxos|talk]]) 00:36, 11 August 2010 (UTC)
::&quot;Take Me Back to Tulsa&quot; was both written and recorded by Bob Wills before George Strait was born.[[User:TL36|TL36]] ([[User talk:TL36|talk]]) 02:55, 24 July 2014 (UTC)

== Article name ==

Why is this article entitled &quot;Tulsa, Oklahoma&quot; instead of merely &quot;Tulsa&quot;?  &quot;Tulsa&quot; redirects here, and the disambig page doesn't list any articles named &quot;Tulsa&quot; that are unrelated to this city.  I feel that the word Oklahoma in the title is an unnecessary specification.  How do the regular editors feel about proposing a page move?  [[User:Stebbins|Stebbins]] ([[User talk:Stebbins|talk]]) 20:05, 10 August 2010 (UTC)
*I'd be fine with this; as the [[Tulsa (disambiguation)|DAB page]] shows, the other possible targets don't have close to the same claim on the simple name &quot;Tulsa&quot;.--[[User:Arxiloxos|Arxiloxos]] ([[User talk:Arxiloxos|talk]]) 20:23, 10 August 2010 (UTC)

I think this should be done too. There aren't any other cities called Tulsa and I hate when it says 'city, country' if there is no reason too. It just seems so ignorant.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Sweetie candykim|Sweetie candykim]] ([[User talk:Sweetie candykim|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Sweetie candykim|contribs]]) 17:56, 25 April 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== MSA area ==
What's the size of the Tulsa MSA area. I know it's probably 18,000 sqr. miles or something, but an actual number would be good.

:The MSA area is given as 6,240 sq. miles or 16,164 sq. km. on the [[Tulsa Metropolitan Area]] page.[[User:Bruin2|Bruin2]] ([[User talk:Bruin2|talk]]) 17:46, 26 July 2011 (UTC)

[[Mayes County, Oklahoma]] was included into the Tulsa MSA, where they have the Mid-America Industrial park complex. And [[Washington County, Oklahoma]] where [[Bartlesville]] lies in is known for the [[Phillips 66]] oil company. [[Special:Contributions/71.102.12.48|71.102.12.48]] ([[User talk:71.102.12.48|talk]]) 23:30, 10 November 2012 (UTC)

== TulsaWiki ==

Some of you may be interested in getting involved with the new TulsaWiki: http://www.tulsawiki.org/.  We are having a TulsaWiki Edit-a-thon on June 1 in conjunction with the National Day of Civic Hacking (http://ndochtulsa.eventbrite.com/) but feel free to log in and edit anytime. [[User:EntropyAS|EntropyAS]] ([[User talk:EntropyAS|talk]]) 12:24, 15 April 2013 (UTC)

== Hydrography of region ==

I think it's a little odd that only 30 lakes and reservoirs are mentioned, considering most federal government and state hydrology sources consider Oklahoma as having far more than Minnesota, and I've mapped at least twice as many reservoirs and lakes on OpenStreetMap... perhaps citation 36 is unreliable.  [[Special:Contributions/70.169.52.51|70.169.52.51]] ([[User talk:70.169.52.51|talk]]) 07:31, 21 September 2013 (UTC)

== Structure ==

Hi.  I'm going through all the US Cities (as per [[List of United States cities by population]]) in an effort to provide some uniformity in structure.  Anyone have an issue with me restructuring this article as per [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Cities/US Guideline]].  I won't be changing any content, merely the order.  Occasionally, I will also move a picture just to clean up spacing issues.  I've already gone through the top 20 or so on the above list, if you'd like to see how they turned out.  Thoughts?  [[User:Onel5969|Onel5969]] ([[User talk:Onel5969|talk]]) 16:18, 21 February 2014 (UTC)

So you are just changing the format no the content? I am okay with that. [[User:Buffalodan|Buffalodan]] ([[User talk:Buffalodan|talk]]) 17:43, 23 February 2014 (UTC)

== [[Timeline of Tulsa, Oklahoma]] ==
What is missing from the recently created [[Timeline of Tulsa, Oklahoma|city timeline]] article? Please add relevant content. Contributions welcome. Thank you. -- [[User:M2545|M2545]] ([[User talk:M2545|talk]]) 09:39, 30 May 2015 (UTC)

== Tulsa &quot;third largest city in the world.&quot; ==

I think it is possible that reference to Tulsa as the Third Largest City in the World may not be factually accurate.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Maadim|Maadim]] ([[User talk:Maadim|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Maadim|contribs]]) 19:01, 18 September 2015 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Fixed. [[User:Camerafiend|Camerafiend]] ([[User talk:Camerafiend|talk]]) 19:14, 18 September 2015 (UTC)

== Bombing ==

It is my understanding that U.S. airplanes bombed some of Tulsa during the riots: The First Oklahoma Bombing | Democracy Now!
www.democracynow.org/1999/4/2/the_first_oklahoma_bombing
The First Oklahoma Bombing. April 02, 1999. ... then the Tulsa race riot of 1921 surpasses the Oklahoma City bombing as the largest mass murder of civilians on U.S. soil.[[Special:Contributions/64.53.191.77|64.53.191.77]] ([[User talk:64.53.191.77|talk]]) 04:55, 13 March 2016 (UTC)

== Orphaned references in [[:Tulsa, Oklahoma]] ==

I check pages listed in [[:Category:Pages with incorrect ref formatting]] to try to fix reference errors. One of the things I do is look for content for [[User:AnomieBOT/docs/OrphanReferenceFixer|orphaned references]] in wikilinked articles. I have found content for some of [[:Tulsa, Oklahoma]]'s orphans, the problem is that I found more than one version. I can't determine which (if any) is correct for ''this'' article, so I am asking for a sentient editor to look it over and copy the correct ref content into this article.

&lt;b&gt;Reference named &quot;history&quot;:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From [[Judaism]]: John Bright ''A History of Israel''&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From [[World War I]]: {{cite web |url=http://www.history.com/this-day-in-history/european-powers-maintain-focus-despite-killings-in-sarajevo |title=European powers maintain focus despite killings in Sarajevo &amp;nbsp;— History.com This Day in History |date=30 June 1914 |publisher=History.com |accessdate=26 December 2013}}&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From [[Greenwood, Tulsa]]: {{cite web|url=http://blackwallstreet.org/bwshistory/bwstulsa1830-1921.a.htm |accessdate=November 13, 2008 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20081026071428/http://blackwallstreet.org:80/bwshistory/bwstulsa1830-1921.a.htm |archivedate=October 26, 2008 }}&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From [[Tulsa Performing Arts Center]]: http://www.tulsaworld.com/news/article.aspx?subjectid=13&amp;articleid=020318_Ne_focmain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From [[Union Pacific Railroad]]: [http://www.uprr.com/aboutup/history/uprr-chr.shtml UP:Chronological History], Union Pacific Railroad&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From [[Horse racing]]: [http://www.winningponies.com/horse-racing-history.html &quot;History of Horse Racing.&quot;] WinningPonies.com. 7 April 2009.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From [[Tulsa Ballet]]: 
  {{cite web
  | title = Tulsa Ballet 2007-2008 ~ The Classic in Black &amp; White With a Touch of Red
  | publisher = Tulsa Ballet
  | url = http://www.tulsaballet.org/inside_tulsa_ballet/history.htm
  | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20080828023156/http://www.tulsaballet.org/inside_tulsa_ballet/history.htm
  | archivedate = August 28, 2008
  | accessdate = February 5, 2012
  }}
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

I apologize if any of the above are effectively identical; I am just a simple computer program, so I can't determine whether minor differences are significant or not. [[User:AnomieBOT|AnomieBOT]][[User talk:AnomieBOT|&lt;font color=&quot;#888800&quot;&gt;⚡&lt;/font&gt;]] 03:00, 13 June 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:12|one external link|12 external links}} on [[Tulsa, Oklahoma]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=739382498 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive http://www.webcitation.org/6gpGlyhlr?url=http%3A%2F%2Ffactfinder.census.gov%2Ffaces%2Ftableservices%2Fjsf%2Fpages%2Fproductview.xhtml%3Fsrc%3Dbkmk to http://factfinder.census.gov/faces/tableservices/jsf/pages/productview.xhtml?src=bkmk
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20080101160345/http://zip4.usps.com/zip4/citytown.jsp to http://zip4.usps.com/zip4/citytown.jsp
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20090322080208/http://quickfacts.census.gov/qfd/states/40/4075000.html to http://quickfacts.census.gov/qfd/states/40/4075000.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070627065030/http://www.okcommerce.gov/index.php?option=content&amp;task=view&amp;id=332&amp;Itemid=413 to http://www.okcommerce.gov/index.php?option=content&amp;task=view&amp;id=332&amp;Itemid=413
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20131210225357/http://www.tulsareparations.org/TulsaRiot.htm to http://www.tulsareparations.org/TulsaRiot.htm
*Added {{tlx|dead link}} tag to https://www.artdecobrasil.com/apresentacao.ppt
*Added archive http://www.webcitation.org/6YSasqtfX?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.census.gov%2Fprod%2Fwww%2Fdecennial.html to http://www.census.gov/prod/www/decennial.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20090322080208/http://quickfacts.census.gov/qfd/states/40/4075000.html to http://quickfacts.census.gov/qfd/states/40/4075000.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20051001063528/http://www.aa.com/content/amrcorp/pressReleases/2005_03/03_tulmebase.jhtml to http://www.aa.com/content/amrcorp/pressReleases/2005_03/03_tulmebase.jhtml
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.discoverylandusa.com/awards.shtml
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20110822190220/http://www.tulsaairports.com/index.cfm?id=11 to http://www.tulsaairports.com/index.cfm?id=11
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://tulsaok.usachamber.com/custom2.asp?pageid=1189
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070714184501/http://www.tulsaport.com/news_and_events.html to http://www.tulsaport.com/news_and_events.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 10:31, 14 September 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>9m4kzjuh2y4ounm5zv8ppck7cs7sxr7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
