<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Glyphosate</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2008387</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749765121</id>
      <parentid>749734597</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-16T01:53:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lowercase sigmabot III</username>
        <id>17518500</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Archiving 1 discussion(s) to [[Talk:Glyphosate/Archive 12]]) (bot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9180">{{Talk header}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Agriculture|class=b|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Chemicals|class=b|importance=High }}
{{WikiProject Environment|class=b|importance=Mid}}
}}
{{merged-from|Roundup|26 August, 2012}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 12
|minthreadsleft = 4
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|algo = old(30d)
|archive = Talk:Glyphosate/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Auto archiving notice|bot=MiszaBot I |age=3 |units=months }}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=/Archive index |mask=/Archive &lt;#&gt; |leading_zeros=0 |indexhere=yes
}}
{{Calm}}
{{Round in circles}}

==Section 7.1.4: Toxicity/Glyphosate alone/Amphibians==
The [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glyphosate#Amphibians section] is referenced with a self-published source: Marin-Morales MA, de Campos Ventura-Camargo B, Hoshina M (2013). Toxicity of Herbicides: Impact on Aquatic and Soil Biota and Human Health&quot;. In Jessica A. Kelton, Herbicides–Current Research and Case Studies in Use, Lulu com [https://www.google.de/search?q=Shravasti+Dhammika&amp;hl=de&amp;#q=Herbicides%E2%80%93Current+Research+and+Case+Studies+in+Use&amp;hl=de]. When I checked this source, I found out that this review summarizes research by Relyea on Roundup (with surfactant, p.418). 
The next section [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glyphosate#Other_aquatic_fauna], last sentence, also uses the book published by Lulu com as a source and it is also based on test results with Roundup, including surfactant. [[User:JimRenge|JimRenge]] ([[User talk:JimRenge|talk]]) 23:56, 8 August 2016 (UTC)
: So you must move it to other section, but you deleted it. Also, it is not self-published. [[User:Cathry|Cathry]] ([[User talk:Cathry|talk]]) 07:16, 12 August 2016 (UTC)

== human toxicity ==

* &quot;Acute toxicity is dose-related; Skin exposure to ready-to-use glyphosate formulations can cause irritation, and photocontact dermatitis has been occasionally reported. These effects are probably due to the preservative benzisothiazolin-3-one. Severe skin burns are very rare.[114] Inhalation is a minor route of exposure, but spray mist may cause oral or nasal discomfort, an unpleasant taste in the mouth, or tingling and irritation in the throat. Eye exposure may lead to mild conjunctivitis. Superficial corneal injury is possible if irrigation is delayed or inadequate.[114] Death has been reported after deliberate overdose.[114][115] Ingestion of Roundup ranging from 85 to 200 ml (of 41% solution) has resulted in death within hours of ingestion, although it has also been ingested in quantities as large as 500 ml with only mild or moderate symptoms.[116] A reasonable correlation is seen between the amount of Roundup ingested and the likelihood of serious systemic sequelae or death. Ingestion of more than 85 ml of the concentrated formulation is likely to cause significant toxicity in adults.&quot;

I came to this article after accidental skin exposure. Impressed with the level of relevant helpful detail provided!

Article could be improved with details about safe handling of typical formulations. The infobox is helpful:
* GHS precautionary statements
:  P273, P280, P305+351+338, P310, P501

But too cryptic for the typical reader. It would be better for the codes above to be fully unpacked into actual words, such as:
* P280: Wear protective gloves/protective clothing/eye protection/face protection.
-[[Special:Contributions/71.174.180.38|71.174.180.38]] ([[User talk:71.174.180.38|talk]]) 19:27, 13 September 2016 (UTC)

== Safety must be seen in the context of the Human-gut biota symbiant. ==

The following needs careful consideration and the insights it provides should be incorporated into the main Wikipedia on Glyphosate

From: '''The Interplay Between Environmental Chemical Exposures and Obesity: Proceedings of a Workshop.''' Page 109 &lt;ref&gt;The Interplay Between Environmental Chemical Exposures and Obesity: Proceedings of a Workshop
ISBN: 9780309389242&lt;/ref&gt;

''Young asked a question about the presence of small amounts of glyphosate—the pesticide sold as Round Up—in foods, particularly corn and high-fructose corn syrup. A paper published by Shehata and colleagues (Shehata et al., 2013)&lt;ref&gt;Shehata A. A., W. Schrödl, A. A. Aldin, H. M. Hafez, M. Krüger. 2013. The effect of glyphosate on potential pathogens and beneficial members of poultry microbiota in vitro. Current Microbiology 66(4):350–358.&lt;/ref&gt; reported that many pathogenic gut bacteria are resistant to glyphosate, whereas many beneficial bacteria are susceptible to it. Could the presence of glyphosate in corn syrup be a confounding variable in the results showing a link between fructose and metabolic dysfunction? Goldman answered that she has not seen any studies addressing the issue, but that it is a reasonable question to ask.''  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/182.239.194.197|182.239.194.197]] ([[User talk:182.239.194.197#top|talk]]) 20:18, 11 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
{{cot|Citations}}
{{reflist}}
{{cob}}
:So, a study that found a minimum inhibitory concentration of 0.5 mg/mL at the lowest? When levels in food are at parts per million and lower, further diluted when eaten? No. Even if that weren't the case, this fails [[WP:MEDRS]]. --[[User:Tronvillain|tronvillain]] ([[User talk:Tronvillain|talk]]) 20:56, 11 October 2016 (UTC)

== Residue levels in food products ==
It is already well known that glyphosate persists in soils. Recent tests by Ecowatch might be a bit emotional, but the levels in processed foods are indeed &quot;higher&quot; than expected, meaning higher than in some other foods when considering they are formulated from other ingredients. These tests sponsored by Eco-watch were not field tests, but tests conducted on packaged food products from the shelves. Since the consumer most often doesn't eat carrots directly from the field, or the vegetables are formulated into consumer products, it not just a question of agricultural techniques but also of food safety. The National Pesticide Information center does not have any regulatory oversight and only refers to field tests rather than tests on food products directly, which is usually the domain of the FDA. ([[User:Osterluzei|Osterluzei]] ([[User talk:Osterluzei|talk]]) 16:59, 15 November 2016 (UTC))

:The tests were actually funded by US Right To Know rather than Ecowatch. Full report [https://usrtk.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/FDN_Glyphosate_FoodTesting_Report_p2016-3.pdf here]. Where did you read that these were higher than expected? Looking at the values, the highest was in Cheerios at around 1 ppm. This is very much in line with the maximum levels found in UK wheat - see refs in [[Crop_desiccation#Glyphosate]] - but still way below the MRL of 20 ppm. We could do with more details on the residues found in food in comparison to MRLs, but it would be preferable to get this from academic sources rather than activist organisations. [[User:Smartse|SmartSE]] ([[User talk:Smartse|talk]]) 17:23, 15 November 2016 (UTC)

::Yes, Ecowatch is not the organisation having the tests done, the article implied that they were higher than expected with regard to ADI. I clearly stated in my contribution that the levels were below the U.S. limits for common food products and therefore not alarming. Nevertheless, they have tested above 1 ppm as you also wrote, and the Code of Federal Regulation limit (MRL) here is 0.5 ppm for the grain itself, hence the concern is not so far-fetched (difficult what a limit for Cheerios would be, and again the differences in ADI values have concerned consumers). I believe tests conducted by licensed labs such as Anresco (full lab results here: [https://s3.amazonaws.com/media.fooddemocracynow.org/images/anresco_reports_food_testing_2016.pdf anresco_reports_food_testing_2016.pdf]) can have value even for academics, but you are right maybe another more objective paper on such consumer product tests would be favorable. I just don't agree with the interpretation &quot;environmental fate&quot;; once those levels show up in food products, they are considered food contaminants. ([[User:Osterluzei|Osterluzei]] ([[User talk:Osterluzei|talk]]) 18:04, 15 November 2016 (UTC))

:::We're veering towards [[WP:OR|original research]] here, but [http://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/retrieveECFR?gp=1&amp;SID=22006aeec2fa6552cf69c260a071d94f&amp;ty=HTML&amp;h=L&amp;mc=true&amp;r=SECTION&amp;n=se40.26.180_1364 the second ref] you cited gives the MRL for grain as 30 ppm, so 1 ppm is much lower. We need to look for better sources which discuss permissible MRLs and the amount found in foodstuffs because they must be out there. It is very poor that we don't have info on the MRLs or ADIs. There is discussion of ADIs in [https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4756530/ this review] but there might be better ones available. I agree that environmental fate isn't the best place for it, but it didn't seem sensible to leave just one sentence in a section of it's own. [[User:Smartse|SmartSE]] ([[User talk:Smartse|talk]]) 22:16, 15 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>tc4foofu6luk9cgaqkblq9xbmu3761d</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
