<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Multi-armed bandit</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2862893</id>
    <revision>
      <id>743995761</id>
      <parentid>718427204</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-12T13:29:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dlougach</username>
        <id>12389930</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* UCB description */ new section</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8095">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Gambling |class=C |importance=Low}}
{{Maths rating |field=probability and statistics |class=C |priority=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Robotics |class=C |importance=Low |attention=yes}}
{{WikiProject Statistics |class=C |importance=Mid}}
}}
{{User:ClueBot III/ArchiveThis|archiveprefix=Talk:Multi-armed bandit/Archives/|format=Y|age=26297|index=yes|archivebox=yes|box-advert=yes}}

==Whittle and the war==
There was a recent request to verify what was/is attributed to Whittle (1979). What he says is ..
:&quot;As I said the problem is a classic one; it was formulated during the war, and efforts to solve it so sapped the energies and minds of Allied analysts that the suggestion was made that the problem be dropped over Germany, as the ultimate instrument of intellectual sabotage.&quot;
So this corresponds to what is said in the article. [[User:Melcombe|Melcombe]] ([[User talk:Melcombe|talk]]) 10:40, 3 August 2011 (UTC)

:I've seen the same story, but with the &quot;weighing pennies&quot; problem as the timewaster. This account seems more plausible, since that problem is simple enough for lots of people to spend time on it, and it's a pure distraction. I'll edit it to attribute the claim to Whittle.[[User:John Quiggin|JQ]] ([[User talk:John Quiggin|talk]]) 21:01, 14 May 2012 (UTC)

:: I accidentally removed this claim because I hadn't read the talk page (oops!) and the reference was incorrect (pointed to the initial Gittins paper, which clearly did not make the claim). I am going to restore it now [[User:Giuseppe Burtini|Giuseppe Burtini]] ([[User talk:Giuseppe Burtini|talk]]) 23:37, 11 December 2014 (UTC)

:: An excerpt from my M.Sc. thesis follows for further discussion on this attribution and the origin of the multi-armed bandit problem:
:: &quot;''Thompson (1933) provides an answer to a related question: how to identify the probability of a distribution being better than all others from a set of distributions, and has thusly been sometimes credited as the origin of the multi-armed bandit.'' 
:: ''Even more confounding on the origins of the multi-armed bandit, Dr. Peter Whittle said in review of the 1979 paper of Gittins [67] the following:'' 
:::'As I said, the problem is a classic one; it was formulated during the war, and efforts to solve it so sapped the energies and minds of Allied analysts that the suggestion was made that the problem be dropped over Germany, as the ultimate instrument of intellectual sabotage. In the event, it seems to have landed on Cardiff Arms Park. And there is justice now, for if a Welsh Rugby pack scrumming down is not a multi-armed bandit, then what is?' 
:: ''As World War II ended in 1945, this provides evidence that the problem was under discussion at least privately by the military if not elsewhere prior to the Robbins (1952) paper. Robbins (1952) is the first indexed paper to call the problem the multi-armed bandit and provides a formulation similar to the formulation used to date.''&quot; [[User:Giuseppe Burtini|Giuseppe Burtini]] ([[User talk:Giuseppe Burtini|talk]]) 03:21, 6 August 2015 (UTC)

As noted above, this quote comes from Peter Whittle's review of the paper of John Gittins at the Royal Society and can be found here http://www.eecs.berkeley.edu/~russell/classes/cs294/s11/readings/Gittins:1979.pdf at page 165 (page 19 of the PDF file) [[User:Pychron|Pychron]] ([[User talk:Pychron|talk]]) 08:49, 18 March 2016 (UTC)

==The multi-armed bandit model==
The sentence stating &quot;The regret &lt;math&gt;\rho&lt;/math&gt; after T rounds is defined as the difference between the reward sum associated with an optimal strategy and the sum of the collected rewards:&quot;  is incorrect. It should say &quot;...is defined as the expected difference between...&quot; not &quot;the difference between&quot; since &lt;math&gt;T\mu^*&lt;/math&gt; represents an expected value. [[User:Chafe66|Chafe66]] ([[User talk:Chafe66|talk]]) 20:11, 30 November 2012 (UTC)


:In fact, it is my position that defining regret in many cases is non-trivial. The regret at time &lt;math&gt;t&lt;/math&gt; may be defined one of a few different ways and indeed varies between papers. Especially important is the difference in strong and weak or pseudo-regret, but also the difference in expected value regret (taking expectation of the arm pulled, versus sampling from it) and experimental regret (using the best trace in an experimental context as the oracle for defining correctness). On Wikipedia, however, the aim is for verifiability, so the definition should only consider the published forms of regret definitions for now. It should acknowledge how they differ though. [[User:Giuseppe Burtini|Giuseppe Burtini]] ([[User talk:Giuseppe Burtini|talk]]) 23:35, 11 December 2014 (UTC)

:: I can't see how anything but an expected value makes any sense at all here. Any one experimental case is irrelevant. What matters is how an algorithm does *on average*, and that means taking expectations.[[User:Chafe66|Chafe66]] ([[User talk:Chafe66|talk]]) 07:54, 29 May 2015 (UTC)

::: For one possible counterexample, in some application areas you care about other moments of regret or percentiles of regret rather than expectation. This is important (in my humble opinion) when we discuss variants such as risk-adjusted bandits, applications in medical trials (maximum allowed risk) and financial market applications (maximum allowable drawdown). [[User:Giuseppe Burtini|Giuseppe Burtini]] ([[User talk:Giuseppe Burtini|talk]]) 14:40, 1 June 2015 (UTC)

== NeuralBandit and adversarial vs. contextual categorization ==

{{strikethrough|With only a cursory exploration at this point, it appears to me that NeuralBandit (and perhaps its parent algorithm, Banditron, currently unmentioned) belongs in the adversarial section, or perhaps contextual should be restructured to be a sub-type of adversarial. An adversarial bandit is one with no constraints on its underlying reward distribution, while a contextual bandit is one where the reward is expected to be generated by some other stochastic model. I think the distinction and hierarchy of sub-bandit problems requires some discussion, so I haven't gone ahead and made the change yet. [[User:Giuseppe Burtini|Giuseppe Burtini]] ([[User talk:Giuseppe Burtini|talk]]) 14:52, 13 December 2014 (UTC)}} 

: I retract the above after substantial further research. The authors of the NB paper call it contextual, it should be listed as contextual. [[User:Giuseppe Burtini|Giuseppe Burtini]] ([[User talk:Giuseppe Burtini|talk]]) 03:17, 6 August 2015 (UTC)

== Markovian Setting ==

The text states that the Gittins Index is defined for a Markovian setting of the MAB.  Instead, the Gittins Index is defined also to non-Markovian settings, it is its calculation that so far has been devised only in a Markovian setting (both fully and partially observable). [[User:Pychron|Pychron]] ([[User talk:Pychron|talk]]) 08:49, 18 March 2016 (UTC)

== Reward distributions ==

Reading this page and learning about bandits for the first time.  I'm confused about the regret distributions &lt;math&gt;B = \{R_1, \dots ,R_K\}&lt;/math&gt;, as they related to the regret bounds stated later (for example &lt;math&gt;O(\sqrt{T})&lt;/math&gt; and regret bounds stated in terms of &lt;math&gt;K&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;T&lt;/math&gt; in other articles).  These bounds don't make sense unless the reward distributions are bounded - I strongly suspect in &lt;math&gt;[0,1]&lt;/math&gt;.  Is that correct? Should this bound be stated in the article?  Even the notation &lt;math&gt;B&lt;/math&gt; seems to vaguely imply this but I can't find it stated anywhere.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Emdeefive|Emdeefive]] ([[User talk:Emdeefive|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Emdeefive|contribs]]) 13:06, 3 May 2016 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== UCB description ==

In my opinion, this article should give some basic overview of the UCB method. It mentions it in a couple of generalizations, but doesn't even explain what it is. [[User:Dlougach|Dlougach]] ([[User talk:Dlougach|talk]]) 13:29, 12 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>n2oqh6dzfvelhuqzhss2jwlftom4w1u</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
