<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Gay bar</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2374368</id>
    <revision>
      <id>723429520</id>
      <parentid>713673812</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-06-03T00:34:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Another Believer</username>
        <id>5886041</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>{{Wiki Loves Pride 2014}}</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20382">{{WikiProject banner shell|1=
{{WikiProject LGBT studies| class=Start}}
{{WikiProject Beer|class=start|importance=low|pubs=yes}}
{{WikiProject Food and drink|class=start|importance=|bar=yes}}
}}
{{Wiki Loves Pride 2014}}

== [[Die Busche]] ==

I've deleted the url of the club &quot;Die Busche&quot; because it's a wrong link.

== [[The Dover Castle]] merged here ==

See [[Wikipedia:Articles for deletion/The Dover Castle]]. [[User:Johnleemk|Johnleemk]] | [[User talk:Johnleemk|Talk]] 14:04, 23 January 2006 (UTC)

== Needs published source ==

Moved this to talk:

&quot;&quot;The Gay Bar&quot; is a local grassroots movement at [[UC Berkeley]] that advocates &quot;spending all [their] money at the gay bar&quot; and &quot;taking [you] to a gay bar&quot; as well as &quot;[[sodomy]].&quot;

[[User:Jokestress|Jokestress]] 19:34, 23 June 2006 (UTC)

Isn't that just another name for an [[LGB society]] ? [[User:Veryblueboy|horseboy]] 17:04, 22 July 2006 (UTC)


== Rewrite ==

I've added slightly to the introduction and rewritten the &quot;Characteristics&quot; section (and renamed it). My aim was to broaden the definition of a gay bar and to point out that the variations pretty much mirror the variations of &quot;straight&quot; bars. I've also tried to soften the emphasis on music and beef up the information about sex on the premises venues. I've also tidied up various bits and pieces and hopefully made the article more comprehensive. 

I still think that the list of &quot;notable gay nighclubs&quot; is next to useless. It's very North American centred. I would have thought that a Wikipedia link should be a minimum requirement for inclusion here. 

I also think that the list of Gay DJs is superfluous and again suggests that gay bars are all about music. Again, I'd have thought that Wikipedia links should be a minimum requirement, although I don't really see the point of this list at all. 

--[[User:Wastekiller|Wastekiller]] 15:00, 3 August 2006 (UTC)

==Notable gay nightclubs==
Some of the clubs listed seem notable. Others seem more like ads. My preference would be to make all of them internal, Wikipedia links, and thus let the normal rules of WP notability sort them out. Any objections or concerns? Obviously, this would involve my doing some research to dig up enough detail to make each external link into an article. -[[User:Harmil|Harmil]] 02:16, 4 August 2005 (UTC)

::I'm in support.  [[User:Exploding Boy|Exploding Boy]] 02:20, August 4, 2005 (UTC)

::I agree. [[User:Mushroom|Mushroom]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Mushroom|Talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 17:45, 19 August 2006 (UTC)

:: I would suggestion doing away with notablity all together and draw up a list of gay bars in general.

:::I don't think that's really an option, because Wikipedia shouldn't contain lists of non-notable things. [[User:Cadr|Cadr]] 14:57, 4 September 2006 (UTC)

:::: it has a long list of gay porn actors, I would hardly call most of them notable. It's an online encyclopedia not a notalopedia

:::::What list? We have a [[List of male performers in gay porn films]] but this is a list of male performers in gay porn films. Their sexuality is irrelevant. Also, all of these people are I presume noteable as all are blue links and therefore have wikipedia articles. If you feel any of them are not noteable according to wikipedia's criteria, feel free to nominate them for deletion. [[User:Nil Einne|Nil Einne]] 15:16, 23 July 2007 (UTC)

::I really don't think that an article about the Gay Bar (as concept) is the place for a list of commercial venues (whether they're bars or nightclubs or anything else). Such a list could never be comprehensive, and even if it was, I don't see what it achieves. WP is not intended as a resource for that kind of information - which is much more easily available at a local level anyway. If somebody really wants to draw up a list of historically notable gay bars, clubs and other commercial venues, then I think Harmil's approach should be adopted, and that it should be a seperate article - something like &quot;Notable Gay Commercial Venues&quot; with could then be linked to from all sorts of GBLT articles. [[User:Wastekiller|Wastekiller]] 12:38, 9 September 2006 (UTC)

This list really need to be trimmed or removed. Please read [[WP:NOT]], which is the relevant policy. Particularly, [[WP:NOT#Wikipedia_is_not_a_directory]]. If a list of &quot;notable&quot; gay bars is to be retained, it should not contain external links and should link only the bars that have some ongoing historical relevance to the topic in general. The current list is far from that. I would support removing the list and adding inline prose references to notables establishments in the &quot;History&quot; section. As it stands, the section is a magnet for inappropriate commercial links (per [[WP:EL]]). Likewise, the list of Gay DJs probably doesn't belong in this article, or at least should only contain those DJs with articles where their notability can be explained. [[User talk:Mike Dillon|Mike Dillon]] 22:56, 16 December 2006 (UTC)

::As [[WP:NOT]] a directory of gay clubs, I've removed those that don't have their own Wikipedia article. I suggest that for future additions to the list, the club should either have its own article on Wikipedia (and so be a Wikilink) or a reference be provided as to its notability i.e. a newspaper article remarking on its importance (not the club's own publicity).
::Actually, some of those articles on clubs are a bit dubious- references asserting notability are probably needed to show their notability if we aren't to see them in AfD. - [[User:WJBscribe|'''WJB'''''scribe'']]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:WJBscribe|('''WJB''' ''talk'')]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 13:37, 17 December 2006 (UTC)
:::OK, done the same with '''Gay DJs''', again I think they should be links to arrticles, or have a ref supporting inclusion. - [[User:WJBscribe|'''WJB'''''scribe'']]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:WJBscribe|('''WJB''' ''talk'')]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 13:42, 17 December 2006 (UTC)

maybe there should be page showing notable gay bars by country, such as first gay bar etc. its a little less biased - having just a few here seems to suggest these are pre-eminent maybe? like, some gay bars are famous in their own countries, but maybe not as much outside of their own countries. for example ireland's oldest gay bar/club, the george, is a household name in ireland (for good and bad reasons) because it has been open for so long, and in a country with a huge catholic majority (homosexuality only decriminalised in 1993!). having said that it probably isn't well know outside of ireland (i dunno, is it?). anyway just my two cents. [[User:89.100.207.169|89.100.207.169]] 15:25, 22 January 2007 (UTC)bmackers

:Being a household name in Ireland is sufficient notability. In fact, the article for [[The George, Dublin]] exists, so I've added it to the list. [[User talk:Mike Dillon|Mike Dillon]] 15:39, 22 January 2007 (UTC)

I've trimmed the list down a little, and removed some utterly non-notable stuff.  A lot more needs removing, however.  The list should include only ''notable'' bars, so there should be some explanation as to the venue's notability.  Eg: Stonewall Inn?  Yes, because it was the site of the Stonewall Riots.  Random bar that hosts a popular gay night?  No.  [[User:Exploding Boy|Exploding Boy]] 18:31, 15 June 2007 (UTC)

Added The Coleherne and the Black Cap - London pubs with a lot of history, preserved as part of LGBT history in wikipedia.
Paul Jeffrey Thompson 18:42, 18 May 2010 (UTC)  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Pjthompso|Pjthompso]] ([[User talk:Pjthompso|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Pjthompso|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Added Royal Vauxhall Tavern since its South London's oldest surviving gay venue. &gt;VinnY&lt;  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/2.96.34.220|2.96.34.220]] ([[User talk:2.96.34.220|talk]]) 17:08, 18 November 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==External Links==

*[http://www.entrepreneur.com//startingabusiness/article184288.html Entrepreneur.com: 10 Businesses Facing Extinction in 10 Years] September 19, 2007

I removed this link because it no longer leads to the original article. Rather, it takes you to an anti-spyware software sales page. [[User:Greenmnm69|Greenmnm69]] 05:15, 21 August 2008 (UTC)

==Disappearance of gay bars==

I've reverted the whole section on the &quot;disappearance&quot; of gay bars; it's largely POV, and is sourced only to the Entrepreneur article, whose source in turn is an Orlando Sentinel article specifically about the Orlando, Florida area. It's an interesting point, and I suspect there is some truth in it, but we need to be better-sourced and less sweeping with a major assertion like that.

The Sentinel article can be found here (and doubtless on the newspaper's own site too):
http://www.conxity.com/forum/showthread.php?p=203

By the way, I managed to open the Entrepreneur article safely in Safari, if anyone's interested in reading it. [[User:Barnabypage|Barnabypage]] ([[User talk:Barnabypage|talk]]) 11:16, 22 August 2008 (UTC)

I don't know how, but I don't really believe the Entrepreneur article. It pretty much portrays a hypothetical situation. The way it's written, right there in Paragraph 1 of this entry, says&quot;the relevance of gay bars has diminished.&quot; This is based on an estimation, a projection, by Entrepreneur almost 3 years ago. I challenge their statement. Even if it is remotely nearing truth, I don't believe it belongs up there in Paragraph 1. Perhaps put a &quot;Controversies&quot; section down on the main page somewhere and talk about the forced closings, raids, and current challenges due to decreased patronage due to social media challenges, etc.  My $0.02, but I hope some poor kid who's just coming out doesn't read that and think &quot;Oh well, I can just stay indoors and interact with people online via social media instead of meet them for realsies in social situations&quot;. [[User:Ohnonotagain416|Ohnonotagain416]] ([[User talk:Ohnonotagain416|talk]]) 17:20, 8 November 2011 (UTC)

As a brief follow-up to what I just said, I noticed the list of bars at the bottom that read (closed) - well that's all fine but we don't mention that new bars opened. Gay businesses are always opening and closing. One bar goes, another pops up across the street. [[User:Ohnonotagain416|Ohnonotagain416]] ([[User talk:Ohnonotagain416|talk]]) 17:27, 8 November 2011 (UTC)

:Quite - it's the nature of the bar business, not just the gay one. Many fail and a few last. [[User:Barnabypage|Barnabypage]] ([[User talk:Barnabypage|talk]]) 18:17, 8 November 2011 (UTC)

== Image note ==

I added a note to [[:File:Barzilay Venue in Tel Aviv Israel.jpg]] saying [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Gay_bar&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=393713377&amp;oldid=393479960 Appearing in this image in no way acknowledges any sexual orientation] and have been reverted several times by [[User:Emerson7]]. Due to several recent gay suicides from harassment, I feel this note is very important so we can try and prevent more suicides, as by not implying that the men in this image are gay/bisexual. No one in this image gave Wikipedia permission to show them in a gay bar...yes I know we don't need permission, and they are in a public place, but in this situation I feel privacy and '''safety''' should outweigh anything else. Thoughts? &lt;font face=&quot;Kristen ITC&quot;&gt;[[User:Ctjf83|&lt;font color=&quot;#ff0000&quot;&gt;C&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#ff6600&quot;&gt;T&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#ffff00&quot;&gt;J&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#009900&quot;&gt;F&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#0000ff&quot;&gt;8&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#6600cc&quot;&gt;3&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User Talk:Ctjf83|chat]]&lt;/font&gt; 01:52, 18 November 2010 (UTC)
: Wikipedia has a well-established policy on disclaimers of any kind: [[WP:NODISCLAIMERS]]...if their identity or safety is a concern the image should be removed. [[User:Casascius|Casascius♠]] ([[User talk:Casascius|talk]]) 04:33, 18 November 2010 (UTC)
::Additionally to all the points made by [[WP:NODISCLAIMERS]], anyone inclined to harass someone because their photo appears in a gay-related Wikipedia article is highly unlikely to be deterred by a patently disingenuous disclaimer anyway. [[User:Barnabypage|Barnabypage]] ([[User talk:Barnabypage|talk]]) 11:10, 18 November 2010 (UTC)
:::besides being utterly contrary to wp policy, there are literally tens of thousands of images on wikipedia that show individuals in &lt;s&gt;such&lt;/s&gt; public places. it is not the business of this publication--or most any other for that matter--to guard one's public behaviour. if there's a specific issue with a specific image, there are other avenues for redress. --[[User talk:emerson7|emerson7]] 17:50, 18 November 2010 (UTC)
::::Seems like an [[WP:IAR]] case to me. Tens of thousands of images that show people in places where they might not want evidence? I find that unlikely. I await further input. &lt;font face=&quot;Kristen ITC&quot;&gt;[[User:Ctjf83|&lt;font color=&quot;#ff0000&quot;&gt;C&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#ff6600&quot;&gt;T&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#ffff00&quot;&gt;J&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#009900&quot;&gt;F&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#0000ff&quot;&gt;8&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#6600cc&quot;&gt;3&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User Talk:Ctjf83|chat]]&lt;/font&gt; 21:16, 18 November 2010 (UTC)
: This Wikimedia Commons guideline may be relevant: [[Commons:Commons:Photographs of identifiable people|Commons:Photographs of identifiable people]]. [[User:Quigley|Quigley]] ([[User talk:Quigley|talk]]) 00:11, 22 November 2010 (UTC)
::Ok, good link. &lt;font face=&quot;Kristen ITC&quot;&gt;[[User:Ctjf83|&lt;font color=&quot;#ff0000&quot;&gt;C&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#ff6600&quot;&gt;T&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#ffff00&quot;&gt;J&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#009900&quot;&gt;F&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#0000ff&quot;&gt;8&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#6600cc&quot;&gt;3&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User Talk:Ctjf83|chat]]&lt;/font&gt; 23:50, 22 November 2010 (UTC)

==Cafe Odeon==
I usually visit Grand Cafe Odeon in Zurich and its clear that Odeon is not a Gay Bar. Theres no reference about Odeon was ever used as Gays or lesbians of Zurich.--[[User:Patagonian|Patagonian]] ([[User talk:Patagonian|talk]]) 18:17, 15 May 2012 (UTC)
::i've been going since 15 years. and i'm not the only one as evidenced [http://zurich.gaycities.com/bars/ here] and [http://zurich.gaycities.com/bars/1433-odeon here]. --[[User talk:emerson7|emerson7]] 22:27, 15 May 2012 (UTC)
:::According to [http://www.lonelyplanet.com/switzerland/zurich/restaurants/bar/cafe-odeon ''Lonely Planet''], it's mixed. [[User:AV3000|AV3000]] ([[User talk:AV3000|talk]]) 00:44, 16 May 2012 (UTC)
::::indeed, which means it completely falls within the scope of this article. --[[User talk:emerson7|emerson7]] 00:51, 16 May 2012 (UTC)

I usually visit Odeon since 1990 and i have never heard about any kind of gay or lesbian act in the Cafe. emerson7, your arguement is false.--[[User:Patagonian|Patagonian]] ([[User talk:Patagonian|talk]]) 12:23, 16 May 2012 (UTC)

http://travel.nytimes.com/travel/guides/europe/switzerland/zurich/49221/cafabar-odaon/restaurant-detail.html --''&lt;font face=&quot;bold&quot;&gt;[[User:Wikiwind|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#633B7E;color:#FFD550;padding:0 2px&quot;&gt;В и к и&lt;/span&gt;]][[User talk:Wikiwind|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#FFD666;padding:0 2px;color:#0000;&quot;&gt; T &lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/font&gt; 16:44, 16 May 2012 (UTC)

== Oldest in NYC? ==

[[Gay bar#Modern era|§ Modern era]] says
:Julius is New York City's oldest continuously operating gay bar and is possibly the oldest continuously operating gay bar in the world.
But I see claims for the Candlelight Lounge, later renamed Candle Bar (emphasis added):

*DaveCullen.com's [http://www.davecullen.com/forum/index.php?topic=20158.285 Gay History -- How We Got Here], in a post by &quot;Jack too&quot; dated March 29, 2007:
:Saturday, June 28th [...] Nothing seemed unusual for a Saturday night.  What we had seen, of course, was the beginning of the second night of the Stonewall riots.  The crowd we saw had been in front of the Stonewall bar, though we didn't realize that it was at that particular part of the street. 
:[...]
:The following Wednesday night I stopped in the Candlelight (then the only gay bar on the Upper West Side of Manhattan, and a legally licensed bar – it is '''the oldest continuously operating gay bar in New York City''', by the way) and someone asked me if I had heard about what happened in the Village. 

*On Tumblr, under a photo titled [https://www.flickr.com/photos/19233144@N04/6957596724/ 7112Julius's Bar at Waverly Place &amp; West 10th Street in Greenwich Village], dated April 13, 2012, and posted by &quot;Jerome&quot;:
:Julius is a tavern in the New York City Greenwich Village neighborhood. It is often called the oldest continuously operating gay bar in New York; however, its management was actively unwilling to operate as such and harassed gay customers until 1966. In fact, the distinction of being the longest continuously running gay in New York belongs to the Candle Bar (formerly the Candlelight Lounge) at 309 Amsterdam Avenue, '''which was openly operating as a gay bar with a gay staff before April 1966, while the Julius bar was enforcing its policy of harassing and ejecting gay men. The Candle Bar has continued operating as a gay establishment uninterruptedly to the present day.'''

I'm not going to try to adjudicate between these. Instead, I'm posting a pointer on [[Wikipedia talk:WikiProject LGBT studies]], under [[Wikipedia talk:WikiProject LGBT studies#Oldest gay bar in NYC?|Oldest gay bar in NYC?]].

To discuss this with me, please {{Tn|Ping}} me. [[User:Thnidu|Thnidu]] ([[User talk:Thnidu|talk]]) 02:24, 13 January 2015 (UTC)

== Context needed for the image of Cafe Odeon in Zurich ==

Cafe Odeon is not listed under notable gay bars. There is no context for its inclusion in the section. If it can be shown to have some relevance to the section and/or article, please add context to the caption. [[Special:Contributions/108.86.234.251|108.86.234.251]] ([[User talk:108.86.234.251|talk]]) 22:49, 20 February 2015 (UTC)

== Three Sisters ==
{{Resolved}}
{{ping|Another Believer}} -- you've marked this as 1969 thru 2004?  Didn't it open in 1964 and become a gay bar in 1997? [[User:Valereee|valereee]] ([[User talk:Valereee|talk]]) 18:42, 16 August 2015 (UTC)
: {{Ping|Valereee}} Thank you for catching this. Sorry, years were intended for another entry. Corrected. ---[[User:Another Believer|&lt;span style=&quot;color:navy&quot;&gt;Another Believer&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;sub&gt;([[User talk:Another Believer|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#C60&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/span&gt;]])&lt;/sub&gt; 18:44, 16 August 2015 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Gay bar]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=686502346 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20080912160258/http://www.gaybarculture.com:80/ to http://www.gaybarculture.com

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers. —[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 14:30, 19 October 2015 (UTC)

== Add a list of specifically lesbian bars? ==

After the Lexington Bar, a lesbian bar in the Mission District of San Francisco, closed in 2014, a lot of articles came out from LGBT sources discussing the fact that lesbian bars are disappearing across the U.S. (possibly due to financial issues). As such it seems important to have a list of bars that specifically cater to lesbians on this page, since there are so few of them. What do you all think of adding a section under &quot;Gay bars&quot; that says &quot;Lesbian bars&quot; so that we can keep track of those?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Gobonkersnow|Gobonkersnow]] ([[User talk:Gobonkersnow|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Gobonkersnow|contribs]]) 23:11, 22 October 2015 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;</text>
      <sha1>l1mhay2jo2s7omegmhc5afb4bi7ksn1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
