<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Walk This Way</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>3319980</id>
    <revision>
      <id>634534400</id>
      <parentid>463023378</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-11-19T13:35:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DepressedPer</username>
        <id>4390460</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Tagged WP hip hop.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12657">{{talkheader}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{Songs|class=C}}
{{WikiProject Aerosmith|class=C|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Hip hop|class=C|importance=high}}
}}

== NPR Interview Info ==

NPR Fresh Air on Aug. 30, 2007 re-broadcasted an interview with Steven Tyler &amp; Joe Perry that was originally done in 1997.  Around the 22:36 minute mark they talk about this song specifically in relation to how it was created.  Joe cites the meter of James Brown and Neville Brothers.  The hook was created at a sound check in Hawaii.  Steven actually lost the lyrics and then rewrote them and wrote the lyrics again on the wall at The Record Plant.  Apparently he left the original lyrics in a cab and they were never to be found again.  I'm not sure how to format all that for the story, but it's relevant and backed up with primary source documentation.
[http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=14053440 NPR Link]  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/69.134.160.178|69.134.160.178]] ([[User talk:69.134.160.178|talk]]) 06:50, 10 November 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== group sex? ==

looking at the lyrics now, i suppose i can see how you might think group sex is being hinted at, but it never would've occurred to me without reading that here first. is there a source for this, or is it someone's personal interpretation? --[[User:Kingnixon|dan]] 09:41, 2 October 2006 (UTC)

== Image Removed ==

I have removed the &quot;cover&quot; of Girls Aloud and Sugababes version of &quot;Walk This Way&quot; as it is obvious it is not the official cover.  

*the author simply copy and pasted the a pic of the sugababes on top of a pic of Girls Aloud.
*2 members of Girls Aloud are &quot;giving the finger&quot; 

Here is the picture, if you would like to see it Image:Walkthisway.jpg 
'''[[User:hippi ippi|&lt;font color=&quot;orange&quot;&gt;hippi ippi&lt;/font&gt;]]''' 03:36, 4 February 2007 (UTC)

Rock is being cheapened, if legendary rock/hip hop songs are being sung by wannabe barbie dolls with no real talent what so ever.

Rock? Girls Aloud/Sugababes is not rock, for a start. And you're probably deaf, so I forgive you for not realising that they obviously have better voices than Aerosmith and DMC. Anyway, is this - http://eil.com/Gallery/390772b.jpg an official alternate cover? [[User:-Anthony-|-Anthony-]] 07:55, 15 March 2007 (UTC)

== ... ==

''&quot;The song has been covered by UK girl groups Girls Aloud and Sugababes as the official Comic Relief single in 2007.&quot;'' 

...is just sooo asking to be vandalised. Heh. [[User:Andy29|andy29]] 02:24, 14 March 2007 (UTC)

== Sugababes snub? ==

I removed the following comment since I don't think there's any way to prove it is true and thus does not belong in the article:

This is hugely due to the sales from Girls Aloud fans, after the song was snubbed by so called Sugababes fans who branded it 'horrible' due to the lack of vocal talent on the Sugababes part. [[User:LPMA|LPMA]] 22:09, 18 March 2007 (UTC)

==Non-free use disputed for Image:Walk This Way 2.JPG==
I'm moving the following message from my talk page, as these notices really should be posted on article talk pages rather than the original uploader's talk page:  [[User:Postdlf|Postdlf]] 15:48, 8 July 2007 (UTC)

:There is a concern that the rationale provided for using [[:Image:Walk This Way 2.JPG]] &quot;fair use&quot; may be invalid. Please read the instructions at [[Wikipedia:Non-free content]] carefully, then go to [[:Image:Walk This Way 2.JPG|the image description page]] and clarify why you think the image qualifies for fair use. Using one of the templates at [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline]] is an easy way to ensure that your image is in compliance with Wikipedia policy, but remember that you must complete the template. Do not simply insert a blank template on an image page.

:If it is determined that the image does not qualify under fair use, it will be deleted within a couple of days according to our [[WP:CSD#Images/media|Criteria for speedy deletion]]. If you have any questions please ask them at the [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions|Media copyright questions page]]. Thank you.&lt;!-- Template:No fair --&gt; '''&lt;span style=&quot;color:#000088;&quot;&gt;—♦♦ &lt;/span&gt;[[User:SoothingR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#000088;&quot;&gt;''S''ʘʘ''THING''&lt;/span&gt;]][[User talk:SoothingR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#0066FF;&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;(Я)&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]]''' 07:30, 8 July 2007 (UTC)

== B-side? ==

The single cover lists &quot;Come Together&quot; as the B-side, but Come Together is not listed as a B-side in the infobox. Can somebody look into whether this was an alternate B-side or something like that? [[User:TheCatalyst31|TheCatalyst31]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:TheCatalyst31|Reaction]]•[[Special:Contributions/TheCatalyst31|Creation]]&lt;/sup&gt; 16:52, 29 July 2007 (UTC)

== Ja Rule, Nelly, and Sum41 ==

Shouldn't there be a blurb about their performance of &quot;Walk this Way&quot; at the 2002 MTV (or was is Much Music?) awards?

...

On second thought, forget about it. I just watched it again. Ouch.

[[Special:Contributions/70.74.205.41|70.74.205.41]] ([[User talk:70.74.205.41|talk]]) 02:27, 22 November 2007 (UTC)

== Dick Brave &amp; The Backbeats ==

They actually did a really nice cover. Should be mentioned.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/91.62.54.72|91.62.54.72]] ([[User talk:91.62.54.72|talk]]) 10:23, 15 April 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== [[Young Frankenstein]] ==

The song's title was inspired by the line in Young Frankenstein. Why is there no mention of that all other than a brief mention that they use the line in Mel Brooks movies? here is a refereance http://www.aeroforceone.com/index.cfm/pk/view/cd/NAA/cdid/312697/pid/302766 [[Special:Contributions/24.45.87.159|24.45.87.159]] ([[User talk:24.45.87.159|talk]]) 21:52, 7 August 2010 (UTC)
*by the way i am actually [[User:JDDJS]] I just don't want to log in the computer i'm using. [[Special:Contributions/24.45.87.159|24.45.87.159]] ([[User talk:24.45.87.159|talk]]) 21:59, 7 August 2010 (UTC)

Congratulations, your addition was referenced in S22E22 of The Simpsons, LOL. [[Special:Contributions/68.231.146.198|68.231.146.198]] ([[User talk:68.231.146.198|talk]]) 02:52, 25 May 2011 (UTC)

I was wondering that, too.

Your link was helpful. Here's the quote from it:
     &quot;But even diehard fans will probably learn something new in this oft-told tale, including the touching way in which Perry brings his tightknit family on the road and homeschools his children and the revelation that &quot;Walk This Way' was inspired by Marty Feldman's famous line as the hunchback in &quot;Young Frankenstein.'&quot;

Young Frankenstein came out in 1974, and this song came out in 1975.

Plus, here's this from the &quot;Young Frankenstein&quot; Wikipedia article:
     &quot;Cultural legacyWhen the film was in theaters, the band Aerosmith was working on its third studio album, Toys in the Attic. The members of the band had written the music for a song but couldn't come up with any lyrics to go with it. After a while, they decided to take a break and see a late night showing of Young Frankenstein, where the &quot;Walk This Way&quot; gag provided the basis (or phrase) for the Aerosmith hit &quot;Walk This Way&quot;.[12]&quot;

However, the Wikipedia article on &quot;Frankenstein&quot; doesn't mention the movie, &quot;Young Frankenstein&quot;.

So here's what we have. Five articles:
     1) the &quot;Aerosmith&quot; article
     2) the &quot;Walk this Way&quot; article
     3) the &quot;Frankenstein (disambiguation)&quot; article
     4) the &quot;Young Frankenstein&quot; article
     5) the &quot;Lynyrd Skynyrd&quot; article

1) the &quot;Aerosmith&quot; article
The &quot;Aerosmith&quot; article has this, in the section &quot;...1971-1975&quot;:
       &quot;Walk This Way&quot;, re-released in 1976, reached the Top 10 in early 1977.[7]

The &quot;Aerosmith&quot; article has this, in the singles hits list (listed chronologically):
     &quot;1977: &quot;Walk This Way&quot;, No. 10&quot;

In both of these, the phrase, &quot;Walk This Way&quot;, is a link to the &quot;Walk This Way&quot; article.

'''So to me it looks as if the &quot;Aerosmith&quot; article should be edited to include the &quot;Walk This Way&quot; anecdote that you mention. It should be put in the section &quot;...1971-1975&quot;, so that people can see that one of the things that might have made the Aerosmith album, &quot;Toys in the Attic&quot; a hit album could have been that the song, &quot;Walk This Way&quot;, inspired by the recent and popular movie, &quot;Young Frankenstein&quot;, was on it.'''


2) the &quot;Walk This Way&quot; article
The &quot;Walk This Way&quot; article has this:
     &quot;Legacy&quot;Walk This Way&quot; was one of two hit singles by the band to hit the Top 10 of the Billboard Hot 100 in the 1970s, the other one being a re-release of &quot;Dream On&quot;. &quot;Walk This Way&quot;, though, helped &quot;Toys in the Attic&quot; to be the bestselling Aerosmith album, and one of the most critically acclaimed. Aerosmith's version of &quot;Walk This Way&quot; often competes with &quot;Sweet Emotion&quot; and &quot;Dream On&quot; for the title of Aerosmith's signature song, being one of the band's most important, influential, and recognizable songs. The band rarely omits it from their concert setlist, still performing their classic version of the song to this day. The song has also long been a staple of rock radio, garnering regular airplay on mainstream rock, classic rock, and album-oriented rock radio stations. In 2009, it was named the 8th greatest hard rock song of all time by VH1.[5]&quot;

'''So to me it looks as if the &quot;Walk This Way&quot; article should be edited to include the &quot;Walk This Way&quot; anecdote that you mention. It could be put in earlier in the article, under the heading,&quot;Song Information&quot;, but I think it would be better to put it in here, under &quot;Legacy&quot;, as a second paragraph, starting with &quot;The song was inspired by...&quot;'''

3) the &quot;Frankenstein (disambiguation)&quot; article
The &quot;Frankenstein (disambiguation)&quot; article has no mention of the movie, &quot;Young Frankenstein&quot;, although other &quot;Frankenstein&quot; movies are mentioned.

'''So to me it looks as if the &quot;Frankenstein (disambiguation)&quot; article should be edited to include a reference to the movie, &quot;Young Frankenstein&quot;. But I don't think it needs to have a &quot;Walk This Way&quot; reference, because the &quot;Young Frankenstein&quot; article will have that.'''


4) the &quot;Young Frankenstein&quot; article
The &quot;Young Frankenstein&quot; article, as I mentioned above, has this. This is what it says:
&quot;Cultural legacyWhen the film was in theaters, the band Aerosmith was working on its third studio album, Toys in the Attic. The members of the band had written the music for a song but couldn't come up with any lyrics to go with it. After a while, they decided to take a break and see a late night showing of Young Frankenstein, where the &quot;Walk This Way&quot; gag provided the basis (or phrase) for the Aerosmith hit &quot;Walk This Way&quot;.[12]&quot; (I repeat it just so we can see it more clearly.) This seems fine to me. Here's what reference 12 is: &quot;^ &quot;Walk their way | Aerosmith News&quot;. AeroForceOne. http://www.aeroforceone.com/index.cfm/pk/view/cd/NAA/cdid/312697/pid/302766. Retrieved 2011-01-20.&quot;

'''So I don't think the &quot;Young Frankenstein&quot; article needs to be edited further, unless a further supporting reference, yours, might be included, just for reader interest.'''


5) the &quot;Lynyrd Skynyrd&quot; article
The &quot;Lynyrd Skynyrd&quot; article has the following, under the heading, &quot;Literature&quot;:

Davis, Stephen (1997). Walk This Way: The Autobiography of Aerosmith. HarperCollins. p. 304. ISBN 0-380-97594-7. http://books.google.com/?id=k3xeHAAACAAJ&amp;dq=Walk+This+Way:+The+Autobiography+of+Aerosmith. Retrieved October 18, 2008.


There is a link, but only to the book. But I searched separately, and found the &quot;Walk This Way&quot; article. Then it was super to see this topic, right here on the talk page!!!

'''I just wanted to know which came first, and was there a connection, between the movie and the song.'''

This talk page explained that, but it would be nice to see it in the article(s).

'''But I don't think the &quot;Lynyrd Skynyrd&quot; article needs to be edited with regard to this.'''


I came to the &quot;Lynyrd Skynyrd&quot; article from a newspaper article on the Juggernaut Jug Band, which did a cover of &quot;the Lynyrd Skynyrd classic, 'Gimme Three Steps'&quot;.

'''But I don't think that the Juggernaut Jug Band needs to have its own article, or be referenced in the &quot;Lynyrd Skynyrd&quot; article.'''


'''Thanks very much for having put this topic in the talk pages, and I would say, be bold! edit this article, and any others that you think are appropriate, with your reference and also the one from the &quot;Young Frankenstein&quot; article.'''

[[User:Entwhiz|Entwhiz]] ([[User talk:Entwhiz|talk]]) 03:32, 29 November 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>a3mdqs4mjmnv8rxvxzsbx45qebci1ub</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
