<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Ashura</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1460445</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746129947</id>
      <parentid>745992684</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-25T12:23:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Emir of Wikipedia</username>
        <id>28856560</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Concerns raised by copyeditor */ new section</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="70867">{{ITN talk|2 March|2004}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2005-02-19|oldid1=16335612|date2=2006-02-09|oldid2=38965294|date3=2007-01-29|oldid3=103984185|date4=2008-01-19|oldid4=184915646|date5=2009-01-07|oldid5=262524144|date6=2009-12-27|oldid6=334397020|date7=2010-12-16|oldid7=402665823|date8=2011-12-05|oldid8=464204261|date9=2014-11-04|oldid9=632445751|date10=2015-10-24|oldid10=686943375|date11=2016-10-12|oldid11=743976364}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Islam|class=c|importance=Top|Shi'a-Islam=yes}}
{{WikiProject Holidays|class=c|importance=Mid}} 
{{WikiProject_Iran|class=c|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject_Iraq|class=c|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=c|importance=Top}}
{{GOCE|user=Corinne|date=24 October 2016}}}}
{{Copied
|from       = Day of Ashura#Legacy
|from_oldid = 733354556
|to         = Battle of Karbala#Legacy
|to_diff    = https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Day_of_Ashura&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=733679994&amp;oldid=733354556
|to_oldid   = 733522184
|date       = 08 August 2015
|small      =
}}

==SAW==
What means that &quot;SAW&quot; behind some names? Why is it placed there? [[User:81.91.217.19|81.91.217.19]] 18:22, 29 January 2007 (UTC)

I think what you mean is like Muhammad SAW. It is not behind some names, but only behind the prophet Muhammad SAW's name which means SallAllahu Alaihi Wasallam or it can be translated to 'Peace upon him'.

:Well, I think (S.A.W.)s shold be removed from the article, since this is an encyclopedia and objectivity is needed. Otherwise we would need to change all &quot;Jesus&quot; to &quot;our father and savior Jesus Christ&quot;. That's not my idea. check [[muhammad]] page and you don't see any SAWs there. Regards. [[User:Ombudsee|Ombudsee]] 12:12, 30 January 2007 (UTC)

There are hadith which mention the importance of uttering glad tidings upon the prophet (SAW) upon hearing his name. What harm does adding (SAW) do? Why does is affect objectivity? The words Peace upon him, don't imply any disputed status, like &quot;father&quot; or &quot;saviour&quot;. [[User:Yusufk|Yusufk]] 20:20, 30 January 2007 (UTC)

Removing the SAW from behind Prophet Muhammad's SAW name is like removing the capitalization of God when speaking of articles on Christianity or Judaism. It is not biased to have respect for the traditions of a group of people. It is biased to disrespect those traditions. [[User:Dnkrumah|Dnkrumah]] 11:00, 4 February 2007 (UTC)

No honorifics.[[Special:Contributions/207.87.238.194|207.87.238.194]] ([[User talk:207.87.238.194|talk]]) 18:00, 6 November 2014 (UTC)

== Jewish Residents of Medina ==

::It was also a fast day for the Jews of Medina, in remembrance of their salvation from the Pharaoh of Egypt.

But the Jewish calendar is lunar/solar, which means it goes out-of-phase with the Muslim calendar. From this technicality: how would Jews be able to observe anything based on the Muslim calendar? (Jews cannot observe anything based on the Gregorian calendar). [[User:Elpincha|elpincha]] 21:50, 2 Feb 2005 (UTC)

The hadith mentions that the Prophet(sws) saw that the Jews fasted on the 9th of Muhharam and then he asked when it was. There could be several reasons for this and one of them could be that the Jews of that area followed the local calender or that the fast was set to the Muslim calender for the ease of the Muslims.

Either way it is a simple fact that the fast was for all Muslims and was set on the 9th according to the hadith. So it should included in the article because a critique of calender differences is for another site surely? --[[User:Cjuk|Cjuk]] 16:14, 19 Feb 2005 (UTC)

In answer to the above question, according to the wikipedia article,the [[islamic calendar]] was changed from lunar/solar, to strictly lunar in the last years of Muhammed's life, which would mean that the dates of the muslim calendar and the hebrew calendar originally were the same and went out of phase only later.

I still don't understand why the Jews were fasting at this time. looking at the projected dates of coming Ashurah's, they seem to fall in winter. unless you take on a personal fast, there is no Jewish fast day in the winter [[User:Akerensky99|Akerensky99]] 17:01, 9 February 2006 (UTC)

I did some research on the web and found that the Jewish &quot;[[Fast of the Firstborn]]&quot; is on Nissan 14. Ashura day falls on April 7, 632 in the Islamic year 11 and Nissan 8, 4392. I Think we are very close here. [[User:Habbak|Habbak]] 22:43, 29 January 2007 (UTC)

:Gosh, people! The Hebrew calendar '''''was''''' originally a purely lunar calendar. And instead of trying to find whether they, maybe, at one time co-incided, how about thinking whether when they were both lunar calendars, the months were the same.
:&amp;mdash; [[User:iFaqeer|iFaqeer]] ([[User talk:iFaqeer|talk to]] or [[Special:EmailUser/IFaqeer|email]] me) 13:07, 3 December 2012 (UTC)

== Sunni/Shi'a observance ==

There is a major difference in the way this day is observed between Sunni and Shi'a Muslims. I think something like separate sections be used to clarify this. --[[User:Yodakii|Yodakii]] 05:38, 4 September 2005 (UTC)

I agree with this point and think that the article as it stands is highly biased toward the Shi'a point of view. There is too much emphasis on the Martyrdom of Hussayn ibn Ali. Yes, it should be mentioned as important, but it is by no means THE most important event that occurred on the 10th of Muharram. It is for this reason that I think the POV tag remain and I propose that the contents be rearranged and split into separate Shi'a and Sunni sections. [[User:Yusufk|Yusufk]] 20:01, 30 January 2007 (UTC)

This article[http://islam.about.com/b/a/257572.htm] would be a good starting point:
&quot;The Day of 'Ashura
This coming week marks the Muslim observance of the &quot;Day of 'Ashura.&quot; The word 'ashura literally means &quot;10th,&quot; as it falls on the 10th day of Muharram, this first month of the Islamic year. 'Ashura is an ancient observance that is now recognized for different reasons and in different ways among Sunni and Shi'a Muslims.

Among Sunni Muslims, the month of Muharram and the Day of 'Ashura itself, is a simple remembrance of the Prophet Moses and his liberation from the Pharoah. It is strongly recommended, but not required, to spend two days fasting on and around the Day of 'Ashura. Among Shi'a Muslims, however, the days leading up to 'Ashura, and the remembrance of the day itself, are very mournful and grief-filled. The days are filled with passion plays, assemblies, and public displays of grief over the martyrdom of Husayn in 680 C.E.

During Muharram and 'Ashura, the rift between Shi'a and Sunni Muslims is naturally highlighted by the differences in their beliefs and practices. Particularly in modern Iraq, where sectarian violence is continually escalating, tensions may run very high during this time.&quot;

[[User:Yusufk|Yusufk]] 20:57, 30 January 2007 (UTC)

I agree the differences are highlighted sufficiently in the text. [[User:Dnkrumah|Dnkrumah]] 11:14, 4 February 2007 (UTC)

== Zoroastrian influence ==
In Iran, in Tunisia (and maybe in other islamic countries), Āshūrāh is somtimes celebrated with a ritual that involves jumping over a fire (and trying not to get one's self burned). This along with the fact that Āshūrāh is more important for Shia then for Sunni, and Shia being heavly influenced by Persian culture, suggests some Zoroastrian influence (Zoroastrians considered fire a symbol of God), maybe even Zoroastrian origin.

You are talking about Iranian newyear, not Ashurah. --[[User:Striver|Striver]] 23:44, 8 February 2006 (UTC)

::Jumping over fire in Iran take place in the evening of the last Tuesday of [[Iranian]] calendar year. They call it '''Wednesday Ceremony''' cince it is the night before the last Wednesday. The last Wednesday of the Iranian calendar year occures on the ''second half of March''. But [[Ashura]] happened on ''October''. Therefore no influence from Zoroastrians to Ashura could be recognized.
::[[User:Farhoudk|Farhoudk]] 06:58, 23 January 2007 (UTC)

(--24 Kb of unsigned, anonymous material put here by 
[[Special:Contributions/24.148.188.235|24.148.188.235]] ([[User talk:24.148.188.235|talk]]) 
between 22 August and 6 September 2008 has been deleted, because [[WP:SOAP|WP is not a soapbox]]. [[User:Moonraker12|Moonraker12]] ([[User talk:Moonraker12|talk]]) 12:19, 9 September 2008 (UTC)--)

[In Sunni Islam] Ashura is significant as the day that Allah (God) saved Moses (peace be upon him) and the Israelites by parting the Red Sea and drowning Pharaoh. When the Prophet Muhammad (peace be upon him)* migrated to Medina, the Jews told him that Moses (peace be upon him) fasted in gratitude on Ashura, and Jewish practice was to fast Ashura as well.

Upon learning this, the Prophet (peace be upon him) replied, “We have more right to Moses than you,” and he commanded Muslims to fast Ashura. Later, when fasting the entire month of Ramadan became obligatory, the Ashura fast was declared optional, and Muslims were instructed to differentiate their fast from the Jews by fasting the 9th or 11th of Muharram along with the 10th.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Lukman1416|Lukman1416]] ([[User talk:Lukman1416|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Lukman1416|contribs]]) 23:57, 20 December 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Āshūrāh rather than Aashurah ==

The word 'Āshūrāh means &quot;tenth&quot; in Arabic. Its first letter is a sound that is projected from the throat. It is generally tranlsiterated into English as an apostrophe ('). The 2nd letter is similar to &quot;a&quot; in &quot;far&quot;. This is a long &quot;a&quot;, usually transliterated as (ā). For example, Islām, or  Qur-ān, or Ramadhān.

Therefore, in accordance with general and standard transliteration, and with Wiki standards, the word should be represented as 'Āshūrāh rather than Aashurah. Or to make it neater, yet still in accordance with Wiki standards, Āshūrāh. [[User:Adamcaliph|Adamcaliph]] 16:15, 03 October 2005 UTC

Ancient Iraq and Iran were ruled by the Assyrians (or Ashuryans), known as Ashuras (hence Ashurbanipal,etc.), who were well known for their cruelty. Could Āshura (derived from ashura in the Indo-Iranian languages) be a lingering memory of that period? Does anyone have any ideas?

:I think the two words just happen to sound similar. Besides, the two words start with different sounds. Acc. to the transcription on this page, the word &quot;Ashura&quot; starts with a 'ein and a long a; according to the Arabic page on Assyria (linked to from the English page), the Arabic word for Assyria is 'Ashuria' and starts with an alif and a short a.--[[User:70.107.173.227|70.107.173.227]] 19:25, 19 January 2007 (UTC)

== Photos ==
These photos are ridiculous.  Everyone coming to the article expects to see the flagellation and blood, so why ignore it in the visual depictions of Ashurah?
:possibly because we don't have any such photos under a free license. if you can make it to beirut or karbala, erm, within the next few hours, maybe we will.  &amp;#8212;[[User:Mirv|Charles P._]]&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Mirv|(Mirv)]]&lt;/small&gt; 05:22, 9 February 2006 (UTC)

::a trip to karbala isn't necessary.  the pakistanis do it in new york.

::: The article does not mention the slicing of the head with knives. Why not? --[[User:Jamiem|Jamiem]]

:well, if anyone can get a photograph of that, that would be great. all i saw [[Montreal|here]] was symbolic breast-beating that wouldn't look out of place during the agnus dei of a catholic mass. &amp;#8212;[[User:Mirv|Charles P._]]&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Mirv|(Mirv)]]&lt;/small&gt; 16:03, 9 February 2006 (UTC)

:Check out the British Daily Mail: http://www.dailymail.co.uk/pages/galleries/galleries.html?in_page_id=711&amp;in_gallery_type_id=3

:The photos are there and they are disgusting.  How can this article not mention this?  I am amazed by this omission.   [[User:RussianBoy|RussianBoy]] 19:35, 14 February 2006 (UTC)

:Here are some photos from Lebanon that can be used in the article: [http://www.flickr.com/photos/18705609@N00/sets/649045/]. They are under a Creative Commons license. [[User:Jungli|Jungli]] 20:42, 14 February 2006 (UTC)

&quot;RESPECT WHAT ALLAH HAS HONORED, FOR VERILY TO HONOR THINGS DUE TO VIRTUE WHICH ALLAH HAS ACCORDED THEM IS AMONG THE TRAITS OF THE INTELLIGENT.&quot;

Why those photos here???

To attribute the significance of Aashurah to Sayyiduna Hussain (RA)'s martyrdom is totally baseless because the sanctity of Aashurah is proven, beyond doubt, from the time of Rasulullah (SAW), whilst Sayyiduna Hussain (RA) was martyred fifty years after the holy prophet Mohammed (SAW) left this earthly abode. The fact that the martyrdom of Sayyiduna Hussain (RA) occurred on the Day of Aashurah has absolutely no bearing on the significance of this day nor is the sanctity of this day derived from this event. [[User:Jamsa|Jamsa]] 12:45, 25 January 2007 (UTC)

If you are worried about blood then it is also prudent to stress that the vast majority of Shi'a Clergy also disapprove of the way some take things to an extreme during these celebrations. [[User:Dnkrumah|Dnkrumah]]

== Shi'a not Muslims ==

I find it personally offending as a Muslim ( sunni ) that this article portrays ashura as a Muslim &quot; holiday &quot; as if it were so for the entire Muslem community . Ashura is a day of significance to Muslems , yes , it is the day prophet Moses was saved and Muslems thank God for saving their dear prophet by fasting that certain day as prophet Muhammad urged . I'm afraid the average reader would not be able to make difference between the way Shi'as observe this day and the way sunnis do . Note that the grotesque actions of the Shi'a is extremely condemned by the vass majority  of sunnis( if not unanimously ). It would be much clearer if the article was seperated into two , or at least the sunni opinion of Shi'a practices is made more obvious . &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Hhnnrr|Hhnnrr]] ([[User talk:Hhnnrr|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Hhnnrr|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

:You make a good point. I have put a POV tag on it, and hopefully someone (perhaps yourself) can get around to making it more clear cut. If not, I'll try to do so soon. [[User:Pepsidrinka|Pepsidrinka]] 15:34, 22 February 2006 (UTC)

:The article in no way portrays Ashoura as a day commemorated equally by Sunnis and Shi'a!  The introduction explicitly enumerates the several events said to have occurred on Ashoura on which the large majority of Muslims agree (I have removed some minor subjective content from the introduction).  The article then goes on to separate Shi'a commemoration from Sunni commemoration by separate headings.  It is quite clear from the content that Sunnis and Shi'a have very different views regarding the significance of Ashoura (&quot;The day carries considerably less significance for Sunnis than it does for Shi'as.&quot;).  Your concerns for the &quot;average reader&quot; are nonsense, though your ridiculous objections to the article do not surprise me in light of your bold assertion above that &quot;Shi'a are not Muslims.&quot;  Nice try. &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:207.172.222.90|207.172.222.90]] ([[User talk:207.172.222.90|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/207.172.222.90|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

:Can we please remove the POV tag? I see no reason for it since the separate Sunni and Shia commemorations are explicitly stated. It is obvious and logical however that this article will dwell more on the Shia aspects because Ashura is so much more significant to them. [[User:Jungli|Jungli]] 09:52, 25 February 2006 (UTC)

:It's time to remove the POV tag.  There is no religious bias in this article - no support for one sect or the other.  No opinions are presented as fact.  As Jungli points out, there will obviously be more focus on the Shi'a commemoration in light of the holiday's special significance to them.  That someone finds the neutral description of a predominantly Shi'a holiday &quot;personally offending&quot; is no reason to keep this tag up.  It would, however, be religious bias to adopt Hhnnrr's Sunni viewpoint and strip this article down to a Sunni description of Ashurah.  [[User:68.239.0.68|68.239.0.68]] 15:58, 25 February 2006 (UTC)

:I know of Sunni people who beat their chests to mourn the death of Husayn ibn Ali.

There is definitely a reason to keep the POV tag. There are distinct differences in beliefs around Ashura and two distinct points of view regarding the significance of the day. However, the Shi'a point-of-view, seems to take center stage, with the majority of information centered around the Martyrdom of Hussayn ibn Ali. [[User:Yusufk|Yusufk]] 20:09, 30 January 2007 (UTC)

== why be rude ?! ==

Why is it that some wiki writers find it necessary to be rude in order to prove a point ? I may have been wrong ( even though I believe I was not ), yet still my comments could have been answered to a bit more politely ! . My title does not say Shi'a are NOT Muslims ( regardless of my belief ) it only expresses what I thought would be a possible misconception , especially that the first thing you see when you open the page is a picture of severely bleeding men ! ( I have an open proxy therefore i didnt add my comments to the past comments - I am blocked from editing )Thanks anyway ..[[User:Hhnnrr|Hhnnrr]] 13:08, 23 February 2006 (UTC)

:The photo of the sword ritual might be misplaced, but I am not so sure.  True, the vast majority of Muslims certaintly don't practice this ritual on Ashurah, and even prominent Shi'a clerics (say, Ayatollah Ali Al-Sistani) have condemned it.  Placing it at the top of the article may suggest that it is a more prominent or accepted practice than it really is.  But at the same time, the practice is perhaps the most distinctive feature of the yearly Ashurah commemoration, and I personally felt it was the most interesting.  That's why I uploaded the photo, though someone else has placed it prominently on top.  Any thoughts?  [[User:9591353082|9591353082]] 19:57, 23 February 2006 (UTC)

== page title ==

The current title of Ashurah is wrong. The correct way would be `Ashura'. Assuming the Arabic is correct, there is not a Ta' marbuta on the end, which means there is no reason that there should be an &quot;h&quot; on the end. Google hits for [http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;q=ashura&amp;btnG=Google+Search ashura] receive over one million, while [http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;q=ashurah&amp;btnG=Google+Search ashurah] receives 23 thousand (probably several being mirrors of this page). I'm changing the title and content of the article. [[User:Cunado19|&lt;font color=&quot;#d14c04&quot;&gt;'''Cuñado'''&lt;/font&gt;]] [http://www.bahai.us/ [[image:Bahaitemplatestar.png|20px]]] - [[User talk:Cunado19|&lt;font size=&quot;-3&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 16:32, 9 May 2006 (UTC)

== The Date of Ashura ==

On this page, the date of Ashura for 2007 is 28 Jan. Does this mean sunset of 28 Jan, or sunset of 27 Jan?--[[User:70.107.173.227|70.107.173.227]] 19:24, 19 January 2007 (UTC)
:Acc. to the newspaper, Ashura is today, 29 January, and not 28 January as it says in the article. This also agrees with the link given at Remembrance of Muharram for finding the 1st of Muharram. Acc. to that site, the 1 Muharram was 20 Jan, so 29 Jan, being nine days later, should be the 10th Muharram. Am I missing something?--[[User:Gheuf|Gheuf]] 22:18, 29 January 2007 (UTC)

== No True Scotsman ==

&quot;These violent acts could also have been works of Wahhabis or Salafis who often guise themselves as Sunni Muslims. True Sunnis are peace-loving and while they do not subscribe to Shiites Ashura practices, they acknowledge that such differing of views in non-theological matters exists and should be tolerated for the better good, especially since the Ashura rites is something that has been carried out for generations.&quot;

This section contains a logical fallacy of the type [[No_true_Scotsman]] and should really have some sources if it's to be taken seriously.  There are also some grammar issues. &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[Special:Contributions/129.7.240.226|129.7.240.226]] ([[User talk:129.7.240.226|talk]]) 13:02, 25 January 2007 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;

==Merging==
I found that [[Remembrance of Muharram]] can be merged in [[Day of Ashura#Shi'a commemoration]] because they're very similar.--[[User:Sa.vakilian|Sa.vakilian]] 04:24, 26 January 2007 (UTC)
:Yes but then you have the article basically big on Sunni perspectives, small on Shiite ones. That's not NPOV. I suggest keep this article. [[User:Bless sins|Bless sins]] 22:40, 26 January 2007 (UTC)
::We can add Shi'a POV. There's enough information about the history of commemoration of Ashura among Shi'as.--[[User:Sa.vakilian|Sa.vakilian]] 07:59, 27 January 2007 (UTC)
::I rearranged the article because I think it isn't a Shi'a-Sunni conflict. There are Sunnis who mourn for Husayn ibn Ali and even non-Muslims. Now what's your idea about merging--[[User:Sa.vakilian|Sa.vakilian]] 17:08, 27 January 2007 (UTC)

Please write your idea about merging [[Remembrance of Muharram]] into [[Day of Ashura]].--[[User:Sa.vakilian|Sa.vakilian]] 18:05, 28 January 2007 (UTC)

I am not sure this article fully describes the entire Shi'a observance. This article concentrates on Ashura itself. The other article discusses the entire Shi'a observance of Muharram which last 10 days. That fact makes the articles somewhat different in scope and direction. To incorporate the complete Shi'a observance into an article entitled Day of Ashura, while it could probably be done well, it would be somewhat misleading as the entire observance is a series of activities conducted over the first 10 days of Muharram. I believe the articles should remain separate for that reason. [[User:Dnkrumah|Dnkrumah]] 11:38, 4 February 2007 (UTC)

==Popular customs==
In this part we explain popular customs not necessarily religious one. I mean there may be contradiction between what people do and Islam like hurting or cutting the body. So please write religious ideas in the relevant sections.--[[User:Sa.vakilian|Sa.vakilian]] 06:59, 29 January 2007 (UTC)

==flailing==

image 6 of http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/in_pictures/6309869.stm shows flailing. Can you please add a section that fully explains the flailing rites? I'd love to learn about it.--[[User:Sonjaaa|Sonjaaa]] 15:04, 29 January 2007 (UTC)

:It's called ''tatbir'' ([[ar:تطبير|تطبير]]). It's always controversial, and a lot (or most) clerics say it's bad, but some people just don't care. It's an old tradition. &lt;font face=&quot;verdana&quot; size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;—[[User:Mohammed Khalil|&lt;font color=red&gt;MK&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Mohammed Khalil|(talk)]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 22:15, 29 January 2007 (UTC)

== spelling ==

The name Husayn is spelled a number of different ways throughout the article. I understand that this is common in transliteration, but most languages now have official transliterations (pinyin, romaji, etc). Even if not, one should be picked and stuck with it throughout.

Also, he is referred to as al-Husayn in some places - specifically, after mention of his tomb. This is confusing - I'm not sure if it's a typo or if I just don't understand these cultural naming schemes. Again, some note should be made and something consistent should be used throughout, I think. &lt;b&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;[[User:Cat Parade|cat]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;[[User:Cat Parade|Parade]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt; 02:26, 30 January 2007 (UTC)
----

Arabic transliteration is unfortunately very variable in current practice, partly due to major pronunciation differences in different dialects. The ordinary English spelling of this name is &quot;Hussein&quot; -- perhaps this is unpopular with Shias due to Saddam.

Any noun in Arabic is preceded by &quot;al&quot; (or an assimilated form like &quot;as&quot; before &quot;s&quot;) which means &quot;the&quot; -- and whether to include this in translation also varies greatly.

== Beating with Swords ==

The article doesn't mention the self-beating with swords that we see in news photos.

Perhaps this is limited to certain denominations? It should be described. &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[Special:Contributions/75.6.251.63|75.6.251.63]] ([[User talk:75.6.251.63|talk]]) 17:03, 30 January 2007 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;
:You can see popular customs. There is a link which shows it.--[[User:Sa.vakilian|Sa.vakilian]] 03:19, 31 January 2007 (UTC)

== Transliteration in intro - are apostrophes quote marks or glottal stops? ==

The transliteration in the intro has:

‘Āshūrā’

With apostrophe marks before and after.

I can't tell if this is supposed to be transliteration of Arabic glottal stops -- or quotes.

If they are quotes they should definitely be removed -- not needed and obviously confusing. &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[Special:Contributions/75.6.251.63|75.6.251.63]] ([[User talk:75.6.251.63|talk]]) 17:23, 30 January 2007 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;

== External Links ==
I removed a link to the web site &quot;when-is.com.&quot; This is a junk site which has the dates for each year on a ''separate page''. Obviously it's a spam site, and moreover it has less, not more information than the article proper. Other Wikipedia articles on Islam link to it, i suggest they all be removed. [[User:KriZe|KriZe]] 15:43, 31 January 2007 (UTC)


==Rearrangement:POV or NPOV==
Although commemoration of [[Imam Hussayn]] has great position in the Shiism but its restriction to Shia is a mistake. Sunnis glorify him too.[http://www.islamonline.net/English/ArtCulture/2004/03/article06.shtml]
As I know, there isn't any Shi'a in Indonesia, Thus some Sunnis commemorate Huusains martyrdom like [[Tabuik]]. Also Armenians who are not Muslim commemorate Ashura in Iran.  I prefer to rearrange this article:
:1- Etymology of Ashura
:2- Hussayn's Martyrdom (or Karbala) commemoration
::2-1-History
::2-2-Customs
:3- commemoration Other religious events 
:4- Violence during Ashura
:5- Ashura in the Gregorian calendar
--[[User:Sa.vakilian|Sa.vakilian]] 08:09, 27 January 2007 (UTC)


I rearranged this article few days ago after I had proposed it here.
Contents
    * 1 Etymology of Ashura
    * 2 Commemoration of the martyrdom of Husayn ibn Ali
          o 2.1 History
                + 2.1.1 Significance of Ashura for Shi'a
          o 2.2 Popular customs
          o 2.3 Sunni Viewpoint of Martyrdom of Hussayn ibn Ali
          o 2.4 Commemoration of Husayn ibn Ali by non-Muslims
          o 2.5 Socio-political aspects
    * 3 Other Islamic commemorations
    * 4 Violence during Ashura
    * 5 Ashura in the Gregorian calendar

Now if anybody wants to rearrange it again, please discuss here first.--[[User:Sa.vakilian|Sa.vakilian]] 13:23, 30 January 2007 (UTC)


This arrangement does not make sense and is biased to the Shi'a point of view.
The &quot;Commemoration of the martyrdom of Husayn ibn Ali&quot; has nothing to do with the day of Ashura from the Sunni point of view nor do the customs mentioned.
Therefore I would suggest that the article be split into a separate Shi'a and Sunni point of view.

Contents
    * 1 Etymology of Ashura
    * 2 Significance of Ashura for Shi'a
          o 2.1 Commemoration of the martyrdom of Husayn ibn Ali
          o 2.2 History
          o 2.3 Shi'a customs
          o 2.4 Commemoration of Husayn ibn Ali by non-Muslims
    * 3 Significance of Ashura for Sunni
          o 3.1 Sunni viewpoint of Martyrdom of Hussayn ibn Ali
    * 4 Socio-political aspects
    * 5 Other Islamic commemorations
    * 6 Violence during Ashura
    * 7 Ashura in the Gregorian calendar

--[[User:Yusufk|Yusufk]] 19:33, 30 January 2007 (UTC)

:Regarding the Ashura article, from my (Sunni perspective) the page does not give a balanced point of view. The day is significant to all Muslims, Sunni and Shi'a, but if someone had to read the article, they would not understand that there are two points of view. For instance, statements like &quot;Commemoration of Ashura is not a festival, but rather a sad event for both Shi'as and Sunni Muslims&quot; are misleading. To me and other Sunni's I know, the day was proclaimed to be a holy day by our prophet SAW because of all the positive things that happened on the day. Sunni's are encouraged to spend on their families (gifts etc.). Yes, a sad event did occur on the day, but it is the general opinion of Sunni's I know that this does not detract from the positive events that occurred on the day. Furthermore, the &quot;popular customs&quot; section does not apply to Sunni's but the article gives an impression that it does.
:A fair approach to both Sunni and Shi'a would be to separate the article into separate Shi'a and Sunni sections.[[User:Yusufk|Yusufk]] 12:55, 31 January 2007 (UTC)
::Are you sure that there isn't any differnce among Sunni's sects e.g. Shafei and Hanafi or Arab Sunnis and Pakistani ones or Sunnis who are Zaheri(Ahl Hadith) and Bateni(Sufis)--[[User:Sa.vakilian|Sa.vakilian]] 18:37, 31 January 2007 (UTC)
:::I will just give one comment about Ashura. Ashura is important to others (who are not Shia) because of one sole reason and that is celebration of liberation of Israelites from Egypt. Prophet Moses (as) kept fast on this day and jews kept in their tradition atleast till the time of the prophet Muhammad. This is the fundamental importance to the large majority Muslim population. And this aspect is not highlighted in the article. IMHO [[User:truthspreader|&lt;b&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#0D9D2D&quot;&gt;TruthSpreader&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/b&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:truthspreader|&lt;font color=&quot;#0C9AAD&quot;&gt;reply&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 01:46, 1 February 2007 (UTC)
::OK. I accept. But please let me improve Yusufk arrangement:

Contents
    * 1 Etymology of Ashura
    * 2 Commemoration of the martyrdom of Husayn ibn Ali
          o 2.1 History
          o 2.2 Significance of Ashura for Shi'a
          o 2.3 Popular customs
          o 2.4 Commemoration of Husayn ibn Ali by non-Muslims
          o 2.5 Socio-political aspects
    * 3 Significance of Ashura for Sunni
          o 3.1 Sunni viewpoint of Martyrdom of Hussayn ibn Ali
    * 4 Violence during Ashura
    * 5 Ashura in the Gregorian calendar

::First, I agree with writing &quot;Significance of Ashura for Sunni&quot; and even put it before Shi'a one but I insist on putting &quot;Commemoration of the martyrdom of Husayn ibn Ali&quot;  as the main title and putting &quot;Significance of Ashura for Shi'a&quot; under it. In this way we can put &quot;Commemoration of Husayn ibn Ali by non-Muslims&quot; and &quot;Popular customs&quot; under it without making misunderstanding.
::Second, we should write &quot;popular customs&quot; instead of &quot;Shi'a customs&quot; because it may be against  Shi'a Fiqh. 
::Third, We can put &quot;Socio-political aspects&quot; under &quot;Commemoration of the martyrdom of Husayn ibn Ali&quot;.
--[[User:Sa.vakilian|Sa.vakilian]] 02:51, 1 February 2007 (UTC)


::This is acceptable to me although it would make more sense to have &quot;Significance of Ashura for Shi'a&quot; on the same level as &quot;Significance of Ashura for Sunni&quot;, perhaps a compromise could be:
Contents
    * 1 Etymology of Ashura
    * 2 Commemoration of the martyrdom of Husayn ibn Ali
          o 2.1 History
          o 2.2 Popular customs
          o 2.3 Sunni viewpoint of Martyrdom of Hussayn ibn Ali
          o 2.4 Commemoration of Husayn ibn Ali by non-Muslims
          o 2.5 Socio-political aspects
    * 3 Significance of Ashura for Shi'a
    * 4 Significance of Ashura for Sunni
    * 5 Violence during Ashura
    * 6 Ashura in the Gregorian calendar
::The order in terms of Shi'a and Sunni does not matter to me, I just think that it will be valuable to muslims and non-muslims if this article demonstrates probably the most significant difference in opinion of shi'a and sunni muslims.
[[User:Yusufk|Yusufk]] 09:34, 1 February 2007 (UTC)
:::I agree with this and just one issue has remained. If we separate &quot;Significance of Ashura for Shi'a&quot; from &quot;Commemoration of the martyrdom of Husayn ibn Ali&quot;, then what can we write under &quot;Significance of Ashura for Shi'a&quot;?--[[User:Sa.vakilian|Sa.vakilian]] 16:27, 1 February 2007 (UTC)
:::It is my understanding that of most significance to Shi'a is the Commemoration of Martyrdom of Hussayn ibn Ali, which is why I suggested having it as a sub-topic of Significance of Ashura for Shi'a.
Perhaps if  we combine it like this:
Contents
    * 1 Etymology of Ashura
    * 2 Significance of Ashura for Shi'a and the Commemoration of the martyrdom of Husayn ibn Ali
          o 2.1 History
          o 2.2 Popular customs
          o 2.3 Sunni viewpoint of Martyrdom of Hussayn ibn Ali
          o 2.4 Commemoration of Husayn ibn Ali by non-Muslims
          o 2.5 Socio-political aspects
    * 3 Significance of Ashura for Sunni
    * 4 Violence during Ashura
    * 5 Ashura in the Gregorian calendar
[[User:Yusufk|Yusufk]] 09:54, 3 February 2007 (UTC)
:Do you know what's the problem? The problem is the importance of &quot;Commemoration of the martyrdom of Husayn ibn Ali&quot; by itself for many people who are not Shi'a. I mean you can say &quot;Significance of Ashura for Sunni&quot; and it doesn't make any problem, but when you say &quot;Significance of Ashura for Shi'a&quot; it makes some problems. First, some people who mourn for Imam Husayn aren't Muslim and some of them may Sunni. Second, it has become a popular custom which is originated from religion but it isn't restricted to it. For this reason I made a separate part for &quot;Commemoration of the martyrdom of Husayn ibn Ali&quot; a part for &quot;Other Islamic commemorations&quot;. &quot;Significance of Ashura for Shi'a and the Commemoration of the martyrdom of Husayn ibn Ali&quot; doesn't sound good.
:I don't want to write an article which based on Shi'a POV and I told to my Sunni friends to participate but they don't. On the other hand &quot;Significance of Ashura for Shi'a&quot; is one of the subtitles of &quot;Commemoration of the martyrdom of Husayn ibn Ali&quot;. I understand that this classification in unbalanced and sounds bad too. Therefor I tried not to put Sunni versus Shi'a. I hope that I could explain my POV.--[[User:Sa.vakilian|Sa.vakilian]] 10:46, 4 February 2007 (UTC)
::It may not be your intention to write a biased article, but as the article stands right now, it is totally biased to the Shi'a POV. To a neutral person, this article would give the impression that the day of Ashura is centered around the martydon of Husayn. The fact is that this is not true for Sunni's. This article is titled, &quot;Day of Ashura&quot; and not &quot;Commemoration of the martyrdom of Husayn ibn Ali&quot; and should reflect that. Whether Shia's like it or not, we (Sunni's) do not regard Husayn ibn Ali with the same importance as that of Shia's and the Sunni opinion regard the events that the Prophet highlighted as important to be of more importance on the day. Your friends may be trying to avoid conflict or argument, but thats just the way it is and this, being an encyclopedia should reflect the facts. 
[[User:Yusufk|Yusufk]] 14:14, 5 February 2007 (UTC)
:It is not acceptable to have Shi'a or Sunni specific POV placed in sections that can't be distinguished as such. The article now has distinct sections for the Sunni POV and the Commemoration of the martyrdom of Husayn ibn Ali. I will attempt to fill in more details on the Sunni POV and encourage other Sunni's to do the same. I also urge everyone to refrain from putting biased opinions in the introduction of the article and suggest that Shia's and Sunni's contribute to sections relevant to their beliefs and not attempt to second-guess the beliefs of others.
[[User:Yusufk|Yusufk]] 14:56, 5 February 2007 (UTC)

::I agree with this arrangement:
    * 1 Etymology of Ashura
    * 2 Significance of Ashura for Sunni
    * 3 Commemoration of the martyrdom of Husayn ibn Ali
          o 3.1 History
                + 3.1.1 Significance of Ashura for Shi'a
          o 3.2 Popular customs
          o 3.3 Sunni Viewpoint of Martyrdom of Hussayn ibn Ali
          o 3.4 Commemoration of Husayn ibn Ali by non-Muslims
          o 3.5 Socio-political aspects
    * 4 Violence during Ashura
    * 5 Ashura in the Gregorian calendar
  
But I prefer this one more:
    * 1 Etymology of Ashura
    * 2 Significance of Ashura for Sunni
    * 3 Commemoration of the martyrdom of Husayn ibn Ali
          o 3.1 History
          o 3.2 Significance of Ashura for Shi'a
          o 3.3 Popular customs
          o 3.4 Sunni Viewpoint of Martyrdom of Hussayn ibn Ali
          o 3.5 Commemoration of Husayn ibn Ali by non-Muslims
          o 3.6 Socio-political aspects
    * 4 Violence during Ashura
    * 5 Ashura in the Gregorian calendar
 --[[User:Sa.vakilian|Sa.vakilian]] 19:18, 5 February 2007 (UTC)

:That looks fine to me also, I'll make the change. [[User:Yusufk|Yusufk]] 21:06, 5 February 2007 (UTC)

===Tolerance===

If only all Muslims, in fact all believers in general respected each others beliefs in this way. Yes, there are differences of opinion, but we accept that each has a right to his own and accommodate each other. It's never a good idea to offer what you think is someone else's point of view, rather make it possible for them to explain it the way they see it. And when it comes to fights, know that very few will admit being the first wrong doer, so just accept that it should never happen again rather than argue whose fault it is. [[User:Yusufk|Yusufk]] 09:05, 5 March 2007 (UTC)

==Violence during Ashura==
I removed what you had added to this part[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Day_of_Ashura&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=115636732] because this is not relevant to this article. There are another articles to mention that issue. --&lt;font face=&quot;monospace&quot;&gt;[[User:Sa.vakilian|Sa.vakilian]]([[User talk:Sa.vakilian|t]]-[[Special:Contributions/Sa.vakilian|c]])&lt;/font&gt; 08:00, 24 April 2007 (UTC)

==Zeynab quotations and sermons==
1-
''[[Zaynab]] quoted as she passed the prostrate body of her brother, [[Husayn]]. &quot; O Muhammad! O Muhammad! May the angels of heaven bless you. Here is Husayn in the open, stained with blood and with limbs torn off. O Muhammad! Your daughters are prisoners, your progeny are killed, and the east wind blows dust over them.&quot; By God! She made every enemy and friend weep. The history of Al-Tabari, Volume XIX The Caliphate of Yazid, translated by I. K. A. Howard, p:164''

This quotation is available in Muslim histories of Shia and Sunni. You can find it in Al-Tabari as well as Ibn Athir's book. 

2- Then [[Zaynab]] made people of [[Kufa]] and [[Demasque]] weep.

Her sermons are too important not only from religious poin of view but also in Arabic literature. ''Ibn Abi Tahir'' has narrated her sermons in her famous work ''Eloquences of women''(Balaqat al-Nisa). [http://www.al-islam.org/ashura/33.htm#r21].:I dont have any real problem with #1, but #2, can you provide any source of authentic and historic and factual account or evidence to back up this statement that he supposedly &quot;made people of [[Kufa]] and [[Demasque]] weep&quot;, this statement seems to be [[Wikipedia: 

This would satisfy you about her role.[http://www.bookrags.com/Zaynab_bint_Ali]--&lt;font face=&quot;monospace&quot;&gt;[[User:Sa.vakilian|Seyyed]]([[User talk:Sa.vakilian|t]]-[[Special:Contributions/Sa.vakilian|c]])&lt;/font&gt; 10:52, 19 January 2008 (UTC)

Unencyclopedic|Unencyclopedic]], and should be removed. [[User:RebelzGang|RebelzGang]] ([[User talk:RebelzGang|talk]]) 02:10, 20 January 2008 (UTC)
::It's wriiten in encyclopedia of religion:&quot;The first assembly (majlis) of mourning for Ḥusayn is said to have been held by Zaynab in prison. In Damascus, too, she is reported to have delivered a poignant oration.&quot;[http://www.bookrags.com/research/zaynab-bint-al-eorl-14/sect5.html] --&lt;font face=&quot;monospace&quot;&gt;[[User:Sa.vakilian|Seyyed]]([[User talk:Sa.vakilian|t]]-[[Special:Contributions/Sa.vakilian|c]])&lt;/font&gt; 04:34, 29 February 2008 (UTC)

::@RebelzGang,
Do you really want to lay it that way? Then give me encyclopedic sources for the Hadith at the begining, o wait, you can't. Is that a reason to delete it? Some might argue yes, other however, as do I, find it important for these religious-details to be incorporated. Of course we can never be 100% sure what was said in Her original sermons, nor what details were lost during translation. But that also accounts for the Qu'ran doesn't it?
--[[Special:Contributions/83.80.236.182|83.80.236.182]] ([[User talk:83.80.236.182|talk]]) 14:30, 30 December 2008 (UTC)

== Photos from the Ashura Ritual ==

[http://www.welt.de/english-news/article2984926/Ashura-Ritual.html]

WTF is wrong with these people?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/4.246.200.25|4.246.200.25]] ([[User talk:4.246.200.25|talk]]) 04:39, 23 January 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
________________________________________

In regards to the photos posted about Ashura I must say that they are of poor quality and should be replaced immediately. I am referring to the Bahrain and malasyia photos, please replace with one from Iraq or Iran, these two countries are the only reason the religion is still around. Mashala  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.80.104.39|24.80.104.39]] ([[User talk:24.80.104.39|talk]]) 20:05, 18 June 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Shariah Law ==

Removed a paragraph:

The Shariah law however, shuns acts that resemble Jews and Christians. Thus it is reported in Mishkaat that Muhammad said, &quot;Fast on the day of Ashura and oppose the Jews regarding it. Thus fast on the day before it and on the day after.&quot; (Taken from The Significance of Muharram by Rafique Valli, lecturer at the Islamic University for Girls, Johannesburg)

Since this seems to be a very select bias, and not logically consistent. The Prophet fasted on the 10th, the Prophet defined Shariah and therefore could not have gone against it, thus fasting on the 10th is Shariah and can't possibly be against it by definition.

[[User:Wadkdc|dk4]] ([[User talk:Wadkdc|talk]]) 14:38, 18 December 2009 (UTC)


==Tabari worst source==


This quotation is available in Muslim histories of Shia and Sunni. You can find it in Al-Tabari as well as Ibn Athir's book.

Tabari is biased towards Shias and has even condmened them as kafirs and heretics. This source should not be used for it is not credible. I find the Sunni POV's on tis discussion page very offensive. I understand that Ashura has been somewhat a controversiaL topic but there is no need to belittle Shias who follow the Prophet's House devoutly and mourn the death of the Prophet's grandson one this day. The Prophet once said &quot;I am of Hussein and Hussein is of me.&quot; I have many Sunni friends and it is remarkable that most of them have a preconceived bias towards Shias because of the things they are taught about Shias in many Sunni Arab countries, especially the Wahhabis Salafis. They know very little about the ahlu beit (the Prophet, Ali, Fatima, Hasan , Hussein) and often criticize Shias (even though they're right) though for the wrong reasons. Hussein was fleeing to Iran when his 72 family members when he was martyred by the religiously bankrupt Yazid. 

This article should mention something about how there was a mass gathering in Iraq in 2003 after Saddaam was removed on the day of Ashura, Millions of Iranians and Iraqi gathered at Najaf and Karbala to commemorate Ashura. Sorry if this doesnt make much sense and thanks.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/70.79.154.36|70.79.154.36]] ([[User talk:70.79.154.36|talk]]) 07:22, 23 December 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Al-Tabaie is one of the authentic historians who narrates Battle of Karbala on the basis of Abu-Mikhnaf. Most of what he's narrated in this case is acceptable among Shia historians.--&lt;font face=&quot;monospace&quot;&gt;[[User:Sa.vakilian|Seyyed]]([[User talk:Sa.vakilian|t]]-[[Special:Contributions/Sa.vakilian|c]])&lt;/font&gt; 20:16, 25 December 2009 (UTC)

==Iranian/Iraqi Shia Ashura picture==

Great pictures and info! But can someone be so kind as to add a picture from an Iraqi or Iranian Ashura ceremony? With all due respect Iran and Iraq surely should have a picture on this wikipedia page given that...well I don't think theres a need to even say it...is there?

Thanks

[[Special:Contributions/24.80.104.208|24.80.104.208]] ([[User talk:24.80.104.208|talk]]) 09:18, 25 December 2009 (UTC)ditc

==Regarding protests of Dec 27 2009==
There is mention now in the article of Yesterday's protests in Iran. Are they significant enough and relevant enough to Ashura that they should be included? Moreover, they must be reworded to remove bias. It calls the last elections in Iran a &quot;fraud election&quot; rather than a &quot;contested&quot; one and it has an over all unprofessional air. Actually, this entire article needs serious cleaning up.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.59.153.34|24.59.153.34]] ([[User talk:24.59.153.34|talk]]) 19:54, 28 December 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Pilgrimage(s) to Karbala ==

My understanding is that for many (Shiite?) Muslims, Ashura is observed with a pilgrimage to Karbala, and that there can be another pilgrimage to Karbala forty days later at the end of the mourning period. Is there a convenient place for the reader to find a discussion of this? [[Special:Contributions/68.5.144.164|68.5.144.164]] ([[User talk:68.5.144.164|talk]]) 17:52, 1 February 2010 (UTC)

==Trouble adding references==

I don't know why the two links I added go straight to the picture instead of to footnotes at the bottom of the article that could then be clicked on.  They came out with double brackets around them on the preview, so I removed them.  When I saved and clicked on them, they took me straight to the quite shocking photos--especially the first one.  So I restored the double brackets, but the same thing happens.

I'm no big-time editor, but have added references numerous times in the past that worked properly.  Both links are to major, mainline news sources:  USA Today and Reuters.  [[User:Yopienso|Yopienso]] ([[User talk:Yopienso|talk]]) 00:16, 19 February 2010 (UTC)

==Slashing with blades==

An unnamed editor with no talk page has deleted pertinent information and photos from mainline, verifiable, NPOV sources I posted.  I do not want to revert his editing without a proper discussion, but do want to see this information restored.  [[User:Yopienso|Yopienso]] ([[User talk:Yopienso|talk]]) 02:52, 22 February 2010 (UTC)
: Well, the photos in your external links presumably depict this, but there is no mention of it in the Reuters article, nor in any of the photos' captions. However, [http://uk.reuters.com/article/idUKTRE50646520090107?sp=true this Reuters article] does describe it, while also mentioning that this practice is disputed among Shia'as (and note [[User:Dnkrumah]]'s comment earlier on this page). [http://www1.voanews.com/english/news/a-13-2009-01-06-voa21-68710867.html This VOA article] mentions it as well. -- [[User:Gyrofrog|Gyrofrog ]] [[User_talk:Gyrofrog|(talk)]] 16:00, 24 February 2010 (UTC)

== Main Story section ==

I have deleted the &quot;Main Story&quot; section.  It was [[WP:ATTRIB|unattributed]] and [[WP:NPOV|PoV]] (e.g. &quot;Al Hussein will remain as a revolution against all tyrants and oppressors&quot;) and some portions were (at least to me) incomprehensible (e.g. &quot;Imam Hussein by his realistic personality and death defeated the tyrant&quot;).  Most of the section was created in a single edit on 2009-12-28 ([http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Day_of_Ashura&amp;diff=334562951&amp;oldid=334507581 link]).  I personally don't think the section, as written, added any value to this article (no offense intended), but if others wish to restore it, they should carefully consider cleaning up the text, not to mention adding [[WP:RS|reliable sources]]. -- [[User:Gyrofrog|Gyrofrog ]] [[User_talk:Gyrofrog|(talk)]] 07:07, 24 February 2010 (UTC)

*Agreed.  Any comment on my question immediately above?  [[User:Yopienso|Yopienso]] ([[User talk:Yopienso|talk]]) 09:18, 24 February 2010 (UTC)

: Based on my previous reasons, I have reverted the restoration of the article section. -- [[User:Gyrofrog|Gyrofrog ]] [[User_talk:Gyrofrog|(talk)]] 22:07, 21 April 2010 (UTC)

:: I have again reverted the restoration of the &quot;Main Story&quot; section. I had previously warned the anonymous IP responsible but the edits in question occur about a month apart. -- [[User:Gyrofrog|Gyrofrog ]] [[User_talk:Gyrofrog|(talk)]] 19:44, 19 May 2010 (UTC)

== Edit request from Loveaustralia82, 16 December 2010 ==

{{tlx|edit semi-protected}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Day_of_Ashura

In this article the word (pilgrimage) is wrongly used.It is a religious term to do pilgrimage to MECCA city only.It is one of the 5 pillars of islam.Shia'a do piligrimage to MECCA but what they do visit to Karbala (Imam Husain)is so huge in numbers that it looks like pilgrimage, but in escence it is not performing HAG (OR PILGRIMAGE)which is the term used to visit MECCA ONLY and doing some rituals.Using the term pilgrimage to kerbala for shia'a put them in non muslims category which is a huge mistake.Shia'a have to perform pilgrimage to MECCA.By not correcting this word you are making enemity between shia'a and sunni muslims and should be addressed promptly.
Read about hai to mecca on this shia'a web site

www.bayynat.org

&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[User:Loveaustralia82|Loveaustralia82]] ([[User talk:Loveaustralia82|talk]]) 23:04, 16 December 2010 (UTC)

: Aren't the visits to these sites made in a religious context? Isn't that what a [[pilgrimage]] is? -- [[User:Gyrofrog|Gyrofrog ]] [[User_talk:Gyrofrog|(talk)]] 23:18, 16 December 2010 (UTC)

==mis attributed quote==

Commemoration of Ashura has great socio-political value for the Shi'a, who have been a minority throughout their history. &quot;Al-Amd&quot; asserts that the Shi'a transference of Al-Husayn and Karbala ' from the framework of history to the domain of ideology and everlasting legend reflects their marginal and dissenting status in Arab-Islamic society.[original research?][citation needed] According to the prevailing conditions at the time of the commemoration, such reminiscences may become a framework for implicit dissent or explicit protest. It was, for instance, used during the Islamic Revolution of Iran , the Lebanese Civil War, the Lebanese resistance against the Israeli occupation and in the 1990s Uprising in Bahrain. Sometimes the `Ashura' celebrations associate the memory of Al-Husayn's martyrdom with the conditions of Islam and Muslims in reference to Husayn's famous quote on the day of Ashura: &quot;Every day is Ashura, every land is Karbala&quot;.[

&quot;Everyday is Ashura, Every land is Karbala is a saying that was popularized by Dr.Ali Shariati, architect and ideologue of the Iranian Revolution. There are no references that back up the claim that Hussein said this...  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.80.104.182|24.80.104.182]] ([[User talk:24.80.104.182|talk]]) 06:30, 22 January 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:It is correct, the saying has been wrongly attributed to [[Imam Husain]]. It is [[Ali Shariati]]'s [[Ali_Shariati#cite_ref-9|saying]]. 
:Ali Shariati said, &quot;Every day is Ashura, every land is Karbala.&quot; It means the same thing as Karl Marx's answer to John Swinton (John Swinton, &quot;Karl Marx,&quot; The Sun, 6 September 1880): &quot;What is?&quot; I had inquired, to which, in deep and solemn tone, he replied: &quot;Struggle!&quot;
:--&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:green&quot;&gt;[[User:Faizhaider|Sayed Mohammad Faiz Haider]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:Faizhaider|t]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Faizhaider|c]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[User:Faizhaider/Autograph_Book|s]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/i&gt; 10:50, 22 January 2011 (UTC)
==File:Husayn callig.gif Nominated for Deletion==
{|
|-
| [[File:Image-x-generic.svg|100px]] 
| An image used in this article, [[commons:File:Husayn callig.gif|File:Husayn callig.gif]], has been nominated for deletion at [[Wikimedia Commons]] in the following category: ''Deletion requests October 2011'' 
;What should I do?
''Don't panic''; a discussion will now take place over on Commons about whether to remove the file. This gives you an opportunity to contest the deletion, although please review Commons guidelines before doing so.
* If the image is [[WP:NFCC|non-free]] then you may need to upload it to Wikipedia (Commons does not allow fair use)
* If the image isn't freely licensed and there is no [[WP:FUR|fair use rationale]] then it cannot be uploaded or used.

''This notification is provided by a Bot'' --[[User:CommonsNotificationBot|CommonsNotificationBot]] ([[User talk:CommonsNotificationBot|talk]]) 20:44, 24 October 2011 (UTC)
|}

==Quote Formatting==
Why is there this strange blue quote box? I have not seen the formatting that is used in this article in any others. Aren't quotes (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Manual_of_Style#Block_quotations) supposed to be indented in Wikipedia? [[User:Darkgroup|Darkgroup]] ([[User talk:Darkgroup|talk]]) 19:12, 4 December 2011 (UTC)

==History of the commemoration by Shi'a==
Language error leading to confusion: The second paragraph in this section has a sentence reading: &quot;he and his small group of companions and family members, who were between 72 men.&quot;  That &quot;between 72 men&quot; leads to to confusion because of the language error.  Does it mean:

# he and his family members were physically located amongst (within) a group of 72 men?
# he and his family members had 72 men in their group?
# he and his family members were men only, totaling a number of between something and 72?

Please can someone look this up and correct this.  [[User:Kmasters0|Kmasters0]] ([[User talk:Kmasters0|talk]]) 10:23, 25 December 2011 (UTC)

{{done|Clarified the sentence to &quot;he and his small group of companions and family members (in total who were around 72 men and few ladies and children)&quot;.}} Hopefully sentence is clearer than before. --&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:green&quot;&gt;[[User:Faizhaider|Sayed Mohammad Faiz Haider]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:Faizhaider|t]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Faizhaider|c]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[User:Faizhaider/Autograph_Book|s]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/i&gt; 12:35, 25 December 2011 (UTC)

==Yom Kippur==
A well known practice in the Jewish tradition is fasting on [[Yom Kippur]] (tenth of Tishrei, first month in the Jewish calendar) to commemorate God's forgiving the Children of Israel's worshiping the calf. Goitein [http://books.google.ps/books?id=cmn8U8uNtFAC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=goitein+studies&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=OiHSUajgKuW54ASj8oGQAg&amp;ved=0CCgQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=ashura&amp;f=false] affirms the Ashura-Kippur relation and suggests the Pharaoh explanation of the practice is spurious.—[[User:Arpose|Arpose]] ([[User talk:Arpose|talk]]) 00:55, 2 July 2013 (UTC)
==Improving the Article==
*I am going to improve this article a little bit so that it won't have the problem labeled at the top of the article page. Doing so I will have to delete some parts of it for which there is not enough valid sources.[[User:Hadi.anani|Hadi.anani]] ([[User talk:Hadi.anani|talk]]) 05:07, 31 October 2014 (UTC)

==Day of Ashura==
{{ping|Sa.vakilian|Yusufk}} This is an article concerning the day of Ashura, But the readers cannot get much information about the day. It says Yazid wanted &quot;the Bay'ah (allegiance) of Husayn ibn Ali. A segment of Muslims believed Yazid was openly going against the teachings of Islam...&quot; and then we read that he and his small group were killed on their way to Kufa in search of water. there is a big gap between these two. The readers have the right to know why husain decided to go to Kufa. I am trying to add some more information but someone is deleting it. I also added a painting called [http://www.iranreview.org/content/Documents/Analysis-of-The-Evening-of-Ashura-Painting.htm The evening of Ashura] but it has been deleted either.[[User:Hadi.anani|Hadi.anani]] ([[User talk:Hadi.anani|talk]]) 05:10, 2 November 2014 (UTC)
:{{ping|Hadi.anani}} There is another article which describes what happened in Ashura:[[Battle of Karbala]]. This article is about the importance of Day of Ashura. Although a short summary of the event is sufficient, I agree on adding short explanation of Imam Hussain's uprising as you told.--&lt;font face=&quot;monospace&quot;&gt;[[User:Sa.vakilian|Seyyed]]([[User talk:Sa.vakilian|t]]-[[Special:Contributions/Sa.vakilian|c]])&lt;/font&gt; 05:51, 2 November 2014 (UTC)
{{re|Sa.vakilian}} I agree. We cannot talk about its important without explaining why it is important. It is important just because it is commemorated by people and people mourn and go to Karbala on this day? Or because cut themselves on this day? I think it is kind of distorting the main event as it happens day by day. [[User:Hadi.anani|Hadi.anani]] ([[User talk:Hadi.anani|talk]]) 07:14, 2 November 2014 (UTC)
::We can add few sentence to explain the issue in brief. --&lt;font face=&quot;monospace&quot;&gt;[[User:Sa.vakilian|Seyyed]]([[User talk:Sa.vakilian|t]]-[[Special:Contributions/Sa.vakilian|c]])&lt;/font&gt; 04:33, 3 November 2014 (UTC)
{{ping|Hadi.anani}}, as I told you, if you want to add the details, you should do it in [[Battle of Karbala]]. Therefor, I moved the details to that article. --&lt;font face=&quot;monospace&quot;&gt;[[User:Sa.vakilian|Seyyed]]([[User talk:Sa.vakilian|t]]-[[Special:Contributions/Sa.vakilian|c]])&lt;/font&gt; 06:04, 4 November 2014 (UTC)

== image RFC ==

[[File:Ashura cutting.jpg|thumb|Pakistani Shiite Muslims perform religious rituals during an Ashura procession in Quetta on November 25, 2012.]]
Should an image (either the one right, or a similar other one) be included in the article in the section on [[Day_of_Ashura#Cutting_with_knives_or_chains]] 

===Survey===
* '''include''' notable part of the day, and similar images are very regularly included by [[WP:RS]] in their stories about the day.The image was previously removed per [[Wikipedia:Image_use_policy#Moral_issues]] But I note that the people are a) in a group. b) not identifiable (their faces are not visible) c) in public [[User:Gaijin42|Gaijin42]] ([[User talk:Gaijin42|talk]]) 14:57, 28 November 2014 (UTC)
*'''Include''' per Gaijin42, per [[WP:NOTCENSORED]], and per reliable sources such as the [http://www.bbc.com/news/world-29895503 BBC], ''[http://www.theguardian.com/world/gallery/2014/nov/04/shia-festival-of-ashura-around-the-world-in-pictures The Guardian]'', and''[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2014/11/03/ashura-2014_n_6094360.html Huffington Post]''. [[User:Yopienso|YoPienso]] ([[User talk:Yopienso|talk]]) 08:07, 30 March 2015 (UTC)

===Threaded comments===

{{hat}}
== OBVIOUS QUESTION: WHAT DAY OF THE YEAR IT THIS, DUH? ==

my initial browsing research seems to indicate that it's the day before 9/11.  I'm sitting here, minding my own business and in pops the question &quot;I wonder if 9/11 was intended to cover something ELSE that was going on.&quot; so I went and Googled &quot;9/10&quot; just to see if anything interesting happened the day before the earth stood still.

And up pops the Day of Ashura.

Now, knowing as I do that China controls the search results via Google, the obvious question is &quot;Why is Wikipedia hiding the fact that 9/10 is the Day of Ashura, and then I start having to read about it even if it has nothing to do with what *I* want to know.  I'm spending my time making certain that something I'm confident doesn't have what I'm looking for, actually DOESN'T have what I'm looking for.  I find this inconvenient and distracting.  It's like someone's MAKING me ADHD.

And part of me considers that the Muslims of the time periods where these traditions were established might not have used the 365 days a year Roman calender, but instead might have used a more primitive and inferior moon-based system.  The mathematics are too complex to use a moon based system to achieve accurate navigation.  Shackleton would never have made it.  No Geographical exploration, no indoor toilets and no iPhones.  These things must be done in order.  Ergo, Muslims were (and are) inferior as an objectively defined culture, depending on one's standards.  But if you deny the legitimacy of the existence of the question &quot;Can cultures be objectively measured, and compared?&quot;, then the outcome of any &quot;allowed&quot; debate is predetermined, and I don't like the destination and am looking for a way to avoid it.[[User:Jonny Quick|Jonny Quick]] ([[User talk:Jonny Quick|talk]]) 07:41, 30 March 2015 (UTC)
{{hab}}

== Info box Pic ==

The pic in the infobox is showing [[Arbaeen]] rally. It should be replaced by a suitable pic showing the day of ahsura. [[User:Mhhossein|Mhhossein]] ([[User talk:Mhhossein|talk]]) 11:43, 3 September 2015 (UTC)

== 24 October 2015 ==

{{ping|AstroLynx}} Please see the [http://www.staff.science.uu.nl/~gent0113/islam/ummalqura.htm reference]. [[User:Saff V.|Saff V.]] ([[User talk:Saff V.|talk]]) 09:48, 15 October 2015 (UTC)

: The date converter on the website you refer to gives 23 October as the date for 10 Muharram - so what is your point? [[User:AstroLynx|AstroLynx]] ([[User talk:AstroLynx|talk]]) 09:53, 15 October 2015 (UTC)
::According to calendar, first day of Muharram in 1437 AH is 14 October and 23 October is Ashura. Excuse me. [[User:Saff V.|Saff V.]] ([[User talk:Saff V.|talk]]) 09:58, 15 October 2015 (UTC)

== Number of pilgrims per year ==

Would it be possible to create a section for the number of pilgrims attending the ceremony? You know something similar to the Hajj section 'Number of pilgrims per year' https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hajj#Number_of_pilgrims_per_year

If I'm not mistaken, the number of pilgrims attending outnumbers the Hajj (I've read 10 million before but I may be wrong)  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.84.88.181|24.84.88.181]] ([[User talk:24.84.88.181|talk]]) 18:54, 17 October 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Day of Ashura]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=686487301 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20061211012221/http://www.islamonline.net:80/English/ArtCulture/2004/03/article06.shtml to http://www.islamonline.net/English/ArtCulture/2004/03/article06.shtml

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers. —[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 12:07, 19 October 2015 (UTC)

== Photo needs resizing ==

I have just restored a photo to section 3.3, Azadari rituals. It is larger than the others and needs to be downsized, but I don't know how to do that. Please do it if you can! Thanks. [[User:Yopienso|YoPienso]] ([[User talk:Yopienso|talk]]) 13:50, 26 September 2016 (UTC)
:{{done}} [[User:Emir of Wikipedia|Emir of Wikipedia]] ([[User talk:Emir of Wikipedia|talk]]) 14:01, 26 September 2016 (UTC)

== Requested move 1 October 2016 ==

&lt;div class=&quot;boilerplate&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #efe; margin: 2em 0 0 0; padding: 0 10px 0 10px; border: 1px dotted #aaa;&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Template:RM top --&gt;
:''The following is a closed discussion of a [[WP:requested moves|requested move]]. &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on the talk page. Editors desiring to contest the closing decision should consider a [[Wikipedia:move review|move review]]. No further edits should be made to this section. ''

The result of the move request was: '''moved'''. [[User:SSTflyer|&lt;span style=&quot;color:Black&quot;&gt;SST&lt;/span&gt;]][[User talk:SSTflyer|&lt;span style=&quot;color:DarkRed&quot;&gt;flyer&lt;/span&gt;]] 12:46, 8 October 2016 (UTC)
----


* [[:Day of Ashura]] → {{no redirect|Ashura}}
* [[:Ashura]] → {{no redirect|Ashura (disambiguation)}}
– &quot;Day of&quot; seems to have been added only as a disambiguator against other similarly titled pages (see the dab page). Analogous to for example Christmas —instead of &quot;Day of Christmas&quot;—, this holiday is simply referred to as &quot;Ashura&quot; in English-language sources. Ashura's [[WP:PTOPIC|primary topic]] is by far the Islamic holiday (13,700 GBooks, 4500 GNews hits for ''ashura islam'') vs the Tsubasa character (349 GBooks, 66 GNews hits for ''ashura tsubasa''), or the Mazinger G character (790 GBooks, 103 GNews for ''ashura mazinger'') Pretty much all major language-wikis, use a simple &quot;Ashura&quot; or a local spelling variant. [[User:HyperGaruda|HyperGaruda]] ([[User talk:HyperGaruda|talk]]) 07:03, 1 October 2016 (UTC)
*{{ok}} I support the move.--&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:green&quot;&gt;[[User:Faizhaider|Sayed Mohammad Faiz Haider]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:Faizhaider|t]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Faizhaider|c]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[User:Faizhaider/Autograph_Book|s]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/i&gt; 09:17, 1 October 2016 (UTC)
* '''Support''' the move. --[[User:Mhhossein|&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Aharoni&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#002E63&quot;&gt;M&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#2E5894&quot;&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#318CE7&quot;&gt;hossein&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Mhhossein|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#056608&quot;&gt;'''talk'''&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 18:27, 1 October 2016 (UTC)
*'''Support''' [https://www.google.com/search?tbo=p&amp;tbm=bks&amp;q=%22ashura+is%22&amp;num=10#q=%22ashura+is%22&amp;tbm=bks&amp;start=20 &quot;Ashura is&quot; test in Google Books], for once there actually is a primary topic, go figure. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 18:29, 1 October 2016 (UTC)
*'''Neutral.''' However, I would like to suggest that if this article is renamed, then [[Day of Arafah]] should be renamed also.—[[User:Quick and Dirty User Account|Quick and Dirty User Account]] ([[User talk:Quick and Dirty User Account|talk]]) 10:38, 3 October 2016 (UTC)
**{{reply to|Quick and Dirty User Account}} That is a place though too. [[User:Emir of Wikipedia|Emir of Wikipedia]] ([[User talk:Emir of Wikipedia|talk]]) 11:04, 3 October 2016 (UTC)
***Thanks for pointing that out, {{u|Emir of Wikipedia|Emir}}. If this page is renamed, then I’ll consider whether to make a formal proposal on moving Day of Arafah.—[[User:Quick and Dirty User Account|Quick and Dirty User Account]] ([[User talk:Quick and Dirty User Account|talk]]) 11:26, 3 October 2016 (UTC)
::::And while we're at it: [[Day of Tasu'a]] can go to {{noredirect|Tasu'a}}, although a simple {{tl|db-move}} can be used there, since the intended title is only a redirect. --[[User:HyperGaruda|HyperGaruda]] ([[User talk:HyperGaruda|talk]]) 20:22, 7 October 2016 (UTC)
----
:''The above discussion is preserved as an archive of a [[Wikipedia:Requested moves|requested move]].  &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on this talk page or in a [[Wikipedia:Move review|move review]]. No further edits should be made to this section.''&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- Template:RM bottom --&gt;

== Gregorian dates ==

Are we going to maintain a log of all past Gregorian dates until the end of times? Because to me, that seems like a violation of [[WP:NOTSTATS]]. &lt;s&gt;1 past, 1 present and 1 future date&lt;/s&gt; Three dates (last year, this year and next year) should be enough to see how Anno Domini and Anno Hegirae are connected. --[[User:HyperGaruda|HyperGaruda]] ([[User talk:HyperGaruda|talk]]) 17:10, 11 October 2016 (UTC)
:I also think updating those three years suffices. --[[User:Mhhossein|&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Aharoni&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#002E63&quot;&gt;M&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#2E5894&quot;&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#318CE7&quot;&gt;hossein&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Mhhossein|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#056608&quot;&gt;'''talk'''&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 18:05, 11 October 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:2|one external link|2 external links}} on [[Ashura]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=745177522 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20130326073754/http://www.porsojoo.com/en/node/70869 to http://www.porsojoo.com/en/node/70869
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20091126163157/http://www.usc.edu/schools/college/crcc/engagement/resources/texts/muslim/hadith/bukhari/031.sbt.html#003.031.222 to http://www.usc.edu/schools/college/crcc/engagement/resources/texts/muslim/hadith/bukhari/031.sbt.html#003.031.222

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 18:19, 19 October 2016 (UTC)

== Concerns raised by copyeditor ==

I requested a copyedit at this guild for this article. This was completed by [[User:Corinne]] and was great, however they raised some concerns on my [[User talk:Emir of Wikipedia#Ashura|talkpage]]. Please check them out and tell me what you think. [[User:Emir of Wikipedia|Emir of Wikipedia]] ([[User talk:Emir of Wikipedia|talk]]) 12:23, 25 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>qrtunu350qt4qa06xq19u78pqzffak1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
