<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:William Speirs Bruce</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>9953642</id>
    <revision>
      <id>699146723</id>
      <parentid>692063342</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-01-10T15:31:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Wizardman</username>
        <id>713860</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>it's an FA and you tag it as a stub?&gt; sigh</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9920">{{Talk header}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=9 June 2008
|action1link=Talk:William Speirs Bruce/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=218263317

|action2=PR
|action2date=02:36, 19 June 2008
|action2link=Wikipedia:Peer review/William Speirs Bruce/archive1
|action2result=reviewed
|action2oldid=220256954

|action3=FAC
|action3date=02:47, 2 July 2008
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/William Speirs Bruce
|action3result=promoted
|action3oldid=222959039

| topic         = world history
|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=December 3, 2009
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Biography
|living=no
|class=FA
|s&amp;a-work-group=yes &lt;!-- Science and Academia --&gt;
|listas=Bruce, William}}
{{WikiProject Antarctica|class=FA|importance=Top|Argentina=yes|Argentina-importance=mid|British=yes|British-importance=top}}
{{WikiProject Scotland|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject British Overseas Territories|class=FA|importance=low}}
}}

==Truncated biography==
Does anyone intend to continue this article, which stops when Bruce was 26 years old and has nothing whatever to say about the important events of his life? At present it is hardly more use than a stub. [[User:Brianboulton|Brianboulton]] ([[User talk:Brianboulton|talk]]) 00:12, 24 March 2008 (UTC)

Unfortunately I was unable to complete the biographical entry I started. Please feel free to continue it, or to dispense with it as you see fit.[[User:Imkgeo|Imkgeo]] ([[User talk:Imkgeo|talk]]) 11:30, 18 April 2008 (UTC)

:I am intending to build up the Scottish National Antarctic Expedition first. When I 've done that I will tuen my attention here. [[User:Brianboulton|Brianboulton]] ([[User talk:Brianboulton|talk]]) 11:50, 4 May 2008 (UTC)

::I am now working on the extension of this biographical article. Because my sources are different from those used by Imkgeo I have had to abandon most of his/her material as I can't cite it. [[User:Brianboulton|Brianboulton]] ([[User talk:Brianboulton|talk]]) 21:05, 26 May 2008 (UTC)

==Citations==
{{dablink|Please note, this is not a GA review, but it may help with future review processes.}}
The internet inline citations used in this article are improperly formatted and this problem may hinder a GA nomination. Internet citations require at the very least information on the  title, publisher and last access date of any webpages used. If the source is a news article then the date of publication and the author are also important. This information is useful because it allows a reader to a) rapidly identify a source's origin b) ascertain the reliability of that source and c) find other copies of the source should the website that hosts it become unavaliable for any reason. It may also in some circumstances aid in determining the existance or status of potential copyright infringments. Finally, it looks much tidier, making the article appear more professional. There are various ways in which this information can be represented in the citation, listed at length at [[Wikipedia:Citing sources]]. The simplest way of doing this is in the following format:

&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|(insert URL)|title=|publisher=|work=|date=|author=|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt; 

As an example:

*&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.discovery.org/a/3859|title=Avoiding a Thirty Years War|publisher=www.discovery.org|work=[[The Washington Post]]|date=2006-12-21|author=Richard W. Rahn|accessdate=2008-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt; 

which looks like:

*{{cite web|url=http://www.discovery.org/a/3859|title=Avoiding a Thirty Years War|publisher=www.discovery.org|work=[[The Washington Post]]|date=2006-12-21|author=Richard W. Rahn|accessdate=2008-05-25}}

If any information is unknown then simply omit it, but title, publisher and last access dates are always required. I strongly recommend that all internet inline references in this article be formatted properly before this article undergoes GA review, and indeed this is something that a reviewer should insist you do before promoting your article. If you have any further questions please contact me and as mentioned above, more information on this issue can be found at [[Wikipedia:Citing sources]]. Regards
::In response to the (unsigned) above I have reformatted the inline citations. I would point out, however, that the properly formatted information per &lt;nowiki&gt;{{cite web}}&lt;/nowiki&gt; is included the Sources section. [[User:Brianboulton|Brianboulton]] ([[User talk:Brianboulton|talk]]) 15:50, 9 June 2008 (UTC)

{{Talk:William Speirs Bruce/GA1}}

== Proposal to remove date-autoformatting ==

Dear fellow contributors

[[Wikipedia:Manual_of_Style_%28dates_and_numbers%29#Date_autoformatting|MOSNUM]] no longer encourages date autoformatting, having evolved over the past year or so from the mandatory to the optional after much discussion there and elsewhere of the disadvantages of the system. Related to this, MOSNUM prescribes [[Wikipedia:Manual_of_Style_%28dates_and_numbers%29#Full_date_formatting|rules for the raw formatting]], irrespective of whether or not dates are autoformatted. [[Wikipedia:Manual_of_Style_%28links%29#Overlinking_and_underlinking|MOSLINK]] and [[Wikipedia:Context#What_generally_should_not_be_linked|CONTEXT]] are consistent with this. 

There are at least six disadvantages in using date-autoformatting, which I've capped here:
{{hidden|contentstyle=border:1px solid #C0C0C0; |headerstyle=color:black; background: #C0C0C0; |header= Disadvantages of date-autoformatting|content=&lt;/br&gt;

*'''(1) In-house only'''
:*(a) It works only for the WP &quot;elite&quot;. 
:*(b) To our readers out there, it displays all-too-common inconsistencies in raw formatting in bright-blue underlined text, yet conceals them from WPians who are logged in and have chosen preferences.  
:*(c) It causes visitors to query why dates are bright-blue and underlined.

*'''(2) Avoids what are merely trivial differences'''
:*(a) It is trivial whether the order is day–month or month–day. It is more trivial than color/colour and realise/realize, yet our consistency-within-article policy on spelling ([[WP:ENGVAR]]) has worked very well. English-speakers readily recognise both date formats; all dates after our signatures are international, and no one objects.

*'''(3) Colour-clutter: the bright-blue underlining of all dates'''
:*(a) It dilutes the impact of high-value links.
:*(b) It makes the text slightly harder to read.
:*(c) It doesn't improve the appearance of the page.

*'''(4) Typos and misunderstood coding'''
:*(a) There's a disappointing error-rate in keying in the auto-function; not bracketing the year, and enclosing the whole date in one set of brackets, are examples.
:*(b) Once autoformatting is removed, mixtures of US and international formats are revealed in display mode, where they are  much easier for WPians to pick up  than in edit mode; so is the use of the wrong format in country-related articles.
:*(c) Many WPians don't understand date-autoformatting—in particular, how if differs from ordinary linking; often it's applied simply because it's part of the furniture.

*'''(5) Edit-mode clutter'''
:*(a) It's more work to enter an autoformatted date, and it doesn't make the edit-mode text any easier to read for subsequent editors.

*'''(6) Limited application'''
:*(a) It's incompatible with date ranges (&quot;January 3–9, 1998&quot;, or &quot;3–9 January 1998&quot;, and &quot;February–April 2006&quot;) and slashed dates (&quot;the night of May 21/22&quot;, or &quot;... 21/22 May&quot;).
:*(b) By policy, we avoid date autoformatting in such places as quotations; the removal of autoformatting avoids this inconsistency.}}

Removal has generally been met with positive responses by editors. I'm seeking feedback about this proposal to remove it from the main text (using a script) in about a week's time on a trial basis. The original input formatting would be seen by all WPians, not just the huge number of visitors; it would be plain, unobtrusive text in the prevailing format for the article, which would give greater prominence to the high-value links. BTW, anyone has the right to object, and my aim is not to argue against people on the issue. [[User:Tony1|&lt;font color=&quot;darkgreen&quot;&gt;'''Tony'''&lt;/font &gt;]] [[User talk:Tony1|&lt;font color=&quot;darkgreen&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font &gt;]] 12:52, 30 July 2008 (UTC)

== Scottish? ==

He was born/grew up in England and had a Welsh mother. Did he see himself as &quot;Scottish?&quot; If not, calling him British is more neutral.--[[Special:Contributions/85.211.120.106|85.211.120.106]] ([[User talk:85.211.120.106|talk]]) 13:09, 22 August 2013 (UTC)

== Bruce's marriage details ==
The following text was added to the &quot;Marriage and family life&quot; section in August 2012, by an IP editor, presumably Colin B. Withers:

&quot; However, his marriage has now been found. It took place on the 26 January 1901, at Nigg, in Ross &amp; Cromarty, at the Chapelhill United Free Church after banns. Bruce gave his occupation as Naturalist and Zoologist, son of Samuel Noble Bruce, surgeon MRCS, and a bachelor, while Jessie gave her status as a spinster, daughter of Alexander Mackenzie, master tailor, deceased. Bruce gave his residence as 17 Joppa Road, Portobello, Edinburgh, while Jessie gave hers as Chapelhill, Nigg, and as one of the witnesses was Isabella Mackenzie it would appear that Nigg was Jessie's home parish. (Colin B. Withers).&quot;

This is interesting and relevant. It would be good to include in the article at  least the date and location of the wedding, if not the supplementary detail. However, we need a reliable source for any information that is added; this is a [[WP:FA|featured article]] for which the standards of sourcing are stringent. An online genealogy  site would not be considered of sufficient reliability. If Colin Withers is still watching this page, perhaps he would state exactly where he got the information from. [[User:Brianboulton|Brianboulton]] ([[User talk:Brianboulton|talk]]) 15:13, 1 July 2015 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>ru0qzlirzmgx56wd3uoo5e8xm9t7yhg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
