<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Queen bee</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>380178</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746871110</id>
      <parentid>746871044</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-30T02:24:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SineBot</username>
        <id>4936590</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Signing comment by [[Special:Contributions/78.52.7.11|78.52.7.11]] - &quot;&quot;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16570">{{WikiProject Insects|class=B|importance=mid|Hymenoptera=yes|Hymenoptera-importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Agriculture||class=B|importance=low|beekeeping=yes|beekeeping-importance=}}

==Queen bee nutrition==
This article describes recent findings according to which it is not the presence of royal jelly in the diet that makes a bee a queen, but the absence of honey and pollen in her diet:
&quot;It turns out, it’s the other way around. Not feeding an immature queen pollen and honey is what makes her royal, not her exclusive access to royal jelly.&quot;
https://www.wired.com/2015/09/royal-jelly-isnt-makes-queen-bee-queen-bee/
Hopefully someone with expert knowledge can verify/update this (I just happened to find it, and am by no means knowledgeable enough to verify it).  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/78.52.7.11|78.52.7.11]] ([[User talk:78.52.7.11#top|talk]]) 02:24, 30 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Untitled==
References -

The link for &quot;Bees Gone Wild&quot; takes you to a site advertising building your own web site, which must be in error.  Do you mean the Bees Gone Wild Apiaries, in Derry, PA?  If so the link should be: http://mysite.verizon.net/vzeod3nx/id1.html

As a side issue, I'd like to find a link, article, or publication dealing with how to retrieve the queen from a swarm that has left the hive and taken up residence elsewhere.  This must be a very specialized, difficult thing to do.  There is a brief portion in this video that describes someone who rescues a swarm (queen plus workers who have swarmed with her)and sets up a new hive: http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ekoeQodrVoM
but it doesn't give much information.

Thanks.  M.W.[[User:Smallgwg|MW]] ([[User talk:Smallgwg|talk]]) 14:20, 31 March 2014 (UTC)

==Untitled==
I have actually heard the piping of queen bees. It sounds like the peep of a peeper frog or the sound of a rather high-pitched whistle or harmonica.

Research in the 60s (?) indicated that the body of the queen produces a hormone that inhibits queen-rearing behavior on the part of worker bees.  She can only produce a certain amount. So the more bees there are in a colony the lower the concentration of this hormone. When it falls below a critical value, then the queen-rearing behavior is released for normal swarming. Should the queen be killed the concentration of the hormone falls quickly to zero and the workers select several of the recently laid eggs to rear as queens.

I think that the article should reflect this fact.

----
Who will be first to fill in the [[taxonomy]]? [[User:RedWolf|RedWolf]] 06:20, Nov 27, 2003 (UTC)

Surely there is an article on the honeybee. Presumably the taxonomy stuff would go there.

[[User:Patrick0Moran|Patrick0Moran]] 07:18, 27 Nov 2003 (UTC)
----
I added the links back because of two reasons: 1) people who work on articles of colors can look what links there and add this to the information about uses of colors, and 2) it enables colorblind people to actually read the article. I hope it's aestethically pleasing as well :) [[User:Nikola Smolenski|Nikola]] 08:11, 29 Nov 2003 (UTC)

== Incorporating other articles into this article ==

I'm looking for information on bees. I found the information about '''one''' aspect of the bee colony, ie ''the queen'' scattered around on '''four''' seperate page entitled 

#Queen bee
#Virgin queen (with a disambig. from Elizabeth I of England)
#Piping queens (describing the noise angry females of the species make) 
#Supersedure (describing the process by which one queen replaces another)

Why spread all this stuff around when it can be neatly and conveniently placed in one article? Wikipedia is an encyclopedia, not a dictionary. Anyone looking up bees wants the info in one place. To have different articles for hives, swarms, piping queens etc etc etc is superfluous. 

I'm not suggesting that any of the information is superfluous, just the superfluity of seperate articles.
If anyone objects, they can put it all back. I'll leave the other pages where they are for a few days, but will transfer any discussion pertaining to the other three topics listed above to this page. Unfortunately, the history of the editting will be lost.

--[[User:Amandajm|Amandajm]] 07:50, 22 August 2006 (UTC)

== Talk: Piping Queen, transferred from other page ==

==Piping note==

:''The piping sound is a G sharp or A natural.''

Couldn't this vary from species to species? (A larger queen might produce a lower note, for instance?) - [[User:Furrykef|furrykef]] ([[User_talk:Furrykef|Talk at me]]) 21:31, 11 May 2006 (UTC)

== Maximum temperature for Raw Honey ==

I understand to be called raw, honey must not be heated above a certain temperature.  I don't know what those limits are, but I am under the impression it has something to do with destroying enzymes in the honey.  Does anyone know the limits?

transferred by --[[User:Amandajm|Amandajm]] 07:54, 22 August 2006 (UTC)

There have been articles and discussions in bee journals for years on the subject.  As far as I know there is no official standard, at least not in the US.  &quot;Raw&quot; means whatever you like it to mean.  Since the bees heat the hive to about 95 F or so and since all liquid honey is at least coarsely filtered to get out chunks of wax and dead bee parts, and since there is no official designation about how finely fliltered and how high a temperature constitutes raw, the term by itself doesn't mean anything.  Of course if you know your honey producer personally you can ask what they do, or in this case, don't do to your honey.

[[User:Michael Bush|Michael Bush]] ([[User talk:Michael Bush|talk]]) 20:13, 6 February 2008 (UTC)
:I found an article on the net [http://members.aol.com/beetools/heater.htm here] which gives some temperatures (in Fahrenheit) to match the temperature in a honey super in Summer. Honey in storage does (mine does) crystalize over time, and when you need to bottle some more it helps to have a honey heater to bring it back to liquid form. &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot; face=&quot;Vladimir Script&quot;&gt;[[User:Sting au|&lt;b&gt;Sting au&lt;/b&gt;]]&lt;/font&gt; ''&lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Sting au|&lt;span style=&quot;color:gold; &quot;&gt;Buzz Me...&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/small&gt;'' 22:37, 6 February 2008 (UTC)

==Edit history of Virgin queen==
*(cur) (last)  04:54, 27 May 2006 XC0000005 (Talk | contribs) (Reword some unclear sentences, expand (minorly)) 
*(cur) (last)  22:00, 4 May 2006 Swatjester (Talk | contribs) m (Reverted edits by 151.37.129.122 (talk) to last version by XC0000005) 
*(cur) (last)  21:59, 4 May 2006 151.37.129.122 (Talk) 
*(cur) (last)  18:06, 15 December 2005 XC0000005 (Talk | contribs) (Reword to fix description of virgin queens (mingling with other bees doesn't make them harder to find, it's the fact that they skitter off that does it.).) 
*(cur) (last)  17:45, 11 October 2005 Keenan Pepper (Talk | contribs) m (grammar &amp; style) 
*(cur) (last)  13:00, 5 October 2005 Appleseed (Talk | contribs) (tweak category) 
*(cur) (last)  00:28, 26 August 2005 68.39.174.230 (Talk) (Work) 
*(cur) (last)  05:07, 16 August 2005 Leonard G. (Talk | contribs) 
*(cur) (last)  03:21, 15 May 2005 Nameneko (Talk | contribs) m (sp) 
*(cur) (last)  20:34, 9 May 2005 71.99.220.87 (Talk) 
*(cur) (last)  06:40, 25 April 2005 68.39.174.150 (Talk) (Rearrainge) 
*(cur) (last)  19:32, 15 April 2005 Shoefly (Talk | contribs) 
*(cur) (last)  09:20, 14 April 2005 Allard (Talk | contribs) m 
*(cur) (last)  05:40, 20 March 2005 Shoefly (Talk | contribs) 
*(cur) (last)  02:29, 14 February 2005 Pollinator (Talk | contribs) (flesh out article) 
*(cur) (last)  03:54, 1 February 2005 Shoefly (Talk | contribs) 

==Edit history of Piping queens== 
*(cur) (last)  00:50, 28 June 2006 NeonMerlin (Talk | contribs) m (sp) 
*(cur) (last)  22:27, 26 May 2006 XC0000005 (Talk | contribs) (Revised, added supersedure to reasons why there's be multiple queens) 
*(cur) (last)  13:00, 5 October 2005 Appleseed (Talk | contribs) (tweak category) 
*(cur) (last)  16:59, 26 September 2005 MacsBug (Talk | contribs) m (Fixed spelling error in top section) 
*(cur) (last)  03:05, 9 September 2005 Kjkolb (Talk | contribs) (wikified further as possible and removed tag) 
*(cur) (last)  03:47, 2 September 2005 Kent Wang (Talk | contribs) m (copy edit) 
*(cur) (last)  00:32, 26 August 2005 68.39.174.230 (Talk) (Some work) 
*(cur) (last)  00:29, 26 August 2005 68.39.174.230 (Talk) (Added template) 
*(cur) (last)  00:05, 26 August 2005 68.39.174.230 (Talk) (Again) 
*(cur) (last)  00:05, 26 August 2005 68.39.174.230 (Talk) (Fix bad link) 
*(cur) (last)  00:05, 26 August 2005 68.39.174.230 (Talk) (Some work, needs more) 
*(cur) (last)  01:06, 16 May 2005 Shoefly (Talk | contribs) (→See also) 
*(cur) (last)  01:00, 16 May 2005 Shoefly (Talk | contribs) 
*(cur) (last)  20:50, 14 May 2005 Shoefly (Talk | contribs) 
*(cur) (last)  03:43, 14 May 2005 Shoefly (Talk | contribs) 

== Edit History of Supersedure ==

*(cur) (last)  17:00, 12 June 2006 Larsinio (Talk | contribs) m 
*(cur) (last)  01:02, 20 May 2006 Bryan Derksen (Talk | contribs) (replace overly broad see also list with just those entries that seem most relevant to the article) 
*(cur) (last)  23:01, 23 March 2006 Mirv (Talk | contribs) (xref) 
*(cur) (last)  18:25, 18 March 2006 Bluebot (Talk | contribs) (bold formatting title using AWB) 
*(cur) (last)  04:03, 6 December 2005 Shoefly (Talk | contribs) 
*(cur) (last)  02:07, 12 November 2005 Shoefly (Talk | contribs) m (Supercedure moved to Supersedure) 
*(cur) (last)  10:26, 11 November 2005 158.36.44.66 (Talk) (&quot;supercession&quot; and &quot;supercedure&quot; changed because word does not exist (verb is latin &quot;sedere&quot; to sit)) 
*(cur) (last)  02:29, 26 August 2005 Leonard G. (Talk | contribs) (rm unsatisfied links) 
*(cur) (last)  01:27, 25 August 2005 Shoefly (Talk | contribs) 
*(cur) (last)  04:35, 23 August 2005 Leonard G. (Talk | contribs) 
*(cur) (last)  04:30, 23 August 2005 Leonard G. (Talk | contribs) (Forced supercedure, balling the queen) 
*(cur) (last)  05:22, 16 August 2005 Leonard G. (Talk | contribs) 
*(cur) (last)  06:28, 2 April 2005 FirstPrinciples (Talk | contribs) (update link) 
*(cur) (last)  04:10, 10 March 2005 Shoefly (Talk | contribs)

==Moving of histories==
These histories are inactive, but at least reveal who has contributed to the articles.
--[[User:Amandajm|Amandajm]] 08:10, 22 August 2006 (UTC)

== Virgin Queens sting rivals ==

The article indicates that a virgin queen will kill potential rivals by stinging them.  But I had heard that queens have no stingers - that part having been modified for egg laying.  So do they sting, or possibly bite their rivals?

Paul 
epalb@honey.email.ne.jp
: Whoever told you that queens have no stingers was incorrect.  I can't speak for every species of bee but [[honeybee]] queens certainly have stingers.  It is part of the ovipositor but that does not preclude it's use as a stinger.  It is different from the worker bee's stinger in that it is smooth instead of barbed but that's about it.  [[User:Rossami|Rossami]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Rossami|(talk)]]&lt;/small&gt; 20:07, 27 October 2006 (UTC)
::That reminds me of someone who confidently told me on the basis of his own experience that carpenter bees do not have stingers. I caught a female carpenter bee and identified a very large and efficient looking stinger. I told my friend that he probably had been playing with a drone.  [[User:Patrick0Moran|P0M]] 21:40, 28 April 2007 (UTC)
==Question about &quot;queen substance&quot; ==
The last time I read anything in book form on the subject it was affirmed that the pheromone that workers lick from the body of the queen not only inhibits workers from laying eggs, but it also inhibits them from making queen cells.  If the queen dies or the population grows so large that the pheromone is too diluted by the time it is shared out among all the bees, then workers will start to make queen cells.  Have researchers revised this finding? [[User:Patrick0Moran|P0M]] 21:40, 28 April 2007 (UTC)

That's my understanding also - the presence of Q substance inhibits Q cell building. [[User:Dublinblue|Dublinblue (Simon in Dublin)]] ([[User talk:Dublinblue|talk]]) 19:00, 17 November 2007 (UTC)

See page 11 of Wisdom of the hive by Tom Seeley: 
&quot;the queen's pheromones are neither necessary nor sufficient for inhibiting worker's ovaries. Instead, they strongly inhibit the workers from rearing additional queens. It is now clear that the pheromones that provide the proximate stimulus for workers to refrain from laying eggs come mainly from the brood, not from the queen (reviewed in Seeling 1985; see also Willis, Winston, and Slessor 1990).&quot; 

[[User:Michael Bush|Michael Bush]] ([[User talk:Michael Bush|talk]]) 18:35, 29 January 2008 (UTC)

==Beekeeping?==

There are a lot of interjections in this article about beekeeping - I imagine that a lot of the editing of this article is done by beekeepers.  However, I think it somewhat distracts from the flow of the article.  [[User:Tiki2099|Tiki2099]] ([[User talk:Tiki2099|talk]]) 22:53, 2 September 2008 (UTC)

== Queen killing worker bees? ==

I saw a documentary on bees that stated how if a worker bee lays an egg and the queen discovers it, by detection of pheromones on the egg, she will kill the egg and also the bee that laid it. I was wondering if anyone has a reference for this behaviour by the queen bee. It seems like something that should be included in the article. [[User:Alialiac|Alialiac]] ([[User talk:Alialiac|talk]]) 06:50, 29 January 2012 (UTC)

Workers will sometimes lay eggs in the absence of a queen or if she's failing. I've not heard of an existing queen killing the worker though? There is a wiki article here [[Laying_worker_bee]] about laying workers. Typically the eggs are all male (drones). [[Special:Contributions/107.4.200.112|107.4.200.112]] ([[User talk:107.4.200.112|talk]]) 19:11, 16 April 2012 (UTC)

== Supersedure ≠ Emergency cell ==

Supersedure cells (including insurance cups) are formed while the original queen is still alive and possibly still laying. Emergency cells are created when there is &quot;no&quot; queen. Additionally, &quot;balling&quot; is not the only method a previous queens are deposed. Old queens often produce insufficient pheromones, so the attendant bees stop feeding them - and in turn they dies of starvation.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/207.87.238.194|207.87.238.194]] ([[User talk:207.87.238.194|talk]]) 15:06, 24 July 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
The picture does look like emergency cells, not supersedure cells. Tried to edit to correct but I think I messed it up for worse. Now it is correct &quot;supersedure cell&quot;, but for an emergency cell, and the file name is still wrong. Someone with a bit more of Wiki savvy please correct. Thank you.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/207.87.238.194|207.87.238.194]] ([[User talk:207.87.238.194|talk]]) 15:14, 24 July 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:2|one external link|2 external links}} on [[Queen bee]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=730734148 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20061103152001/http://joebee.homestead.com:80/joebee.html to http://joebee.homestead.com/joebee.html
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20060914020538/http://www.bioweb.uncc.edu/Faculty/Schneider/pdf%20files/ARE%202004.pdf to http://www.bioweb.uncc.edu/Faculty/Schneider/pdf%20files/ARE%202004.pdf

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 21:28, 20 July 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>93vwfnrzr9lyp3k08l8mtorxcldvje8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
