<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Africa–China relations</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>25030669</id>
    <revision>
      <id>742695132</id>
      <parentid>719315000</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-05T06:38:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot (v1.2.4)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="48340">{{WikiProject banner shell|1=
{{WikiProject China|class=C|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Africa|class=B|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject International relations}}
}}
{{To do}}
{{merged-from|Sino-African relations|2012-06-19}}

{{Archive box|
*[[Talk:Involvement of the People's Republic of China in Africa/Archive01|Archive 1]]
}}

== References system (to summarize) ==
{{summarization|1=
Hello, I noticed a large effort on reference and spelling. I will slowly restore the previous reference organization, my aim being from the start to move toward a system such [[History_of_the_Song_Dynasty#Notes]]. I understand your effort, but I do my best to keep a 'easy to edit' wiki text. Recent studies ([http://blog.wikimedia.org/2009/04/24/usability-study-results-sneak-preview/ Usability Study Results (Sneak Preview)]) enlighten the need of simpler wiki text, that's also my believe, and that ease my research-edit work.
In the end, I also plan to replace my codes such &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;ref&gt;CES, p8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;, by the more academic Cambridge style &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Zha Daojiong, 2005, p8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;. Let me just some few days. 

Also, please talk first when you wish such radical changes (ref, source section), I have now to edit one by one all the concerned ref, which will take me about one hours, to don't revert your copyedits. XD [[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 11:08, 9 June 2009 (UTC)

:''Move from Yug's talkpage:''
:Please note that footnotes are generally preferred to whole article references on Wikipedia, as are wholly self-contained inline citations, hence why I significantly tweaked the referencing in the article and reverted your recent edits which undid my edits. Note that no references were deleted or substantively altered through my initial edits, and that the changes were quite labor-intensive to do. --[[User:Cybercobra|Cybercobra]] ([[User talk:Cybercobra|talk]]) 12:41, 9 June 2009 (UTC)
::As previously explain, I noticed your work, and manage slowly to keep all your copy edits. I prefer the former ref system, which is use in other articles (FA Song dynasty), and which ease my edit/redaction work. Later ref changes are also planed. [[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 12:52, 9 June 2009 (UTC)
::In short, the new ref system add confusion to the wiki text and the sources section. I also made some improvement (ref IMF), and correction (ref CB5). [[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 12:58, 9 June 2009 (UTC)
:::The editability of wiki markup for new users should not be a direct concern of editors; we have little impact on it anyway (compared to what the usability team could do) and mere simplicity of markup is no reason to use a nonstandard (or at least significantly less popular) referencing scheme. I would welcome a third opinion though, to help ensure I'm not off base on this. With regards to why I did not bring it up on the talkpage before making the changes, I considered the changes minor as they did not substantively effect content and they helped bring the page more into line with usual Wikipedia practice. Also, no one [[WP:OWN]]s articles, so strictly speaking, permission isn't required (I didn't expect this to be controversial or contentious). --[[User:Cybercobra|Cybercobra]] ([[User talk:Cybercobra|talk]]) 13:02, 9 June 2009 (UTC)
:::If anything, I made the references less confusing, as clicking the ref link would take one directly to a full citation without having to lookup the abbreviation in the list at the end. Again, would appreciate third opinion on this. --[[User:Cybercobra|Cybercobra]] ([[User talk:Cybercobra|talk]]) 13:02, 9 June 2009 (UTC)
::I put my work on wiki, so share the edit work is clearly ok. I notice that's I'm still deeply involve in this article redaction, and such ref scheme change, as well as source section change are perturbing, while I don't see the benefice of the new ref scheme. As I said, the page is still under construction (rewording, adding, deleting). This ref changes confuse the situation, give no benefice, and take us energy better to spend into rewording, data/source improvement and copyedit. The  [[History_of_the_Song_Dynasty#Notes]] being a FA article, I guess that such ref system is ok. That's what I look for : notes on one section, book-webbook in an other. [[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 13:18, 9 June 2009 (UTC)
}}
:After several days looking carefully at the Ref section and system in other articles, I understood what Cybercobra was actually doing, and that it's indeed a commonly use and also efficient ref system. (see my mid-apologizes on [[User talk:Cybercobra|talk]]). Accordingly, the system of ref should be rework in this way. So, need to :
:－ replace &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;ref&gt;CES, p8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;, by the more academic &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Zha Daojiong, 2005, p8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt; (Cambridge style) ;
:－ sources uses just some few time : include the {source|} template in the first &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt; balise.
[[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 21:52, 28 July 2009 (UTC)

==Help==
Does this article still need copy-editing? Many edits have already been made, apparently, but I believe that this article still needs a lot of work, since it is barely legible in many cases (to me, at least). If yes, please help, Yug! As I have already said, I can hardly understand some sections, and I don't want to change what you had wanted to say, since I understand nothing about the subject. [[User:KingOfFruit|KingOfFruit]] ([[User talk:KingOfFruit|talk]]) 01:31, 7 September 2009 (UTC)

Yes. I don't know enough about this topic to do so, but, attempting to read it, much of the &quot;English&quot; is barely even understandable (and some of it just plain isn't understandable). I've tried to take remove uncited statements that seem randomly inserted, but someone keeps putting them back.[[Special:Contributions/118.71.10.95|118.71.10.95]] ([[User talk:118.71.10.95|talk]]) 10:04, 15 September 2009 (UTC)
:Uncited statements don't have to be remove. False statements have to be remove.
:Some time, I just lost the source of some statements.
:Wow... I didn't knew my English was that's bad XD I guess it's link to the level of complexity of this article. It's, indeed, my first 'expert article' write in English. Issues, concepts are complex, this vocabulary is specific and pretty fresh for me. That make the full harder to write down clearly. ... *sad* [[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 03:35, 9 November 2009 (UTC)

== What horrible writing ==

Judging by the quality of the English in this article, I think it's safe to say that it was a Sino-African collaboration. --[[Special:Contributions/75.155.166.155|75.155.166.155]] ([[User talk:75.155.166.155|talk]]) 06:18, 10 November 2009 (UTC)
:Nope, French-English collaboration, by people who are strong enough to want improve things, not just make random attacks ([[User talk:75.155.166.155|which seems to be your level of contribution]]). Not yet perfect. Help still welcome :) --[[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 07:33, 10 November 2009 (UTC)
::I agree with the quality of English in this. It's a superb article, but was clearly written by somebody with a poor grasp on the language. I'd edit it, but I don't want to muck up the article as I know nothing but Sino-African relations! :)  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/216.75.189.205|216.75.189.205]] ([[User talk:216.75.189.205|talk]]) 01:34, 13 November 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== WTO China section: recent cuts==
:[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Involvement_of_the_People%27s_Republic_of_China_in_Africa&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=324900117&amp;oldid=324784232 Some content deletions]
To Onopearls: I understand the motivation, but I find it too harsh. Process are lost. Such the important association of diaspora, ambassy, low cost goods for the fast 90's turn toward market integration. But, I guess, you are not wrong neither, the section was too specific and long. I will just add back some general ideas/concepts, '''not''' specific case. ;) --[[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 07:33, 10 November 2009 (UTC)


This article is very biased  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/202.58.161.222|202.58.161.222]] ([[User talk:202.58.161.222|talk]]) 16:01, 10 November 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Thanks for your opinion-comments: What a beautiful argumentation and research! =&gt; Thanks to don't wast my time. [[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 06:37, 8 May 2010 (UTC)

== Suggestions ==

I think I might like to help improve this article. My plan would be as follows:

1. Rearrange and combine the different sections, removing any redunant content (for example # 6.2.5 Corruption friendlyness could be combined with # 7 Limits)

2. Copyedit for spelling and grammar

3. Work on the references 

I'll try to retain as much content as possible and work through it step by step.

What does everyone else think? Should I be bold and start with editing immediately? [[User:Rtdixon86|Rtdixon86]] ([[User talk:Rtdixon86|talk]]) 19:15, 10 November 2009 (UTC)
:Perfectly welcome :] 
:Futher more, I note that some user added a &quot;merge&quot; template. My believe is the opposite: [[Sino-African relations]] and [[Involvement of the People's Republic of China in Africa]] are over lapping, and this should be undo. [[Sino-African relations]] should focus on diplomatic history, while Involvement[...] in Africa should keep the trade &amp; today-focus relate issues. [[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 12:35, 11 November 2009 (UTC)

::1. We could cut section 4 History of Sino-African relations to a summary and link to the other article we have on that subject. This would reduce the size of this article and make it easier to work with.
::2. The first three sections could be combined into an Introduction section.
::3. We could probably reduce the size of the Conclusion. 
::What do you think? [[User:Rtdixon86|Rtdixon86]] ([[User talk:Rtdixon86|talk]]) 20:38, 11 November 2009 (UTC)

== Article length &amp; coherence ==

Once improved, this will be a superb article. It has the information and sources, however it is obviously too long - there is such as thing as being too in-depth - and any person with even a passing fluency of English can tell that this article was not written by a native speaker. It is in need of several editors with a literate understanding of the English language to re-write it, as I did with the opening paragraph and several of the following ones. I will attempt to work on it, but it will be a massive undertaking for a single editor to get done in any short period of time. Anyone who can help, I urge them to do so! Wikipedia is made by editors working together to make articles great. Thanks, [[User:Onopearls|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color: silver&quot;&gt;Ono&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #92000a&quot;&gt;pearls&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Onopearls|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/Onopearls|c]])&lt;/sup&gt; 17:31, 25 June 2010 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Thanks Onopearls for your good will ! Yug --&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+ Progression, please take one section !
! Section level 2 (==) || {&lt;nowiki&gt;{I take|Name}&lt;/nowiki&gt;}/{&lt;nowiki&gt;{done}&lt;/nowiki&gt;}
|-
| 1 People's Republic of China &amp; 2 Africa || &lt;nowiki&gt;{{I take|yourName}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;
|-
| 3 Chinese diaspora and private projects || &lt;nowiki&gt;{{I take|yourName}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;
|-
|... || &lt;nowiki&gt;{{I take|yourName}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;
|}
:Covered the first six sections (level 2s), up to but not including 7. Macroeconomic and political strategy. Tons of relevant material to work with. I didn't look here first, so I might have duplicated someone else's section... [[User:Ocaasi|Ocaasi]] ([[User talk:Ocaasi|talk]]) 03:54, 2 July 2010 (UTC)

== Major cleanup ==

The article looks better through the first 6 sections.  The last 3 (macroeconomic and political strategy, criticism, and conclusion) is where length really becomes an issue.  It might be necessary to fork off part of that, incorporate it into the Sino-African relations article, or whittle it down to more of a single section summary of strategy/criticism.[[Special:Contributions/69.142.154.10|69.142.154.10]] ([[User talk:69.142.154.10|talk]]) 12:23, 3 July 2010 (UTC)
:I will manage the fork this summer. :] [[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 18:49, 4 July 2010 (UTC)
::Finished remaining parts of clean-up, including the last three sections.  It reads more easily now, thanks to a bunch of copy-editing and the excellent underlying research. I recommend double-checking the article for spelling errors, accidental bias, and general flow.  It might be close to good-article status and worth another peer review.  I no longer think the latter sections require forking, although it could be considered. [[Special:Contributions/69.142.154.10|69.142.154.10]] ([[User talk:69.142.154.10|talk]]) 09:54, 5 July 2010 (UTC)

== Africa Wikiproject Assesment==
After reviewing per request, I'm moving this up from C-class to B-class. I think this could get through GA. Some issues that would need to be addressed in order to get it up to A-class:

* The section &quot;Effects of the global economic downturn (2007 to the present)&quot; needs to be rewritten to remove the run-on sentences. 
* There a couple of citation needed tags on sections that need to be either sourced or removed. The one that bothers me the most is in &quot;Role of Chinese embassies&quot;.
* The &quot;Conclusion&quot; section need to be removed in my opinion. Why would an encyclopedia article have a conclusion? I think most of the information in this section needs to be rewritten to be NPOV, and should go in the Sino-African relations article.
* I found the references confusing. Are the works listed under further reading the same works that are in the footnotes? If so, further reading should be renamed to Bibliography, as the books and articles are being cited.
* I would tweak some of the formatting on the tables, so not to have two tables on one line. 

I don't know very much about the article's subject, but it is obvious a lot of good work has recently been put into this article. Again, I think this could be a GA even without the above issues being addressed. All of the above is just my opinion, and keep up the good work! :)--[[User:Banana04131|Banana]] ([[User talk:Banana04131|talk]]) 05:12, 7 July 2010 (UTC)

== Rename 2010 ==
&lt;div class=&quot;boilerplate&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #efe; margin: 2em 0 0 0; padding: 0 10px 0 10px; border: 1px dotted #aaa;&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Template:RM top --&gt;
:''The following discussion is an archived discussion of a [[WP:RM|requested move]]. &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on the talk page. No further edits should be made to this section. ''

The result of the move request was: '''not moved'''. I cannot discern consensus for any particular move. The intended scope of the article and whether it needs splitting or merging with [[Sino-African relations]] needs to be decided before a consensus for the title will emerge. [[User:Fences and windows|&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:white; color:red;&quot;&gt;Fences&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:white; color:#808080;&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;[[User talk:Fences and windows|&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:white; color:black;&quot;&gt;Windows&lt;/span&gt;]] 23:09, 29 July 2010 (UTC)

----


[[Involvement of the People&amp;#39;s Republic of China in Africa]] → [[Economic relations between China and Africa]] — I'd like to re-name this article. The new name is grammatically more clear and also more accurate. &lt;span style=&quot;font-size:smaller&quot;&gt;| Relisted [[user:billinghurst|billinghurst]] ''&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:smaller&quot;&gt;[[user talk:billinghurst|sDrewth]]&lt;/span&gt;'' 16:54, 16 July 2010 (UTC) |&lt;/span&gt;[[User:Ocaasi|Ocaasi]] ([[User talk:Ocaasi|talk]]) 12:34, 8 July 2010 (UTC)
*'''Oppose'''  The name is not more accurate.  The article only discusses the economic relations between the [[People's Republic of China]] and Africa.  There is no mention of economic relations between the [[Republic of China]] and Africa.  Perhaps a move to [[Economic relations between the People's Republic of China and Africa]] would be acceptable.  [[User:Skinsmoke|Skinsmoke]] ([[User talk:Skinsmoke|talk]]) 02:50, 9 July 2010 (UTC)
:*The biggest issue is to delimit the scope of the title to economics, since that is the predominant focus of the article. The geo-political semantics are important but were not the impetus for the move. 
:*There is a fairly extensive history section which addresses relations of China's dynasties as well as of pre-PRC governments. So, I'm not sure the name you suggested is an overall improvement, because while it accomplishes avoiding the suggestion that the ROC is somehow ''not'' China, it gives the impression that the article's focus is only on the PRC as opposed to the economic history of the region up through the PRC but not including Taiwan.  
:*What about using the suggested name but including a hatnote linking to [[Economic relations between Taiwan and Africa]]? I don't want to exclude or mistreat Taiwan, but the ROC has a completely different economic scope that for purposes of this article has almost nothing to do with mainland China. 
:*There are other options: People's Republic of China, China, China (excluding Taiwan), China (excluding the Republic of China), Mainland China, or some other configuration.
:*It's also worth mentioning that the name should fit the article, but the article can also grow/shrink/change to better suit whatever name is chosen. [[User:Ocaasi|Ocaasi]] ([[User talk:Ocaasi|talk]]) 05:22, 9 July 2010 (UTC)
*'''Support''' More accurate than current title, and as Ocaasi points out, the history section goes back to the Tang dynasty. --[[User:Cybercobra|&lt;b&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;3773A5&quot;&gt;Cyber&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;FFB521&quot;&gt;cobra&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Cybercobra|(talk)]] 06:53, 9 July 2010 (UTC)
*'''Barely Oppose''' -- I would support economic involvement of the PRC in Africa or something like that, but I don't think economic relations is the right title. I do agree that the new title is too vague for Wikipedia. [[User:Onopearls|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color: silver&quot;&gt;Ono&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #92000a&quot;&gt;pearls&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Onopearls|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/Onopearls|c]])&lt;/sup&gt; 07:09, 9 July 2010 (UTC)
:*Economic relations is the general, academic term to describe economic activity that goes on between two political entities, regardless of which one is the primary investor/importer or consumer/exporter.  I guess I'm not seeing the difference in emphasis between involvement and relations?  Does involvement emphasize the uni-directionality (China to Africa) of the relationship, since Africa isn't doing much investing inside of China?  
:*What would it take for the broader term to fit--added sections about African migration and investment on the mainland?  I'm just guessing there's not too much of it or that it wouldn't be hard to incorporate if the broader title was chosen. 
:*Also, [[Economic involvement of the People's Republic of China in Africa]] seems a bit ungainly if it can be avoided.[[User:Ocaasi|Ocaasi]] ([[User talk:Ocaasi|talk]]) 16:07, 9 July 2010 (UTC)

*'''Support''' per nom.  The current title is needlessly vague.  — &lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid blue;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User talk:AjaxSmack|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#fef;background:navy;&quot;&gt;''' AjaxSmack '''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 04:56, 10 July 2010 (UTC)\

I read around the debates on China/Taiwain/PRC/ROC and I think I was a little underinformed.  China is rarely used by itself to refer to the PRC, and it would be contentious to do so in this title. Mainland China as a term has its own history, and it is less contentious but also commonly used in articles as a redirect to a PRC-titled page.  Which seems to leave two options, that I'll recommend a quick vote on:

*'''PRC'''. Economic relations between the People's Republic of China and Africa
*'''mainland'''. Economic relations between mainland China and Africa

:[[User:Ocaasi|Ocaasi]] ([[User talk:Ocaasi|talk]]) 09:40, 13 July 2010 (UTC)

::The connotation that 'mainland' gives me is as contrasted to Hong Kong and Macao, and not necessarily just Taiwan. It's not in common use for this purpose (PRC as opposed to ROC) except in the Chinese political class. Excluding the Hong Kong and Macao as an oversight may be acceptable in some articles, but definitely not in economics related articles. [[User:Splittist|Splittist]] ([[User talk:Splittist|talk]]) 15:30, 13 July 2010 (UTC)

::: This is obviously not the case. Hong Kong and Macao are separate economies. The customs territory of the PRC, e.g., does not cover Hong Kong and Macao. [[Special:Contributions/112.118.162.227|112.118.162.227]] ([[User talk:112.118.162.227|talk]]) 13:10, 26 July 2010 (UTC)
*'''Vote PRC'''  Would support a move to [[Economic relations between the People's Republic of China and Africa]].  [[User:Skinsmoke|Skinsmoke]] ([[User talk:Skinsmoke|talk]]) 07:22, 14 July 2010 (UTC)

: Agree. [[Special:Contributions/112.118.162.227|112.118.162.227]] ([[User talk:112.118.162.227|talk]]) 13:10, 26 July 2010 (UTC)

:Comment.  There has been counter-proposals, and comments and move to confirm a consensus opinion would be appreciated.  At this stage there is no evidence of a consensus position. [[user:billinghurst|billinghurst]] ''&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:smaller&quot;&gt;[[user talk:billinghurst|sDrewth]]&lt;/span&gt;'' 16:54, 16 July 2010 (UTC)

'''Quick vote for consensus'''.  I believe there's reasonable consensus for the following: ''Economic relations between the People's Republic of China and Africa''. Briefly, it is more specific ('economic relations' over ' involvement'), and it does not take a POV on regional geopolitics ('P.R.C.' over 'China'); also, it is in line with  naming conventions about Chinese issues, which generally support using the names of actual governments when dealing with issues not merely geographical or cultural, and avoiding terms which might seem like taking sides in a political maelstrom.  While the shorter 'China' was tempting, it has been discussed before, and given the scope of the article, which mainly focuses on the P.R.C., would not be worth the ambiguity or potential for controversy.

*'''Support.''' [[User:Ocaasi|Ocaasi]] ([[User talk:Ocaasi|talk]]) 20:48, 16 July 2010 (UTC)
*'''Support'''  [[User:Skinsmoke|Skinsmoke]] ([[User talk:Skinsmoke|talk]]) 02:20, 17 July 2010 (UTC)
*It's better than the current title but I still prefer the move as proposed since it is more succinct and reflects the pre-1949 material in the article.  — &lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid blue;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User talk:AjaxSmack|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#fef;background:navy;&quot;&gt;''' AjaxSmack '''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 03:01, 18 July 2010 (UTC)
*'''Comment'''  Then I suggest that you expand the article to include the [[Republic of China]]'s involvement in Africa as well.  Unless you do (or split the pre-1949 into another article) ''China'' is simply unacceptable under the terms of the agreement Wikipedia reached on the ''China naming dispute''.  [[User:Skinsmoke|Skinsmoke]] ([[User talk:Skinsmoke|talk]]) 07:12, 18 July 2010 (UTC)
*'''Comment''' Expanding this article to include Taiwan could make it much longer.  It's already very long.  I'd prefer instead to create a new page called ''Economic relations between Taiwan (ROC) and Africa'', or something like that, and deal with the topic separately.  Perhaps they could be merged later once the articles are more refined. [[Special:Contributions/69.142.154.10|69.142.154.10]] ([[User talk:69.142.154.10|talk]]) 10:11, 18 July 2010 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''' I still don't think that the proposed name is the right one for this article, mainly because the article talks mainly about the PRC's overall involvement in Africa, not about economic relations. See [[Sino-African relations]]. [[User:Onopearls|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color: silver&quot;&gt;Ono&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #92000a&quot;&gt;pearls&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Onopearls|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/Onopearls|c]])&lt;/sup&gt; 22:43, 18 July 2010 (UTC)
*'''Comment''' It's ridiculous that we're worrying about the ''name'' of the article when it is in such terrible shape. We should be discussing how to best go about fixing it instead of quarreling over the name, which can be decided at any point. Thanks, [[User:Onopearls|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color: silver&quot;&gt;Ono&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #92000a&quot;&gt;pearls&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Onopearls|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/Onopearls|c]])&lt;/sup&gt; 22:43, 18 July 2010 (UTC)
* '''Sceptical''': this article is about &quot;Chinese... involvement... in Africa&quot;, including economic (mainly), friendship/ideologic, and diplomatic. &lt;br /&gt;Not only economic: The Oil issue is, by example, more strategic, energetic, than economic. Same for arms sales, such in the case of the Chad's coup, and for the section #Macroeconomic and political strategy, which is mainly diplomatic/ideologic.&lt;br /&gt;Not only PRC: I don't like PRC because PRC softly lock to 1949-today (90% of the article), to PRC's gov, and PRC citizens, while a large part of this story is wrote down by Africans born Chinese, or Taiwaneses. But let's be ok for this one.&lt;br /&gt;In Africa (involvement &gt;&gt; relations): There is almost nothing about 'Africa in China'. Accordingly, we are not talking about relations (the both places), but about involvement of the first (China) in the second (Africa)'s land. &lt;br /&gt;As it is now: I think '': Involvement_of_the_People's_Republic_of_China_in_Africa'', or '':Involvement_of_the_China_in_Africa'' are suitable names. A renaming likely means a split. [[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 02:37, 19 July 2010 (UTC)

'''No consensus. Just leave it.''' Ok, I started this just to give polish to the recent article cleanup.  It doesn't matter much in practice and clearly steps on complicated issues.  So, just leave it as was, if that's ok (seems the likely outcome now anyway).  More work on the article will bring the content in line with the title (or vice/versa). [[User:Ocaasi|Ocaasi]] ([[User talk:Ocaasi|talk]]) 05:35, 26 July 2010 (UTC)

*''' Oppose'''. This article is not just about economy.., but also political influences. [[Special:Contributions/112.118.162.227|112.118.162.227]] ([[User talk:112.118.162.227|talk]]) 13:10, 26 July 2010 (UTC)
:''The above discussion is preserved as an archive of a [[WP:RM|requested move]].  &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on this talk page. No further edits should be made to this section.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- Template:RM bottom --&gt;

== Cooling of Ango-Chinese relations ==
* [http://groups.google.com/group/ChinaAfrica/browse_thread/thread/e748d259c90fcf62 Hostility Toward Workers Cools Angola-China Relationship ]
Really interesting. Many informations. I encourage you to read it. [[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 18:10, 17 August 2010 (UTC)
:Thanks for the link.  This is good, and a very realistic view, whereas even with the criticism this article paints a generally very positive picture of trade.  Can we integrate it? [[User:Ocaasi|Ocaasi]] ([[User talk:Ocaasi|talk]]) 02:44, 26 September 2010 (UTC)

== 3 Questions ==

I recently split the conclusion and combined it into the 'Political Background' section as an 'Incentives for Cooperation' subsection and the other half into the 'Macroeconomic and Political Strategy' section.  

1) Does that work?  Does it need further integration?

2) Should the 'Political Background' section be merged into the 'Overview of Trade'?  They're currently sections 1 and 3, with the history section inbetween.  It seems like they should be grouped together and come ''after'' the History section. Thoughts?

3) Assuming all of these recent changes, is the article ready for a formal peer review or GA review?

[[User:Ocaasi|Ocaasi]] ([[User talk:Ocaasi|talk]]) 02:43, 26 September 2010 (UTC)

== Wikileaks cables reveal U.S. attitudes towards Chinese involvement in Africa ==

Haven't had a chance to look through these yet:

* WikiLeaks cables: China's aid to Africa has strings attached  Leaked US embassy cables show African governments like dealing with China. But they shouldn't forget that China's interest in Africa is driven by foreign policy and commercial objectives http://www.guardian.co.uk/global-development/poverty-matters/2010/dec/10/wikileaks-cables-china-aid-africa

* US diplomats suspect China's growing role in Africa is not altruistic but economic, according to secret memos published on Wikileaks.  The cables from a senior American official in Nigeria describe China as &quot;aggressive and pernicious&quot;, and that &quot;China is in Africa primarily for China&quot;. http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-11955697

* Newly leaked U.S. diplomatic cables published by WikiLeaks show senior U.S. officials in Africa were highly critical of China's economic policies on the continent and made sometimes embarrassing comments about African leaders and crises. The revelations have angered U.S. officials who say they are illegal and dangerous. http://www.voanews.com/english/news/africa/US-Diplomat-China-Displays-No-Morals-in-Africa--111594489.html

More from [http://www.google.com/#q=wikileaks+china+africa&amp;hl=en&amp;prmd=ivnu&amp;source=univ&amp;tbs=nws:1&amp;tbo=u&amp;ei=lw4CTcKCMsT_lgfl4-GCCA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=news_group&amp;ct=title&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CDIQqAIwAA&amp;fp=46a3aa67685d478a google news] [[User:Ocaasi|Ocaasi]] ([[User talk:Ocaasi|talk]]) 11:28, 10 December 2010 (UTC)

&lt;nowiki&gt;Insert non-formatted text here&lt;/nowiki&gt;
== Article ==

This looks like it may be useful.  It's in JSTOR: ''Red Star, Black Gold'' http://www.jstor.org/pss/4007084 [[User talk:Ocaasi|Ocaasi]] &lt;sup&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Ocaasi|c]]&lt;/sup&gt; 08:43, 18 April 2011 (UTC)

== Reference system: upgrate to harvard style ==
Hello, the reference system need a serious upgrade. Currently, the &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt; cite a code (ex: ABD), which itself refer to a source (ex: Africa’s Business and Development, 2007, ....).
It need a more serious reference system.
{| class=&quot;wikitable right&quot;
|+ Replacement
! || Sections || current/former || new/next
|-
| {{in progress}} || #Source section || incomplete and depressed &lt;nowiki&gt;{{Cite book|blabla}}&lt;/nowiki&gt; || completed &amp; anchor friendly &lt;nowiki&gt;{{citation|last=|first=|title=|year=}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;
|-
| not ready || Article || &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ABD, p28&quot;&gt;ABD, p28/ref&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;br /&gt;|| &lt;nowiki&gt;({{Harvnb|AuthorLastName|YYYY|p=pages}})&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
|-
| colspan=4|
China is trading with Africa ({{harvnb|Marafa|2007|p=27}})
* ABD : {{citation|title=Africa’s Business and Development Relationship with China: Seeking Moral and Capital Values of the Last Economic Frontier|url=http://www.afdb.org/fileadmin/uploads/afdb/Documents/Knowledge/25040356-FR-CHINA-AFRICA-AFRICAN-ECONOMIC-CONFERENCE2007-MARAFAL.PDF|last=Marafa|first=L. M.|university=Chinese University of Hong Kong, Department of Geography and Resource Management|year=2007|date=Nov. 15|publisher=2007 African Economic UN Conference|place=Addis Ababa, Ethiopia|pages=28}}
|}
[[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 13:32, 6 March 2012 (UTC)
* FIRST STEP: #Reference / #Sources sections largely upgraded to {citation} {{done}}
** 2 citations incomplete : EXIM, + APG.
** Bugs: The parameter &quot;date=&quot; where I putted the month and day seems to override &quot;year=&quot;
*** Explanation: Should be either just |year=YYYY, either |date=YYYY, Month day, and the template extract automatically the year YYYY from the date.
I have to go, help welcome.
[[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 14:26, 6 March 2012 (UTC)

== Requested move 2012 ==
&lt;div class=&quot;boilerplate&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #efe; margin: 2em 0 0 0; padding: 0 10px 0 10px; border: 1px dotted #aaa;&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Template:RM top --&gt;
:''The following discussion is an archived discussion of a [[WP:RM|requested move]]. &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on the talk page. No further edits should be made to this section. ''

The result of the move request was: '''moved'''. There is also consensus that [[Sino-African relations]] should be merged into this article, but that does not require an admin. If merging, please follow the instructions at [[WP:MERGE]]. [[User:Jenks24|Jenks24]] ([[User talk:Jenks24|talk]]) 22:14, 10 June 2012 (UTC)

----


[[Involvement of the People's Republic of China in Africa]] → {{no redirect|1=Africa&amp;ndash;China relations}} – This being a more standard title for Wikipeida relations articles. As per Wikipedia consensus &quot;[[China]]&quot; has replaced the &quot;People's Republic of China&quot;. The current title is POV by only assuming a one-sided relationship. There is also the [[Sino-African relations]] article but that article should  properly handle issues such as the history before the creation of the People's Republic of China and the Republic of China.[[User:Acadēmica Orientālis|Academica Orientalis]] ([[User talk:Acadēmica Orientālis|talk]]) 15:51, 26 May 2012 (UTC)
:This talk already occured. The two topics are differents.
:* Africa⇔China relations
::* China IN Africa (China⇒Africa) : see [[Involvement_of_the_People%27s_Republic_of_China_in_Africa]]
::* Africa IN China (Africa⇒China) 
:[[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 12:57, 27 May 2012 (UTC)
::The usual practice for relations articles to is deal with both relationships in the same article. See for example [[Africa–India relations]], [[United States–European Union relations]], [[India–United States relations]], [[China–India relations]], and so on. [[User:Acadēmica Orientālis|Academica Orientalis]] ([[User talk:Acadēmica Orientālis|talk]]) 13:08, 27 May 2012 (UTC)
*'''Support'''. The common name main title is at China, so descriptive titles should correspond. [[User:Kauffner|Kauffner]] ([[User talk:Kauffner|talk]]) 00:41, 28 May 2012 (UTC)

*Having both [[Africa–China relations]] and [[Sino-African relations]] articles is ridiculous especially since 60+% of the two articles' coverage is duplicate.  Get rid of this [[WP:POVFORK|POV fork]] and [[WP:MERGE|merge]] the articles.  — [[User talk:AjaxSmack|&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid #000073;background:#4D4DA6;padding:2px;color:#F9FFFF;text-shadow:black 0.2em 0.2em 0.3em&quot;&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Georgia&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;'''AjaxSmack'''&amp;nbsp;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 04:40, 28 May 2012 (UTC)
:* We simply have nothing about Africa in China. Merge them will equal to have an unbalanced coverage of 90% of China IN Africa, under the uncorrectly equalitarian title of China-Africa relations. [[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 09:33, 28 May 2012 (UTC)
::*Africa is exporting many commodities to China and there has been an increasing number of African emigrants to China. Anyway, it is not the aim of Wikipedia relations articles to be the judge of who is the dominant partner and state that in the title.[[User:Acadēmica Orientālis|Academica Orientalis]] ([[User talk:Acadēmica Orientālis|talk]]) 12:05, 28 May 2012 (UTC)
:::* We have to match title and content. We don't have content on Africa IN China. If the content is about China IN Africa, we need a such specific title. Simply. [[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 22:29, 28 May 2012 (UTC)
::::We do not split relations articles into one for each side of the relationship. Obviously bilateral agreements and so on involve two parts. Exports go between two nations. For commodities the relationship is usually Africa⇒China and rarely China⇒Africa. Emigration goes in both directions. [[User:Acadēmica Orientālis|Academica Orientalis]] ([[User talk:Acadēmica Orientālis|talk]]) 10:40, 29 May 2012 (UTC)
:::::If we have enough content on a subpart, we do split articles. A merging will produce an article with 90% of its content IN African, except major content deletion. My 2 cents. [[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 20:09, 29 May 2012 (UTC)
::::::AO, merging IS possible. But the result will be hard to manage and balance. [[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 20:19, 29 May 2012 (UTC)
::::::I wrote this articles, I did the academic researches, reading +1000 pages of academic papers with a hand of key authors, that's an emerging field. On the other hand, resources on Africa IN China simply doesn't exist yet. In a merged article, insert &quot;Africa IN China&quot; facts/sources in these sections will be confusing for maintaining it ; while create parallels sections (History of Africa in China#Middle Age, XIX ; XXeme) will be hard or quite short since sources are really scarce, and unbalanced. If you think its manageable, just move on. (I recommand to merge into Involvement of the PRC in Africa since most of the content is here, then move with the history) [[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 20:19, 29 May 2012 (UTC)
:::::::See [[Wikipedia:Ownership of articles]]. [[User:Acadēmica Orientālis|Academica Orientalis]] ([[User talk:Acadēmica Orientālis|talk]]) 20:49, 29 May 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::hahaha !!! hey, I'am a retired editor, if you want to run and do the merge without the author opinion just go ahead. Do this merge well is a complex work [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3ASino-African_relations&amp;diff=297150806&amp;oldid=297150395 I planed but never had time to do]. If you want to merge the big into the small, it's ok too. [[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 21:01, 29 May 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::[[Wikipedia:How_to_fix_cut-and-paste_moves#Merging_page_histories_of_pages_with_many_revisions]] [[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 21:09, 29 May 2012 (UTC)
:&lt;s&gt;Skeptical&lt;/s&gt; Support: I just flied slowly over the article. It's mainly from the China IN Africa viewpoint, but still &quot;bilateral&quot;. Merge ok. [[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 20:40, 29 May 2012 (UTC)
::Oppose obviously. Again, all Wikipedia relations articles are symmetrical, including all other China and Africa relations articles. No reason to make Africa a special exception and claim that Africa has no influence on China. Bilateral agreements involve two partners. Not just China imposing demands on Africa. Immigration goes in both directions. And so on... [[User:Acadēmica Orientālis|Academica Orientalis]] ([[User talk:Acadēmica Orientālis|talk]]) 20:49, 29 May 2012 (UTC)
:::Sources are what they are, the field is not mature yet. If you have a way to do a good merge, move ahead, it's a wiki. [[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 21:09, 29 May 2012 (UTC)
::::I can do the merge. Am I correct in thinking that you no longer oppose a merge to the Sino-African article? [[User:Acadēmica Orientālis|Academica Orientalis]] ([[User talk:Acadēmica Orientālis|talk]]) 21:49, 29 May 2012 (UTC)
:::::As I said, I'm not really active on that field now. But I rather support your former proposal &quot;Involvement_of_the_People%27s_Republic_of_China_in_Africa =&gt; China-Africa relations + There is also the Sino-African relations article but that article should properly handle issues such as the history before the creation of the People's Republic of China and the Republic of China.&quot; This can be done by some sections moves both way. [[User:Yug|Yug]] [[User talk:Yug|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 13:22, 30 May 2012 (UTC)
:''The above discussion is preserved as an archive of a [[WP:RM|requested move]].  &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on this talk page. No further edits should be made to this section.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- Template:RM bottom --&gt;

== Merger proposal ==
{{discussion top|1=The result of this discussion was to merge and create subarticle for economic content.[[User:Acadēmica Orientālis|Academica Orientalis]] ([[User talk:Acadēmica Orientālis|talk]]) 03:09, 19 June 2012 (UTC)}}
I propose that the [[Sino-African]] article should be merged with this article. See the results of the above requested move. The two names obviously seem to refer to the same relations. A reason for having a separate Sino-African article may be to handle issues such as the history before the creation of the People's Republic of China and the Republic of China. However, the [[China]] article currently mentions all of the history of China and not just that of the People's Republic of China. [[User:Acadēmica Orientālis|Academica Orientalis]] ([[User talk:Acadēmica Orientālis|talk]]) 06:18, 11 June 2012 (UTC)
:You are right it is quite the same. We can change the title of  the Africa China relations article to a more relevant one. That article is more about the economic involvement of the [[PROC]] in Africa, for example; Economic relations between China and Africa or Chinese economic involvement in Africa, just some suggestions. But I don't think it is necessary to merge those two articles. They have actually the same title but different subjects. [[User:Runehelmet|Runehelmet]] ([[User talk:Runehelmet|talk]]) 20:42, 11 June 2012 (UTC)
::&quot;Sino–African relations&quot; should as a minimum be &quot;African–Sino relations&quot; instead. But &quot;Africa–China relations&quot; is IMO better. There may be enough space for a separate subarticle for economic relations which in that case should be called &quot;Africa–China economic relations&quot;. Such a subarticle is easily created after a merge in order to get rid of one of the two article with very similar names so I suggest we proceed with the merge and then create a new subarticle called &quot;Africa–China economic relations&quot;. [[User:Acadēmica Orientālis|Academica Orientalis]] ([[User talk:Acadēmica Orientālis|talk]]) 21:01, 11 June 2012 (UTC)
{{discussion bottom}}

==New sections==
I was interested in greatly expanding this article by going into the relations between each country and China.  Economic,political,cultural and so on.  I've already amassed 25 articles about China and Nigeria relations so I'd like to start there.  When I'm finished can I add it to this article or link it in some way, which would be better?  I'm looking for people to collaborate with so if anyone is interested get in touch with me and/or click on the google drive link on my talk page to see the collection of articles I have on this topic. Thanks [[User:Notgoingtotellyou|Notgoingtotellyou]] ([[User talk:Notgoingtotellyou|talk]]) 18:57, 28 December 2015 (UTC)

: Great work [[User:Notgoingtotellyou|Notgoingtotellyou]].  A great place to start with Sino-Nigerian relations would be the article page on [[China–Nigeria relations]] so I would suggest start with updating that with your amassed sources and then add a one paragraph section summarising it in this article.--[[User:Discott|Discott]] ([[User talk:Discott|talk]]) 14:43, 29 December 2015 (UTC)

I looked at the page for Nigeria china relations and it sure is short!! I already have enough sources to expand it 20 fold :-) I will do south Africa next so maybe we can collaborate on that one if you'd like.  I found a good website that includes all of africa's academic journals if you'd be interested and you can search for any article you'd like.  It's at www.ajol.info.  Another association that has many Africa articles is http://www.chinaafricarealstory.com/.  Nellco.org is also a great site to search for academic journal articles.  I posted my offer to collaborate 5 days ago on the Wiki China page and you are the first person to respond.  Is there not much traffic on the Wiki China page or are people just not interested in collaborating with me? Thanks [[User:Notgoingtotellyou|Notgoingtotellyou]] ([[User talk:Notgoingtotellyou|talk]]) 22:34, 29 December 2015 (UTC)
 
Would you like to collaborate on the Nigeria article? This is my first time writing in 2 years and I've never written such a long detailed article before.[[User:Notgoingtotellyou|Notgoingtotellyou]] ([[User talk:Notgoingtotellyou|talk]]) 09:38, 30 December 2015 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:2|one external link|2 external links}} on [[Africa–China relations]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=702040728 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20090303164611/http://www.bangorschools.net:80/hs/SR/IbnBattutta.html to http://www.bangorschools.net/hs/SR/IbnBattutta.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20090624051028/http://www.csmonitor.com:80/centennial/timeline/2008/07/china-boosts-african-economies-offering-a-second-opportunity/ to http://www.csmonitor.com/centennial/timeline/2008/07/china-boosts-african-economies-offering-a-second-opportunity/

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=true}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 02:03, 28 January 2016 (UTC)

==Assessment comment==
{{Substituted comment|length=146|lastedit=20120610220939|comment=Fail point 4 'The article is reasonably well-written' to be set on B class article. The 5 others B class point are ok. (10:09, 28 July 2009 (UTC))|correctarchive=yes}}
Substituted at 04:55, 23 March 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:2|one external link|2 external links}} on [[Africa–China relations]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=742695129 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20130508162350/http://ke.china-embassy.org/eng/sbgx/t202741.htm to http://ke.china-embassy.org/eng/sbgx/t202741.htm
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20090228140945/https://www.globalpost.com:80/dispatch/china-and-its-neighbors/090219/chinas-little-africa-under-pressure to http://www.globalpost.com/dispatch/china-and-its-neighbors/090219/chinas-little-africa-under-pressure

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 06:38, 5 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>mebqdiitbo864p20thih5pxtl5o8sh4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
