<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Capernaum</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2806047</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749481046</id>
      <parentid>635859884</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-14T15:44:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot (v1.2.7.1)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8030">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Israel
|class=C
|importance=low
}}
{{WikiProject Palestine
|class=C
|importance=low
}}
{{WikiProject Archaeology
|class=C
|importance=low
}}
}}
{{reqmapin|Israel}}
{{SPATRAnom}}

== &quot;casa de San Pedro&quot; ==

&quot;During this phase, the major discovery was the ''casa de San Pedro'', a neighborhood of the town from the evangelical era&quot;: is there any reason that this phrase ''&quot;casa de San Pedro&quot;'' has been left in Spanish, rather than just translated as &quot;Saint Peter's house&quot;? Also is it possible that there is an error in the Spanish original here, because ''casa de San Pedro'' seems an unlikely name for a neighborhood. -- [[User:Jmabel|Jmabel]] | [[User talk:Jmabel|Talk]] 03:23, 4 October 2005 (UTC)
: The German-language article says that this is the name of a house, not a neighborhood. -- [[User:Jmabel|Jmabel]] | [[User talk:Jmabel|Talk]] 03:27, 4 October 2005 (UTC)

==Neutral Point of View?==
There is no way that this article shows a neutral point of view. It talks about the house of Peter(reported in 100+ AD) was venerated having been sanctified by the presence of Jesus??? This isn't a neutral encyclopedia type statement. The articles arn't a soapbox. [[User:Johnor|Johnor]] 08:01, 31 January 2006 (UTC)

So... The obvious question (since this was translated from a poorly cited Spanish language article): is there independent citation for this being the actual house of St. Peter, rather than just one with the appropriate architecture that has been designated as such? - [[User:Jmabel|Jmabel]] | [[User talk:Jmabel|Talk]] 08:03, 29 January 2006 (UTC)

FWIW [http://israelvisit.co.il/KfarNahum.htm this page] on a site that seems, in general, to have a Jewish rather than a Christian POV, says &quot;Tradition holds that this was Peter’s house. It served as a meeting place for believers during Christianity’s formative years. One hundred thirty-one inscriptions in Greek, Aramaic, Syrian, and Latin, many including Jesus’s name, were discovered in the plaster.&quot; So it seems clear that it was an Early Christian place of worship; the question is whether it was Peter's actual house. - [[User:Jmabel|Jmabel]] | [[User talk:Jmabel|Talk]] 08:09, 29 January 2006 (UTC)

Ok that is a valid point, but why would the 'sanctified by the presence of Jesus' stand as it is now still written whether it was Peter's house or not? [[User:Johnor|Johnor]] 08:11, 31 January 2006 (UTC)

My apologies, friends.  I voted for the Spanish Translation designation last October with a promise to provide references for the articles and to &quot;neutralize&quot; (is that actually the right word?) the POV.  Events overtook me, and so I'm only now getting back to the task.  Sorry I missed the translation phase: I've caught a couple of technical terms that make better sense (in English) now that they're not straight translations from the Spanish.  As for the POV: I'm working to document the objections to the Franciscan claims regarding what they call the &quot;Sacra Insula&quot; -- it's most interesting that this has ''always'' been &quot;Insula 1&quot; on their maps from the earliest days -- and I think that when the objections are included and referenced, the POV will become much more N than before.  I did a class presentation on this site a year ago, so I'm more primed than usual on this topic.  The class focused on First Century CE, though, so I hope I can remember more of the Byzantine and Arab periods from the Orthodox side of the big fence.  We're always so focused on the religious matters that we don't pay any attention to a very interesting little village that lasted centuries after the years of Jewish / Christian origins.  Have patience with this article, though.  It didn't do a bad job (it is certainly miles better than the original English article), and it shouldn't be that hard to redeem.  --[[User:KJPurscell|KJPurscell]] 10:21, 1 February 2006 (UTC)

: There, I think I've got it.  Hope the POV is a little more under control and the references clear.  --[[User:KJPurscell|KJPurscell]] 00:28, 3 February 2006 (UTC)

== Capharnaum / Cafarnaum ==

I originally did not find this wikipedia article, because this town is commonly referred to as Capharnaum / Cafarnaum in other languages, not Capernaum. Perhaps a redirect for Capharnaum/Cafarnaum could be created?

An entertaining aside:
: I've been trying to unravel a small mystery: the word is commonly used to describe a place of that is in chaos or disorder in French. Example: &quot;Ce chambre est un Cafarnaüm!&quot;. Maybe it's just used as a colorful replacement for the word &lt;i&gt;fouille&lt;/i&gt; (archaeological excavation) http://fr.wiktionary.org/wiki/capharna%C3%BCm
--[[User:Cnadolski|Cnadolski]] 22:06, 2 November 2006 (UTC)


== comment moved from article ==
In this side you show only the catholic church but you must know that beside this church and beside the same place ,it is a beautiful greek orthodox church , place for pray and silence &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Joseflittman|Joseflittman]] ([[User talk:Joseflittman|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Joseflittman|contribs]]) 7 February 2007&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

== Church of the Seven Apostles ==

Can someone familiar with the subject please link the orphan [[Church of the Seven Apostles]] somewhere in this article? —[[User:Ynhockey|Ynhockey]] &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Ynhockey|Talk]])&lt;/sup&gt; 23:20, 26 February 2011 (UTC)

== Mosaic uncovered 1991 pictures the image written in John's Revelation--woman bearing child as dragon waits to devour it. ==

I visited Capernaum in 1991 and was entranced by the synagogue there.  My wife and I both witnessed the partially uncovered floor mosaic that seemed to depict the Woman-child-dragon motif which is found in written description in the Christian book of Revelation of St.John.  I have searched for years for some mention of this mosaic, its place in a synagogue, and its meaning in a Jewish setting.  It puzzles me that the record is blank.  As a Jew it makes perfect sense to me that this was a Jewish symbolism indicating the dangers to Israel and to any Messiah who might come in that era of uneasy relations with Christianity in Roman Palestine.  Has anyone else seen the mosaic?  What do you make of it...and of the absence of reporting of it?

Bruce Cassler  bcass05@gmail.com  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.181.247.25|24.181.247.25]] ([[User talk:24.181.247.25|talk]]) 14:19, 22 July 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Pronunciation ==

Could someone please check the pronunciation showing &quot;Capernaum (kə-PUR-nee-əm); is NAU rendered as NEE? [[User:Mannanan51|Mannanan51]] ([[User talk:Mannanan51|talk]]) 05:15, 29 November 2014 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Capernaum]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=749481045 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070304080302/http://www.sacred-destinations.com:80/israel/capernaum-photos/index.htm to http://www.sacred-destinations.com/israel/capernaum-photos/index.htm

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 15:44, 14 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>92xz713gdnayvbqz9vxxj8alspjpsfb</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
