<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Rwandan Revolution</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>29235639</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738172663</id>
      <parentid>737894935</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-07T10:39:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Amakuru</username>
        <id>985645</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* 1958 attempt to marginalise Rudahigwa */ re</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9819">{{GA|06:41, 13 March 2015 (UTC)|topic=History|page=1|oldid=651159850}}
{{oldpeerreview|archive=1}}
{{Talk header}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Africa |Rwanda=yes|class =GA| importance =mid | Rwanda-importance = high}}
{{WikiProject Belgium|class=GA|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Colonial Empires|class=GA|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject History|class=GA|importance=low}}
}}
{{GOCE|user=Miniapolis|date=7 March 2015}}
{{dyktalk|20 March|2015|entry= ... that 336,000 [[Tutsi]] fled [[Rwanda]] during the '''[[Rwandan Revolution]]'''?}}

==Review==
*[[Wikipedia:Canada Education Program/Courses/The World since 1789 (Stéphane-D. Perreault)/Articles]]

It was required that on November 15th we were to have posted our draft articles up to be peer reviewed. There is no recent editing on this article at all so doing the whole peer review thing is kind of difficult but here is what I came up with, I hope it helps and good luck!

The first thing I would like to note is that the article does not have anywhere near the word requirements, but once it is started on, that will obviously improve. I believe it is quality, not quantity. Don’t just go on about something irrelevant to the article to reach the word count, staying on topic is key at this point. It is not thorough enough to be a reliable source for any reader yet, but once again, that will be improved once there are changes made. For the amount of information in the article at this point in time, the amount of references is sufficient but as the article grows, more will need to be added along with the information. It would be a good idea to add in headings to organize the article a little more and to help the readers navigate to where they want to be. I would suggest playing around with the formulas on changing the font, making headings and adding links in your sandbox. I found it really helped me and after a short while I was capable of doing the formulas on my own without even looking at the former examples. Another thing I found very helpful was when I found something important like a name or a date, I made sure it was correct by looking at another source and comparing the two. It would be nice to see more information regarding who was involved, who was in charge, the exact location, more detail on the battle itself, the cause of the battle, the aftermath, and as much background information as you could possibly find. When you are putting in the information however, be careful that you do not plagiarize. Reference things and give credit to those who deserve it! Try not to be bias in the article, it will not look very good for you when people read it. Research is very important, the more information you can get to describe the topic, the better. You can never have too many facts.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Molenchuk|Molenchuk]] ([[User talk:Molenchuk|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Molenchuk|contribs]]) 02:48, 20 November 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Removed edit==
I've been working myself to develop the article, and I can see someone else also wrote a considerable amount. His edit was deleted however. I'm not sure what the grounds were for deletion. Im restoring the edits by merging the existing and current article. It was sourced, and it doesnt seem that the content is untrue. I hope someone else will read the article and comment on the updates. [[User:Ottawakismet|Ottawakismet]] ([[User talk:Ottawakismet|talk]]) 16:43, 5 January 2013 (UTC)
*That edit was done by the sockpuppet of a banned user. It appears that account's edits were reverted per [[Wikipedia:Deny recognition]]. Please vet the content before you add it in to ensure there is no misinformation or [[WP:SNEAKY|sneaky vandalism]]. —[[User:Maclean25|maclean]] ([[User talk:Maclean25|talk]]) 19:13, 5 January 2013 (UTC)

== Work in progress ==

{{ping|Charles Essie}} - thanks for coming by and putting the tags on the top of the article, and just to let you know that I am actively working on this page at the moment. So far I've focussed on some of the background and prelude to the revolution, which has led to the lopsided structure in which the related fluff occupies more space than any commentary on the revolution itself. I very much hope that I will be able to rectify this over time, hopefully in the next couple of months. Thanks! &amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Amakuru|Amakuru]] ([[User talk:Amakuru|talk]]) 22:50, 9 January 2014 (UTC)

== Ruanda-Urundi ==

Before independence, to the best of my knowledge, the idea of Rwanda and Burundi did not exist - Ruanda and Urundi did! Would it not make sense to use terms which had contemporary meaning throughout the article? —''[[User:Brigade Piron|Brigade Piron]]'' ([[User talk:Brigade Piron|talk]]) 08:35, 8 March 2015 (UTC)
:Hi {{ping|Brigade Piron}}, I think this is really just a question of spelling and orthography. The terms &quot;Ruanda&quot; and &quot;Urundi&quot; were coined by Germany (I think) when they colonised, but were based on the precolonial names for the [[Kingdom of Rwanda]] and [[Kingdom of Burundi]]. The two words here are taken from the local languages. I doin't know how the colonies and their predecessors were known in English sources at the time (I haven't had access to many of those), but a majority of modern English sources do use &quot;Rwanda&quot; and &quot;Burundi&quot; when referring to the precolonial kingdoms. For example: [https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=rhsRrxZtJwMC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA7#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false]. I think a bit more explanation in the text might be in order though, I've noticed the term &quot;Ruanda-Urundi&quot; only appears as a main topic, not in the prose, that's something I'll look into clarifying. &amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Amakuru|Amakuru]] ([[User talk:Amakuru|talk]]) 10:18, 8 March 2015 (UTC)
::Thanks {{ping|Amakuru}}! Fantastic work on the article. —''[[User:Brigade Piron|Brigade Piron]]'' ([[User talk:Brigade Piron|talk]]) 10:21, 8 March 2015 (UTC)
:::Incidentally, I've made some cosmetic changes to the prose and added a picture. I hope you don't object! —''[[User:Brigade Piron|Brigade Piron]]'' ([[User talk:Brigade Piron|talk]]) 10:21, 8 March 2015 (UTC)
::::{{ping|Brigade Piron}} No, that's fine, thanks for assisting! I'm not quite sure about the RPF / FPR thing though... the books I have on the subject all call it &quot;Rwandan Patriotic Front&quot; (or &quot;Rwandese Patriotic Front&quot; in the case of the Gerard Prunier book), with the initials &quot;RPF&quot;. This is consistent with it being founded in an English speaking country, although confusingly [[:File:Rwandan_Patriotic_Front_Flag.png|the flag]] does spell it &quot;FPR&quot;, perhaps as a means of appealing more to the French speaking population in Rwanda at the time of the civil war. Anyway, more generally, I'm hoping to have a run at [[WP:GA]] with this shortly, and maybe then onto [[WP:FA]]. Do you think it's ready for that yet? Are there any sections that need expanding or changing, in your view? Thanks again! &amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Amakuru|Amakuru]] ([[User talk:Amakuru|talk]]) 10:32, 8 March 2015 (UTC)
:::::Yes, I don't think there should be any problem getting the article to GA without content change. I worry that it might be a bit cursory for FA though. Good luck! —''[[User:Brigade Piron|Brigade Piron]]'' ([[User talk:Brigade Piron|talk]]) 11:41, 8 March 2015 (UTC)
::::::{{ping|Brigade Piron}} yes, I see what you mean, looking at it now. I guess each of the subsections in the Revolution section could be expanded by a couple of paragraphs for completeness. Thakns &amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Amakuru|Amakuru]] ([[User talk:Amakuru|talk]]) 15:41, 8 March 2015 (UTC)

{{Talk:Rwandan Revolution/GA1}}

{{Template:Did you know nominations/Rwandan Revolution}}

== 1958 attempt to marginalise Rudahigwa ==

Anyone able to confirm this?

''In 1958 the Belgian colonial ministry tried to strip Rudahigwa of his power, reducing him to a figurehead,{{sfn|Linden|Linden|1977|p=257}} but his popularity with the regional chiefs and the Tutsi (who feared the growing Hutu movement) sparked a series of strikes and protests.{{sfn|Linden|Linden|1977|p=258}}''

Unfortunately, p.257 is missing from the preview, but although [https://books.google.co.nz/books?id=DgXoAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA258#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false p.258] mentions a strike, and a protest, it doesn't sound like they were because Tutsi chiefs were concerned about moves to marginalise Rudahigwa.

I've not seen mention elsewhere of the attempt to reduce the king to a figurehead in 1958.  [[User:Bromley86|Bromley86]] ([[User talk:Bromley86|talk]]) 23:27, 23 August 2016 (UTC)
:{{ping|Bromley86}} unfortunately I don't have that book to hand - I originally sourced those passages from a copy at the British Library two years ago. If I get the chance soon, I@ll go back and try to verify what it says. Thanks &amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Amakuru|Amakuru]] ([[User talk:Amakuru|talk]]) 17:39, 5 September 2016 (UTC)
::{{ping|Bromley86}} I've had a chance to look at the page in question now, and it is reproduced here: [http://tinypic.com/r/4rdef9/9]. The particular line in question says &quot;{{tq|Although the Belgians decided that Rudahigwa should 'reign and not rule', the decision was difficult to implement.}}&quot; This is cited to a G. Mosmans, who is also mentioned on the same page. Although the protests weren't directly about the attempt to sideline Rudahigwa, the Tutsi conservative movement apparently resulted from increasing hostility by the Belgian administration towards the king and the Tutsi court. If you think any of this is misrepresented in the article, pleae let me know. Thanks &amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Amakuru|Amakuru]] ([[User talk:Amakuru|talk]]) 10:39, 7 September 2016 (UTC)

{{reflist talk}}</text>
      <sha1>7k15snsc31xhr04lysn78473vqfbg5a</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
