<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>24074521</id>
    <revision>
      <id>702195471</id>
      <parentid>659467068</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-01-29T01:38:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cyberbot II</username>
        <id>16283967</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9090">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Environment|climate change=yes|class=B|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject New Zealand|class=A|importance=mid|politics=yes|politics-importance=mid}}
}}
{{archives}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
| algo                = old(365d)
| archive             = Talk:New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme/Archive %(counter)d
| counter             = 3
| maxarchivesize      = 70K
| archiveheader       = {{talk archive navigation}}
| minthreadstoarchive = 1
| minthreadsleft      = 5
}}

== Sector entry dates obligations and allocations table ==

Hi everyone!
I just wanted to check that this table in the article is correct. It says for a few sectors that the transitional cost in CP1 is &quot;One unit for two tonnes (50%) or fixed surrender price $NZ25/tonne&quot;, but my understanding is that the price is one unit for two tonnes '''AND''' a fixed surrender price, so a price of $12.50/tonne. That is what it seems to say at the beginning of the article at the summary: 

''&quot;A transition period will operate from 1 July 2010 until 31 December 2012. During this period the price of NZUs will be capped at NZ$25. Also, one unit will only need to be surrendered for every two tonnes of carbon dioxide equivalent emissions, effectively reducing the cost of emissions to NZ$12.50 per tonne (MfE 2009, second bullet point).&quot;''

Could someone clarify this? I've also bolded the titles in the table to make it easier to read. Cheers  [[User:Ballofstring|Ballofstring]] ([[User talk:Ballofstring|talk]]) 05:50, 12 May 2011 (UTC)

:Hi Ballofstring. You are right. It is one unit for two tonnes '''AND''' a fixed surrender price. See the second to last para of http://www.mfe.govt.nz/publications/climate/development-industrial-allocation-regulation-ets/page2.html 

:BTW Nice edits. Thanks for your contribution. [[User:Mrfebruary|Mrfebruary]] ([[User talk:Mrfebruary|talk]]) 06:54, 12 May 2011 (UTC)

Hi again, just wondering whether the fishing industry actually has any obligations under the ETS to surrender permits – don't they just get free permits to offset the increased fuel costs (i.e., they are not a point of obligation as the fuel they buy will already have been priced under the ETS?)? The introduction says the fishing industry is not a participant... so the table might be incorrect in that they don't have any obligation and will never have to purchase emissions permits? [[User:Ballofstring|Ballofstring]] ([[User talk:Ballofstring|talk]]) 07:19, 23 May 2011 (UTC)

:Hi Ballofstring. Yes well spotted. Fishing has no compliance obligations and is not a 'participant'. See footnote 1 http://www.climatechange.govt.nz/consultation/fishing-allocation/draft-fishing-allocation-plan/page1.html#_ftn1  So their 'allocation' of units is not a &quot;grandfathering&quot; nor based on &quot;output intensity&quot;. It is a  compensation payment. Also, adding 'reward' after obligation in the forestry row. I am not sure if that fits well. Still thinking about it. [[User:Mrfebruary|Mrfebruary]] ([[User talk:Mrfebruary|talk]]) 10:52, 23 May 2011 (UTC)

:: Hi Mrfebruary. Yeah I know what you mean, it is a bit clunky/doesn't really fit with the rest of the table. I just wanted to communicate the fact that the ETS can be both a reward and a punishment for the forestry industry depending on whether they cut down the trees or not (I don't completely understand the forestry obligations). It's probably simpler to remove the 'reward' bit... [[User:Ballofstring|Ballofstring]] ([[User talk:Ballofstring|talk]]) 06:32, 26 May 2011 (UTC)

:::Hi Ballofstring. I have mulled it over. I am thinking of having two rows in the table, one for pre-1990 forests, which are allocated a fixed number of units as compensation; and one for post 1989 (Kyoto) forests which may earn units to recognise sequestration of carbon. [[User:Mrfebruary|Mrfebruary]] ([[User talk:Mrfebruary|talk]]) 07:05, 26 May 2011 (UTC)

::::The changes you've done look good I think! [[User:Ballofstring|Ballofstring]] ([[User talk:Ballofstring|talk]]) 11:37, 28 May 2011 (UTC)

== Consistent styling ==

Hi {{ping|Mrfebruary}} just a quick note regarding referencing styles. As you've probably seen I've changed quite a few references to get rid of the vertical alignment. I did that because I think it looks way better/I wasn't aware that vertical alignment was an accepted style. But now that I've done some digging it looks as though vertical styling is acceptable. So sorry for coming to an article you've spent a lot of time on and changing the referencing style! My main questions is where we go from here – we should probably try and be consistent. So should we slowly transition (back) to a vertical alignment style?

(Another thing I've done is get rid of a whole lot of italics for quotes, as [[WP:MOSQUOTE]] seems to indicate that you don't need any formatting. Hope that's okay!) [[User:Ballofstring|Ballofstring]] ([[User talk:Ballofstring|talk]]) 07:43, 16 February 2015 (UTC)

:Hi Ballofstring. I don't have really strong views about 'vertical styling' of references. I think I used to do it so that when editing I could easily distinguish the article text from the reference text. Also no problem about the italics. [[User:Mrfebruary|Mrfebruary]] ([[User talk:Mrfebruary|talk]]) 08:21, 17 February 2015 (UTC)

::Hi! Okay if you don't have strong views, should we move to horizontal styling? Or we can stay with vertical – up to you! (By the way, if you're not aware of it [[User:Cacycle/wikEd|wikiEd]] is a really useful tool which highlights syntax and can get around the problem of refs getting mixed in with everything else.) [[User:Ballofstring|Ballofstring]] ([[User talk:Ballofstring|talk]]) 08:44, 17 February 2015 (UTC)

:::Yes, lets move to horizontal styling. No, I wasn't aware of wikiEd, but I'm now a convert![[User:Mrfebruary|Mrfebruary]] ([[User talk:Mrfebruary|talk]]) 08:31, 13 March 2015 (UTC)

== Effects of the ETS? ==

Hi all! Just wondering if it would be worth exploring the ''effects'' of the ETS. I.e. how the ETS has done nothing at all to reduce emissions because the price is too low. — Any thoughts? [[User:Ballofstring|Ballofstring]] ([[User talk:Ballofstring|talk]]) 07:47, 16 February 2015 (UTC)

:Yes, by all means! A section perhaps titled 'Effectiveness' or something similar? The recent Treasury Briefing to the Incoming Government and the Ministry for the Environment equivalent both mentioned the NZETS. And it's described in a 2014 World Bank report. I am also aware of a PhD on the NZETS. Simon Terry of the Sustainability Council has also written recently on current Government policy. I was also thinking that section titled &quot;Trading&quot; with year by year subtitles needs a rewrite. The subheadings should be topics not years, e.g. price movements, market size. [[User:Mrfebruary|Mrfebruary]] ([[User talk:Mrfebruary|talk]]) 08:30, 17 February 2015 (UTC)

::I have been thinking a bit more - of at least two sections or subsections; 'effects on prices' and 'effects on emissions'.[[User:Mrfebruary|Mrfebruary]] ([[User talk:Mrfebruary|talk]]) 08:53, 13 March 2015 (UTC)

== Tool for accessing archived pages ==

Hi! Considering there are quite a few links to old press releases and articles here that need an archive link, I just thought I'd share with you a trick I recently learnt (which you probably know about already). Basically the trick is to create a bookmark in your browser which you hit when you're at a dead page, and it then checks the web archive (archive.org) if they have that page. The link is
{{quote box|align=center|javascript:void(window.open('https://web.archive.org/web/*/'+location.href));}}
It is obscenely useful! See this [[Help:Using the Wayback Machine#JavaScript_bookmarklet| Wikipedia help page]] for more info. Cheers — [[User:Ballofstring|Ballofstring]] ([[User talk:Ballofstring|talk]]) 03:15, 19 February 2015 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=702195468 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20120929004136/http://www.3news.co.nz/Fonterra-vs-Greenpeace-The-debate-continues/tabid/572/articleID/130992/Default.aspx to http://www.3news.co.nz/Fonterra-vs-Greenpeace-The-debate-continues/tabid/572/articleID/130992/Default.aspx

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 01:38, 29 January 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>byztjhzw4259s73s4gw429rr688hdmo</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
