<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Palm Island, Queensland</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1218877</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749028453</id>
      <parentid>707437556</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-11T22:26:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot (v1.2.7.1)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26930"> 

{{WP Australia|QLD=yes|past-acotf=21 January - 4 February 2007|class=GA|importance=Mid|QLD-importance=Mid|Indigenous=yes|Indigenous-importance=high}}

{{WikiProject Geography| class=GA|importance=Low}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=PR
|action1date=11 April 2006
|action1link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Palm Island, Queensland/archive1
|action1oldid=47686070

|action2=GAN
|action2date=3 March 2007
|action2link=Talk:Palm Island, Queensland#GA passed
|action2result=listed
|action2oldid=112232554

|action3=PR
|action3date=15 September 2007
|action3link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Palm Island, Queensland/archive1
|action3oldid=157841748

|action4=GAR
|action4date=16 September 2007
|action4link=Talk:Palm Island, Queensland#GA Pass
|action4result=kept
|action4oldid=158186352

|action5=PR
|action5date=23 September 2007
|action5link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Palm Island, Queensland/archive1
|action5oldid=159614295

|action6=PR
|action6date=13:27, 31 December 2010
|action6link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Palm Island, Queensland/archive2
|action6result=reviewed
|action6oldid=405063304

|topic=Geography
|currentstatus=GA
}}
&lt;!-- please start a new peer review next time --&gt;
{{todo}}
{{Archivebox
|*[[/Archive 1]]
*[[/Archive 2|/Archive 2 (including acotf)]]
}}

==GA on hold==
The article has plenty of sources and images, however I have put the article on hold for seven days until the following suggestions are fixed and information is cited.
#Wikilink or further explain: &lt;s&gt;pneumonia, United States of America, malnutrition, fruit juice, strike,  superintendent, sexual abuse, slingshots, pub, autopsy, manslaughter, trout, crayfish, coral reefs, mangroves, mango, banana, pawpaw, wild plum trees, flash flood, sewage treatment plant, butcher, petrol, X-ray, ambulance, pharmacy, antenatal,&lt;/s&gt;
#&lt;s&gt;There seems to be a hard return between Kukamunburra remains returned &amp; 'Penal settlement' 1920s-60s; remove it.&lt;/s&gt; fixed
#&lt;s&gt;In the 'Penal settlement' 1920s-60s section, I'm not sure if Government is supposed to be capitalized in the third paragraph. If is, ignore this suggestion.&lt;/s&gt; Ignored
#&lt;s&gt;In the 'Penal settlement' 1920s-60s section again, a lot of the sentences begin with &quot;In 19xx&quot;; reword the statements to give them more variety.&lt;/s&gt; fixed
#&lt;s&gt;For the many instance of a full date (listing the month, day, &amp; year) wikilink it.&lt;/s&gt; fixed
#&lt;s&gt;&quot;A riot erupted.[21]&quot; Statement's a little short, see if you can add it to another sentence or elaborate on it.&lt;/s&gt; fixed
#&lt;s&gt;Add a period in the third paragraph after the last sentence in the Geography section.&lt;/s&gt; fixed
#&lt;s&gt;&quot;Cyclones As an island in North Queensland Palm Island is vulnerable to cyclones.&quot; Either remove the cyclones or make it a subheading (if you do make it a subheading, you should elaborate on the section more).&lt;/s&gt; fixed
#&lt;s&gt;Crayfish is one word in the Natural environment and cyclones section but in the economy section it's two words. Use the correct choice. Also in the economy section, put the second sentence in one of the other paragraphs or expand on it. Single sentences should not stand alone.&lt;/s&gt;fixed
#&lt;s&gt;Aquaculture is not capitalized.&lt;/s&gt; fixed
#&lt;s&gt;&quot;The farm is purported to have cost $20million. Put space between 20 and million.&lt;/s&gt; fixed
#&lt;s&gt;&quot;Palm Island has an extreme level of theft, domestic violence, sexual assaults against children and abject drunkenness, this behaviour is attributed to boredom, aimlessness, lack of education, absence of role models and a complete loss of self-worth.&quot; Break it up into two sentences and add inline citations.&lt;/s&gt; Fixed, move citations needed to below
#&lt;s&gt;&quot;The Justice group has a statutory role with the courts in administering justice[41] and is funded by the Queensland Government as a way of trying to keep indigenous children on Palm out of the criminal justice system, the program was created in response to the Royal Commission into Aboriginal Deaths in Custody.&quot; Split into two sentences.&lt;/s&gt;
#&lt;s&gt;&quot;In the three years after the Community Justice Group was established Palm Island juveniles appearing before magistrates courts fell by a third.&quot; Add comma after established and add inline citation.&lt;/s&gt; fixed
#&lt;s&gt;&quot;The Coolgaree nippers club is the first indigenous club in Surf Lifesaving Queensland, Coolgaree is affiliated to Arcadian surf lifesaving club in the first year of the nippers club operating (1999) juvenile crime rates on Palm Island dropped from 186 offences to 99.&quot; Use semicolon after Queenland.&lt;/s&gt; fixed
#&lt;s&gt;&quot;QC investigated alcohol abuse in indigenous communities and was shocked by the extent of the State-wide problem, he recommended to the Queensland Government that unless things improved dramatically within a period of three years than alcohol should be banned in consultation with the communities.&quot; Split into two sentences. Add inline citation.&lt;/s&gt;, Split, moved to citations
#&lt;s&gt;The Sports section should be epanded upon, look to other countries/cities for examples.&lt;/s&gt; added
#&lt;s&gt;&quot;The island has two schools; St Michael's Catholic School (Prep to grade 7) and the Bwgcolman Community School {Prep to Grade 10).&quot; Use colon after schools, and switch the { to a ( for Prep to Grade 10.&lt;/s&gt; fixed
#&lt;s&gt;&quot;In 2004 the army completed $10 million worth of work constructing roads and a permanent water-supply dam on the island.&quot; Add to another paragraph or elaborate, don't let it stand alone.&lt;/s&gt; fixed
**If any of my grammar suggestions are incorrect, it's because I'm going by American English, so please correct any suggestions according to Queensland English.

Add inline citations for:
*&lt;s&gt;The rest of the circus group carried on to the European leg of the tour, by the end of 1885 only three of the Murris were still alive.&lt;/s&gt;
*&lt;s&gt;The 55th Seabee Construction Battalion created a 1000 person camp and would house 12 flying boats and store 60,000 gallons of fuel and would repair an average of 4 aircraft per day. (Also change &quot;1000 person&quot; to &quot;1000-person&quot;. The statement should also be reworded or possibly broken up into two.)&lt;/s&gt; fixed, already cited
*&lt;s&gt;Zen Pearls Pty Ltd and Indian Pacific Pearls Pty Ltd (both controlled by Michael Crimp) established pearl farms in 1998 with the permission of the Great Barrier Reef Marine Park Authority (which controls the sea waters around the islands), despite the opposition of the people of Palm Island.&lt;/s&gt;
*&lt;s&gt;The Australian Army made a significant effort to clean up the island during 1997.&lt;/s&gt;
*&lt;s&gt;These restrictions include a limit of on.e carton of beer disembarking from the ferry service&lt;/s&gt;
*&lt;s&gt;Alcohol sales from the canteen are again restricted to one carton per person, or per vehicle.&lt;/s&gt;
*&lt;s&gt;However, there are various conflicting local estimates of the population size; up to 4,000 residents has been estimated with the most commonly used figure being 3,500.&lt;/s&gt; info changed and new sources added
*&lt;s&gt;In 1979 an outbreak of hepatoenteritis, known as the Palm Island mystery disease, was reported and described a hepatitis-like illness (associated in many cases with dehydration and bloody diarrhoea) in 138 children and 10 adults of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander descent.&lt;/s&gt;
*&lt;s&gt;Palm Island has an extreme level of theft, domestic violence, sexual assaults against children and abject drunkenness&lt;/s&gt;
*&lt;s&gt;This behaviour is attributed to boredom, aimlessness, lack of education, absence of role models and a complete loss of self-worth.&lt;/s&gt;
*&lt;s&gt;QC investigated alcohol abuse in indigenous communities and was shocked by the extent of the State-wide problem&lt;/s&gt;
*&lt;s&gt;He recommended to the Queensland Government that unless things improved dramatically within a period of three years than alcohol should be banned in consultation with the communities.&lt;/s&gt;
*&lt;s&gt;Palm Island community council relied on revenue generated by alcohol sales at the community canteen, the investigation report recommended this perceived conflict of interest end.&lt;/s&gt;

Fix these in seven days and I'll pass the article. If you don't think that you can complete these in time, let me know, and I'll fail it for now so you can renominate it later when the requested changes are fixed. Otherwise let me know when you finish or if you have any questions on my talk page. --[[User:Nehrams2020|Nehrams2020]] 05:46, 25 February 2007 (UTC)

==GA passed==
Excellent work on fixing all of the suggestions and adding citations. Make sure that all new information that is added to the article is sourced, helping the article keep its good quality. Keep looking to expand it and consider looking into FAC guidelines. As a side note, GAC currently has a large backlog that could use experienced editors' help. Even if you only rate one or two articles, that would be great. Keep up the good work, and continue to improve the article. --[[User:Nehrams2020|Nehrams2020]] 03:20, 3 March 2007 (UTC)

==New sub article==
The article is becoming too long and we will need to create some sub articles soon, obviously the History/Notable events section is the most dominant and ready to be moved to a new article and summarised for the main article.  This is not a task I'm looking forward to :) What do people think of [[History of Palm Island, Queensland]]?  [[User:WikiTownsvillian |Wiki]][[User talk:WikiTownsvillian|Townsvillia]][[Special:Contributions/WikiTownsvillian|n]] 09:08, 7 April 2007 (UTC)

:Hi WikiTownsvillian. I'm all for the split you are suggesting. But write the summary which will stay here, before you create the new article. [[User:GarrieIrons|Ga]][[User_talk:GarrieIrons|rr]][[Special:Contributions/GarrieIrons|ie]] 00:07, 23 April 2007 (UTC)

==move article==
What are people's thoughts about moving this article to [[Great Palm Island]] and redirect [[Palm Island, Queensland]], and [[Great Palm Island, Queensland]]?  ''Great Palm Island'' seems to be the official name while Palm Island is the commonly known name.  I use [http://www.parliament.qld.gov.au/PISC/view/committees/documents/PISC/reports/report.pdf this] document, page 1, as the source. I suggest dropping the &quot;Queensland&quot; as there is probably not another island called Great Palm Island. Thanks, [[User:WikiTownsvillian |Wiki]][[User talk:WikiTownsvillian|Townsvillia]][[Special:Contributions/WikiTownsvillian|n]] 09:05, 12 June 2007 (UTC)
:My intial thought is no, Palm Island is the commmon name and while Great Palm Island might be technically correct, isn't there a guideline to name articles by there most common usage?  --[[User:Stephen|&lt;b&gt;Steve&lt;/b&gt; &lt;sub&gt; (Stephen) &lt;/sub&gt;]][[User talk:Stephen|&lt;sup&gt; talk &lt;/sup&gt;]] 23:20, 12 June 2007 (UTC)
::I don't know actually, would be interested to find out, will look into it over the next day or two.  Thanks, [[User:WikiTownsvillian |Wiki]][[User talk:WikiTownsvillian|Townsvillia]][[Special:Contributions/WikiTownsvillian|n]] 23:54, 12 June 2007 (UTC)
:::[[Wikipedia:Naming conventions]].  &quot;Names of Wikipedia articles should be optimized for ... a general audience over specialists.&quot; --[[User:Stephen|&lt;b&gt;Steve&lt;/b&gt; &lt;sub&gt; (Stephen) &lt;/sub&gt;]][[User talk:Stephen|&lt;sup&gt; talk &lt;/sup&gt;]] 00:18, 13 June 2007 (UTC)
::::I was confused for a while that both the island and the settlement were called &quot;Palm Island&quot;.&amp;nbsp; My vote is to call this article &quot;Great Palm Island, Queensland&quot;.&amp;nbsp; That leaves room for another article about the settlement called &quot;Palm Island, Queensland&quot;.&amp;nbsp; Those names are consistent with the Google map.&amp;nbsp; But &quot;Great Palm Island&quot; works for me, too. [[User:Unscintillating|Unscintillating]] ([[User talk:Unscintillating|talk]]) 04:29, 30 December 2010 (UTC)
:::::I've created a new article [[Great Palm Island, Queensland]] as previously discussed here.  The new article only needed the &quot;Geography&quot; and the &quot;Natural Environment and Cyclones&quot; sections from the existing article, along with the island infobox, leaving all of the history here.  I'll be figuring out next how to redirect the existing [[Great Palm Island]] to the new article. BTW, reliable references including from the Australia government use the name &quot;Great Palm Island&quot; on maps for the name of the island. [[User:Unscintillating|Unscintillating]] ([[User talk:Unscintillating|talk]]) 04:44, 5 January 2011 (UTC)
:::::::The article on the island should be at [[Great Palm Island]]. Mandatory disambiguation is only inflicted on settlements and geographic features are spared and can use their common sense &quot;plain&quot; name, without appending the state at the end. Good work on the split but don't forget to fix this article to make it clear that this is about the settlement and '''not''' the island. -- [[User:Mattinbgn|Mattinbgn]] ([[User talk:Mattinbgn|talk]]) 05:08, 5 January 2011 (UTC)
{{od}}This wasn't about disambiguation, it was a style choice.&amp;nbsp; Being stateside, &quot;Great Palm Island&quot; may be globally unique, but it is also globally anonymous.&amp;nbsp; Adding the &quot;, Queensland&quot; is also consistent with &quot;Palm Island, Queensland&quot;.&amp;nbsp; But like I said earlier, &quot;Great Palm Island&quot; also works for me.  Thanks for supporting and moving the split forward, the lede was the tough part.&amp;nbsp; The bad news is that this split has only reduced the Article by 7K. [[User:Unscintillating|Unscintillating]] ([[User talk:Unscintillating|talk]]) 06:47, 6 January 2011 (UTC)

==New images==
Hi all, are there any suggestions as to how to go about getting as many of [[User:WikiTownsvillian/gallery#Palm_Island|these]] images in as possible? there's not many natural places to put them where they link to the text so do you think it would be alright to just spatter them across the article? Thanks, [[User:WikiTownsvillian |Wiki]][[User talk:WikiTownsvillian|Townsvillia]][[Special:Contributions/WikiTownsvillian|n]] 10:49, 20 July 2007 (UTC)

==Standardise Murri/Indigenous Australians/Aboriginals==
Hi all, what are your thoughts about standardising throughout the article how Indigenous Australians broadly in Queensland are referred to.  I would suggest that &quot;Murri&quot; or &quot;the Murri people&quot; would be the most appropriate, and in the lead when it is first mentioned put in brackets: (otherwise known as Indigenous Australians or Aboriginals and Torres Strait Islanders).  What do people think?  [[User:WikiTownsvillian |Wiki]][[User talk:WikiTownsvillian|Townsvillia]][[Special:Contributions/WikiTownsvillian|n]] 10:37, 16 September 2007 (UTC)

==GA Pass==
This article has been reviewed as part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Good articles/Project quality task force]]. I believe the article currently meets the criteria and should remain listed as a [[WP:GA|Good article]]. The article history has been updated to reflect this review. Regards, [[User:Epbr123|Epbr123]] 17:28, 16 September 2007 (UTC)

== [[Palm_Island%2C_Queensland#.27Aboriginal_natives_shall_be_counted.27_1967-1985|Aboriginal natives shall be counted]] ==

I set up this section to cover the transition period between the settlement being a penal settlement to having its own self governing local council.  I have unfortunately not put any info into this section yet but the history of Palm is incomplete without covering this two decade period; it is an important part of their recent history and of course Indigenous history generally.  Particularly in the 'Path to self governance' section I refer to compensation paid for &quot;underpaid wages between 1975 and 1986&quot;, if anyone can find more info about this it would be appreciated. Cheers, [[User:WikiTownsvillian |Wiki]][[User talk:WikiTownsvillian|Townsvillia]][[Special:Contributions/WikiTownsvillian|n]] 15:18, 22 September 2007 (UTC)

*Becasue of the lack of connection between the referendum and Palm Island history so far - I have taken that ref out.  I will reorder so the 1999 compensation fits in the self-governemnt section.  I agree there is obviously a gap in history but I don't have info to fill it.  --[[User:Matilda|Matilda]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:Matilda|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 00:59, 10 December 2007 (UTC)

==Gone for a Song==

A new book has come out about the 2004 Death in Custody, a bit of info about it has been added recently by an anon.  The book is about 250 pages long and is obviously fairly in-depth.  It is by Jeff Waters who is an ABC journalist. 

The book has 12 pages of 'Sources' at the back, included in that list of sources is this Wikipedia article. &lt;font face=&quot;comic sans ms&quot; color=&quot;#454545&quot;&gt;[[User:WikiTownsvillian |Wiki]]&lt;/font&gt;[[User talk:WikiTownsvillian|Townsvillia]][[Special:Contributions/WikiTownsvillian|n]] 05:43, 2 June 2008 (UTC)

:Also (and this is a bit exciting) the image [[:Image:Palm Island Jetty.JPG|Palm Island Jetty]] that I sourced and uploaded last year and which is now at the top of the article has been modified and used as the image for the front cover of the book!

:They have cropped it, coloured the image to be red and black only and added clouds to it. Just goes to show how far your work can travel under the GNU Free Documentation License system :) &lt;font face=&quot;comic sans ms&quot; color=&quot;#454545&quot;&gt;[[User:WikiTownsvillian |Wiki]]&lt;/font&gt;[[User talk:WikiTownsvillian|Townsvillia]][[Special:Contributions/WikiTownsvillian|n]] 06:00, 2 June 2008 (UTC)
:: Impressive! Great work mate :) [[User talk:Orderinchaos|Orderinchaos]] 09:21, 2 June 2008 (UTC)
::: Do you get a cut of the royalties for image sourcing?  I undid the anon's additions as there was considerable editorialising in the additions.  Are you going to get a copy of the book?  It's about time we made the final push to get this to FA, what do you think?  --[[User:Stephen|Step]][[User talk:Stephen|hen]] 01:23, 4 June 2008 (UTC)
::::I have emailed Jeff (via his PR agent) to see if he has any material to add to the article. --[[User:Stephen|Step]][[User talk:Stephen|hen]] 01:47, 4 June 2008 (UTC)
:::::As you probably know, anything on wikipedia is released from any obligation of royalties even if it is used for commercial purposes.  However I did contact the person who took the photo to let him know about it, apparently the publishers did contact him and seek permission to use the image, which was nice of them considering they were not under an obligation to do so.  He is also acknowledged in the book as being the author of the photo which again is great. 
:::::I would be very happy to be a part of a push for FA for this article.  Cheers, &lt;font face=&quot;comic sans ms&quot; color=&quot;#454545&quot;&gt;[[User:WikiTownsvillian |Wiki]]&lt;/font&gt;[[User talk:WikiTownsvillian|Townsvillia]][[Special:Contributions/WikiTownsvillian|n]] 00:06, 5 June 2008 (UTC)
:::::PS yes I picked up a copy of the book. &lt;font face=&quot;comic sans ms&quot; color=&quot;#454545&quot;&gt;[[User:WikiTownsvillian |Wiki]]&lt;/font&gt;[[User talk:WikiTownsvillian|Townsvillia]][[Special:Contributions/WikiTownsvillian|n]] 00:08, 5 June 2008 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Palm Island, Queensland]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=698972164 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20080602183434/http://www.nla.gov.au:80/pressrel/1997/201097.html to http://www.nla.gov.au/pressrel/1997/201097.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 12:07, 9 January 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:12|one external link|12 external links}} on [[Palm Island, Queensland]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=704463072 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20070206032054/http://www.abc.net.au:80/news/newsitems/200111/s417112.htm to http://www.abc.net.au/news/newsitems/200111/s417112.htm
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20080418093111/http://www.abc.net.au:80/news/newsitems/200112/s439216.htm to http://www.abc.net.au/news/newsitems/200112/s439216.htm
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20051106131837/http://abc.net.au:80/news/newsitems/200508/s1446119.htm to http://www.abc.net.au/news/newsitems/200508/s1446119.htm
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20060824080127/http://news.sbs.com.au/livingblack/index.php?action=proginfo&amp;id=311 to http://news.sbs.com.au/livingblack/index.php?action=proginfo&amp;id=311
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20110316071612/http://www.parliament.qld.gov.au/view/publications/documents/research/ResearchBriefs/2002/2002026.pdf to http://www.parliament.qld.gov.au/view/publications/documents/research/ResearchBriefs/2002/2002026.pdf
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20060918083421/http://www.liquor.qld.gov.au/Indigenous/Alcohol+Management+Plans/Palm+Island to http://www.liquor.qld.gov.au/Indigenous/Alcohol+Management+Plans/Palm+Island
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20070707062313/http://www.datsip.qld.gov.au/resources/publications/documents/future-directions-palm-island-resource-officer-report.pdf to http://www.datsip.qld.gov.au/resources/publications/documents/future-directions-palm-island-resource-officer-report.pdf
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20080828171629/http://www.themonthly.com.au/tm/node/185 to http://www.themonthly.com.au/tm/node/185
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20070925233302/http://www.parliament.qld.gov.au/PISC/view/committees/documents/PISC/reports/report.pdf to http://www.parliament.qld.gov.au/PISC/view/committees/documents/PISC/reports/report.pdf
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20070925233256/http://www.parliament.qld.gov.au/PISC/view/committees/documents/PISC/response%20to%20PISC.PDF to http://www.parliament.qld.gov.au/PISC/view/committees/documents/PISC/response%20to%20PISC.PDF
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20060901002408/http://atns.net.au/biogs/A002600b.htm to http://www.atns.net.au/biogs/A002600b.htm
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20071007011934/http://www.indigenous.gov.au/sra/qld/fact_sheets/qldnov0506.html to http://www.indigenous.gov.au/sra/qld/fact_sheets/qldnov0506.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 19:19, 11 February 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:3|one external link|3 external links}} on [[Palm Island, Queensland]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=707437551 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20090703093514/http://apps.aec.gov.au:80/esearch/electorate.cfm?Electorates__Electorate=HERBERT%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20 to http://apps.aec.gov.au/esearch/electorate.cfm?Electorates__Electorate=HERBERT%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20070927194103/http://www.cis.org.au/exechigh/Eh2007/EH20007.htm to http://www.cis.org.au/exechigh/Eh2007/EH20007.htm
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070610220714/http://news.sbs.com.au/livingblack/index.php?action=proginfo&amp;id=367 to http://news.sbs.com.au/livingblack/index.php?action=proginfo&amp;id=367

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 21:50, 28 February 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:10|one external link|10 external links}} on [[Palm Island, Queensland]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=749028452 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.abc.net.au/rn/backgroundbriefing/stories/2007/1884420.htm
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://publib.slq.qld.gov.au/footprints/communities/mainlandmap.htm#palm
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.newsoftheodd.com/article1006.html
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.liquor.qld.gov.au/Indigenous/Alcohol+Management+Plans/Palm+Island
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.pcyc.org.au/news/BSC/BSC-SPRING05.pdf
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.pcyc.org.au/branch/palisl.htm
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.health.qld.gov.au/townsville/IMHS/Indigenous/palm.asp
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20060506105216/http://www.accq.org.au:80/comm/palm.htm to http://www.accq.org.au/comm/palm.htm
*Added {{tlx|dead link}} tag to http://www.pcyc.org.au/branches/palm-island/index.php
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070206023827/http://www.mcmc.qld.gov.au:80/community/search/palm_island.php to http://www.mcmc.qld.gov.au/community/search/palm_island.php
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20060917224058/http://www.mcmc.qld.gov.au/community/documents/palm-island-map.pdf to http://www.mcmc.qld.gov.au/community/documents/palm-island-map.pdf

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 22:26, 11 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>1n9go6933e51l3mhy0jnha2u4clbb8o</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
