<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Thomas Percy (Gunpowder Plot)</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>3076967</id>
    <revision>
      <id>532932891</id>
      <parentid>532892055</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-01-13T22:52:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Nick Michael</username>
        <id>418768</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Proposed change of name */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9662">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=21:15, 5 November 2010
|action1link=Talk:Thomas Percy (Gunpowder Plot)/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=394898215

|action2=FAC
|action2date=21:35, 26 November 2010
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Thomas Percy (Gunpowder Plot)/archive1
|action2result=promoted
|action2oldid=399020884

|action3=FTC
|action3date=03:48, 28 January 2011 (UTC)
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured topic candidates/Gunpowder Plot/archive1
|action3result=promoted

|ftname=Gunpowder Plot
|topic=Royalty, nobility and heraldry
|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=5 November 2012
}}
{{WikiProject Biography
|living=no
|class=FA
|listas=Percy, Thomas
}}

==Untitled==
&quot;Holbech House&quot; is normally spelled as &quot;Holbeach House&quot;. It is on the borders between Staffordshire and Warwickshire, on the Warwickshire side.
:wrong: it is [[Holbeche House]] in [[Kingswinford]], which was in Staffordshire.  [[User:Peterkingiron|Peterkingiron]] ([[User talk:Peterkingiron|talk]]) 10:20, 5 April 2010 (UTC)

==Untitled==
[http://www.warwickshire.gov.uk/Web/corporate/pages.nsf/Links/1A8F72E33301250D8025702D004EC84F Enjoy Warwickshire: Warwickshire and the gunpowder plot]
:I have yet again reverted the unsubstantiated claim that Thomas Percy was a knight (with the prefix &quot;Sir&quot;) added by an anon editor.  The above Warwickshire website (which I did not find) does indeed give him this title, but I have checked Antonia Fraser, ''Gunpowder Plot'' (Mandarin, London 1997), 184-6, where the events at Holbeche house are described (and index).  She does not give Percy this title.  She is careful to give it to others, such as Sir Richard Walsh, High sheriff of Worcestershire, whose sheriff's posse was responsible for the arrests, presumably on the principle that hot pursuit allowed him to follow traitors beyond his county boundary.  
:If there is substantial '''academic''' [[WP:RS|evidence]] for the knighthood, it needs to be set out in the text about his earlier life and properly cited.  The reliability of the above Warwickshire tourism page is not clear: there are links to various other websites, but it is not clear where the information come from.  [[User:Peterkingiron|Peterkingiron]] ([[User talk:Peterkingiron|talk]]) 10:20, 5 April 2010 (UTC)


:Thank you Peterkingiron. I used to spend quite a lot of effort maintaining Thomas as a commoner in this article, and like you I have never encountered any evidence for a knighthood, whether bestowed or inherited. [[User:Nick Michael|Nick Michael]] ([[User talk:Nick Michael|talk]]) 13:51, 5 April 2010 (UTC)

== hmmm ==

I've removed the following text from the article, not because I doubt its authenticity, but because I can't find any mention of it in more modern sources (beyond vague mentions of his unpopularity in his role at Alnwick).  I can't even find it in the online versions of the source it claims to come from:

&lt;nowiki&gt;In 1602 he was accused of several misdemeanours involving mismanagement or embezzlement of his master's property: 

*{{cquote|…there was a bell carryed out of [[Warkworth Castle|Warkworth castle]] and sold by Sir John Ladyman, Mr. Percye’s deputie, to a Scottishman for £10, and a token sent by Mr. Percye to one Henrye Finch to carrye the bell to the Scottishman’s ship at Almouth.}}

And bribery: 

*{{cquote|John Wilkinson of Over Busdon says that Mr. Percy had £30 for his farmhold, being but 18s. of ancient rent, besides £4 he gave to Sir John Ladyman and Gabriel Ogle for procuring the bargain at Mr. Percy’s hands.&lt;ref&gt;Informations against Mr. Thomas Percy for divers misdemeanours with his justifications of himself, 1602. ''Annals of the House of Percy, ii. p. 591''&lt;/ref&gt;}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;

Can anyone help? &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:grey 0.2em 0.2em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;[[User:Parrot of Doom|Parrot]] [[User talk:Parrot of Doom|of Doom]]&lt;/span&gt; 11:48, 17 October 2010 (UTC)
:This looks credible, but we need access to the book cited.  The second quote certainly reads like bribery, but I would prefer it only to appear in WP if the accusation in the source book, not merely as a WP editor's interpretation.  There might be an innocent explanation.  [[User:Peterkingiron|Peterkingiron]] ([[User talk:Peterkingiron|talk]]) 17:28, 17 October 2010 (UTC)

::The book in question can be found on Google Books: [http://books.google.ch/books?id=JBAXAAAAYAAJ&amp;q=%22annals+of+the+house+of+percy%22&amp;dq=%22annals+of+the+house+of+percy%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=37nSJbXgC5&amp;sig=NpnPaHCbJdmRSxO5M1eBSk8NeEI&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=inW7TPDnJoXGswbQ9oi_DQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CBcQ6AEwAQ]. I would request the extracts reinstated as they not only a valuable example of Percy's misdemeanours but are also correctly referenced. Thanks. [[User:Nick Michael|Nick Michael]] ([[User talk:Nick Michael|talk]]) 22:20, 17 October 2010 (UTC)

:::Perhaps then you could find the above text in that book, because I can't. &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:grey 0.2em 0.2em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;[[User:Parrot of Doom|Parrot]] [[User talk:Parrot of Doom|of Doom]]&lt;/span&gt; 23:06, 17 October 2010 (UTC)

It's where it says it is: [http://books.google.ch/books?hl=en&amp;id=0L0aAAAAYAAJ&amp;dq=editions%3ANYPL33433081848776&amp;q=ladyman#search_anchor]. Please reinstate, or justify deleting referenced quotations. Thanks. [[User:Nick Michael|Nick Michael]] ([[User talk:Nick Michael|talk]]) 13:44, 18 October 2010 (UTC)

:I'm sorry I didn't mean my post to sound antagonistic.  The above is fine, its unfortunate however, that we can't see the text in its full context.  How about I expand the article to include some &quot;controversy&quot; with regard to the above, and include them in the notes?  I'm a little hesitant to rely wholly on those quotes, as they're in a pretty old source, and also because no other author I have read on this subject has mentioned them. &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:grey 0.2em 0.2em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;[[User:Parrot of Doom|Parrot]] [[User talk:Parrot of Doom|of Doom]]&lt;/span&gt; 19:05, 18 October 2010 (UTC)

::No antagonism taken Parrot. The source is old, indeed, but contemporary - not some late C19 amateur historian commenting, but good C17 text. But by all means comment on them and put them in the notes. The fact that no other author has mentioned them merely says something about the other authors! But I really think they're entirely worthy of inclusion in one form or another as they are evidence of Percy's character. [[User:Nick Michael|Nick Michael]] ([[User talk:Nick Michael|talk]]) 19:29, 18 October 2010 (UTC) PS: I see you have used the same source (de Fonblanque) for another quotation.

:::Only small things really, in my scattergun attempt to rely on more than two sources (Fraser and Haynes).  I think its best to write something like &quot;a 16xx report makes mention of x and y, etc etc&quot;, and add the entire quotes to the notes section.  It'll flow better that way as well, its just that I hesitate to bolster the negative parts of his character with such old sources, that's usually the job of modern authors. &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:grey 0.2em 0.2em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;[[User:Parrot of Doom|Parrot]] [[User talk:Parrot of Doom|of Doom]]&lt;/span&gt; 20:03, 18 October 2010 (UTC)

Sounds good to me. I'm away and offline for a week, so expect to see a finished and brilliant article on my return! It's certainly going that way... [[User:Nick Michael|Nick Michael]] ([[User talk:Nick Michael|talk]]) 03:12, 19 October 2010 (UTC)

*I think I've sorted this now.  Another minor issue I have, is this line &quot;Thomas subsequently aided Essex in a conspiracy to entrap the Scottish warden of the middle marches,[3]&quot; - its from the ODNB and Nicholls is a reliable enough source, but I've been unable to expand on what the conspiracy was.  I think that the warden concerned is [[Robert Ker, 1st Earl of Roxburghe]] but I've drawn a blank on the rest.  It needs expanding for sure. &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:grey 0.2em 0.2em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;[[User:Parrot of Doom|Parrot]] [[User talk:Parrot of Doom|of Doom]]&lt;/span&gt; 21:39, 19 October 2010 (UTC)

{{Talk:Thomas Percy (Gunpowder Plot)/GA1}}

==Pedantry==
For the sake of grammar I changed &quot;whom he supposed had reneged&quot; to  &quot;who he supposed had reneged&quot; . &quot;Who&quot; is the subject of &quot;had reneged&quot;. You can write &quot;whom he supposed to have reneged&quot; but you can't really write the phrase as it stands. Very nit-picking, I know, but this is an encyclopaedia.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Campolongo|Campolongo]] ([[User talk:Campolongo|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Campolongo|contribs]]) 09:37, 5 November 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:I must admit I had to think about which is correct, but I have no problem with your change.  Either works for me. &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:grey 0.2em 0.2em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;[[User:Parrot of Doom|Parrot]] [[User talk:Parrot of Doom|of Doom]]&lt;/span&gt; 10:04, 5 November 2012 (UTC)

==Proposed change of name==
I find the title awkward, because &quot;Gunpowder Plot&quot; is an event rather than an occupation or some other similar word which describes a person. May I suggest [[Thomas Percy (conspirator)]]? Several other biographies use that form, such as [[Charles Paget (conspirator)]] and [[George Brooke (conspirator)]]. [[User:Moonraker|Moonraker]] ([[User talk:Moonraker|talk]]) 18:01, 13 January 2013 (UTC)

:I agree with Moonraker's proposal of [[Thomas Percy (conspirator)]]. This is better and more succinct than &quot;Plotter&quot; or &quot;Gunpowder Plot&quot;. [[User:Nick Michael|Nick Michael]] ([[User talk:Nick Michael|talk]]) 22:52, 13 January 2013 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>nojfsod1ors2thqoprytv6d9lwb2qwm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
