<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Geology of the Lassen volcanic area</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>7554744</id>
    <revision>
      <id>731332563</id>
      <parentid>717976025</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-07-24T17:31:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mamayuco</username>
        <id>26498899</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>not high importance</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9894">{{Article history
|action1=FAC
|action1date=00:00, 16 July 2007
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Geology of the Lassen volcanic area
|action1result=promoted
|action1oldid=144739841
|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=January 22, 2008
}}
{{WikiProject banner shell|collapsed=yes|1=
{{WikiProject Geology|class=FA|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject California|importance=high|class=FA}}
{{WikiProject Volcanoes|class=FA|importance=low}}
}}

==Featured &amp; Disputed?==
How does this work. Surely if there is disputed content it can't be a featured article? If the area of dispute has been cleared up, please remove the tag... it doesn't look good to see a featured article with that tag smack bang at the top. [[User:Kare Kare|Kare Kare]] 03:02, 21 June 2007 (UTC)
:The article was promoted prematurely; I made an attempt to address the concerns of the person who placed the tag just hours before promotion. The user has not looked over my changes yet. I've ask Raul to relist as a FAC so we can have the best possible version of the article linked in the above history when it does get promoted. --[[User:Maveric149|mav]] 06:56, 21 June 2007 (UTC)

:I '''strongly disagree''' with the use of the {{tl|disputed}} tag on this article as it stands. I agree with [[User:KP Botany]] that the article more information is needed for the early Cenozoic (I also mentioned this in the FAC). However, this is an omission, not a factual inaccuracy. The template{{tl|disputed}} is used for articles with multiple false or unverified statements. I think we should change the template to {{tl|vagueintro}}, to more closely match KP's criticism.

:I would fix the article myself, but I do not have the reference texts at hand: I think we have to either wait for mav to fix the article, or perhaps KP can step in and fix it. [[User:Hike395|hike395]] 15:54, 21 June 2007 (UTC)

::Correct tag added. --[[User:Maveric149|mav]] 20:24, 21 June 2007 (UTC)

can someone please remove the karate kid picture and replace it with the graphic?  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Chladek|Chladek]] ([[User talk:Chladek|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Chladek|contribs]]) 20:53, 22 January 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Missing history==
KP/all - at least in general terms, what events that occurred post Klamath/Sierra basement break and pre-Sierra uplift do you think are relevant to an article about the Lassen volcanic area? If none or few, then I will add that info. However, I'm tempted to simply start this article as it did originally - with the events leading to the formation of the Tuscan Formation since we have a fairly clear link between that and the geology we see today. Not to mention, that the Tuscan is known to exist right below the surface in several places within the park and does crop out in places near park borders. 

One has to limit what is talked about in some way, and other park geology articles focus on formations/layers that actually crop out in or immediately around the park with short mentions about removed or deeply buried layers (self-limiting the discussion in a fairly natural way). I think that would make for a more on-topic article that will flow better. What do you think? --[[User:Maveric149|mav]]

:Personally, I think that the Cenozoic history of the area is interesting, but doesn't need to go into the introduction, because it is a side issue. I went back and did some research: I think you hit the high points already --- the Eocene and Miocene vulcanism, the Modoc flood basalts, Mount Maidu. So, I don't think you need to add any more. [[User:Hike395|hike395]] 12:11, 22 June 2007 (UTC)

===Tag issue===
OK - if that is the consensus, then we can remove the tag in 24 hours. --[[User:Maveric149|mav]] 00:52, 26 June 2007 (UTC)

I've since started the article with the tilting of the Sierras and laying down of the Tuscan formation, thus directly addressing KP's objection of mentioning the Sierra/Klamath split 140 mya and then not mentioning any geology up to the Tuscan formation. So, can we get rid of the tag? I can't think of anything else that needs to be added or taken away from the intro/lead. --[[User:Maveric149|mav]] 13:48, 9 July 2007 (UTC)

I think there's a lot of the Cenozoic that can simply be left out of an article on the geology of the Mt. Lassen area, but if you include any you must be certain you are talking about an earlier Sierra.  I think the notes left by another user on the FAC page would greatly help the introduction.  I remain concerned about some aspects of this article.  I made suggestions about technical references that could readily be incorporated into this text for accuracy, but you've chosen to stick with only general referances.  I feel that is a mistake and leads to things like a lead paragraph where you jump around in major events in time.  You start with recent uplift, go to subduction for hundreds of millions of years, then date these volcanoes at 70 MY, yet the Wikipedia article on the Cascade Vocanoes says volcanism began in the arc 37 MYA.  I don't agree with the tag being removed, and I don't agree that this is FA, at least the introduction.  In general it's well written and well researched, except for missing some details that can only come from reading more recent technical papers--the sources cited are insufficient for the topic of the article.  [[User:KP Botany|KP Botany]] 18:43, 9 July 2007 (UTC)

The introduction remains vague, and the tag should stay until the introduction is all that it should be:

&quot;Oceanic tectonic plates have plunged below the North American Plate in this part of North America for hundreds of millions of years. Heat from these subducting plates has fed scores of volcanoes in California, Oregon, Washington and British Columbia over at least the past 30 million years (see Geology of the Pacific Northwest) and is also responsible for activities in the Lassen volcanic area.

Between 2 and 4 million years ago, volcanic-derived mud flows called lahars streamed down several major sources that included nearby but now extinct Mount Yana and Mount Maidu to become the Tuscan Formation.&quot;

We have three things going on here right from square one, we have hundreds of millions of years of tectonic plates, then the article discusses the current subduction complex, the Laramide Orogeny and younger events--well, what the heck is this hundreds of millions of years of subduction about, then?  You start at the bottom in the intro, then move to the current setting and move back in time in the article, then call the Sierran uplift the &quot;basement rocks?&quot;

No, the introduction is vague, almost entirely unrelated to the article, and the tag should remain as long as this is an issue.  [[User:KP Botany|KP Botany]] 21:20, 10 July 2007 (UTC)

:I'll take another look and make another shot at addressing your points. I've already started to use journal cites. --[[User:Maveric149|mav]] 11:18, 11 July 2007 (UTC)

== Strong objection to tag being removed ==

The introduction IS vague, and the tag IS needed.  I object to its being removed without discussion, and my comments about it being removed being ignored by the remover.   The tag does belong right now on this article to alert the reader to issues of major concern about the introduction of this article, which is not comprehensible from a geological perspective.  This has not been dealt with, and apparently it will not be dealt with as the push for FA status is going forward full force, and apparently my objections about the geology of this article are a bit too much for those supporting it.  I bow out and leave it to all of you to push this forward as a FA.  [[User:KP Botany|KP Botany]] 04:57, 15 July 2007 (UTC)

:You previously suggested removing all info about Cretaceous events. I did so. I also removed mention of the Sierra uplift from the intro because it is not directly related to the geology of this particular volcanic area. Should that go back? Also, what other parts of the geology of this area need to be in the intro? Recall that intros need to be ''concise'' encyclopedia articles in their own right. So we can't include everything there; just the most relevant and important info. As for the tag; everybody else who has commented on that issue has agreed that none is needed. I also voluntarily had this article un-FACed in spite of it having more than enough support to pass so I could incorporate your feedback into improving it. That said, I very much want to address your concerns, but that is a bit difficult if more of a specific critique is not forthcoming. In the meantime, I'll search the academic literature for relevant papers and try to find time to visit a nearby university that has the journals. If you have any ideas on papers I should look at, then please provide them. :) --[[User:Mav|mav]] 15:00, 15 July 2007 (UTC)

== Introduction ==

Seems to me that the introduction seems to be a little long and technical.  Shouldnt some of that information be trimmed and merged into the main article? [[Special:Contributions/76.212.151.84|76.212.151.84]] ([[User talk:76.212.151.84|talk]]) 05:53, 23 January 2008 (UTC) Sandy
:The intro is a summary of the whole article and is within the correct range for an article this size. See [[WP:LEAD]]. --[[User:Mav|mav]] ([[User talk:Mav|talk]]) 03:06, 26 March 2008 (UTC)

== 1917 or 1921? ==

As it turns out: both. There's no strict definition of the end of an eruption. The last major eruption was in 1917, &quot;activity&quot; continued until. 1921, and Lassen still leaks a little steam today. Theis is explained in the Tuttle book.

Mav: I don't have access to the fifth edition --- if you like, you could find this fact in the fifth edition, and combine the refs. —[[User:Hike395|hike395]] ([[User talk:Hike395|talk]]) 16:13, 29 February 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>aa2nv2300g070gh8g56goq6wpb5tus5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
