<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:University of Maryland, College Park</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1180288</id>
    <revision>
      <id>707814420</id>
      <parentid>706608218</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-03-01T23:08:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cyberbot II</username>
        <id>16283967</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="41503">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=FAC
|action1date=10:00, 14 October 2005
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/University of Maryland, College Park/archive1
|action1result=not promoted
|action1oldid=25478845

|action2=GAN
|action2date=26 September 2006
|action2result=not listed
|action2oldid=77972752

|action3=GAN
|action3date=2 June 2007
|action3result=not listed
|action3oldid=135368856

|currentstatus=FFAC
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Universities|class=B}}
{{WikiProject Maryland|class = B|importance = high}}
{{WikiProject ACC|class=B}}
}}
{{todo|1}}
{{archive box|
[[/Archive 1]]  Nov 2004 to May 2006
}}

==General Housekeeping Comments==

I think this page has lost its way a bit. In my view, the main page should really be that--a primary overview. Some of the sections get into far too much detail, most of it uninteresting to those who are seeking general info. I'm trying to use the [[University of Virginia]] as a model page. We should leave all these extra details and factoids off the main page since there are so many sub-pages devoted to individual topics (e.g. athletics, notable alumni). Some of the changes I list below have already been made but there are some things that I would like community feedback on before any action is taken.

Suggestions:
*Pictures
**Why are they so tiny? Perhaps we can enlarge the pictures once superfluous information is removed (see below).
*Academics
**List the colleges, in two columns if need be, to break up the endless lines of text.
**Move the info about the Nobel Laureates into this section (see UVA's page).
**Get rid of the info about the honors programs, except those that are exceptionally interesting, such as Hinman CEOs. The first sentence of the paragraph says it all, &quot;The Honors Program is similar to most other honors programs throughout the country.&quot; So why is it on the page??
*Athletics
**I'm a UM alum and I love the Terps but can we please just move the team histories to the athletics page? I say highlight the major events (NCAA tourneys, etc) and have the general team info.
*Testudo
**I'll try to find references for those events and add a picture. Right now, it's just a glob of text.
*Notable People
**We need to cut back on the people. Moving the Nobel Laureates up to Academics will give up some space but others just simply need to be moved to the list page. I mean, do we really need to mention the Athletic Director of the University of Oklahoma? UM's own athletic director isn't even mentioned on the page!
***The criterion I would use for this section is to think about whether your mother would know who these people are: Jim Henson, Connie Chung, Larry David, Congressman Hoyer? Probably yes. Joe Castiglione? Michael Griffin? Gordon England? I would say probably not.
**The list of all athletes turned pro is neat but doesn't need to be on the main page; there are just a lot of them. They should be included in the separate Terrapins Athletics article or in the notable people list.
*Sections that should be removed or seriously overhauled.
**Hoff Theater - remove.
***I disagree with this. The Hoff Theater is a rather interesting part of being at Maryland for a lot of people. 
**Events - remove.
**Department of Public Safety - remove.
**The Greek Life section should really be about ALL student life at Maryland. A list of frats and sororities is, in my view, pretty useless.
**References: I don't know why the same page (e.g. the UM Timeline) has to be referenced over and over. Isn't once enough to link to the information? Perhaps better primary source references can be found. I will definitely look. Thanks, [[User:Epicadam|Epicadam]] ([[User talk:Epicadam|talk]]) 22:38, 17 April 2008 (UTC)

== Point of Failure ==

I'm a student at U of M, and neither I, nor any of my friends, have never seen this plaque mentioned in the wiki warning students about the legend.  I really don't think there actually is one.  Can someone confirm?  Perhaps I'm just blind.
[[User:70.108.29.250]] 21:19, 22 August 2006 (UTC)

:Then remove the information unless it can be verified.  Leave the fact tag, however, since the entire paragraph is uncited. --[[user:tomf688|tomf688]] ([[User talk:Tomf688|talk]] - [[Special:Emailuser/Tomf688|email]]) 21:55, 22 August 2006 (UTC)

:I, too, am a student at UMD. The 'point of failure' is there, but the plaque nearby does not warn freshman of the dangers. It explains what happened and why the point is there, but it doesn't tell people about the legend at all.
::Another UMD student here.  The only basis we really have for the legend is what our tour guides tell us during Open House and Freshman Orientation, really.  There doesn't seem to be any actual &quot;physical&quot; proof. [[User:Recalcitrancy|Recalcitrancy]] 02:48, 2 August 2007 (UTC)
::Another UMD student, although it's not written anywhere, it's common knowledge, and most people go out of their way to avoid stepping on that spot.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/129.2.175.87|129.2.175.87]] ([[User talk:129.2.175.87|talk]]) 15:08, 29 March 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:::WHICH legend got removed?  And, has anybody checked the page on Professor [[John Pease]] whose piece I bumped into? --[[User:Leahtwosaints|leahtwosaints]] ([[User talk:Leahtwosaints|talk]]) 00:10, 19 May 2008 (UTC)

::Another UM student, I've heard much about the legend, including sometimes hearing &quot;a friend of a friend of a friend&quot; stories advocating that it is true. I would say the point of failure is the most active superstition still alive at UMD besides the idea that the turtle in front of McKeldin will give you luck if you rub it's nose/put an offering.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/96.244.223.244|96.244.223.244]] ([[User talk:96.244.223.244|talk]]) 19:08, 12 June 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==History of the anti-war movement at Maryland==

I think some mention needs to be made of the history of the radical movement on and around campus during the late 60s and early 70s particularly as it relates to the anti-Vietnam War movement.  Beginning in May 1970 the campus was shut down for part of three consecutive spring semesters.  I personally recall the events of April 1972 when the campus was shut down by protests, occupied by the National Guard and placed under martial law for approximately a week.  In the early 80s I had the privilege of meeting rock star Commander Cody who gave a concert during this time at Ritchie Colliseum which ended in pandemonium as the crowd tried to take over the Armory with National Guard and State Police barricaded inside.  Cody recalled the episode during my brief encounter with him on the West Coast in 1983.  Then of course there was the food co-op in the Student Union building which I understand still exists almost 30 years after we founded it. [[User:Tom Cod|Tom Cod]] 20:30, 27 August 2006 (UTC)

:This is the last thing we need on the page. Who cares if Maryland was/is a hippie school? Lots of schools protested the war. [[User:Titmanisdaman]] 03:02, 10 December 2008 (UTC)

::Why's that? these articles are supposed to present an NPOV history of these institutions not sanitized articles acceptable to administrators or those in denial about the past.

==Failed GA==
This article failed the GA noms due to lack of [[WP:CITE|inline citations]]. If you feel the this article is still GA quality please feel free to seek a [[WP:GA/R|review]]. --[[User:Tarret|Tarret]] 21:58, 26 September 2006 (UTC)

== Academics and Rankings Section ==

I added both an academics section and a rankings section to the article. I realize that a lot of these rankings are criticized, but people use them as references and that makes them relevant.

The Academics Section, I believe, should be where we add the content regarding academics at the university. I realize I didn't start off with much, but I think that together, we can all do research and make that section better.&lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[User:Krobilla|Krobilla]] ([[User talk:Krobilla|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Krobilla|contribs]]) 05:36, November 13, 2006  (UTC{{{3|}}})&lt;/small&gt;

== Original research ==

The section regarding campus legends clearly contains some [[WP:OR|original research]].  These claims need to be cited, or they may be deleted. --[[user:tomf688|tomf688]] ([[User talk:Tomf688|talk]] - [[Special:Emailuser/Tomf688|email]]) 05:01, 26 November 2006 (UTC)

:I have added citations to some of the campus legends, but I was unable to find anything about the biology-psychology building. I am going to keep looking. [[User:Krobilla|Krobilla]] 00:44, 2 December 2006 (UTC)

::After searching UMD's web page, doing a google search, and searching The Diamondback, I was unable to find anything about Bio-Psych building. I propose that the section be removed. [[User:Krobilla|Krobilla]] 00:50, 2 December 2006 (UTC)

:::Thanks for your work.  I agree, and I'm going to remove it. --[[user:tomf688|tomf688]] ([[User talk:Tomf688|talk]] - [[Special:Emailuser/Tomf688|email]]) 04:11, 7 December 2006 (UTC)

&quot;Prior to the establishment of the medical school at the University of Maryland, Baltimore, the medical school was located in College Park, and Morrill Hall is actually where the cadavers were kept.&quot;  This seems highly unlikely since the medical school was founded in 1807 and Davidge Hall on the Baltimore campus was built in 1812, well before the College Park campus was established.[[User:SHJohnson|SHJohnson]] 02:26, 7 October 2007 (UTC)

== Greek life ==

The &quot;Greek life&quot; section has a list of the fraternities/sororities on the campus, but doesn't contain much other content.  It would be nice to have it expanded to at least a couple of paragraphs. --[[user:tomf688|tomf688]] ([[User talk:Tomf688|talk]] - [[Special:Emailuser/Tomf688|email]]) 05:07, 26 November 2006 (UTC)

I added some very basic information, which I will cite fairly soon. [[User:Krobilla|Krobilla]] 00:45, 2 December 2006 (UTC)

The section about hazing needs to be removed. Sure, they were large events on the campus, and Dr. Clement got criticized, but this is not how I want my school to be advertised to someone who did not know much about the school. I'm sure there are much more positive things that could be written. Also, there should be a distinction between academic and social fraternities. [[User:Titmanisdaman|Titmanisdaman]] 15:29, 18 June 2008 (UTC)

==New Userbox template==

Here's an alternative Userbox template for any Terp to use:   [[User:JGHowes|JGHowes]] 16:06, 1 March 2007 (UTC)

{{User:JGHowes/Templates/Univ_MD}}{{[[User:JGHowes/Templates/Univ_MD]]}}


== GA Fail ==

Just looking at it the first thing that I notice about this article is it's lack of references.  There are entire sections that have no references.  Do not post anything without a reference. While there are other things this is the biggest area of concern that you should try to fix, in the meantime I will thoroughly review the rest of the article. I really feel like putting a fact tag on the entire article.  It is well written but without sources it cannot be verified. [[User:Professor Davies|Professor Davies]] 18:17, 2 June 2007 (UTC)

== Name ==

Isn't the school officially entitled: University of Maryland and not University of Maryland, College Park, which is just a form of clarification when discussing the University of Maryland System?  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Josephabradshaw|Josephabradshaw]] ([[User talk:Josephabradshaw|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Josephabradshaw|contribs]]) 14:41, 18 February 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

The correct name is the University of Maryland, College Park.
(It helps to hold a position in the Undergraduate Admissions office! :)  FINALLY, answering all those emails is paying off! --[[User:Leahtwosaints|leahtwosaints]] ([[User talk:Leahtwosaints|talk]]) 00:10, 19 May 2008 (UTC)

==Jim Henson statue==

There is a very special [[Jim Henson]] comemmoratory statue at the University. [[User:Angie Y.|Angie Y.]] ([[User talk:Angie Y.|talk]]) 19:39, 12 May 2008 (UTC)

== University of Maryland Food Co-op ==

The University doesn't want to advertise the existance of a student owned, run, and controlled Food Co-op in the Student Union Building, since they view it as financial competition. I'd like to see a mention of the Co-op, and do it myself. I'm mentioning it now, since I was one of the founders of the co-op.  It's noteworthy because it opened only after students had the foresight to use unclaimed money from a mandatory &quot;student activities fund&quot; which had been underused, unnoticed for years, and which the Administration quietly kept.  When the Admin. refused to allow use of any facility or funds, the students responded. Several hundred students demonstrated, at a time when huge demonstrations no longer took place.  It is student owned &amp; controlled.  So, would anyone mind if I word it properly and reference it?  I mean, affordable (and in 1976 ''edible'') food for an hour of volunteering between classes?  Not to mention the fact that the students have continued to keep this vital alternative open for over 30 years now.  I'm mentioning my desire to include a very concise entry on the page, because I plan to adhere to NPOV, but yes, I was involved in starting that place.  Thanks. --[[User:Leahtwosaints|leahtwosaints]] ([[User talk:Leahtwosaints|talk]]) 00:10, 19 May 2008 (UTC)

:I say go for it. Not sure you have to go into all the detail about student funds, etc. for one because that was 30 years ago and two, unless them hiding funds has any particular significance today, it's not really worth mentioning.

:But, the co-op is one of the more interesting features on campus. I'd say it should be part of a new student life section, instead of info about just frats and sororities. [[User:Epicadam|Epicadam]] ([[User talk:Epicadam|talk]]) 19:57, 20 May 2008 (UTC)
:Do please add stuff about the co-op!  Add whatever you feel like, and we can look over it to help make it more NPOV. [[User:Jussen|Jussen]] ([[User talk:Jussen|talk]]) 02:41, 22 May 2008 (UTC)

* More re: the Co-op 
Sorry it's been 6 MONTHS since I brougt up the Co-op. Thanks for the encouragement. I agree with Epicadam that it might merit only a short blurb and then a link to another page about it. I was the V.P. of the Co-op back then (we had to be incorporated in case of  personal lawsuits) but I'd keep it to a bare minimum. I began college at age 15, and was the youngest founder, so I recall nearly every detail and own clippings from the ''[[Diamondback]]'', from '76-'81 with great photos -anyone have a scanner?- and know where most founders now are, who may have some refs too, and some other sources. Once I find time from [[Wikimedia Commons]], I want to make a page for the Co-op because it sprang out of unusual circumstances, initiative, hard work, and shows both [[diversity]] and [[ingenuity]] of which few other schools can boast, surviving over 30 yrs., developing a [[culture]] and [[community]] on Campus all its own. Anyone else here who would be willing to contribute? --[[User:Leahtwosaints|leahtwosaints]] ([[User talk:Leahtwosaints|talk]]) 16:53, 23 January 2009 (UTC)

::This has already been said, but for a major State university that has been around since before the Civil War, the plight of a food co-op doesn't merit much of a  place in the article. There is also [[wp:coi]] issues here.  Perhaps a tiny part in student life, and start a new article about it, though I'm not sure if you can find enough references to establish [[wp:n|notability]]. I used to buy incense sticks there. --[[User:Omarcheeseboro|Omarcheeseboro]] ([[User talk:Omarcheeseboro|talk]]) 21:15, 23 January 2009 (UTC)

== Public Ivy edit war ==
I see there's an edit war going on about the [[Public Ivy]] claim. Perhaps qualifying the sentences with &quot;according to ...&quot; would make everyone happy. BTW, I think that the detractor's statement &quot;Until it is demonstrated that the tiny journal JBEH speaks on behalf of all of academia, or that anyone takes the Public Ivy books seriously, THIS DOES NOT BELONG.&quot; is asking for an impossible to achieve standard; &quot;all academia&quot;? Seesh. UMD's grad program is ranked above many Ivy League schools in some areas, e.g. Physics and Computer Science, and these rankings come from sources other than JBEH. [[User:VasileGaburici|VasileGaburici]] ([[User talk:VasileGaburici|talk]]) 11:14, 8 September 2008 (UTC)
:&quot;According to...&quot; is completely unnecessary verbage.  It's obvious to anyone who actually takes 5 seconds to read the article that only Moll and his co-authors can categorize an institution as a &quot;Public Ivy.&quot;
:If you, our disruptive friend, or anyone else wants to move this fact to somewhere else in the article that's perfectly fine with me.  If someone wants to remove it because they have evidence that it's not notable, not important, discredited, etc. then that's fine with me, too.  But I am not okay with anyone removing information from any article simply because they [[WP:NPOV|don't like it or agree with it]].  --[[User:ElKevbo|ElKevbo]] ([[User talk:ElKevbo|talk]]) 11:58, 8 September 2008 (UTC)
:: I see your point regarding &quot;According to...&quot; being unnecessary. But the average reader may not be aware that Public Ivy is a &quot;proprietary&quot; label dispensed only by Moll &amp; Co. I certainly wasn't aware of it before I clicked the link, and I do have a (graduate) degree from UMD, CP. So, I suggest we move the Public Ivy statement to the &quot;rankings&quot; section because this label is a qualitative statement, so it is a (boolean) ranking originating from a single source, just like the US News &amp; World Report rankings are produced only by that magazine. [[User:VasileGaburici|VasileGaburici]] ([[User talk:VasileGaburici|talk]]) 14:51, 8 September 2008 (UTC)
:::Sounds good to me!  --[[User:ElKevbo|ElKevbo]] ([[User talk:ElKevbo|talk]]) 15:54, 8 September 2008 (UTC)

== Rankings ==
Perhaps these should distinguish between graduate and undergraduate programs. UMD generally does better on the former than the latter. [[User:VasileGaburici|VasileGaburici]] ([[User talk:VasileGaburici|talk]]) 11:14, 8 September 2008 (UTC)
: Actually, I beg to disagree. It depends on the major. I strongly advise any current student to speak to Barbara Gill, the Director of Undergraduate Admissions. There is a lot to be said for some of the LEP (Limited Enrollment Programs), such as the business school. The Undergraduate Office are unable to allow any student into their desired LEP major even if they jump the hurdle and make it into the incoming frosh class, without them having significantly higher grades than are required just to be eligible for Fall admission, so she surely has references to show the necessity for this, and why UMCP is such a sought-after school. In addition, don't underestimate the Honors program. I don't know if it is still as good as when Dr. Mack was head of the main program until 2005? I seem to recall 2004, UMCP was ranked 4th, or something like that for the residential living-learning communities (I hope I'm remembering correctly.) Wish we could do research, but that's forbidden here.. another question for Barbara Gill, perhaps. --[[User:Leahtwosaints|leahtwosaints]] ([[User talk:Leahtwosaints|talk]]) 17:41, 23 January 2009 (UTC)

== Food Co-op==
Please see my tardy addition to the Co-op question above. Thanks.--[[User:Leahtwosaints|leahtwosaints]] ([[User talk:Leahtwosaints|talk]]) 17:41, 23 January 2009 (UTC)

== [[John Walter Smith]] ==

He was just removed from the alumni list.  Hrm.  His article says he attended the Agriculture College of Maryland.  Isn't that now part of UMCP?  [[User:Henrymrx|Henrymrx]] ([[User_talk:Henrymrx|t]]&amp;middot;[[Special:Contributions/Henrymrx|c]]) 05:37, 2 April 2009 (UTC)
:Yes, UMD was known as the Maryland Agricultural College until 1916. However, the [[John Walter Smith]] article was incorrect (I fixed it); the second source cited there says specifically that he did not attend college. As governor, he did do some things involving the management of MAC, which I guess is where the confusion for that article's editor arose. [[User:Strikehold|Strikehold]] ([[User talk:Strikehold|talk]]) 05:59, 2 April 2009 (UTC)

==Whether the &quot;flagship&quot; status of a university can be presented as objective fact==
There is currently an RfC on this question at [[Talk:University of Maine#Flagship RFC]]. &lt;span style=&quot;color:Purple; font-size:15pt;&quot;&gt;☺&lt;/span&gt;[[User:Coppertwig|Coppertwig]] ([[User talk:Coppertwig|talk]]) 12:54, 16 May 2009 (UTC)
:Well, I don't know about Maine, but the College Park campus was declared the &quot;flagship&quot; campus by the state legislature sometime in the late 80s or early 90s.  No, I don't have a source for that. I can probably dig one up if you want to make a big deal out of it. [[User:Henrymrx|Henrymrx]] ([[User_talk:Henrymrx|t]]&amp;middot;[[Special:Contributions/Henrymrx|c]]) 13:10, 16 May 2009 (UTC)
:The College Park campus is referred to as the flagship campus on the University System of Maryland's website: http://www.usmd.edu/institutions/Profile.php?Inst=UMCP [[User:CheeToS|CheeToS]] ([[User talk:CheeToS|talk]]) 06:45, 8 September 2009 (UTC)

== GA Nomination ==

Isn't generally best for someone who is actively working on the article to do the GA nom?  Perhaps they still plan on adding more content, cleaning things up, etc.  --[[User:Omarcheeseboro|Omarcheeseboro]] ([[User talk:Omarcheeseboro|talk]]) 19:54, 18 June 2010 (UTC)
:Content wise, I think this article is at the GA level already, and I think the reviewer will likely ask us to do things like reference secondary sources, format them using the cite templates, and other technical things that I do well, so I decided to try for GA status. If anyone doesn't want to try for that, let me know. [[User:JamaUtil|JamaUtil]] ([[User talk:JamaUtil|talk]]) 21:37, 18 June 2010 (UTC)

::The article is coming along well, but there are still several sections with no footnotes (starting around the faculty section onwards). This will be asked for in the GA review... [[User:Strikehold|Strikehold]] ([[User talk:Strikehold|talk]]) 21:53, 18 June 2010 (UTC)

:::I see no reason to rush the nom.  While it's likely not to be reviewed for at least a few weeks, it could be picked up anytime.  I feel it's best to withdraw the nom for now and go over the tasks to improve the article. --[[User:Omarcheeseboro|Omarcheeseboro]] ([[User talk:Omarcheeseboro|talk]]) 22:02, 18 June 2010 (UTC)

::::Let me know when you're ready! [[User:JamaUtil|JamaUtil]] ([[User talk:JamaUtil|talk]]) 17:33, 21 June 2010 (UTC)

== Unnecessary footnotes ==

I recently noticed that there were a few new footnotes linking to pages for maps and whatnot. Is this truly necessary? For example, under the &quot;Campus Description&quot; header, it says &quot;A map of campus can be found here [59] and a walking-tour map featuring campus landmarks can be found here.[60]&quot; with the footnotes linking to PDFs of maps. Can't you simply mention the information without linking to it? Plus, aren't footnotes supposed to be used to validate a statement rather than transfer you to a page like a bibliography? I just think it's weird and I don't see other university wikis with that. 

The footnotes are also in the Resident Life header (can't you just name the halls in a grid rather than redirect people to the DRL website?) and the Transportation header (I doubt anyone besides those associated with the university care about Zipcar services, and those who do care already know how to access them so a link on Wikipedia is really unnecessary)

Like I said, I just think the footnotes and the sentences in general are weird and unnecessary. Why write &quot;you can find this thing here&quot; when &quot;here&quot; doesn't even lead to anywhere? --[[User:Kamaki|Kamaki]] ([[User talk:Kamaki|talk]]) 01:03, 13 July 2010 (UTC)

:I agree they were weird, I changed them to:  ..X is [http:/// here] and ..Ys are [http:/// here].  I do think they have some useful information, I only took out the one on current parking rates, but left all the location ones in. [[User:JamaUtil|JamaUtil]] ([[User talk:JamaUtil|talk]]) 14:55, 13 July 2010 (UTC)
::Sorry, but inline external links are even worse.  See [[Wikipedia:ELPOINTS#Important_points_to_remember|#2 in this guideline about External links]]. I left a note on your talk page. --[[User:Omarcheeseboro|Omarcheeseboro]] ([[User talk:Omarcheeseboro|talk]]) 15:03, 13 July 2010 (UTC)

== Page Move? ==

This hasn't been brought up in a while, so I want to gauge current consensus. Does it make sense to move this article to [[University of Maryland]]? I believe doing so satisfies [[WP:COMMONNAME]] and &quot;University of Maryland&quot; redirects here anyway. Thoughts? Best, [[User:Epicadam|epicAdam]]&lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Epicadam|talk]])&lt;/sup&gt; 16:32, 15 August 2010 (UTC)

== Out of Date Rankings ==

The Rankings section of this article is in shoddy shape.  Rankings from different years are used, and there's no consistency.  New 2010 numbers are out there and available, we just need to find the best, most [[WP:NPOV]], and most [[WP:RELIABLE]] sources.  Here are a few after a quick search:
* [http://www.newsdesk.umd.edu/facts/2010rank.cfm UM Newsdesk 2010 Facts and Figures]
* [http://www.arwu.org/ Academic Ranking of World Universities Official Website]
Let's try to bring all the facts and figures up-to-date. &lt;span style=&quot;background-color:darkblue&quot;&gt;[[User:Amitparikh|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ffffff&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;Amit&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;''']]&lt;/span&gt;[[User talk:Amitparikh|'''&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:white;color:darkblue&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;►&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;''']] 13:07, 4 September 2010 (UTC)

:A recent edit ([http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=University_of_Maryland,_College_Park&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=389443938&amp;oldid=389341809 diff]) altered a lot of the University's national/international ranking numbers.  The edit summary that was given states ''&quot;I have updated the ranking for this current year&quot;'', but there are no updated references or new references.  In fact, some of the older references date back to 2007 and are either dead links or completely invalid now.  These facts/figures are contentious, but important to this article, so please, before updated ranking numbers, make sure you have a [[WP:RS|reliable source]] ready to include as a reference.  Thanks!  &lt;span style=&quot;background-color:darkblue&quot;&gt;[[User:Amitparikh|&lt;font color=&quot;white&quot;&gt;'''&amp;nbsp;Amit&amp;nbsp;'''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;[[User talk:Amitparikh|'''&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:white;color:darkblue&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;►&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;''']] 13:48, 8 October 2010 (UTC)

== Misspelled &quot;School&quot;  ==

The &quot;Robert H. Smith School of Business&quot; redirects here.  Unfortunately, &quot;School&quot; spelled &quot;Scool&quot;!  Probably a Duke ?..lol.. and it would be really funny except Facebook picks up Wikipedia's university pages and so the misspelling is carried over there too.  Several friends have commented that I went to a school that can't spell &quot;school.&quot;  Anyone here know how to fix it?

University of Maryland, College Park
From Wikipedia, the free encyclopedia
(Redirected from Robert H. Smith Scool of Business)  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/71.191.197.234|71.191.197.234]] ([[User talk:71.191.197.234|talk]]) 01:04, 12 January 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

::I had the scool article deleted. &quot;[[Robert H. Smith School of Business]]&quot;  has its own article.. the scool redirect was created in 2005 for some unknown reason.  As you may able to guess, there's no way for Wikipedia to delete it from Facebook.  I tried &quot;reporting&quot; the page on facebook, though the options were about pornography and spam.  --[[User:CutOffTies|CutOffTies]] ([[User talk:CutOffTies|talk]]) 13:03, 12 January 2011 (UTC)

== Fear the Turtle ==
The article says this was coined in the early 2000's, but that's simply not true.  I went to MD from 96-00 and I clearly remember the phrase on T-shirts and posters in 98 or 99..  [[User:Bethereds|Bethereds]] ([[User talk:Bethereds|talk]]) 00:54, 17 January 2011 (UTC)

:The slogan &quot;Fear the Turtle&quot; was created and trademarked by Drew Elburn of Reistertown, MD in 1998. 
:Credit to: http://wnst.net/baltimore-sports/fear-the-turtle-nevermore-umd-drops-the-fear-the-turtle-slogan/
:&lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Mellowman33|Mellowman33]] ([[User talk:Mellowman33|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Mellowman33|contribs]]) 11:06, July 21, 2015‎&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

== Employees/criticism section removal ==

The section titled &quot;Employees&quot; and then titled &quot;Criticism&quot; was removed for &quot;[[Wikipedia:RECENT|WP:RECENT]]. this is an article about a university that's been around since 1856 see [[Wikipedia:WEIGHT#Undue_weight|WP:WEIGHT]]. also the sources are from the student paper written by same author, or some bloggish site see[[Wikipedia:RS|wp:RS]].&quot;

The section listed relatively recent labor disputes with the contracted Wings construction company, contracted Daycon cleaning supplies company, and direct employees of the University who have been alleging abuse. [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=University_of_Maryland,_College_Park&amp;diff=444099038&amp;oldid=444098548 Here] is the last version before it was removed.

Included among the sources was a report by the National Labor Relations Board, an impartial adjuciations board, as well as a report by the Black Faculty and Staff Association at the University of Maryland. These two reports were both well-researched and put out by respected institutions.

I understand that a student newspaper is not a favored news source, though the Diamondback is ranked 8th best student newspaper by the Princeton Review ([http://collegemediamatters.com/2011/08/03/princeton-review-best-college-newspapers-2011-list/ link to article]). At any rate, there were actually two authors at the Diamdonback who were cited. The &quot;bloggish&quot; site also had two authors, at least one of whom was also incredibly well-researched and versed in the happenings.

Between these sources, I believe the section should be allowed to stand, particularly if it is given a disclaimer noting that these situations are relatively recent (though still valid to the understanding of the university and its functioning in a way that contributes to the historically long-standing study of labor relations which predates the founding of the University). [[User:Samtastic02|Samtastic02]] ([[User talk:Samtastic02|talk]]) 20:27, 10 August 2011 (UTC)
:The material that was removed seems to be much too long for this article.  A few sentences may be appropriate but multiple paragraphs is out of proportion for this particular article. [[User:ElKevbo|ElKevbo]] ([[User talk:ElKevbo|talk]]) 22:12, 10 August 2011 (UTC)
::Thank you for bringing this to the talk page.  I was the one who originally removed it, mostly per [[wp:undue]]: ''Discussion of isolated events, criticisms, or news reports about a subject may be verifiable and neutral, but still be disproportionate to their overall significance to the article topic''.  I'm no expert on this, but I believe that these type of labor concerns are in no way unique in a University context or in general.  In the context of everything else you could include about this subject, it is insignificant.  
::One way to refute this is to provide citations in third party independent [[wp:rs|reliable sources]].  The school newspaper is obviously not independent.  The other sources is a blog which is not a reliable source, and The Black Faculty and Staff Association at the University of Maryland, and the National Labor Relations Board are not independent. --[[User:CutOffTies|CutOffTies]] ([[User talk:CutOffTies|talk]]) 00:50, 11 August 2011 (UTC)

:::Please explain how the school newspaper and NLRB are not independent. [[User:ElKevbo|ElKevbo]] ([[User talk:ElKevbo|talk]]) 01:13, 11 August 2011 (UTC)
::::I mean independent of the subject matter.  A school newspaper (particularly a daily one) is going to write about the school.  The Black Faculty and Staff Association at the University of Maryland is concerned about Black Faculty and Staff Association at the University of Maryland. The Labor Relations Board is concerned with Labor Relation issues. Compare that to publications like The Washington Post, Baltimore Sun, Time Magazine - etc... Given that the editor is trying to establish significance to the content, I think it needs to be in one of these 'independent' publications to assert it --[[User:CutOffTies|CutOffTies]] ([[User talk:CutOffTies|talk]]) 01:36, 11 August 2011 (UTC)
:::::Ah, ok.  I think you're placing the bar a bit too high but it's not entirely unreasonable.  For me, if the NLRB had to get involved then it seems somewhat significant since they literally &quot;made a federal case out of it&quot; so a brief mention seems warranted. [[User:ElKevbo|ElKevbo]] ([[User talk:ElKevbo|talk]]) 05:02, 11 August 2011 (UTC)
==File:UMD Testudo Statue.JPG Nominated for Deletion==
{|
|-
| [[File:Image-x-generic.svg|100px]] 
| An image used in this article, [[commons:File:UMD Testudo Statue.JPG|File:UMD Testudo Statue.JPG]], has been nominated for deletion at [[Wikimedia Commons]] in the following category: ''Deletion requests October 2011'' 
;What should I do?
''Don't panic''; a discussion will now take place over on Commons about whether to remove the file. This gives you an opportunity to contest the deletion, although please review Commons guidelines before doing so.
* If the image is [[WP:NFCC|non-free]] then you may need to upload it to Wikipedia (Commons does not allow fair use)
* If the image isn't freely licensed and there is no [[WP:FUR|fair use rationale]] then it cannot be uploaded or used.

''This notification is provided by a Bot'' --[[User:CommonsNotificationBot|CommonsNotificationBot]] ([[User talk:CommonsNotificationBot|talk]]) 03:43, 29 October 2011 (UTC)
|}
==File:Tree walk map.pdf Nominated for speedy Deletion==
&lt;!--TSTAMP:{{{4}}}--&gt;
{|
|-
| [[File:Image-x-generic.svg|100px]] 
| &lt;!--IMAGES--&gt;
An image used in this article, [[:File:Tree walk map.pdf|File:Tree walk map.pdf]], has been nominated for speedy deletion for the following reason: ''All Wikipedia files with unknown copyright status'' 
&lt;!--/IMAGES--&gt;
;What should I do?
''Don't panic''; you should have time to contest the deletion (although please review [[WP:CSD|deletion guidelines]] before doing so). The best way to contest this form of deletion is by posting on the image talk page.
* If the image is [[WP:NFCC|non-free]] then you may need to provide a [[WP:FUR|fair use rationale]]
* If the image isn't freely licensed and there is no fair use rationale, then it cannot be uploaded or used.
* If the image has already been deleted you may want to try [[WP:DRV|Deletion Review]]
To take part in any discussion, or to review a more detailed deletion rationale please visit the relevant [[:File:Tree walk map.pdf|image page (File:Tree walk map.pdf)]]

''This is Bot placed notification, another user has nominated/tagged the image'' --[[User:CommonsNotificationBot|CommonsNotificationBot]] ([[User talk:CommonsNotificationBot|talk]]) 09:38, 23 May 2012 (UTC)
|}

== Merge from [[Center for Bioinformatics and Computational Biology]] to [[University of Maryland, College Park]] ==

Center for Bioinformatics and Computational Biology is not notable enough for an article of its own (and has been tagged as such for six years) but could be a useful section in this article. [[User:Boleyn|Boleyn]] ([[User talk:Boleyn|talk]]) 07:33, 15 September 2014 (UTC)
*'''Oppose:''' Would look like an obscure detail in this article. Try to expand that article.  [[User Talk:DissidentAggressor|The Dissident Aggressor]] 13:03, 17 September 2014 (UTC)
*'''Oppose:''' CBCB is one of the larger research centers at UMD.  It could probably be expanded rather easily if someone cared to. --[[User:Padenton|Padenton]] ([[User talk:Padenton|talk]]) 18:29, 9 March 2015 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:3|one external link|3 external links}} on [[University of Maryland, College Park]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=701633627 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20080724071759/http://www.start.umd.edu/about/ to http://www.start.umd.edu/about/
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20120526073339/http://www.solardecathlon.gov:80/scores.html to http://www.solardecathlon.gov/scores.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20120505155422/http://www.diamondbackonline.com/news/new-reusable-dining-container-use-grows-1.2792784 to http://www.diamondbackonline.com/news/new-reusable-dining-container-use-grows-1.2792784#.T6bhmJhEa_Z

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 17:54, 25 January 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:6|one external link|6 external links}} on [[University of Maryland, College Park]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=706608216 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20100608032824/http://umd.universityvisitorsnetwork.com:80/gardens.php to http://umd.universityvisitorsnetwork.com/gardens.php
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20120505101157/http://www.diamondbackonline.com/news/sustainability-minor-to-launch-next-semester-1.2734616 to http://www.diamondbackonline.com/news/sustainability-minor-to-launch-next-semester-1.2734616#.T6bTyZhEa_a
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20120505143648/http://www.diamondbackonline.com/news/motion-sensors-installed-in-classrooms-to-save-energy-1.2764215 to http://www.diamondbackonline.com/news/motion-sensors-installed-in-classrooms-to-save-energy-1.2764215#.T6biLJhEa_Z
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20120409081445/http://www.diamondbackonline.com:80/news/univ-funds-130-000-to-green-projects-1.2809091 to http://www.diamondbackonline.com/news/univ-funds-130-000-to-green-projects-1.2809091#.T6birphEa_Z
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20120421002956/http://www.co.pg.md.us:80/Government/AgencyIndex/DPW&amp;T/Transit/TheBus.asp to http://www.co.pg.md.us/government/agencyindex/dpw&amp;t/transit/thebus.asp
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20060908084925/http://www.rhsmith.umd.edu:80/news/stories/2005/smithgift.html to http://www.rhsmith.umd.edu/news/stories/2005/smithgift.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 07:25, 24 February 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[University of Maryland, College Park]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=707814412 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20120817224527/http://www.diamondbackonline.com/news/a-refreshing-new-option-1.2867399 to http://www.diamondbackonline.com/news/a-refreshing-new-option-1.2867399#.T6bi_JhEa_Y

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 23:08, 1 March 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>m7faowp97wv2btjq141brx3itkbwm4b</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
