<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Olaudah Equiano</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2665223</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746784631</id>
      <parentid>742788346</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-29T15:00:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DavidCane</username>
        <id>196269</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Amend class for WP:LONDON -  A-class not used</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="28793">{{Talk header}}
{{WikiProject banner shell|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=n|class=A|listas=Equiano, Olaudah|a&amp;e-work-group=y|a&amp;e-priority=High}}
{{WikiProject Igbo|class=A|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Africa|class=A|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject African diaspora|class=A|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject London|class=B|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject United Kingdom|class=A|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Transport|class=A|importance=High|maritime=y|maritime-importance=High}}
}}

== [[Wikipedia:WikiProject_Biography/Assessment#Class_parameter|Biography assessment rating]] comment ==
[[Wikipedia:WikiProject Biography/Assessment|WikiProject Biography Assessment]]

==Equiano's death==
The article says Equiano died on the 31th of March 1797, this is a date published in ''The gentleman's magazine''
I 'd like to refer to ''Paul Edwards, EQUIANO'S TRAVELS, 1996''.the editors introduction on page XXI  : &quot; a few years later the editors of the 1809 (Belper) and the 1814 ( Leeds) editions do not know the date of his death. THe editor of 1809 gives it as 1801 and the editor of 1814 admits that he does not know...&quot;[[User:Dorisjanminters|Dorisjanminters]] ([[User talk:Dorisjanminters|talk]]) 21:21, 11 March 2009 (UTC)
j

==Discussion==
From the reading I have done it was Pascal not King who educated Equiano, no? (http://www.brycchancarey.com/equiano/biog.htm) &amp; (http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/aia/part1/1p276.html) [[User:HybridFusion|HybridFusion]] 03:20, 5 October 2005 (UTC)

&quot;Sadly, in his weakened state he fell prey to the mental illness of religion. The other slaves fooled Equiano into believing that if he was not baptized, he would not be able to go to Heaven&quot; This is rediculous... I am not religious at all but thats the least neutral thing i've read in a while.

== Quality of the article ==
I am not a specialist on Olaudah Equiano, but I hope one who can correct this badly written article will read it. I shall not even go into the details, but the English is terrible, the grammar is appalling, the spelling is done in heist and furthermore, even the name of the title hero is shown in two different versions: Olaudah and Olandah.
In my sincere opinion articles like this, give Wikipedia a bad name. I wish I knew enough on the subject matter to edit it myself, but that is not the case. &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[User:Ruskiman|Ruskiman]] ([[User talk:Ruskiman|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Ruskiman|contribs]]) 15:07, 22 December 2006 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;

haste? [[User:Zigzig20s|Zigzig20s]] 04:40, 27 January 2007 (UTC)

There is also at least one factual error. The article states: 'Pascal had him cuffed and told him that he would remain in shakles until he accepted the name chosen for him.' This represents a misunderstanding of the word 'cuffed', which means simply 'slapped', and there is no mention of shakles in the text.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/80.176.229.152|80.176.229.152]] ([[User talk:80.176.229.152|talk]]) 14:24, 18 July 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Refering to OE as &quot;his toy&quot; is very POV and unencyclopedic. &quot;Some historians will say otherwise&quot; is a weasel formation. [[User:Darmot and gilad|Darmot and gilad]] ([[User talk:Darmot and gilad|talk]]) 16:06, 7 October 2010 (UTC)

==Discussion text which makes the article read more like a student essay==
you did not state what language he spoke and what was his education about  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/148.100.224.129|148.100.224.129]] ([[User talk:148.100.224.129|talk]]) 22:44, 8 July 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

I would suggest placing this here, rather than in the article. If anyone has a better suggestion please improve.

'''Birth in colonial America or West Africa ?'''
&lt;blockquote&gt;
1. Written Evidence:
*  ''Support for the idea that Equiano was born in Carolina'' - Equiano's baptismal record at St Margaret’s Church, Westminster, dated 9 February 1759, records that he was born in 'Carolina'; a Royal Navy muster roll from Constantine Phipp’s Arctic expedition of 1773 says that Equiano was born in 'South Carolina'. In both cases, the information almost certainly came from Equiano himself; there are no primary sources. 
*  ''Support for the idea that Equiano was born in Africa'' - Equiano's own autobiography, 'The Interesting Narrative...' tells us that he was born in West Africa. This information also comes from Equiano himself. 

2. Circumstantial Biographical Evidence:
*  ''Support for the idea that Equiano was born in Carolina'' - Equiano gets the dates wrong about the ships in which he was brought from America to England which would be consistent with him having made this part of his story up. Equiano's account of his life is usually very accurate when it can be checked against independent or primary sources, making it surprising that his account of his first ten years can be shown to be inaccurate in parts. Equiano is not recorded as having used the name &quot;Equiano&quot; before publishing his autobiography. All his friends and acquaintances knew him by the name &quot;Gustavus Vassa&quot;. He probably made up the name &quot;Olaudah Equiano&quot; as part of the careful construction of an African persona he carried out in 1789. 
*  ''Support for the idea that Equiano was born in West Africa'' - Although Equiano gets the dates wrong about the ships in which he was brought from America to England, he was a very young child at the time, and suffering a severe trauma, so it is reasonable to assume that his memory might sometimes be at fault. Equiano's account of his life is usually very accurate when it can be checked against independent sources, showing that it was his usual practice to tell the truth as far as he could remember. Although Equiano never used his birth name before 1789, this was not unusual. Few slaves or former slaves used their African names. Equiano's friend Quobna Ottobah Cugoano, for example, used his slave name of John Stuart throughout his life, except on the title page of his book (1787). &quot;Gustavus Vassa&quot; was not his birth name, even had he been born in colonial America, it was given to him later by a master.

3. Equiano's Motivation:
*  ''Support for the idea that Equiano was born in Carolina'' - Equiano's main motivation was to end the slave trade, so he would write or say anything in his published work that he thought he could get away with, as long as it brought the abolition of the slave trade, and slavery itself, closer. Equiano had nothing to hide in his early life, so he told the truth about his birthplace to the church clerk at his baptism and to the naval officer who compiled the muster roll in which he gave his birthplace as South Carolina. 
*  ''Support for the idea that Equiano was born in Africa'' - Equiano's main motivation was to end the slave trade, end slavery, and establish free settlements in West Africa, so he would be very careful to tell the truth in his published work and not write or say anything that might bring him or his campaign into disrepute.  Equiano had been born in West Africa but now had to make the best of his new life and circumstances, and  there was little point in making an issue about his origins, now that his life was in the 'New World' he gave this as his 'adopted' birthplace. 
 
4. Close Reading of the Text:
* ''Support for the idea that Equiano was born in Carolina'' - Much of the early part of 'The Interesting Narrative...', in which Equiano describes West Africa and the Middle Passage, closely resembles similar accounts made by European or American authors, for example, by Anthony Benezet. Equiano probably invented his African childhood, and copied information out of books such as these. The parts of 'The Interesting Narrative...' that describe West Africa and the Middle Passage have a mythological style that makes them unreliable as history. 
* ''Support for the idea that Equiano was born in Africa'' - Much of the early part of 'The Interesting Narrative...', in which Equiano describes West Africa and the Middle Passage, closely resembles similar accounts made by European or American authors, for example, by Anthony Benezet, yet Equiano references many of these works, as would anyone giving a true account, having consulted them in order to help him remember the details of a distant childhood and out of genuine interest in the geography and social anthropology of his homeland. The parts of ''The Interesting Narrative...' that describe West Africa and the Middle Passage are strengthened by this example of thorough research and show that he took his work very seriously and wanted to write to a very high standard.

5. Contemporary Expectations:
*  ''Support for the idea that Equiano was born in Carolina'' - Readers in the eighteenth century were not fools, and demanded the same high level of honesty and veracity that we would now expect. However, Equiano knew that it would be very difficult for his readers to check the truth, or otherwise, of his account. In the late eighteenth century, there were more poems, plays, and novels written against slavery than there were 'serious' political tracts. Readers would thus have been more interested in hearing general truths about slavery than particular histories, and so wouldn't have cared so much about whether the details of Equiano's story were true.  
*  ''Support for the idea that Equiano was born in Africa'' - Readers in the eighteenth century were not fools, and demanded the same high level of honesty and veracity that we would now expect. Thus, Equiano would not have tried to get away with telling a lie about his African origins - somebody, somewhere, would have known the truth.  In the late eighteenth century, there were more poems, plays, and novels written against slavery than there were 'serious' political tracts. Equiano would have known that, to be taken seriously, he had to appear as more than just a writer of fiction, but as someone who could write to a very high literary standard, and tell the whole truth.

6. The Realities of Equiano's Life:
* ''Support for the idea that Equiano was born in Carolina'' - Even though Equiano was born in Carolina, he was a long way from home and, by the 1780s, could get away with saying anything he liked about his past, particularly since communications between England and America had been disrupted in the war of 1775-1783.  When Equiano was asked for his place of birth during his childhood baptism, he may not have had at that time a sufficient mastery of the legal protocols or legalistic language to give the answer that is normally expected (for example, if he had been asked 'where are you from', he may have understood it as 'where have you recently come from'); however, if this was the case, there is no reason why, as an adult and a fluent English speaker, he would continue to say that he had been born in Carolina, as he later did when joining Constantine Phipp’s Arctic expedition of 1773. 
* ''Support for the idea that Equiano was born in Africa'' - Despite the war, links between England and America were still close. Had he been lying, sooner or later someone in America would have detected his falsehood, particularly after his book was published in New York in 1791. Equiano knew that the most intensive search would be made by proslavery campaigners to discredit him. Therefore, he would not have attempted to invent a new identity and birthplace. When Equiano was asked for his place of birth during his childhood baptism, he may not have had at that time a sufficient mastery of the legal protocols or legalistic language to give the answer that is normally expected (for example, if he had been asked 'where are you from', he may have understood it as 'where have you recently come from'); and once the mistake was in writing on his baptismal record, he might have chosen to simply accept the error as unimportant. 

7. Equiano's Psychological State:
*  ''Support for the idea that Equiano was born in Carolina'' - As a terrified and traumatised child, the young Equiano would have been too afraid to tell anything other than the truth when asked for his place of birth at his baptism ceremony. 
*  ''Support for the idea that Equiano was born in Africa'' - As a terrified and traumatised child, the young Equiano may have been too afraid to tell the truth when asked for his place of birth at his baptism ceremony. Many children, especially traumatised children, invent stories to explain their origins. Many such people come to terms with their trauma in later life. This might explain why Equiano tells one story when younger, and another when older. 

8. The Bottom Line:
*  The bottom line is that we just don't know. As the above list shows, there is evidence on both sides of the debate. Just about the only thing we can say for certain is that, when he was younger, Equiano told people he was from Carolina, but when he was older, he told people he was from West Africa. Whether you believe the younger Equiano or the older Equiano is entirely up to you...
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
[[User:Jolayemi|Jolayemi]] 23:17, 22 January 2007 (UTC)

:I would agree to remove it from the article and leave it here instead. [[User:Zigzig20s|Zigzig20s]] 04:55, 27 January 2007 (UTC)

:This text was plagiarized from http://www.brycchancarey.com/equiano/nativity.htm (Text © Brycchan Carey 2003-2005) It should be removed immediately.  However, because it is also one of the best sources examining the two sides of this issue, the article should have a link in the section that discusses Equiano's origin.[[User:Josh a brewer|Josh a brewer]] 07:26, 11 March 2007 (UTC)

::It can (and should be) be referred to by External link, in order to avoid [[copyright violation]].[[User:Parkwells|Parkwells]] ([[User talk:Parkwells|talk]]) 21:23, 6 June 2014 (UTC)

== Comment on my edit ==
I have moved chunks of this article around, with the intention of providing a straightforward account of his life, leaving material as to scholarly controversy to the end.  I have to confess that I know little of the subject and have undertaken this 'blind'.  I hope the result is an improvement.  I have not removed the cleanup and essay tags, because I do not feel qualified to do so, but hope there is some one else who can.  I hope the stylistic probelms are resolved, but not necessarily those of content.   [[User:Peterkingiron|Peterkingiron]] 14:36, 25 February 2007 (UTC)

==A prince?==
In the film, ''[[Amazing Grace (2006 film)|Amazing Grace]],'' he refers to himself as someone who was born a [[prince]] in Africa.  What veracity is there to the claim that he was a prince?  Generally, what was the [[social status]] of his family background? [[User:Dogru144|Dogru144]] 15:16, 4 March 2007 (UTC)

:Yes, sadly the film doesn't have much to do with history.  Equiano is made to stand in for all slaves synecdochically, be they African American, African Caribbean, or African Princes.  In other words, the film does not clear up whether or not Equiano was a prince from Africa or a pauper from South Carolina (though they do cleverly work in a reference to this as a strategy designed to silence him).  Incidentally, during Equiano's lifetime some people claimed that he was from the Caribbean, though he denied these accounts.[[User:Josh a brewer|Josh a brewer]] 07:25, 11 March 2007 (UTC)

In Equiano's autobiography he claims he was the son of a chief... Might be technically incorrect in the movie but the idea is correct. 28/10/2010.

== Duplication ==
The section headed &quot;Pioneer of the abolitionist cause&quot; to some extent duplicates the earlier section with an account of his life - does someone who knows about the narrative he wrote want to give a better comment on it and leave the life-story to the earlier section? In common with earlier editors of this page I fear I'm coming at it blind, I hope my edits for clarity and grammar have improved things slightly. [[User:Euryanthe|Euryanthe]] 12:01, 22 March 2007 (UTC)

== Slavery in England ==
Actually neither edit summary is really correct. The 1807 Act abolished slavery in British overseas colonies; to quote myself at [[Cesar Picton]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt; &quot;The status of slaves imported into England was legally ambiguous and unclear when Picton arrived, but they were certainly not regarded or treated in the same way as slaves in the British American colonies. The situation was clarified considerably by [[Somersett's Case]] of 1772, which although the details are unclear when analysed by lawyers, was generally taken to hold than no person could be a slave in England itself (confirming other reported judgements of 1567 and 1702). Many white apprentices and workers of the time would be classified as near-slaves, though in a time-limited way, by modern standards, and already most black servants seem to have been regarded and treated as free, at least by the time they reached adulthood.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

- but there are odd cases of young boys being advertised for sale after 1772.  I will remove the reference, which is not really accurate if quoted correctly, &amp; replace with a link to Somersett [[User:Johnbod|Johnbod]] 02:15, 29 April 2007 (UTC) 

:With the exception of blacks brought here as domestic servants by planters, there has never been slavery in England, at least not since the Norman period.  However, there were phenomena that may be mistaken for it: 
*Advertisements concerning apprenticing poor children, which was partly a means of providing for their maintenance and education.  
*The transportation of convicts, who arrived in America, and were sold as indentured servants for a term to pay for theri passage.  [[User:Peterkingiron|Peterkingiron]] 21:29, 29 April 2007 (UTC)

That's the theory; in practice things had sometimes been more complicated. [[User:Johnbod|Johnbod]] 21:49, 29 April 2007 (UTC)

==Editing References and External links==
Here are links that are useful for studying the slave trade, but either don't mention, or don't focus on, Equiano:
* [http://www.ltscotland.org.uk/abolition/ Scotland and the Abolition of the Slave Trade - schools resource].
*[http://www.blackhistory4schools.com/slavetrade/ Teaching resources about Slavery and Abolition on blackhistory4schools.com].

I've cut them from the page, but I'm reposting them here it case they're useful to someone else. --[[User:Yamara|Yamara]] 19:45, 25 May 2007 (UTC)

== Equiano's Igbo name ==
A user named &quot;Black plague&quot; makes the following statement: &quot;'Equiano' is how the man rendered his name in English in the 1700's, obviously in a time before the Igbo language had a standard written orthography. Ekwuano is how it's rendered in modern Igbo.&quot;  In response, I posit that the question is simply this: How does Equiano's name appear in his own writing and in secondary sources about him?  Cite a relevant secondary source that gives his name in the modern Igbo, and then we'll talk.[[User:Josh a brewer|Josh a brewer]] 09:54, 11 July 2007 (UTC)

== Slaver? == 
&quot;In addition to being a slave as a young man, he was also a slaver, seaman, merchant, and explorer in South America, the Caribbean, the American colonies, Britain, and the North Pole.&quot; He was an anti-slvery activist and a slaver? That makes no sense. Can anyone verify this?  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Quaoarian|Quaoarian]] ([[User talk:Quaoarian|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Quaoarian|contribs]]) 19:04, 18 September 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Yes, he writes about this in Chapter XI of his autobiography.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/129.252.216.85|129.252.216.85]] ([[User talk:129.252.216.85|talk]]) 13:41, 9 October 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Not sure why, but someone removed the fact that Equiano traveled on an expedition to the North Pole and that he was a slaver in addition to being an anti-slavery activist later in his life.  Just thought I'd point out these omissions--well, deletions.  [[User:Josh a brewer|Josh a brewer]] 18:59, 24 October 2007 (UTC)

== Missing references ==
Should this article not contain some reference to the &quot;Sons of Africa&quot; - the lobby group that Equiano was part of?

The BBC mentions it briefly on their page ... http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/historic_figures/equiano_olaudah.shtml

[[User:ETis|ETis]] 23:54, 23 October 2007 (UTC)

: Yeah, go ahead and add it! --[[User:JayHenry|JayHenry]] 00:41, 24 October 2007 (UTC)

== Incomprehensible Section ==
''According to Equiano's narrative, he remained '' [...]
''the Thirty Years' War when Sweden and England were allies, sank within one nautical mile of the start of her maiden voyage in 1628.[clarification needed] The recovery attempts by the English engineers called in to assist proved fruitless; the ship was firmly stuck in the mud until 1961. During the period Equiano was enslaved by Pascal, the Seven Years' War had pitted Sweden against England and as a reference to the enemy's early 17th century flag ship Vasa, the name would have appeared mocking.''

This badly truncated piece seems to imply that Equiano was named after the Swedish warship [[Vasa (ship)|Vasa]], which sank ignominiously in 1628. However, that ship was named for Gustavus Adolfus Vasa, a much later monarch than Gustavus Vasa.  Are there any references to the origin of his name (Gustavus Vasa) in the reference material? If not, this is speculation, and badly thought out, too.[[User:Anklefear|Anklefear]] ([[User talk:Anklefear|talk]]) 00:19, 14 April 2009 (UTC)

:Agree that this section seems to be missing text. War or no, the idea that his name was a mocking reference to a ship that had sunk more than 120 years previously would need some citation (as does the alternative attribution, to be honest). --[[User:GenericBob|GenericBob]] ([[User talk:GenericBob|talk]]) 03:46, 14 April 2009 (UTC)
::His Swedish name can only refer to the the first king, ([[Gustav I of Sweden|Gustav Vasa/Gustav I)]], and can not have had anything to do with the ship, which was NOT named after [[Gustavus Adolphus of Sweden|Gustav II Adolf]] (the grandson of Gustav Vasa), as that ship was known as &quot;Vasen&quot; (The Sheaf) until the early 20th century, when some decided to link the ship's name to the noble family and royal [[House of Vasa]], which had a sheaf on their coat of arms. [[User:Thomas Blomberg|Thomas Blomberg]] ([[User talk:Thomas Blomberg|talk]]) 03:43, 28 August 2011 (UTC)

== ??? ==
&quot;For instance, Acholonu claims in her book to have interviewed living respondents in the 1980s who remembered growing up with Equiano before his capture in the mid-18th century.&quot;

This makes no sense what so ever, is this true? A source please! -- [[User:Ukabia|Ukabia]] ([[User talk:Ukabia|talk]]) 01:11, 10 May 2009 (UTC)ge t

==Conversion section==
This reads too much like a literary critical discussion.  I removed the names of scholars and left them in reference citations.  Tried to tone language to something more like an encyclopedia article.--[[User:Parkwells|Parkwells]] ([[User talk:Parkwells|talk]]) 19:24, 10 September 2009 (UTC)

== Article is POV about religion ==
This is from the article:

&quot;Sadly, in his weakened state he [Equiano] fell prey to the mental illness of religion. The other slaves fooled Equiano into believing that if he was not baptized, he would not be able to go to Heaven.&quot;

I don't know much about Equiano, but this passage is obviously very biased, so I'll replace it with a simple statement that he converted to Christianity.

== things about olaudah equiano ==
he stop slavey  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/209.80.156.37|209.80.156.37]] ([[User talk:209.80.156.37|talk]]) 18:43, 16 December 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Birthplace Mistake ==
I noticed in the section titled &quot;Early Life&quot;, the article says: &quot;Olaudah Equiano was born in Alaska with Sandra Palin, an Igbo village in the kingdom of Benin...&quot; This is clearly a mistake, possibly because of a &quot;copy-paste&quot; error, but Olaudah Equiano clearly was not born in Alaska.  [[Special:Contributions/66.82.9.82|66.82.9.82]] ([[User talk:66.82.9.82|talk]]) 20:33, 10 December 2010 (UTC)Josh[[Special:Contributions/66.82.9.82|66.82.9.82]] ([[User talk:66.82.9.82|talk]]) 20:33, 10 December 2010 (UTC)

::Vandalism. &lt;font style=&quot;font-family:Monotype Corsiva; font-size:15px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Spanglej|Span]] ([[User talk:Spanglej|talk]])&lt;/font&gt; 13:57, 29 December 2013 (UTC)                                                                     

== Release section ==

Portions of this section are incomplete, or simply confusing grammatically;

''He enabled Equiano to buy his freedom, which he achieved by his early twenties.  King urged Equiano to stay on as a business.  For instance, while loading a ship in Georgia, he was almost kidnapped back into slavery. He was released after proving his education.  Equiano returned to Britain where, after the ruling in Somersett's Case of 1772, men believed they were free of the risk of enslavement. He was released in 1789.''

--sorry, I don't know how to get the quote to wrap

&quot;King urged Equiano to stay on as a business.....&quot; what?  I don't know if this was meant to read &quot;business partner&quot; but as it stands it makes no logical sense.

Then the next sentence begins with &quot;For instance&quot; when it does not follow at all the preceding sentence.

Ultimately the grammar is shaky at best - &quot;men believed they were free&quot; is a bit absurd, and &quot;He was released in 1789&quot; simply needs more information as it leaves all details obscure - from whom? by whom? by his own hand?  After having claimed that Equiano would eventually &quot;buy his [own] freedom&quot;... all subsequent references are done in passive voice - &quot;was released&quot; as if someone else was responsible for the act...

If someone who has the proper info can clean this section up, I do apologize for just pointing out the problems, but I do not know the subject well enough to make honest alterations. [[Special:Contributions/174.70.128.122|174.70.128.122]] ([[User talk:174.70.128.122|talk]]) 04:56, 29 December 2013 (UTC)

:::Thanks for flagging it up. It is the remnant of old vandalism from many months ago and terrible writing from an article that badly needs an overhaul. I have reinstated the original paragraph. &lt;font style=&quot;font-family:Monotype Corsiva; font-size:15px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Spanglej|Span]] ([[User talk:Spanglej|talk]])&lt;/font&gt; 14:12, 29 December 2013 (UTC)

==Name?==
Sometimes he is called Equiano, sometimes Vassa, often in the same section or paragraph. Should he be referred to as Vassa while he is a slave, or Equiano? Im really confused.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/90.200.34.230|90.200.34.230]] ([[User talk:90.200.34.230|talk]]) 11:52, 19 October 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Additions  ==

There were several things I noticed that were wrong with this page. I plan on adding a variety of wiki-links to words that the reader might need the definition too. I will also try to find reputable sources for all the places that indicate they need a citation. I will also change his name so he is referred to by the same name throughout the entire article. Lastly, the article states that his slave narrative was the first know slave narrative, and I don't think that is correct, so I am going to look more into it and correct it if necessary. 

[[User:Zem Mitchell|Zem Mitchell]] ([[User talk:Zem Mitchell|talk]]) 01:15, 3 November 2015 (UTC)

==Assessment comment==
{{Substituted comment|length=518|lastedit=20070525175333|comment={{nw=}}{{nw=}} [[Wikipedia:WikiProject_Biography/Assessment#Class_parameter|Biography assessment rating]] comment {{nw=}}{{nw=}}
[[Wikipedia:WikiProject Biography/Assessment|WikiProject Biography Assessment]]

Could be a B class with some cleanup and inline citations.

The article may be improved by following the [[Wikipedia:WikiProject_Biography#WikiProject_Biography_11_easy_steps_to_producing_at_least_a_B_article|WikiProject Biography 11 easy steps]] to producing at least a B article. -- [[User:Yamara|Yamara]] 17:53, 25 May 2007 (UTC)}}
Substituted at 01:46, 30 April 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>0640ku32hvv2lwlr4b160itiirlt35n</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
