<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Virginia Tech</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>24792566</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750904989</id>
      <parentid>740506314</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-22T04:25:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Caballero1967</username>
        <id>395969</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Dining */ Explaining why I am removing template from the article and asking for explanation and evidence prior to reinstating it.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="65752">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Virginia|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Universities|class=B}}
{{WikiProject ACC|class=B|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Virginia Tech|class=b|importance=top}}
{{Glass|class=b|importance=mid}}
}}
{{Todo|nocats=yes}}
{{tasks
  |requests= [[History of Virginia Tech]], [[Virginia Tech Hokies womens basketball]], [[Whit Babcock]], [[Thanassis Rikakis]], [[Virginia Tech Board of Visitors]], [[Virginia Tech Honors Residential College]], [[Fralin Life Science Institute]], [[Institute for Creativity, Arts and Technology]], [[Institute for Critical Technology and Applied Science]], [[Institute for Society, Culture, and Environment]], [[Virginia Bioinformatics Institute at Virginia Tech]], [[Virginia Tech Carilion Research Institute]], [[Virginia Tech Transportation Institute]], [[Virginia Tech Research Center – Arlington]], [[Virginia Tech Applied Research Corporation]], [[Virginia Tech Southwest Center]], [[Virginia Tech Roanoke Center]], [[Virginia Tech National Capital Region]], [[Virginia Tech Northern Virginia Center]], [[Virginia Tech Hampton Roads Centers]], [[Virginia Tech Caribbean Center for Education and Research]], [[Steger Center for International Scholarship]]
  |copyedit=
  |wikify=[[Virginia Tech commencement speakers]]
  |merge=
  |cleanup=
  |expand= [[Virginia Tech Hokies]], [[Virginia Tech Hokies football]], [[Virginia Tech Hokies men's basketball]], [[Timothy Sands]], [[Hunter Carpenter]], [[Joseph F. Ware, Sr.]], [[Virginia Tech Foundation]], [[Virginia Cooperative Extension]], [[List of Virginia Tech alumni]], [[Virginia Tech Institute for Policy and Governance]], [[Washington-Alexandria Architecture Center]], [[Center for Modeling Immunity to Enteric Pathogens]]
  |disambiguation=
  |stubs=
  |update=
  |npov=
  |verify=
  |other=
}}
&lt;noinclude&gt;[[Category:WikiProject Virginia Tech]]&lt;/noinclude&gt;
{{archive box|auto=yes}}

==Image choice==
Please compare these two images:
[[Image:VirginiaTechCampusBridge.jpg|thumb|left]]
[[Image:Virginiatech-bridge-over-mall.JPG|thumb|left]]
I contend that the bottom one is brighter, has a better view of the VT logo, shows the Hokie stone better, focuses more on the subject of the building than the foreground of the pavement, and in general is a better choice for this article.[[User:HokieRNB|HokieRNB]] ([[User talk:HokieRNB|talk]]) 16:13, 11 March 2008 (UTC)

I would agree with the fact that it shows the hokie stone better but it looks washed out and unprofessional. I have cropped the other image so that it shows the hokie stone better and focuses more on the bridge. I also have added a better lit picture that I have that I think is more professional looking. Let me know what you think: [[Image:TorgBridgeVirginiaTech.jpg|thumb|left|cropped version]] [[Image:VirginiaTechBridge.jpg|thumb|left|alternative, brighter version]]

Don't take this the wrong way, but they all look crooked. I'd use the &quot;level&quot; tool in Photoshop or Gimp to crop them correctly. ([[User:Possum4all|Possum4all]] ([[User talk:Possum4all|talk]]) 06:03, 25 November 2009 (UTC))

==Academics==
Great job whoever just expanded the academics section. It's just what we needed. [[User:Chuy1530|Chuy1530]] ([[User talk:Chuy1530|talk]]) 13:47, 27 June 2008 (UTC)

==Art's Initiative==

Would the art initiatives bit that was recently reverted due to being a blatant copy and paste be worthy of being in the article if it were rewritten? I'd be willing to rewrite it so that it isn't a copyright issue but only if it's deemed appropriate for the article. [[User:Chuy1530|Chuy1530]] ([[User talk:Chuy1530|talk]]) 17:24, 11 July 2008 (UTC)

== Proposal: references should read &quot;Virginia Tech&quot; ==

I move that in other wiki pages that reference this page the link should read &quot;Virginia Tech&quot; not &quot;Virginia Polytechnic Institute&quot;.  &quot;Virginia Tech&quot; is one of the university's official names and is by far the most common name.  It's even on the letterhead.  [[User:SnappingTurtle|SnappingTurtle]] ([[User talk:SnappingTurtle|talk]]) 22:37, 22 August 2008 (UTC)

go for it --[[User:Buridan|Buridan]] ([[User talk:Buridan|talk]]) 11:12, 23 August 2008 (UTC)

== Weight of 2007 massacre ==

Please understand that I don't mean to be obsessed with tragic events here, but I do think that mentioning the [[Virginia Tech massacre]] only as a 'see also' in this page is probably downplaying its significance too much. Especially given that readers unfamiliar with the subject will take some time to recognise that 'Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University' is in fact the same institution commonly referred to as 'Virginia Tech', the lack of any mention in the text may leave people unsure whether they are on the right page. Would it not be worth adding a one sentence mention in the 'History' section with a quick link? Something like &quot;On 16 April 2007, 32 students and members of staff were [[Virginia Tech massacre|shot dead]] and many others wounded by a student in the deadliest shooting incident by a single gunman in United States history.&quot; (or possibly shorter) [[User:Sam Blacketer|Sam Blacketer]] ([[User talk:Sam Blacketer|talk]]) 11:38, 4 October 2008 (UTC)

:: I fully agree. It is obviously (however unsavoury it may be) something that is tied with the university. It does need to be referenced in the intro and more directly in the history summary. This has precedent as evidenced by the [[Columbine High School]] page. It can't simply not be mentioned beyond the reference link. No one intends to be hurtful, but Wikpeadia shouldn't censor itself for the sake of political correctness. If no one has any better suggestions I will do so later. [[User:Syferus|Syferus]] ([[User talk:Syferus|talk]]) 11:47, 16 October 2008 (UTC)

:::It used to have a subsection under History that directed readers to the main article, but it seems that an IP editor removed it [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Virginia_Polytechnic_Institute_and_State_University&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=228232889 diff].  I will add it back.  [[User:Dynaflow|&lt;font color=&quot;#285991&quot;&gt;--'''''Dynaflow'''''&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User_talk:Dynaflow|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#285991&quot;&gt;babble&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 00:35, 17 October 2008 (UTC)

::::I absolutely agree the shootings do not have enough weight. Listing the massacre as the final &quot;See Also&quot; is burying it way too much. I think it needs to be a couple sentences in the history summary, with a link, at the very least. [[User:Otto1970|Otto1970]] ([[User talk:Otto1970|talk]]) 22:50, 19 January 2010 (UTC)

I came here looking for the massacre, I must admit, I doubted for a second if it was a different V-tech, since the word death isn't even mentioned in the article. I think it's cool that some people can baw so much, that the rational people just censor the whole thing to shut them up for good. But I also think it would be smart to start discussing how many shootings/deaths are necessary for them to make it into this page. Kind of, since all this is bound to happen again, why not set right here right now, how many shootings have to take place before they are acknowledged?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/190.50.217.212|190.50.217.212]] ([[User talk:190.50.217.212|talk]]) 09:13, 5 August 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:It's right there in the article:  &quot;In 2007, the school and campus received international attention as the site of the Virginia Tech massacre, which was the deadliest peacetime shooting incident by a single gunman in United States history, on or off of a school campus.&quot; [[User talk:HokieRNB|Hokie]][[User:HokieRNB|RNB]] 01:10, 12 August 2011 (UTC)

== A new bizarre episode involving violent death -- include or not? ==

When I saw [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Virginia_Polytechnic_Institute_and_State_University&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=265641250 this anonymous edit], I assumed it was typical bullshit vandalism.  Indeed, another anon editor removed it almost immediately as an &quot;inaccuracy.&quot;  Just to make sure all my ducks were in a row before leaving the first anon a {{tl|uw-error1}}, I checked the ''Collegiate Times'', and to my surprise found that it seems the first IP editor [http://www.collegiatetimes.com/stories/2009/01/21/stabbing_death_in_donaldson_brown was substantially correct].&lt;br /&gt;Naturally, other editors in the grip of [[WP:RECENTISM]] will want to add this incident to the article, perhaps, as the first person to attempt the addition did, link it implicitly with the Cho incident.  There are a lot of good reasons this new murder should '''not''' be included in the article for the time being and should not be added in the future unless it ends up having some sort of earth-shattering, direction-changing impact on the institution itself.  For a precedent, and a detailed discussion of the aforementioned good reasons to leave this kind of thing out, see [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:St._Mark's_College_(University_of_Adelaide)/RfC:_Should_a_murder_be_included_in_a_college's_article&amp;oldid=182482054 Talk:St. Mark's College (University of Adelaide)/RfC: Should a murder be included in a college's article] (link to last revision before page was courtesy-blanked).  [[User:Dynaflow|&lt;font color=&quot;#285991&quot;&gt;--'''''Dynaflow'''''&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User_talk:Dynaflow|&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#285991&quot;&gt;babble&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 09:11, 22 January 2009 (UTC)

I don't see that it's necessary. Why is it relevant at all on this page? His bio would be the best place, right? Would the top-most Army page get updated? I think not. Why this page? ([[User:Possum4all|Possum4all]] ([[User talk:Possum4all|talk]]) 06:00, 25 November 2009 (UTC))

== Research Computing ==

I'm not really sure how the editing goes, but while doing some work for my resume I found some more information on the newest super computer from the CHECS(Center for High End Computing) site.

http://www.checs.eng.vt.edu/

http://www.vtnews.vt.edu/story.php?relyear=2008&amp;itemno=745  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/198.82.117.165|198.82.117.165]] ([[User talk:198.82.117.165|talk]]) 03:09, 26 January 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:don't know who killed the research computing bit, but it is very important for a section of the audience and key to virginia tech's reputation in many fields. --[[User:Buridan|Buridan]] ([[User talk:Buridan|talk]]) 15:17, 15 February 2009 (UTC)

== Merge discussion ==

*'''Propose''' that [[Virginia Tech Hampton Roads Center]] be merged here. The material would usefull expand the section here on that center, but it's not enough for an article of its own, at the moment anyway. [[User:Itsmejudith|Itsmejudith]] ([[User talk:Itsmejudith|talk]]) 21:39, 18 February 2009 (UTC)

*'''Support''' - There's not really a much information written about it.  A quick searcg via google shows it being mentioned, but no substantial writeups that would indicate a separate article would be justified. -- [[User:Whpq|Whpq]] ([[User talk:Whpq|talk]]) 22:41, 22 February 2009 (UTC)

==Major Major Nidal Malik Hasan==

The article has nothing about the fact that the [[Major Nidal Malik Hasan]] studied in this instituition.[[User:Agre22|Agre22]] ([[User talk:Agre22|talk]]) 02:40, 8 November 2009 (UTC)agre22

Why is this relevant to the institution's wikipedia page? It can simply be reflected in his bio. It's not relevant with respect to the institutional history and academic mission. Nor does it have a place on the page and doesn't deserve it's own callout. ([[User:Possum4all|Possum4all]] ([[User talk:Possum4all|talk]]) 05:52, 25 November 2009 (UTC))

:I concur, but I think it would be appropriate to include it in an expansion of the &quot;alumni&quot; section. I went to [[Texas A&amp;M]] and we made sure to include [[Wen Ho Lee]], despite his notorious past, as he was notable. &lt;span style=&quot;background-color: maroon; color: white&quot;&gt;[[User:BQZip01|&lt;font color=&quot;white&quot;&gt;'''—&amp;nbsp;''BQZip01''&amp;nbsp;—'''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:BQZip01|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 18:43, 25 November 2009 (UTC)

== Math Emporium ==

I'm somewhat surprised that this article makes no mention of the university's &quot;Math Emporium&quot;.  It's been open since 1997, and is part of nearly every undergraduate's experience there.  [[Special:Contributions/198.82.17.209|198.82.17.209]] ([[User talk:198.82.17.209|talk]]) 21:37, 28 June 2010 (UTC)
:{{done}} While there is zero coverage coming up in newspapers and magazines, its actually received a lot of coverage in books, particularly those on the politics and administration of education.  A paragraph has been added.--[[User:RadioFan|RadioFan]] ([[User talk:RadioFan|talk]]) 23:13, 28 June 2010 (UTC)

== December 8, 2011 Event ==

Will someone please keep this up to date as this event progresses.  If it becomes an extremely major event, this will need to be expanded.  I don't get much information from the Midwest.  Thank you.  [[User:Sweet-pea-1981|Sweet Pea 1981]] ([[User talk:Sweet-pea-1981|talk]]) 19:03, 8 December 2011 (UTC)

===section on recent violence at Tech?===
I dont know where/how it would fit on their wiki page, but should something be put in the article about all of the recent violence directly or indirectly involving tech?  It would include the [[Virginia Tech Massacre]], the actions of [[William Morva]] in 2006, the shootings today (Dec 8, 2011), the [http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2009/08/27/virginia-tech-students-fo_n_270892.html VT students executed in Jefferson Forest], [http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,481406,00.html the VT Student stabbed to death and decapitated on campus], and that the shooter from the [[Fort Hood shooting]] was an alum.  Opinion?

Once a Hokie, always a Hokie...  [[User:Jwalte04|Jwalte04]] ([[User talk:Jwalte04|talk]]) 19:11, 8 December 2011 (UTC)

:If there has been a lot of violence at the school, this would definately warrent a seperate section.  As stated before, as I am in the Midwest, I am not aware of everything going on there unless it is a major news story.  I'm only aware of the massacre and the event today.  Items to include in the section would be events and what the university is doing to prevent this from happening in the future. [[User:Sweet-pea-1981|Sweet Pea 1981]] ([[User talk:Sweet-pea-1981|talk]]) 19:19, 8 December 2011 (UTC)

::News story [http://news.sky.com/home/world-news/article/16126496 here]. Reportedly two people killed today.--'''''[[User:ianmacm|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#88b;color:#cff;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;♦Ian&lt;span style=&quot;background:#99c&quot;&gt;Ma&lt;span style=&quot;background:#aad&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;M♦&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:ianmacm|(talk to me)]]&lt;/sup&gt;''''' 19:59, 8 December 2011 (UTC)

:::[http://www.vt.edu/ VT.edu's website] says: &quot;Police investigating shootings on campus; shooter's status unknown. (Posted: 1:49 p.m.) Shortly after noon today, a Virginia Tech police officer stopped a vehicle on campus during a routine traffic stop in the Coliseum parking lot near McComas Hall. During the traffic stop. the officer was shot and killed. There were witnesses to this shooting. Witnesses reported to police the shooter fled on foot heading toward the Cage, a parking lot near Duck Pond Drive. At that parking lot, a second person was found. That person is also deceased. Several law enforcement agencies have responded to assist. Virginia State Police has been requested to take lead in the investigation. The status of the shooter is unknown. The campus community should continue to shelter in place and visitors should not come to campus.&quot;

Still breaking news.--'''''[[User:ianmacm|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#88b;color:#cff;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;♦Ian&lt;span style=&quot;background:#99c&quot;&gt;Ma&lt;span style=&quot;background:#aad&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;M♦&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:ianmacm|(talk to me)]]&lt;/sup&gt;''''' 20:16, 8 December 2011 (UTC)

:The dead person in the parking lot is reportedly the alleged shooter.[http://news.sky.com/home/world-news/article/16126496]--'''''[[User:ianmacm|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#88b;color:#cff;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;♦Ian&lt;span style=&quot;background:#99c&quot;&gt;Ma&lt;span style=&quot;background:#aad&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;M♦&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:ianmacm|(talk to me)]]&lt;/sup&gt;''''' 22:59, 8 December 2011 (UTC)

:Less breaking news now, it's looking more and more like a [http://www.roanoke.com/news/breaking/wb/302178 murder-suicide] and random act of violence.--[[User:Possum4all|Possum4all]] ([[User talk:Possum4all|talk]]) 19:06, 13 December 2011 (UTC)

Saying that there is &quot;a lot of violence&quot; is not supported by Clery act data. Virginia Tech isn't even the highest in the Commonwealth regarding reported violence. You need to qualify your assertion that there's &quot;a lot&quot; of violence with some sort of link or report. --[[Special:Contributions/198.82.10.203|198.82.10.203]] ([[User talk:198.82.10.203|talk]]) 18:19, 9 February 2012 (UTC)

===Userspace draft===
This might be something best put into a userspace draft for now, to avoid recentism.  If it becomes noteworthy the draft can be moved to the mainspace, if it doesn't the important sections can be added to this article.  I'd do it, but I'm busy preparing for finals.&lt;tt&gt;  &lt;/tt&gt;[[User:Ryan Vesey|'''''Ryan''''']]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Ryan Vesey|'''''Vesey''''']]&amp;nbsp;[[Special:Contributions/Ryan Vesey|&lt;small&gt;Review me!&lt;/small&gt;]] 20:30, 8 December 2011 (UTC)

==December 8, 2011==
According to reports, Virginia State Police responded to Virginia Tech in reference to a shooting in reference to a Virginia Tech police officer being shot and killed while on a traffic stop at the Cassell Coliseum parking lot on Spring Road. Virginia Tech police requested that the Virginia State Police assume primary responsibility for the investigation of the incident.  

The individual fled that crime scene in the direction of a second crime scene a quarter of a mile away, where a male body was found at that location with a gunshot wound.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vtnews.vt.edu/articles/2011/12/120811-vtnews-statepolice-statement.html|work=Virginia Tech Website}}&lt;/ref&gt; --[[User:Possum4all|Possum4all]] ([[User talk:Possum4all|talk]]) 15:32, 9 December 2011 (UTC)

In a follow-up press conference, officials said that the [http://www.alerts.vt.edu/ Virginia Tech Alert] System was very helpful and worked as expected. A total of 6 alerts were sent throughout the day, the first was issued at 12:37pm. Dr. Charles Steger, Virginia Tech President, said the system &quot;worked extremely well.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.roanoke.com/news/roanoke/wb/302164|newspaper=Roanoke Times|date=Dec. 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; --[[User:Possum4all|Possum4all]] ([[User talk:Possum4all|talk]]) 15:43, 9 December 2011 (UTC)
{{reflist-talk}}

== Call for discussion/consensus on adding shooting incidents to this page ==

There seems to be quite a few edit adding and removing the 2007 and 2011 shooting incidents.  I recommend that we come to a consensus on whether or not the incidents should be reference. In so much as the University of Texas, Kent State, Columbine High School and others that have had major incidents have a reference to the incident on that schools wiki page as well as a separate, more in depth page for the incident. Since wiki is a place to look for information, I feel that both VT incidents should be included/summarized on the main page and then expanded on a separate page.  To not include them seems to violate the NPOV ideal.  Thanks, chris  [[User:W4chris|W4chris]] ([[User talk:W4chris|talk]]) 16:16, 9 December 2011 (UTC)

:It shouldn't be on this page nor does it deserves it's own page as it's an on-going news item -- and a person-on-person random act of violence. Please see Notability. --[[User:Possum4all|Possum4all]] ([[User talk:Possum4all|talk]]) 16:25, 9 December 2011 (UTC)

::I don't think that the December 2011 incident has the same long term notability as the 2007 incident. It would be strange for this article to make no mention at all of the 2007 incident, and it might look like an attempt to airbrush it out.--'''''[[User:ianmacm|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#88b;color:#cff;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;♦Ian&lt;span style=&quot;background:#99c&quot;&gt;Ma&lt;span style=&quot;background:#aad&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;M♦&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:ianmacm|(talk to me)]]&lt;/sup&gt;''''' 18:02, 9 December 2011 (UTC)

:::I'm not saying to remove the 2007 entry. But the 2011 entry is a [http://www.roanoke.com/news/breaking/wb/302178 murder-suicide]... a crime. Crimes happen all the time on campuses around the country. They don't show up on the main pages on wikipedia as unique entries. It doesn't deserve a place on this page nor it's own unique article. Notability is at play here. --[[User:Possum4all|Possum4all]] ([[User talk:Possum4all|talk]]) 18:46, 9 December 2011 (UTC)

::::Had it not been for the 2007 incident, the 2011 incident would not have received nearly as much coverage. It would be best to see how the coverage of the 2011 incident settles down in the next few days. It is probably not worth a mention in this article, or a separate article.--'''''[[User:ianmacm|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#88b;color:#cff;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;♦Ian&lt;span style=&quot;background:#99c&quot;&gt;Ma&lt;span style=&quot;background:#aad&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;M♦&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:ianmacm|(talk to me)]]&lt;/sup&gt;''''' 18:57, 9 December 2011 (UTC)

:::::I could buy that the 2011 incident does not meet notability but the 2007 shooting definitely does and need to be summarized. [[User:W4chris|W4chris]] ([[User talk:W4chris|talk]]) 20:10, 10 December 2011 (UTC)

:::::::I added a summary and was disappointed to see it removed [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Virginia_Polytechnic_Institute_and_State_University&amp;diff=465040822&amp;oldid=464987025 here]. The current wording is poor and could do with some tidying up.--'''''[[User:ianmacm|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#88b;color:#cff;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;♦Ian&lt;span style=&quot;background:#99c&quot;&gt;Ma&lt;span style=&quot;background:#aad&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;M♦&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:ianmacm|(talk to me)]]&lt;/sup&gt;''''' 20:18, 10 December 2011 (UTC)

{{outdent}}  The 2007 incident has been mentioned in this article and wikilinked to the dedicated [[Virginia Tech massacre]] article which covers the subject extensively.  That has served the Virginia Tech article well for years and last week's incident didn't create a need for more explanation of the 2007 incident.  The current wording is excellent.  If you look back over the article's history you'll find that the sentence was worded carefully (e.g. &quot;the site of&quot;)  to keep to the focus on the subject of this article, the university.  Expanding this information into a paragraph or especially into its own section  is unnecessary and takes the focus this well written article has.  If there were no dedicated article on the subject I'd be all for expanding information here, but there is a dedicated article and no need to duplicate so many details here.  Readers need to know that this happened but this article is about the university, not the 2007 incident, let's not take the focus away.--[[User:RadioFan|RadioFan]] ([[User talk:RadioFan|talk]]) 12:57, 11 December 2011 (UTC)

I think this is logical and parallels entries for other academic institutions. --[[User:Possum4all|Possum4all]] ([[User talk:Possum4all|talk]]) 18:59, 13 December 2011 (UTC)

==Obvious Bias==
This article has been quite clearly doctored in order to remove reference to the 2007 Seung-Hui Cho shooting, arguably (and somewhat unfortunately) the most notable aspect of the entire university. I wouldn't be surprised if this is a result of university PR, but a single sentence at the bottom of the History section and a link to the main article hidden at the bottom is quite simply an embarrassment. It at the very least deserves its own subsection (with a subheading link to the main article), as well as some impartial editors, rather than the VT affiliates currently policing the article and reverting changes under bogus citations of notability and quality. [[Special:Contributions/82.14.195.61|82.14.195.61]] ([[User talk:82.14.195.61|talk]])  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|undated]] comment added 19:38, 12 December 2011 (UTC).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!--Template:Undated--&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:This is pretty much what I thought. There almost seems to be an embarrassment about mentioning the 2007 incident, particularly when compared to articles like [[Columbine High School]] and [[University of Texas at Austin]], which contain clear summaries of the shooting incidents. There is a lack of due weight in the current wording.--'''''[[User:ianmacm|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#88b;color:#cff;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;♦Ian&lt;span style=&quot;background:#99c&quot;&gt;Ma&lt;span style=&quot;background:#aad&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;M♦&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:ianmacm|(talk to me)]]&lt;/sup&gt;''''' 19:58, 12 December 2011 (UTC)
::I concur and I endorse your decision to change the wording.&lt;tt&gt;  &lt;/tt&gt;[[User:Ryan Vesey|'''''Ryan''''']]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Ryan Vesey|'''''Vesey''''']]&amp;nbsp;[[Special:Contributions/Ryan Vesey|&lt;small&gt;Review me!&lt;/small&gt;]] 20:04, 12 December 2011 (UTC)
:::This article is about the university, not the 2007 incident.  It is absolutely appropriate to summarize the 2007 incident in the history section but a subsection is not necessary.  The subject is already well covered in the article dedicated to the subject there is no need to extend coverage here.   Additionally, accusation of bias is serious and shouldn't be tossed about based solely on superficial observation.  --[[User:RadioFan|RadioFan]] ([[User talk:RadioFan|talk]]) 20:59, 12 December 2011 (UTC)
::::I disagree that a subsection is not necessary.  The shooting incident at VT was of a large enough magnitude that it defines the University and Wikipedia should not belittle its influence.&lt;tt&gt;  &lt;/tt&gt;[[User:Ryan Vesey|'''''Ryan''''']]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Ryan Vesey|'''''Vesey''''']]&amp;nbsp;[[Special:Contributions/Ryan Vesey|&lt;small&gt;Review me!&lt;/small&gt;]] 21:11, 12 December 2011 (UTC)
::::I do agree with RadioFan that a single sentence doesn't deserve a section; however, I believe the section should be slightly expanded so it can stand alone.&lt;tt&gt;  &lt;/tt&gt;[[User:Ryan Vesey|'''''Ryan''''']]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Ryan Vesey|'''''Vesey''''']]&amp;nbsp;[[Special:Contributions/Ryan Vesey|&lt;small&gt;Review me!&lt;/small&gt;]] 21:14, 12 December 2011 (UTC)
:::::On reflection, I don't think it needs a section either, but something more like the short paragraph in [[University_of_Texas_at_Austin#Recent_history]].--'''''[[User:ianmacm|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#88b;color:#cff;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;♦Ian&lt;span style=&quot;background:#99c&quot;&gt;Ma&lt;span style=&quot;background:#aad&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;M♦&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:ianmacm|(talk to me)]]&lt;/sup&gt;''''' 21:20, 12 December 2011 (UTC)
::::::The focus here should be on content not size.    What specific content is missing from the information on the 2007 incident?  What needs to be added?--[[User:RadioFan|RadioFan]] ([[User talk:RadioFan|talk]]) 21:22, 12 December 2011 (UTC)
:::::::I believe the identity of the shooter should be included, a sentence on the reaction should be included, and information on the failure of VT to notify it's students properly should be included.  I don't believe that the fine should be included as I believe that would give undue weight to the subject.&lt;tt&gt;  &lt;/tt&gt;[[User:Ryan Vesey|'''''Ryan''''']]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Ryan Vesey|'''''Vesey''''']]&amp;nbsp;[[Special:Contributions/Ryan Vesey|&lt;small&gt;Review me!&lt;/small&gt;]] 21:26, 12 December 2011 (UTC)
::::::::Whether Tech failed to properly notify its students is a matter of opinion, not something that should be claimed as factual.  Obviously, the Obama administration thinks that there was a delay, but Tech disagrees with that assessment.  [[Clery_Act#Timely_Warnings|Timely warnings]] meant something different before April 16, 2007.  The [http://www2.ed.gov/admins/lead/safety/handbook.pdf official Cleary Act handbook from the government] gives samples of Cleary &quot;timely warnings&quot; that are two days and six days after the incidents in question.  That Virginia Tech should have sent out a warning in under two hours is a matter of opinion, not something that should be referred to as a &quot;failure&quot;. --[[User:B|B]] ([[User talk:B|talk]]) 21:54, 12 December 2011 (UTC)
{{outdent}} The identity of the shooter is included in the dedicated article.  I dont see how it would improve the article on the university.  The notification controversy is also well covered and as B notes, is subjective and not appropriate for a summary as a result.  It's better covered in the dedicated article.--[[User:RadioFan|RadioFan]] ([[User talk:RadioFan|talk]]) 22:07, 12 December 2011 (UTC)

I might be missing something, but it looks like it appears in two places.... History and the See Also reference at the bottom of the page. The word &quot;failure&quot; is certainly up for debate, Ryan, and you might want to find a more objective word to communicate the debate about culpability. --[[User:Possum4all|Possum4all]] ([[User talk:Possum4all|talk]]) 18:53, 13 December 2011 (UTC)

== Requested Move: → Virginia Tech ==
&lt;div class=&quot;boilerplate&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #efe; margin: 2em 0 0 0; padding: 0 10px 0 10px; border: 1px dotted #aaa;&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Template:RM top --&gt;
:''The following discussion is an archived discussion of a [[WP:requested moves|requested move]]. &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on the talk page. Editors desiring to contest the closing decision should consider a [[Wikipedia:move review|move review]]. No further edits should be made to this section. ''

The result of the move request was: '''Move'''. We have consensus that this name is overwhelmingly the most common way of referring to the institution. [[User:Cuchullain|Cúchullain]] [[User talk:Cuchullain|&lt;sup&gt;t&lt;/sup&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/Cuchullain|&lt;small&gt;c&lt;/small&gt;]] 16:19, 20 November 2012 (UTC)

----

----

[[Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University]] → {{no redirect|Virginia Tech}} – Although it might sound like a sports-oriented nickname, &quot;Virginia Tech&quot; is in fact the way this school is referred to in all but the most legalistic contexts. On [http://www.vt.edu/about/ their website] or on a [http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-274238686.html typical press release], the proposed form is used everywhere except in the fine print copyright notice. &quot;Virginia Tech&quot; is by far the most common name for this subject on Google Books, according to [http://books.google.com/ngrams/graph?content=Virginia+Tech%2CVirginia+Polytechnic+Institute&amp;year_start=1990&amp;year_end=2008&amp;corpus=15&amp;smoothing=2&amp;share= this ngram]. It is also the search term our readers are most likely to use, according to [https://www.google.com/trends/explore#q=Virginia%20Tech,Virginia%20Polytechnic%20Institute Google Trends]. [[User:Kauffner|Kauffner]] ([[User talk:Kauffner|talk]]) 02:02, 1 November 2012 (UTC)

===Supporting material===
*'''Policy''': “Wikipedia does not necessarily use the subject's 'official' name as an article title; it prefers to use the name that is most frequently used to refer to the subject in English-language reliable sources.&quot; ([[WP:COMMONNAME]])

*'''References''': There is actually a standard history for this school, ''[http://books.google.com.vn/books?id=4fZW2QyggykC&amp;dq= Virginia Tech]'' (2004) by Nelson Harris. The book ''[http://books.google.com.vn/books?id=cJbRHv9dk6wC&amp;dq= No Right to Remain Silent: What We've Learned from the Tragedy at Virginia Tech]'' (2009) by Lucinda Roy was widely read and reviewed. See also ''[http://www.economist.com/node/13447986 The Economist]'', [http://espn.go.com/college-football/team/_/id/259/virginia-tech-hokies ESPN], and ''[http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/us/16cnd-shooting.html?pagewanted=all New York Times]''.

{| class=&quot;wikitable collapsible sortable&quot;
! Organization|| Virginia Polytechnic Institute || Virginia Tech || URLs
|-
|'''Highbeam'''&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;News stories compiled for the last two years&lt;/small&gt;||1,477||17,038||http://www.highbeam.com/Search?searchTerm=%22Virginia+Polytechnic+Institute%22&lt;br&gt;http://www.highbeam.com/Search?searchTerm=%22Virginia+Tech%22
|-
|'''Chronicle of Higher Education'''&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;Past year&lt;/small&gt;||41||1,050||
{{google|&quot;Virginia Polytechnic Institute&quot; site:chronicle.com}}&lt;br&gt;{{google|&quot;Virginia Tech&quot; site:chronicle.com}}
|-
|'''Virginian-Pilot'''||0||7||{{google|&quot;Virginia Polytechnic Institute&quot; site:pilotonline.com}}&lt;br&gt;{{google|&quot;Virginia Tech&quot; site:pilotonline.com}}
|-
|'''Richmond Times-Dispatch'''||0||3||{{google|&quot;Virginia Polytechnic Institue&quot; site:www.timesdispatch.com}}&lt;br&gt;{{google|&quot;Virginia Tech&quot; site:www.timesdispatch.com}}
|-
|'''New York Times'''&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;Past year&lt;/small&gt;||15||145||{{google|&quot;Virginia Polytechnic Institute&quot; site:www.nytimes.com}}&lt;br&gt;{{google|&quot;Virginia Tech&quot; site:www.nytimes.com}}
|}
Although I filtered for news articles only, the Highbeam results for &quot;Virginia Polytechnic Institute&quot; are almost entirely from scientific journals. The VPI hits on the ''Chronicle of Higher Education'' site are for employment ads. The ''New York Times'' VPI results are not for actual news stories either, but rather an artifact of their &quot;E-mail Alert&quot; software. [[User:Kauffner|Kauffner]] ([[User talk:Kauffner|talk]]) 02:02, 1 November 2012 (UTC)

===Survey===
*&lt;s&gt;'''Support'''&lt;/s&gt; '''Oppose'''. Very well researched. More than needed... Changing to oppose in deference to those who actually care. [[User:Apteva|Apteva]] ([[User talk:Apteva|talk]]) 02:28, 1 November 2012 (UTC)
*'''Support''' I also applaud your research, but we include ''more'' than just what is used popularly. [[WP:Article titles|&quot;''[E]ditors choose among [article titles] by considering several principles: the ideal article title resembles titles for similar articles, precisely identifies the subject, and is short, natural, and recognizable.''&quot; Additionally, this is a policy, so ''all'' points must be met or balanced, not solely those mentioned within the subheading of [[WP:COMMONNAME]]. Given that [[Wikipedia:UNIGUIDE|Wikipedia:UNIGUIDE#College_and_university_articles]] also supports this &quot;''Colleges and universities should always be named using the common (not necessarily official) name of the institution. This can often be determined by looking at current branding of a university via their website, published documents, and advertisements.''&quot;, I can see no reason to oppose. The official name should redirect to this article and the full name should be bolded in the lead. [[User:Buffs|Buffs]] ([[User talk:Buffs|talk]]) 03:18, 1 November 2012 (UTC)
*'''Support''' I have little to add here, having requested Kauffner draw up one of his meticulously researched RMs for the article; he didn't disappoint. As someone with a bunch of Hokie family members, I can testify that the [[WP:official name|official name]] of the school is likely to draw a quizzical stare from just about anyone; it's practically trivia at this point. --[[User:BDD|BDD]] ([[User talk:BDD|talk]]) 06:11, 1 November 2012 (UTC)
*'''Support''' as an example we have an article on [[Rutgers University]] and not the full title 'Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey.'  Across Wikipedia, there are dozens of similar examples of using the common name and not the official name.  '''[[User talk:Hot Stop|&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: symbol;&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#0d254c&quot;&gt;Hot Stop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] [[Special:Contributions/Hot_Stop|&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: symbol;&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#0d254c&quot;&gt;(Edits)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]]''' 12:51, 1 November 2012 (UTC)
*'''Support''', as long as you don't make me change my resume or diploma. [[User talk:HokieRNB|Hokie]][[User:HokieRNB|RNB]] 20:12, 3 November 2012 (UTC)
*'''Strongest Oppose Possible''': VT's official name is in fact &quot;Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University&quot;, over the years it was reduced (in nickname) to just &quot;Virginia Tech&quot;.  It's like WVU or UVA, they are still officiall called West Virginia University and University of Virginia respectively even though they are commonly called WVU or UVA (respectively).  Virginia Tech's name is &quot;Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University&quot; and any change would open up college pages to be renamed to their &quot;nicknames&quot;.  This should go before an RfC as well since it is wide-encompassing. - &lt;small style=&quot;white-space:nowrap;border:1px solid #900;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Neutralhomer|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#900;&quot;&gt;Neutralhomer&lt;/span&gt;]] • [[User talk:Neutralhomer|&lt;span style=&quot;color:Black;&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/span&gt;]] • 23:35, 3 November 2012 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
:''The above discussion is preserved as an archive of a [[WP:RM|requested move]].  &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on this talk page or in a [[WP:move review|move review]]. No further edits should be made to this section.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- Template:RM bottom --&gt;

===ANI===
I have taken this issue to [[Wikipedia:Administrators'_noticeboard/Incidents#Issue_Involving_a_University.27s_Name|ANI]] for a community-wide decision as the move is against naming convensions. - &lt;small style=&quot;white-space:nowrap;border:1px solid #900;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Neutralhomer|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#900;&quot;&gt;Neutralhomer&lt;/span&gt;]] • [[User talk:Neutralhomer|&lt;span style=&quot;color:Black;&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/span&gt;]] • 16:45, 20 November 2012 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
:The move was dictated by consensus and seems supported by [[WP:COMMONNAME]]. [[User:GiantSnowman|Giant]][[User talk:GiantSnowman|Snowman]] 16:51, 20 November 2012 (UTC)
::Then shall we rename West Virginia University to &quot;WVU&quot;?  Syracuse University to &quot;Syracuse&quot;?  Which college would get rights to &quot;FSU&quot;?  Which Miami would get &quot;Miami&quot;, the city, the college in Florida or the college in Ohio?  Should Kansas State University be renamed to &quot;K-State&quot;?  Using COMMONNAME, the answer to all these, would be yes, yes, good question, the city, and yes.  We don't use COMMONNAME when it comes to official names and whether anyone wants to admit it or not, the official name of Virginia Tech is and always will be Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. - &lt;small style=&quot;white-space:nowrap;border:1px solid #900;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Neutralhomer|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#900;&quot;&gt;Neutralhomer&lt;/span&gt;]] • [[User talk:Neutralhomer|&lt;span style=&quot;color:Black;&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/span&gt;]] • 17:00, 20 November 2012 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
:::Unfortunately [[WP:OFFICIALNAME]] is not a policy. As stated, feel free to open a new RM and state your case there. [[User:GiantSnowman|Giant]][[User talk:GiantSnowman|Snowman]] 17:03, 20 November 2012 (UTC)
*If someone wants to contest the move, the proper forum is [[WP:Move_review]]. However, I don't see any basis to contest this decision. [[User:Kauffner|Kauffner]] ([[User talk:Kauffner|talk]]) 17:21, 20 November 2012 (UTC)
*Coming late to this discussion, while I agree that this isn't ANI material, the discussion deserves a wider audience and more comprehensive input. To cite a directly comparable instance, my alma mater is the [[Georgia Institute of Technology]]. While it's referred to as Georgia Tech almost exclusively, I'm not aware of any support for a bold move of the primary title to Georgia Tech, nor has the [[California Institute of Technology]] been moved to Caltech, as it is invariably called, and I would oppose a move for either. The seal of the university, prominently displayed, spells out the full name. I suggest that the bold move be undone;'''&lt;font face=&quot;Arial&quot;&gt;[[User:Acroterion|&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;Acroterion&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Acroterion|&lt;font color=&quot;gray&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/font&gt;''' 17:32, 20 November 2012 (UTC)
**Thanks Acroterion, you have a better way of getting a point across than I...especially at this point. - &lt;small style=&quot;white-space:nowrap;border:1px solid #900;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Neutralhomer|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#900;&quot;&gt;Neutralhomer&lt;/span&gt;]] • [[User talk:Neutralhomer|&lt;span style=&quot;color:Black;&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/span&gt;]] • 17:35, 20 November 2012 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
***My chief point is that this was a bold move based on a very narrow input: I would prefer that it first be reverted and reviewed via an RfC rather than moved on the opinion of four editors.MR is a procedural review, and the issue here is one of editorial discretion rather than procedure. '''&lt;font face=&quot;Arial&quot;&gt;[[User:Acroterion|&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;Acroterion&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Acroterion|&lt;font color=&quot;gray&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/font&gt;''' 17:38, 20 November 2012 (UTC)

{{unindent}}I'll try to explain the close in a bit more detail. First off, as was noted in the discussion, the relevant section at [[WP:AT]] says &quot;Wikipedia does not necessarily use the subject's 'official' name as an article title; it prefers to use the name that is most frequently used to refer to the subject in English-language [[WP:RS|reliable sources]].&quot; Additionally, as was also indicated, the college-specific guideline [[WP:UNIGUIDE]] says, &quot;Colleges and universities should '''always''' be named using the '''common (not necessarily official) name''' of the institution&quot; (emphasis mine). In this case, by all evidence, &quot;Virginia Tech&quot; is overwhelmingly the most common way of referring to the university in the sources, and no one appears to dispute that. There are other examples of college articles that use a non-official name when something else is overwhelmingly more common, such [[Ohio State University]], [[Florida A&amp;M University]], and [[Rutgers University]]. As such, the move was supported by policy, practice, and the local consensus in the discussion.&lt;br&gt;
I'm sympathetic to the wish there had been more input, but there's no set amount of input an RM needs, and the fact is this had drawn almost no new comments for two and a half weeks. Especially considering the strength of the evidence, I stand by my reading of the consensus.&lt;br&gt;
As for the potential of this to affect other moves, I don't see that as an adequate reason to avoid an otherwise convincing move. As an aside, I really don't see it happening, anyway. I tend to doubt that, for instance, West Virginia University is really overwhelmingly better known as &quot;WVU&quot;, and in many such cases the nicknames will fail other key [[WP:NAMINGCRITERIA|naming criteria]].--[[User:Cuchullain|Cúchullain]] [[User talk:Cuchullain|&lt;sup&gt;t&lt;/sup&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/Cuchullain|&lt;small&gt;c&lt;/small&gt;]] 20:04, 20 November 2012 (UTC)
:I'd suggest that Wikipedia could use a consensus-driven policy on the naming of colleges and universities. Until now, the naming has been derived from some version of the &quot;official&quot; name, and ''not'' &quot;Virginia Tech,&quot; &quot;Penn State,&quot; &quot;Ohio State,&quot;UMass,&quot; etc.  The major exception, as pointed out above, is Rutgers, which is far preferable to its official title. Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University could be argued to be a similar mouthful, but I would suggest that ample precedent exists with respect to all of the Techs, States, and A&amp;Ms, of which Virginia Tech is now an outlier in the naming convention field. Rather than argue it at RM, which to me is a place to argue procedure (though I stand by the assertion that too few opinions have been solicited: we routinely relist AfDs to get broader consensus, for instance)., I would prefer that it be discussed here or as an RfC. I don't see &quot;local consensus&quot; as sufficient to overturn a ''de facto'' convention for the States and Techs without ''much'' more input from the community.
:A bit of history: when I was looking at colleges in the mid-1970s, Virginia Tech was called VPI: the change to Virginia Tech was part of a rebranding campaign by the university, who found VPI to be a bit vanilla, not without reason, and &quot;Poly&quot; wasn't in the running. The Virginia Tech name has taken root for good as a shorthand, which is fine. 
:Most of time, I'm arguing in favor of [[WP:COMMONNAME]]: in fact, this is probably the first time that I haven't, and I think this points up a significant exception to the policy that has existed without notice until now. I make an analogy to [[WP:ENGVAR]]: we don't change between varieties of English without good cause: I see no compelling reason to alter an informal naming convention in this instance either. At some risk of an [[WP:OTHERSTUFF]] argument, if there is a &quot;convincing argument&quot; for this, then the argument is equally convincing for all the other Tech and State universities, which I suspect would be opposed. I haven't seen an article about the Sandusky affair that gave more than a nod to &quot;Pennsylvania State University,&quot; for instance. I seem to recall an extremely contentious discussion about the &quot;The&quot; in that case, but I don't think a rename to Penn State was ever seriously considered. Similar issues have come up concerning Ohio State. Virtually all articles on universities use the title/lede format format &quot;Northern North Carolina State University, also known as Northern State ...&quot; with a redirect from the informal name. &lt;font face=&quot;Arial&quot;&gt;[[User:Acroterion|&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;Acroterion&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Acroterion|&lt;font color=&quot;gray&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/font&gt;''' 22:18, 20 November 2012 (UTC)
::The biggest thing I take from this is that no one is disputing the fact that Virginia Tech is the most common name. I reiterate that common names are preferable per both the the [[WP:AT]] policy and the college guideline [[WP:UNIGUIDE]], as well as in practice. It's simply not true that articles on colleges always use the &quot;official&quot; name; as was pointed out in the initial discussion, there are plenty of exceptions when something else is overwhelmingly more common. For example, it's [[Ohio State University]], not &quot;''The'' Ohio State University&quot;, [[Pennsylvania State University]], not &quot;''The'' Pennsylvania State University&quot;, [[Florida A&amp;M University]], not &quot;Florida Agricultural and Mechanical University&quot;, [[Louisiana State University]], not &quot;Louisiana State University and Agricultural and Mechanical College&quot;, and [[Rutgers University]], not &quot;Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey&quot;. As such, the local consensus at this move request was in line with both policy and practice.&lt;br&gt;
::Taking this into consideration, I don't see any call to reverse the move unless it's by either another move request or it's overturned, for example by [[WP:MR|move review]]. I'll accept any outcome of a review, of course, but I continue to stand by my original decision.[[User:Cuchullain|Cúchullain]] [[User talk:Cuchullain|&lt;sup&gt;t&lt;/sup&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/Cuchullain|&lt;small&gt;c&lt;/small&gt;]] 04:27, 21 November 2012 (UTC)

I don't have a strong opinion on the topic at hand but I am disappointed that no one has bothered to notify the [[WP:UNI|Wikiproject]] most concerned with this specific article and the broader topic of college/university naming conventions, especially when the initial RM was initiated.  If this discussion proceeds to an RfC or other more formal arena, please notify [[WP:UNI]] so its members can participate. [[User:ElKevbo|ElKevbo]] ([[User talk:ElKevbo|talk]]) 07:01, 21 November 2012 (UTC)

==Precedence and comparison==
Although I initially weighed in with a '''support''' !vote, now that I've had the chance to look a little further, I'm questioning whether this was the right move.  Here is a brief list of comparable articles that should be considered:
*[[California Institute of Technology]] (not Caltech)
*[[Florida Institute of Technology]] (not Florida Tech)
*[[Georgia Institute of Technology]] (not Georgia Tech)
*[[Illinois Institute of Technology]] (not IIT or Illinois Tech)
*[[Indiana Institute of Technology]] (not Indiana Tech)
*[[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]] (not MIT)
*[[New Jersey Institute of Technology]] (not NJIT)
*[[New York Institute of Technology]] (not NYIT)
*[[Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute]] (not RPI)
*[[Rochester Institute of Technology]] (not RIT)
*[[State University of New York Institute of Technology]] (not SUNYIT)
*[[Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University]] (Virginia Tech)
*[[Worcester Polytechnic Institute]] (not WPI)
Does Virginia Tech need to be the ''only'' outlier among polytechnic institutes? [[User talk:HokieRNB|Hokie]][[User:HokieRNB|RNB]] 14:55, 21 November 2012 (UTC)
*'''Agree'''. It's also not e.g. [[Yale]] (very much the COMMONNAME) but [[Yale University]]. --[[Special:Contributions/78.35.246.146|78.35.246.146]] ([[User talk:78.35.246.146|talk]]) 18:56, 21 November 2012 (UTC)
*Because &quot;Virginia Tech&quot; sounds similar to &quot;Florida Tech&quot; we should treat both names the same way? You can't trust your instincts on this. You have to run the numbers, and see how the school presents itself in its literature. ''Chronicles'' has 89 examples of &quot;Florida Institute of Technology&quot; ({{google|&quot;Florida Institute of Technology&quot; site:chronicle.com}}), 30 for &quot;Florida Tech&quot; ({{google|&quot;Florida Tech&quot; site:chronicle.com}}). &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Kauffner |Kauffner ]] ([[User talk:Kauffner |talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Kauffner |contribs]]) 19:55, 21 November 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;
:*It's not about numbers alone. I'm not sure why you think it would be related to &quot;instincts&quot;. And it's not because they ''sound'' similar. It's not a rhyming game.  It's about consistency. Alike articles should be named in alike ways. The list above reflects larger (4000 or more students) polytechnic institutes in the United States, of which Virginia Tech is one of the largest and most well-known. Florida Tech is probably not the best and most clear example; Georgia Tech and Caltech would be better. (&quot;Georgia Tech&quot; shows up 1000 to 1 over &quot;Georgia Institute of Technology&quot; in your search example; &quot;Caltech&quot; is 3 to 2 over &quot;California Institute of Technology&quot;.) I'm not suggesting that the Virginia Tech article shouldn't ultimately be renamed, I'm suggesting that the move was done prematurely without including needed input from a much larger community to gain consensus about ''how similar schools should be named''. [[User talk:HokieRNB|Hokie]][[User:HokieRNB|RNB]] 20:54, 21 November 2012 (UTC)
*As per [[User:HokieRNB|RNB]] the results show this result is out of line. As far as [[WP:COMMONNAME]] goes my increasing observation is that it is either badly written, or not read when cited, or both. We keep on seeing RM discussions that read/interpret the [[WP:COMMONNAME]] guideline as [[WP:STREETNAME]] [[WP:TABLOIDNAME]]  [[WP:NICKNAME]]. At the moment the guideline only says &quot;Article titles should be neither vulgar nor pedantic&quot; which rules out [[WP:VULGARNAME]] [[WP:PEDANTICNAME]] but doesn't tell Users whether en.wp wants to be an encyclopedia or USA Today. Even though in this case Google Books and Highbeam were used, not press, the result is a non-encyclopedic one. Which isn't anyone's fault, but is the result. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 01:45, 22 November 2012 (UTC)
:*Upon further reflection, I believe that [[WP:COMMONNAME]] would support a move to [[Virginia Polytechnic Institute]] (dropping the &quot;and State University&quot; part of the title), but the overriding guideline should dictate that it be named consistently with other similar polytechnic institutes. How soon is too soon to ask for such a move? [[User talk:HokieRNB|Hokie]][[User:HokieRNB|RNB]] 02:26, 22 November 2012 (UTC)
:::On the question of time I think you'd only need agreement of at least 3 people on this talk page to enter an immediate RM, given the small sample on the RM itself. I'll be the third if you get a second. However ''Virginia Polytechnic Institute'' was the old name pre-War, I doubt it'd get much support. The best non-colloquial alternative is back to where the article was. More talk/thought is probably necessary. &lt;s&gt;Opening an RfC on [[Talk:Florida Institute of Technology]] might be a better way to proceed.&lt;/s&gt;  [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 02:50, 22 November 2012 (UTC)
::::There's no set period of time, or a specific number of users in &quot;agreement&quot;, for a new RM, though usually some amount of wait time is expected. And I'd recommend against opening an RfC at [[Florida Institute of Technology]] unless you want to make some change at that article.[[User:Cuchullain|Cúchullain]] [[User talk:Cuchullain|&lt;sup&gt;t&lt;/sup&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/Cuchullain|&lt;small&gt;c&lt;/small&gt;]] 03:30, 22 November 2012 (UTC)
:::::Struck through above, per Cúchullain. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 09:03, 22 November 2012 (UTC)
*I note that [[WP:NICKNAME]] leads to a page on username policy that is unrelated to article titling. IMO, we should use a name that might be given in a formal context like the ''New York Times'' or ''Chronicles of the Higher Education''. This is not something that can be determined by analogy-based reasoning. The school changed its short form name from VPI to Virginia Tech around 2000. &quot;Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University&quot; was always just a lawyers' name. So even someone who went to the school in the 1990s might not have a sense of the current nomenclature. [[User:Kauffner|Kauffner]] ([[User talk:Kauffner|talk]]) 10:51, 22 November 2012 (UTC)
*Few editors like consistency in article titles as much as I do, but Kauffner is right. You can't just change names through analogy; that's [[WP:OTHERSTUFF]] applied to RM. If any of those other schools use their nicknames as consistency as Virginia Tech, it may be appropriate to rename them, but as evidence presented in the RM demonstrates, &quot;Virginia Tech&quot; is much more than an athletic nickname, which many of the above nicknames and abbreviations are. I wonder if the school itself would use the nickname as consistently as it does if its official name weren't so unwieldy, e.g., if it were Virginia Institute of Technology. But that's just speculation. As it stands, official usage, scholarly usage, journalistic usage, and common usage ''all'' agree on &quot;Virginia Tech&quot; in this case. Only a zealousness for official names completely without basis in policy would support the full name—that, or a misunderstanding of the situation, such as mistaking &quot;Virginia Tech&quot; for a purely athletic moniker. I'm happy with this RM being used as a precedent for other schools, but only when usage makes those moves prudent to begin with. --[[User:BDD|BDD]] ([[User talk:BDD|talk]]) 00:36, 7 December 2012 (UTC)

==First SMC to Admit Women==
The article claims VT was the first college in the nation to admit women into its Corps of Cadets. The article gives no source for this and VT's own website states: &quot;In 1973 Virginia Tech was among the first Corps of Cadets in the nation to enroll women, assigning them to L Squadron.&quot; Nowhere does it say it was the first. On the other hand, here is an artcile that specifically states North Georgia College was the first SMC to admit women. http://digitalarchive.gsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1100&amp;context=eps_diss .  [[User:Todd Gallagher|Todd Gallagher]] ([[User talk:Todd Gallagher|talk]]) 17:34, 31 January 2013 (UTC)
:I'm not sure I'd take either source as definitive to identify VT or NGC as solely &quot;first&quot;, since both claim 1973 and aren't more specific than the year.  Without a source offering a dated policy announcement, &quot;among the first&quot; is probably as close as we should get. [[Virginia Tech|&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;maroon&quot;&gt;VT&lt;/font&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;]][[User:VT hawkeye|&lt;b&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#FF6600&quot;&gt;hawkeye&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt;]]&lt;sub&gt;&lt;i&gt;[[User talk:VT hawkeye|talk to me]]&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; 00:59, 18 March 2013 (UTC)

== Location of admissions office ==

Another editor and I disagree whether the following sentence merits inclusion in this article: &quot;The Office of Undergraduate Admissions is located in the [http://www.visit.vt.edu/ Visitor and Undergraduate Admissions Center].&quot;  Can someone else please weigh in?  Thanks!  [[User:ElKevbo|ElKevbo]] ([[User talk:ElKevbo|talk]]) 21:50, 29 July 2014 (UTC)

== List of peer institutions ==

Another editor and I disagree about the inclusion of a list of peer institutions in this article.  The material in question:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
=== Benchmark Institutions ===
Through a series of analyses and negotiations that occur about once every ten years, the State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV) approves a group of peers comparable to each Virginia college and university against which to benchmark faculty salaries. The target for each Virginia institution's overall faculty salary average is the 60th percentile of the average salaries of its peers. Criteria such as enrollments, academic program offerings and degrees awarded, research funding, and the classification of institutions of higher education developed by the Carnegie Commission on Higher Education are used in the analysis to identify comparable peer institutions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Peer Institutions and Comparisons|url=http://www.ir.vt.edu/work_we_do/PeerInstitutions/VT_Compared_Peers.html|publisher=Virginia Tech Office of Institutional Research and Effectiveness|accessdate=May 1, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!colspan=1|Virginia Tech's Benchmark Institutions&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Peer Institutions and Comparisons, SCHEV-Approved Peers|url=http://www.ir.vt.edu/work_we_do/PeerInstitutions/homepage_SCHEV.html|publisher=Virginia Tech Office of Institutional Research and Effectiveness|accessdate=May 1, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

|-
|  style=&quot;vertical-align:top; font-size:small;&quot;|
* University of California, Berkeley
* University of California, Davis
* University of Colorado, Boulder
* Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y.
* University of Florida, Gainesville
* University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign
* Iowa State University, Ames
* University of Maryland, College Park
* University of Michigan, Ann Arbor
* Michigan State University, East Lansing
* University of Minnesota, Twin Cities
* University of Missouri, Columbia
* North Carolina State University, Raleigh
* The Ohio State University, Columbus
* Pennsylvania State University, University Park
* University of Pittsburgh
* Purdue University, West Lafayette, Ind.
* Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey, New Brunswick
* State University of New York at Buffalo
* University of Southern California, Los Angeles
* Stony Brook University, State University of New York
* Texas A&amp;M University, College Station
* University of Texas at Austin
* University of Washington, Seattle
* University of Wisconsin, Madison
|}
{{reflist-talk}}
Can someone else please offer an opinion on the suitability of this material for this article?  Thanks!  [[User:ElKevbo|ElKevbo]] ([[User talk:ElKevbo|talk]]) 21:52, 29 July 2014 (UTC)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

== Information about men's basketball coaching staff ==

Another editor and I disagree about the inclusion of two paragraphs of material about the new men's basketball coach and his staff.  The material in question:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
In March 2014, Virginia Tech Director of Athletics Whit Babcock announced the hiring of [[Buzz Williams]] as the Hokies' new head men's basketball coach. Williams spent the previous six seasons as the head coach at Marquette University, where he compiled a 139-69 record and led the Golden Eagles to five NCAA appearances, including a trip to the regional finals in the 2012-13 season, the same season that the team won the Big East Conference's regular season title. During Williams's tenure, Marquette tallied a 69-39 record in the Big East Conference, and six Marquette players made it to the NBA.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Buzz Williams named new Hokie coach|url=http://www.hokiesports.com/mbasketball/recaps/20140321aaa.html|publisher=HokieSports.com|accessdate=July 28, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2014, Williams announced his staff. Isaac Chew, Steve Roccaforte, and Jamie McNeilly were named assistant coaches. Jeff Reynolds was named the director of men’s basketball operations. Devin Johnson will serve as the director of player personnel for men’s basketball, and Steve Thomas as the director of student-athlete development. Lyle Wolf joined the staff as the assistant to the head coach, and Ernest Eugene was hired as assistant athletics director for sports medicine and will serve as the team athletic trainer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Hokies announce men's basketball staff|url=http://www.hokiesports.com/mbasketball/recaps/20140709aaa.html|publisher=HokieSports.com|accessdate=July 28, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
{{reflist-talk}}

Can others please offer opinions on the inclusion of this material in this article?  Thanks!  [[User:ElKevbo|ElKevbo]] ([[User talk:ElKevbo|talk]]) 21:54, 29 July 2014 (UTC)

== Sub-sections in Athletics ==

I don't think &quot;Virginia Tech&quot; is need for the each of the subsection headings in [[Virginia Tech#Athletics]]. In other words, &quot;Baseball&quot;, &quot;Men's basketball&quot;, etc. seem perfectly fine. Removing &quot;Virginia Tech&quot; is simple enough as long as these subsections are not linked to by other articles. In that case, a [[WP:ANCHOR|anchor]] might be needed to redirect those links as needed. - [[User:Marchjuly|Marchjuly]] ([[User talk:Marchjuly|talk]]) 06:42, 11 September 2015 (UTC)

== Proposed merge with [[Virginia Tech Richmond Center]] ==

Notability is due to VT, size and advert content (i.e. needs cutting to stub) don't warrant much of merge. &lt;span class=&quot;vcard&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fn&quot;&gt;[[User:Widefox|Widefox]]&lt;/span&gt;; [[User talk:Widefox|talk]]&lt;/span&gt; 02:10, 3 November 2015 (UTC)

:Definitely redirect to Virginia Tech. [[User:Czoal|Czoal]] ([[User talk:Czoal|talk]]) 03:13, 3 November 2015 (UTC)

== Proposed merge with [[Virginia Tech School of Public and International Affairs]] ==

fails [[WP:GNG]]. promo article [[WP:TNT]]. Best to [[WP:SPINOUT]] &lt;span class=&quot;vcard&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fn&quot;&gt;[[User:Widefox|Widefox]]&lt;/span&gt;; [[User talk:Widefox|talk]]&lt;/span&gt; 02:22, 4 November 2015 (UTC)
*''Support''' per nominator. &lt;span style=&quot;background:#231F20; color:#FFFFFF; border:1px solid #231F20&quot;&gt;Corkythe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;background:#BB8D0A; color:#FFFFFF; border:1px solid #231F20&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Corkythehornetfan|&lt;span style=&quot;color:white&quot;&gt;hornetfan&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 03:14, 4 November 2015 (UTC)
*&quot;question and clarification&quot; is every other school and college already merged?  if the college of engineering isn't merged too, then this is a solid no, as the international impact of SPIA is significant and notable. but if this is just a cleanup of all schools and colleges then it makes sense. [[User:Buridan|Buridan]] ([[User talk:Buridan|talk]]) 02:16, 7 November 2015 (UTC)
**See [[WP:NOTINHERITED]]. We don't create sets of articles, they have to stand on their own merits. &lt;span class=&quot;vcard&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fn&quot;&gt;[[User:Widefox|Widefox]]&lt;/span&gt;; [[User talk:Widefox|talk]]&lt;/span&gt; 12:19, 4 March 2016 (UTC)

==Virginia Tech Wikiproject and better sports articles==
I created the Virginia Tech Wikiproject and plan to work on beefing the sports articles up.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Go Hokies|Go Hokies]] ([[User talk:Go Hokies|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Go Hokies|contribs]]) 00:36, 13 November 2015 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

===[[Wikipedia:WikiProject Virginia Tech|Wikiproject Virginia Tech]] Recommendations for improving this article:===
*Create a separate article for the history of Virginia Tech
*Provide a paragraph or two about Virginia Tech’s student government
*Provide a paragraph or two about the many different student organizations available
*Provide more granularity into Virginia Tech’s research centers, initiatives, and activities
*Create a separate article providing more detail about Virginia Tech’s libraries
*Create a separate article for Virginia Tech’s Housing
*Improve the List of Virginia Tech Alumni
*Create a separate article listing the notable Virginia Tech faculty and administrators
*Create a separate article for Virginia Tech’s Museums
*Provide a paragraph or two about Virginia Tech’s media outlets
*Provide a paragraph or two about Virginia Tech’s transportation
*Provide a paragraph or two about scholarships available to students
[[User:Go Hokies|Go Hokies]] ([[User talk:Go Hokies|talk]]) 02:02, 17 November 2015 (UTC)


==Dining==
This is a great article with lots of information on many aspects of Virginia Tech. However, isn't it important to elaborate on the dining facilities located on campus for students? No minor flex plans are written, and only one dining hall (D2) is mentioned, shouldn't each dining hall be showcased?
[[User:Ellad|Ellad]] ([[User talk:Ellad|talk]]) 13:53, 21 September 2016 (UTC)

==Removing template for &quot;Multiple Issues&quot;==
I have read this article and compared it with those of VT &quot;sister institutions&quot; and found no reason for assigning the template for &quot;Multiple Issues.&quot; Most of the concerns have been met or were already reached by the time it was first placed here. Moreover, I don't see any explanation on this page supporting the claims in the template. If you think this template is required in this article, I will request you first present your views and evidence here on the talk page before reinstating it or reverting my edit.  [[User:Caballero1967|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#44018F;font-family: Herculanum&quot;&gt;'''Caballero&lt;font color=&quot;#145073&quot;&gt;/&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#006E0D;font-family:Lucida Blackletter&quot;&gt;Historiador&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:Caballero1967 |&lt;u&gt; ⎌&lt;/u&gt;''']]&lt;/sup&gt; 04:25, 22 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>mcop2pr4olbl0tvmet19haedhzas14n</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
