<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Arab nationalism</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>320744</id>
    <revision>
      <id>707997739</id>
      <parentid>707997181</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-03-03T00:38:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Charles Essie</username>
        <id>16892062</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Islamism */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="47097">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Arab world|class=B|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Palestine|class=B|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Lebanon|class=B|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Syria|class=B|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Iraq|class=B|priority=High}}
{{WikiProject Africa|class=B|importance=mid|Algeria=yes|Algeria-importance=High|Libya=yes|Libya-importance=mid|Tunisia=yes|Tunisia-importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Politics|class=|priority=}}
}}
{{Arab-Israeli Arbitration Enforcement}}

==Comment by RK==
Wait a tick...we already have an article on [[Pan-Arabism]], which is on the same topic. Shouldn't we merge these articles into one, and turn the remaining one into a redirect? [[User:RK|RK]] 00:25, 18 Sep 2003 (UTC)
::I agree, it seems to me like its just a different phrase for the same thing but I don't know enough about the subject to say for certain one way or the other. I've created a links from one article to the other. Maybe someone who knows more about it than me can merge the two. [[User:Saulisagenius|Saul Taylor]] 03:56, 23 Dec 2003 (UTC)

:::Pan-Arabism and Arab nationalism are not the same thing. Pan Arabism calls for the creation of an Arab super STATE. Arab nationalism is declaring that the Arabs constitute a nation. It makes no call to unify them in any capacity outside of &quot;feeling&quot;. Many Arab nationalists during the era of Pan Arabism advocated panArabism but many did not and are quite attached to their own Arab states. Algeria which was controlled by the Arab nationalist FLN was not Pan Arabist. It didnt want to unite with the other Arab countries but it did want to form alliance and have &quot;solidarity&quot;. Pan Arabism is a specific form of Arab nationalism, similar to Ba'thism or Nasserism. There should be two separate articles on these topics because they are NOT one in the same. They are related but are at the same time very very different. It is like &quot;ISlam&quot;, there are subforms of ISlam, Sunnah and Shiiah, still ISlamic, but they each have their own article because they are different forms. Arab nationalism would be &quot;ISlam&quot;, PanARabism would be &quot;Sunnah&quot; or &quot;Shiah&quot; in this way. Keep them separate! They are not different names for the same thing, they are related ideologies. Like communism and socialism or Marxism. These are not the same things. -[[El Moro]]

::::Arab Nationalism &quot;makes no call to unify [Arabs] in any capacity outside of `feeling`&quot;??? Here is a quote from &quot;Requiem for Arab Nationalism&quot; by Adeed Dawisha, Middle East Quarterly, Winter 2003, http://www.meforum.org/518/requiem-for-arab-nationalism 
::::''Arab nationalists advocated the rejuvenation of the Arab nation, its political unity, its secularism, and its sovereignty.''
::::Note: El Moro's page was deleted for marketing   --[[User:BoogaLouie|BoogaLouie]] ([[User talk:BoogaLouie|talk]]) 20:59, 23 February 2010 (UTC) 


How can anyone dispute the neutrality of this entry, its concise and to the point without any of the  leanings for or against such an idea. -[[IbnRasheed]]

==POV==

If someone has a POV objection, they should state it here before adding the template. - [[User:Mustafaa|Mustafaa]] 16:52, 3 Jun 2005 (UTC)

:It should be Islamic, not Islamist.

== The colors of the Arab flags ==

It is mentioned that Sykes is the one that proposed the flag colours.  However, up to my knowledge it is based on a verse of poetry by Safi al-din al-Hilli صفي الدين الحلي (forteenth century) which was quite nationalist.  The verse is:

سُودٌ وقائِعُنا بيضٌ صنائِعُنا======خضرٌ مرابِعُنا حمرٌ مواضِينا

Which specifically mentions the four colours (black, white, green and red) in a verse describing Arabs.  I don't have a reference, but I'm sure there is if someone is determined to find one.  --[[User:Maha Odeh|Maha Odeh]] 05:27, 23 August 2007 (UTC)

:The citation for that, evidently, is Fromkin's ''Peace to end all Peace''.  Maybe someone needs to check it out.  [[User:Slackerlawstudent|Slacker]] 08:40, 23 August 2007 (UTC)

:: Yes, I read that Idea came from Safi al-din al-Hilli. [[User:Mussav|Mussav]] ([[User talk:Mussav|talk]]) 15:38, 29 February 2008 (UTC)

==Some areas for improvement==
George Antonious deserves much more than a &quot;see also&quot; link at the end.  Also, there should be some mention of the fact that the Arabic language has two quite distinct and separate words for &quot;nationalism&quot;: ''wataniyya'' وطنية (loyalty to one's home region or specific country) and ''qawmiyya'' قومية (broad pan-Arabism).  Without being seeking to become polemical, it seems only too obvious that qawmiyya has a distinct lack of specific practical concrete achievements, when compared with the broad sweeping claims and grandiose bombastic rhetoric that were closely associated with it over many decades -- and there should be some way of alluding to this fact in the article... [[User:AnonMoos|AnonMoos]] ([[User talk:AnonMoos|talk]]) 10:39, 12 December 2008 (UTC)

==Tagging POV==

Questionable stuff in the article with no or scant sources:&lt;BR&gt;
''Within the Arab nationalist movement are three differentiations: the Arab nation, Arab nationalism, and pan-Arab unity ... Local patriotism centered on individual Arab countries was incorporated into the framework of Arab nationalism starting in the 1920s. '' --[[User:BoogaLouie|BoogaLouie]] ([[User talk:BoogaLouie|talk]]) 21:49, 23 February 2010 (UTC)

== new section 1920s - 40s ==
after reading this article i noticed in the hisotry section there was a gap in the years between the end of WWI and the end of WWII, so i've copied content covering this period from [[Racism in the Palestinian territories#British Mandate in Palestine]]. this content is already related, but it could be improved to make it more relevant to this particular aticle. [[User:WookieInHeat|WookieInHeat]] ([[User talk:WookieInHeat|talk]]) 20:00, 16 November 2010 (UTC)

:And I've reverted.  Please don't [[WP:censorship|censor]] things just because [[Wikipedia:I just don't like it|you don't like it]].  Thanks.  --[[User:GHcool|GHcool]] ([[User talk:GHcool|talk]]) 18:46, 23 March 2011 (UTC)

::huh? i didn't remove anything, i added stuff. [[User:WookieInHeat|WookieInHeat]] ([[User talk:WookieInHeat|talk]]) 04:11, 11 May 2011 (UTC)
:::I think he was talking about me. I had since filled that gap and removed the information which really doesn't belong in this article and is highly biased and misleading in regards to the overall topic. GHcool hasn't provided any reason for keeping this sore thumb of a section in the article and I'll probably remove it in a few days whilst adding information on the Arab nationalist germanophilia which only developed in the 1930s and is certainly relevant to the article. Prior to that Arab nationalists centered their favor on French nationalism and ideas and that should be included as well. By the way, I mean no offense to you at all. You were just to trying to improve the article by providing information for that 20-year gap so your efforts are of course appreciated and I encourage you to continue editing the article if you're interested. Cheers! --[[User:Al Ameer son|Al Ameer son]] ([[User talk:Al Ameer son|talk]]) 04:56, 11 May 2011 (UTC)

== Too much mufti emphasis ==

There seems to be a lot of emphasis on Haj Amin al-Husayni and the implication that Arab nationalism is rabidly racist. The entire 1920s-40s section is centered on the Arab national movement in Palestine during the colonial period, but more so on the idea that Arab nationalists were Nazis and racists. There certainly needs to be a more comprehensive and less biased section on this period of Arab history. I will edit the section (clean up, expand) and I ask anybody who is interested to please join me. Thank you. --[[User:Al Ameer son|Al Ameer son]] ([[User talk:Al Ameer son|talk]]) 04:22, 23 February 2011 (UTC)

:It would be vastly oversimplified to say that they &quot;were Nazis and racists&quot; but unfortunately several strands of Arab nationalism were not too fastidious about drawing inspiration from general fascist movements during the 1920s-1940s (at first more Mussolini than Hitler), from Anton Saadeh to Rashid Ali al-Gaylani to Haj Amin al-Husseini -- and the literal translation of the Arabic word for &quot;pan-Arab nationalism&quot; &lt;big&gt;قومية&lt;/big&gt; is &quot;tribalism&quot;!  20th-century Arab nationalism had many noble aspirations, but also had its seamy side -- as many Kurds, Berbers, Copts, other Christians, and Jews have become painfully aware of over the years... [[User:AnonMoos|AnonMoos]] ([[User talk:AnonMoos|talk]]) 12:26, 23 February 2011 (UTC)

::Yes, but these were the actions and/or beliefs of proclaimed Arab nationalists (Haj Amin, Rashid Ali, Saddam) and this article is on the ideology of Arab nationalism. These men were certainly important figures in Arab history, but they should be given only brief mentions in this article. They were not the thinkers, intellectuals, or developers of the ideology. They did not advance it poltically like Abdel Nasser, the Hashemites and the original Baathists (all three viewed Arab nationalism in a different way I should add). Besides Rashid Ali, these figures (Haj Amin, Saddam, Hafez) clearly rode the wave of Arab nationalist feeling that was sweeping the Arab world at the time and used it to advance their particular political aspirations. The latter two just replaced existing Arab nationalist governments. I would also like to add that Christians were primary founders of the ideology and I never heard of Arab nationalist-led discrmination against Copts or other Christians besides the conflict between the nationalists and the Maronites in Lebanon. Also, [[Antun Saadeh]] actually opposed Arab nationalism, favoring Greater Syrian nationalism. What I'm trying to say is that the current section seems like blatant cherry-picking to describe Arab nationalism as a Nazi fueled movement and concentrates on the developments in Palestine in which Arabs began to revolt against who they saw as unwelcome occupiers of their land i.e. Jewish immigrants and British forces. Obviously, hate for Jews was developing rapidly because of events unfolding in Palestine not because Arabs just simply hate Jews. No excuse for hate, but it's clear this was all politically motivated. --[[User:Al Ameer son|Al Ameer son]] ([[User talk:Al Ameer son|talk]]) 06:38, 24 February 2011 (UTC)

:::Many Christians (from Antonious to Aflaq to Habash) were more enthusiastically nationalist than most Muslims, but that didn't prevent the majority of Arab governments which claimed to be inspired by Arab nationalist ideology from discriminating in a number of subtle or not-so-subtle ways against Christians.  Many Christians in the middle east remember that the first Arab government to be given a degree of independence from European rule celebrated its newly-found independence by [[Assyrian massacre|massacring Christians]] (and the Jews remembered it very clearly too, when they were deciding during the 1930s and 1940s whether not it would be realistically tolerable to live under a future exclusively Arab-run Palestine government) -- and they also remember that Michel Aflaq was given a faked up deathbed &quot;conversion&quot; to Islam, apparently because some Arab nationalists believed that only being a Muslim is truly compatible in the long run with Arab nationalism...

:::On your larger point, Haj Amin al-Husseini certainly didn't significantly contribute to the development of Arab nationalist ideological theories, and I'm not sure why he has to be specifically mentioned in this article at all -- but on the other hand, reducing this article to noble-sounding purely theoretical declarations only, and omitting any mention of the unfortunately all-too-many examples in which such theories ended up having strikingly negative effects when people attempted to implement them in the real world, would unbalance the article. [[User:AnonMoos|AnonMoos]] ([[User talk:AnonMoos|talk]]) 08:17, 24 February 2011 (UTC)

::::I wouldn't tie the massacre of Assyrians in Rashid Ali's Iraq to Arab nationalism, but I'm not informed enough on Iraqi history to really argue that point. Anyway, my disagreement with most of your first statement is irrelevant. On your second note, however, I agree with you 100%. After all that's why there's a History section. Emphasis of the 1920s-1940s period should be on the popular rise and political domination of Arab nationalism in the Mashreq (Iraq, Syria, Palestine, Transjordan, Hejaz). It should concentrate on the indigienous Arab struggles against the various European occupations of those lands, the inter-Arab nationalist rivalries developing at the time, the problems arising in Palestine and its significance as a rallying point for Arab nationalism, and of course any cases where Arab nationalist governments committed any crimes or atrocities against non-Arabs should also be mentioned. Then we could get into the 1950s when Egypt took up the mantle of Arab nationalism and brought it to its peak (and demise). The goal of course to create a ''comprehensive'' and ''balanced'' article. There is certainly major criticism of Arab nationalism by Arabs and non-Arabs alike. So much actually, that I think the best thing to do is create a Criticism section. --[[User:Al Ameer son|Al Ameer son]] ([[User talk:Al Ameer son|talk]]) 17:39, 24 February 2011 (UTC)

The mufti and links to NAZIs have nothing to do with Arab nationalisms. It's like saying Zionism has links to communism, or Zionism has links with hindusim.

Wikipedia continues to be anti-arab.... all articles related to Arabs are anti-arab in a way or another. but i guess it's ok to be anti-arabs... it's not a crime,,, it's actually something being promoted these days... heads up wikipedia  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/213.210.238.186|213.210.238.186]] ([[User talk:213.210.238.186|talk]]) 11:53, 28 March 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:That's interesting -- for almost 40 years, Saudi Arabia's policy with respect to Israel consisted almost solely and exclusively of claiming that Israel was a communist entity which was nefariously scheming to Bolshevize the middle east... [[User:AnonMoos|AnonMoos]] ([[User talk:AnonMoos|talk]]) 16:38, 28 March 2012 (UTC)
:: Do you have any reliable sources for that? I'd hate to know you're editing this page with such beliefs lingering about. Oh and yes, an emphasis on a man of the cloth with regards to political ideologies is very bad for an article touting of reliable information. [[User:Humuphile|Humuphile]] ([[User talk:Humuphile|talk]]) 05:41, 9 June 2012 (UTC)
:::Read what western diplomats who dealt with the Saudis in the 1950s and 1960s especially (but sometimes continuing later) have written.  If there was a distinctively Saudi approach to dealing with Israel before the 1990s, it was &quot;Israel = Bolshevism&quot; and not much else... [[User:AnonMoos|AnonMoos]] ([[User talk:AnonMoos|talk]]) 21:05, 11 September 2012 (UTC)

== Clarifications needed ==

Some of the info in the &quot;Links with Nazism&quot; which I think many would consider controversial needs some clarification. The particular instances are &quot;Due to al-Husayni's role of leadership and his association with the Nazi leader, he was sometimes referred to as the &quot;fuhrer of the Arab world&quot;. Who ''sometimes'' referred to him as the &quot;fuhrer of the Arab world&quot;? I would presume it was his opponents, but this needs to be clarified. Similarly, in the sentence &quot;In 1935, Jamal al-Husayni (Haj Amin's brother) established the Palestine Arab Party, the party was used to create the &quot;fascist-style&quot; youth organization, al-Futuwwa; also sometimes called the &quot;Nazi Scouts.&quot; Again, who ''sometimes'' called them the &quot;Nazi Scouts&quot;? --[[User:Al Ameer son|Al Ameer son]] ([[User talk:Al Ameer son|talk]]) 23:09, 18 March 2011 (UTC)
:As you were posting this, I rewrote the two sentences in question, eliminating the weasel wording (&quot;sometimes called&quot;) and more clearly substituting what the cited sources say. I also tagged one of the sources as being of questionable reliability, but had no obvious reason to ignore the other. If you, on the other hand, have some reason to believe the sites used are not [[WP:RS|reliable sources]], you might want to raise the question at [[WP:RSN]]. [[User:Fat&amp;amp;Happy|Fat&amp;amp;Happy]] ([[User talk:Fat&amp;amp;Happy|talk]]) 02:26, 19 March 2011 (UTC)
::Wow. Thank you very much for the clarifications. This alone has improved the section's NPOV. As for reliable sources, upon a quick scan, the Palm Beach Post source seems to be biased against Arabs while also borderline irrelevant. I won't bring it up myself at the reliable sources noticeboard until I do a slightly more focused background check though. --[[User:Al Ameer son|Al Ameer son]] ([[User talk:Al Ameer son|talk]]) 06:15, 19 March 2011 (UTC)

== Nazism section ==

I have some concerns with this section and they do not relate to [[WP:Censorship]]. One problem is much of the section, especially about the mufti, are irrelevant to this article. It is clear that the mufti was not an Arab nationalist. Sources used in this article, including some used in this section, emphasize the fact that he was not a pan-Arabist, but actually a Palestinian nationalist or a pan-Islamist or both. He may have rode the wave of Arab nationalism which was dominant in this time period to help his own cause and his role in the general Arab movement should be mentioned and is mentioned in the article. It is also made clear in the article that the mufti was not an Arab nationalist. However, the first passage of the &quot;Links with Nazism&quot; section completely focuses on the mufti and his ties with Hitler as if the mufti was a representative of the Arab nationalists or an activist in the Arab national''ist'' movement. This is dangerously misleading. This article is about Arab nationalism and the history of the Arab nationalist movement and not about the relationship between the mufti and Hitler or the mufti's tirades against the Jewish people. This information belongs in the articles on the mufti, Hitler and perhaps Palestinian nationalism, but not this article. It is true, as I could tell from a wide range of sources, that a segment of the Arab population, and Arab nationalists in particular, were sympathizers of Nazi Germany, but it must be clarified as to why. Some of the same sources that are used in this section provide some context behind this sympathy; Arab nationalists at the time were in conflict with the British and French colonial authorities who were also at war with Germany and the Arab people in general fiercely opposed Zionism and Jewish settlement in Palestine. This information must be provided if it is to be a balanced section. This latter issue is why I added the POV tag. 

The sentence ''In the 1930s, wealthy Arab youths, educated in Germany and having witnessed the rise of [[fascist]] paramilitary groups, began returning home with the idea of creating an &quot;Arab Nazi Party&quot;.'' needs to be verified. Besides the only reference used to back this information, I could not find it in google books. Maybe a better search is needed. 

Finally I would like to suggest again that we might need a different section centering on allegations of prejudice by Arab nationalists or Arab nationalism. In that section, we could include the ties with Nazism and anti-Semitism. This section would also include the attempted Arabization of Kurdistan by Saddam's Iraq and Hafez's Syria. We need to address these issues as soon as possible. Any ideas on how to move forward? I would prefer we discuss things here before removing information to avoid edit warring. --[[User:Al Ameer son|Al Ameer son]] ([[User talk:Al Ameer son|talk]]) 04:44, 25 March 2011 (UTC)
:Re:
:{{Quote|The sentence ''In the 1930s, wealthy Arab youths, educated in Germany and having witnessed the rise of [[fascist]] paramilitary groups, began returning home with the idea of creating an &quot;Arab Nazi Party&quot;.'' needs to be verified. Besides the only reference used to back this information, I could not find it in google books. Maybe a better search is needed.}}
:the actual statement on page 106 of the cited book is:
:{{Quote|Palestinian students educated in Germany returned to Palestine determined to found the Arab Nazi Party of Palestine.}}
:it has a footnote (67) appended, but the page containing that footnote was not available in the preview I used. Not to get into the business of linkspam, but Amazon (U.S.) has a better preview for this book than Google (which only provides snippets). It can be found at http://www.amazon.com/Armies-Young-Soldiers-Terrorism-Childhood/dp/0813535689#reader_0813535689 and if you search for ''Arab Nazi Party'' in their preview you can view page 106. Again, I make no assertion as to whether the book is a reliable source or not. [[User:Fat&amp;amp;Happy|Fat&amp;amp;Happy]] ([[User talk:Fat&amp;amp;Happy|talk]]) 05:26, 25 March 2011 (UTC)

the section seems professionally written. type &quot;arab nationalism nazism&quot; into google and you get millions of hits and articles by scholarly sources. [[Special:Contributions/82.102.73.55|82.102.73.55]] ([[User talk:82.102.73.55|talk]]) 19:11, 11 May 2011 (UTC)

:Hello, I'm not sure you are aware of Wikipedia policy. You can't just remove the POV tag because you feel it's not justified. Your revert actually constitutes as [[WP:Vandalism]] and more so [[WP:Edit warring]]. And you certainly need a better argument than the one sentence you gave above. You and nobody else haven't even bothered to address my concerns listed above. Particularly, but not limited to, the irrelevance of the Mufti and his dealings with Hitler since the mufti wasn't an Arab nationalist and the fact that this article isn't centered on individual nationalists, but on the Arab nationalist movement, its history and above all the ideology itself. The section, written professionally or not, is quite misleading. I have studied and continue to study Arab nationalism and I am fully aware that Arab nationalists began to look to Germany for support, militarily and ideologically, in the 1930s because of their main conflict with Britain, France, and Zionism. Germany was at war with the first two and made clear its disapproval of the third. They also believed Germany had no colonial intentions. Furthermore, their ideologues were impressed with 19th-century German nationalism not 20th-century Nazism. Thus their attempts to gain the support of Nazi-run Germany was mostly political. None of this is even mentioned in the section so therefore you have a very unbalanced section which if you take a look above, was simply copied and pasted from [[Racism in the Palestinian territories]] article. Read Bassem Tibi, Sylvia Kedourie, Salim Yaqub, Youssef Choueiri, and Adeeb Dawisha's books on Arab nationalism. Since you appear to be fond of using google scholar, you'll easily find those books (all of which you could at least preview) since they're the first selections google books lists when you search &quot;Arab nationalism.&quot; Also, if you want to improve this article, you should rely on sources that are not attacking or praising the ideology, just writing about it in a neutral manner. As I have stated a number of times at this talk page, I intend to work on these issues, clarify and balance them out. In the end there won't be a blatantly POV and misleading subsection titled &quot;Links with Nazism.&quot; Instead, the information will be added to existing sections, mostly the &quot;Expansion of the movement&quot; subsection and the &quot;Ideology&quot; section. Do NOT remove the POV tag until something is agreed to or you at least achieve something of a consensus until the intended changes are made. Thank you. --[[User:Al Ameer son|Al Ameer son]] ([[User talk:Al Ameer son|talk]]) 20:59, 11 May 2011 (UTC)
::i originally removed the POV tag a few days ago, the IP address is not me though. my reasoning: after reading over the talk page, it appeared the concerns you raised about POV had been addressed, and you hadn't raised any further issues in over a month. the inclusion of the mufti didn't seem to be a POV issue so much as a relevance issue. i disagree though that the mufti was not an arab nationalist, considering that he was a significant leader in the arab world and had close associations with the leaders of various arab nationalist political parties. which as the section establishes, were linked with the rise of nazism in germany in the 1920s-30s, after the defeat of the germans and ottomans in WWI at the hands of the allies.
::regardless, i agree that the section could use some further elaboration and expansion, it is not clear enough in certain areas. if you have reliable sources to support what you would like to add, by all means. i do however object to its total removal as you propose, denial/suppression of this part of arab history would be far more POV than inclusion in its current form. [[User:WookieInHeat|WookieInHeat]] ([[User talk:WookieInHeat|talk]]) 02:27, 16 May 2011 (UTC)
:::A lot of the significant Arab leaders at that time were not specifically Arab nationalists; rather, many were regionalists (Egyptian, Syrian, Sudanese, Saudi, Lebanese, and Palestinian). I don't want to go at lengths about the mufti since this article is not about him, but the mufti was more of a Palestinian nationalist with pan-Islamic tendencies. He was indeed a significant factor in the Arab political scene as the article already illustrates. I just believe we're giving much undue weight to the mufti and the details of the anti-Zionist and anti-British movement in Palestine. There's already a sizable passage on it in the prior section. The second sentence of the second passage seems relevant enough for a mention: it entails the Baathist take on the general atmosphere in the Arab world. Whether [[Sami al-Jundi]] is relevant I don't know. The info on the Futuwwa movement and the British concerns in Palestine about it need not mention in ''this'' article. In ''any case'' there shouldn't be a section on &quot;Links with Nazism&quot; as if it's an implication against the Arab nationalist movement or a major part of the movement's development. I renamed it such in haste, thinking it would be temporary and a matter of time before I wrote a more elaborate take on the new and growing Germanophilia of 1930s Arab anti-colonial politicians. I have to disagree with your statement that Arab nationalism was linked with the rise of Nazism. The two ideas had been completely separate and developed separately and for different reasons. It was only in the 1930s where they formed something of a natural alliance. We should relocate the relevant info in the section to wherever it fits in the &quot;Expansion of the movement&quot; section. I don't want to have a filibuster-like situation where I insist on keeping the POV tag until I make the necessary changes so I encourage editors interested in the improvement of the article to be [[WP:Bold|bold]]. Find info on the history, progress, and development of the Arab nationalist movement in the 1930s-1940s (recommend using the unbiased sources) and help balance the present info. I don't want to &quot;deny or suppress&quot; this part of Arab nationalist history. I pretty much wrote the previous section which focuses on the same time period: 1920s-1930s. It might take a little while for me to continue, so until then I propose anybody else take a crack at elaborating and expanding the info and then we could remove the tag. I can't stress enough, however, that having a separate section for Nazi links is [[WP:UNDUE|undue]]. I also would like to stress that I can't agree to the removal of the POV tag until some of the aforementioned points are addressed. --[[User:Al Ameer son|Al Ameer son]] ([[User talk:Al Ameer son|talk]]) 02:32, 18 May 2011 (UTC)
::::Al Ameer son makes some fair points.  I don't think its necessary to have a Nazism subheading, but I disagree with Al Ameer son when he implies that Nazism was not an important part of Arab nationalist history and philosophy.  Furthermore, I believe that the Husseinis were Arab nationalists both at the local level and at the global level.  Their contribution to Arab nationalism is vital to an overall understanding of the phenomenon.  --[[User:GHcool|GHcool]] ([[User talk:GHcool|talk]]) 05:26, 18 May 2011 (UTC)
:::::sorry for the delay, i've been very busy lately. any way, just wanted to respond to a specific point...&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;''&quot;the mufti was more of a Palestinian nationalist with pan-Islamic tendencies&quot;'' -- Al Ameer son&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;''Mohammad Amin al-Husayni was a Palestinian '''Arab nationalist''' and Muslim leader in the British Mandate of Palestine.'' -- [[Mohammad Amin al-Husayni|Wikipedia]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;''Amīn al-Ḥusaynī, grand mufti of Jerusalem and '''Arab nationalist''' figure who played a major role in Arab resistance to Zionist political ambitions in Palestine and became a strong voice in the Arab nationalist and anti-Zionist movements.'' -- [http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/277483/Amin-al-Husayni Encyclopedia Britannica]&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;''al-Husayni's ... political orientation was plainly '''Arab nationalist''' after the war.'' (WWI) -- [http://www.amazon.com/Confronting-Empire-Constructing-Nation-Nationalists/dp/1845111737 Confronting an Empire, Constructing a Nation: Arab Nationalists and Popular Politics in Mandate Palestine] pg.31&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;al husayni is very relevant to this article, he was a prominent figure of the movement. not to mention literally every other reference - including his wikipedia article - refers to him as an arab nationalist. i will address your other points soon. cheers [[User:WookieInHeat|WookieInHeat]] ([[User talk:WookieInHeat|talk]]) 22:03, 14 June 2011 (UTC)

== Merge ==

Arab nationalism and [[Pan-Arabism]] really emphasize on the same goals and should be viewed as one in the same. [[User:Charles Essie|Charles Essie]] ([[User talk:Charles Essie|talk]]) 18:41, 11 September 2012 (UTC)
::I think you need to justify that a bit more; [[WP:MERGE#Reasons for a merger|what reasons]], exactly, are you saying apply here? [[User:Moonraker12|Moonraker12]] ([[User talk:Moonraker12|talk]]) 22:26, 6 December 2012 (UTC)

*I would '''Oppose''' this merger: as discussed [[Talk:Arab nationalism#Comment by RK|above]], Arab nationalism and Pan-Arabism are separate (albeit related) subjects, and the two articles are very different in content and scope.
:Also, this article (at 43Kb) is already [[WP:SIZERULE|getting to the point]] when splitting it would be advisable; how does making it bigger improve the situation? [[User:Moonraker12|Moonraker12]] ([[User talk:Moonraker12|talk]]) 22:30, 6 December 2012 (UTC)

== Links with Nazism section continued ==

I think it's time to reopen this discussion. Some IPs have been vandalizing the section lately, so it's caught my attention again. Like my previous stance, I support the removal of the section since it's basically a collection of tidbits trying to paint the picture that the nationalists were like Nazis or allies of Nazis, when in reality, Germany, and Nazi Germany in particular, didn't factor so much in the development of the movement. Then of course the title (&quot;Links with Nazism) implies that Arab nationalism was an organized or unitary movement with &quot;links&quot; to the Nazis whereas the movement was a diverse one with different and often clashing trends: the British-aligned Hashemites and their supporters who focused on the Mid-East, the radical pan-Arab Baathists, the Istiqlalists, the Nasserists of the 50s and 60s, and independent nationalist thinkers and politicians. Some individuals within these trends harbored pro-German feeling either because in that era they had a mutual enemy in the British and French who colonized the Arabic-speaking territories or because they were plain supporters of the racist and fascist ideology of Nazism. According to the frequently cited Youssef Choueri, 19th-century German nationalism, not Nazism, was particularly inspiring to the early Arab nationalist thinkers for various reasons. To be clear, I don't support any sort of whitewashing of history and as previously suggested, I say we should merge some of the more significant passages into the main subsections in a chronological order and leave the random tidbits of individual opinions i.e. those of the Baath member Sami al-Jundi, out (at least from this article, it could be included in any of the relevant [[Baath]] articles or if someone creates [[Sami al-Jundi]].) --[[User:Al Ameer son|Al Ameer son]] ([[User talk:Al Ameer son|talk]]) 04:35, 29 January 2013 (UTC)
:There has been a lot written about Arab nationalism's links with Nazism.  I think the section is good as it stands.  --[[User:GHcool|GHcool]] ([[User talk:GHcool|talk]]) 04:15, 30 January 2013 (UTC)
::That's false  and border line original research. You didn't reply to any of my points. To equate the Baath Party, which had individuals with Nazi sympathies, with the Arab nationalist movement as a whole, which is what this article is about, is misleading and goes against NPOV. To claim that the Mufti represented the Arab nationalist movement as a whole is also misleading. Also, if you recall, in the the section above where we were previously discussing this issue, you agreed that we should eliminate the &quot;Nazism&quot; heading. Any links, in the form of sympathy or inspiration, by individual Arab nationalists, with the Nazis or the Nazi ideology does not warrant a section dealing with the development of Arab nationalism. If we're going to have a separate section dealing with say, &quot;discrimination and Arab nationalism&quot; that's a different story. There we could include a passage about the racist sympathies of some of the early nationalists as well as the actions committed by the Baath in Iraq and Syria in the 70s-80s where non-Arabs (Kurds) were killed or displaced—if the reliable sources say it was in the name of Arab nationalism. We could also include the persecution of Islamists and communists by various Arab nationalist movements. Keep in mind that this article isn't about any particular individual or organization and we should avoid [[WP:UNDUE|undue weight]] and trying to paint our own picture of how the movement developed. --[[User:Al Ameer son|Al Ameer son]] ([[User talk:Al Ameer son|talk]]) 05:42, 30 January 2013 (UTC)
:::I don't think so.  Nazism ''did'' influence a large number of influential Arab nationalists during the years of the Third Reich (a critical period for Arab nationalism).  Let's not mince words here.  You're welcome to ''add'' information such as the debate surrounding how much influence Nazism had, but you may not [[WP:CENSOR]] information on this shameful (or proud from some Arabs' point of view) period of Arab history.  --[[User:GHcool|GHcool]] ([[User talk:GHcool|talk]]) 17:43, 30 January 2013 (UTC)
::::Uhh, no, but it doesnt work that way. You cant just say that a removal of irrelevant material is censorship. And in that vein, could you please tell me exactly how [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Arab_nationalism&amp;curid=320718&amp;diff=535724452&amp;oldid=535455750 this] material is related to the topic of the article? &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 23:57, 30 January 2013 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
Material in the article needs to be directly related to the topic of this article. I agree with Al Ameer that material on an individual Arab nationalist thought or did does not belong in this article unless it is directly related to Arab nationalism. This would be like filling the [[Zionism]] article with material on say Yitzhak Rabin's association as PM of Israel with his counterpart in South Africa in a section on Zionist links with Apartheid. That something you think should be &quot;censored&quot; GH? Or should we instead write according to the policies of this website, specifically [[WP:OR]] and [[WP:DUE]]? &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 00:04, 31 January 2013 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
::::When did I say, or even imply, that we should &quot;censor&quot; information dealing with the relations between Nazi Germany and the Arab world? I'm saying that a certain amount of reliably sourced material dealing with ties between the Arab nationalist movement as a whole and Nazi Germany should be merged with the rest of the History section in chronological order. Other material dealing with random nationalist individuals like al-Jundi or Jamal al-Husayni or the obsessive emphasis on the Mufti, should be removed from ''this'' article which isn't a summation of &quot;Arab history,&quot; but strictly about Arab nationalism. There's already a much more detailed article at [[Nazi relations with the Arab world]], the [[Mohammad Amin al-Husayni|Mufti]] has his own long and detailed article and the [[Baathism|Baath Party]] has several articles. Instead of adding more context to the section, it has now become even more one-sided with a blunt generalization that the Arab people are widely supportive of anti-Semitism and the implication that the Qur'an is a tool of anti-Semitism. I've restored the POV tag by the way since none of the earlier concerns were ever addressed (the above discussion ended abruptly without any sort of conclusion) and recent edits have made the segment even more biased. --[[User:Al Ameer son|Al Ameer son]] ([[User talk:Al Ameer son|talk]]) 00:25, 31 January 2013 (UTC)
:::::Fair enough.  I accept Al Ameer son's January 31 proposal, but be warned that if I suspect the dedication to [[WP:Undue weight]] crosses the line into violating [[WP:CENSOR]], I will restore the censored material.  --[[User:GHcool|GHcool]] ([[User talk:GHcool|talk]]) 17:14, 31 January 2013 (UTC)
::::::I got rid of the al-Jundi and Jamal al-Husayni bits and pieces and cut down info on the Mufti that had nothing to do with the Arab nationalist movement but more to do with the Mufti himself and the British Mandate period in Palestine. The Mufti is still mentioned frequently (too often I think). His leadership of the Palestine revolt, his role in the Bloudan Conference, his role in Iraq, his flight from Iraq to Germany, his development of ties with Hitler and the Nazis and attempts to coordinate Arab and German policies vis-a-vis the &quot;Jewish problem&quot; in Palestine, including a quote by him related to that matter is all mentioned. Nazi broadcasts of anti-Semitic messages tailored to the Arabs of the Mid-East and the relationship of Nazi Germany, Britain, Vichy Syria and the Rashid Ali period in Iraq have also remained because of their importance to the rise of Arab nationalism and the dynamics of WWII in the Mid-East as it relates to Arab nationalism (special emphasis on the events in Iraq. I replaced the picture showing the Mufti meeting with Hitler with one showing the Mufti and Rashid Ali commemorating the 1941 Iraq coup in a Berlin ceremony because it's more relevant to the passages dealing with coup and its repercussions while still reflecting the public support the two men were given by Germany. Finally, I've begun expanding the info dealing with the importance of the conflict in Iraq and the earlier revolt in Palestine to the growth of Arabist sentiment, as well as the rival attempts of Egypt and Iraq to foster some form of Arab unity in the lead-up of the Arab League's establishment. --[[User:Al Ameer son|Al Ameer son]] ([[User talk:Al Ameer son|talk]]) 06:12, 2 February 2013 (UTC)
:::::::I liked most of your edits Al Ameer son, but restored some relevant things you deleted.  Sadly, someone rudely [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Arab_nationalism&amp;diff=536236472&amp;oldid=536230225 undid my restorations.] I intend on restoring my restorations in a day once a spirit of calmness once again inhabits Wikipedia's more hot headed editors.  --[[User:GHcool|GHcool]] ([[User talk:GHcool|talk]]) 22:34, 2 February 2013 (UTC)
::::::::Thank you GHcool, but actually I have to oppose most of your edits and restorations which really amount to a near-full restoration of the previous Nazism subsection, minus the heading, and including the abrupt inclusion of a See also link to &quot;[[Nazi relations with the Arab world]].&quot; I already linked it behind different wording, but that could certainly be tweaked for clearer exposure for the readers. Again, using the opinion of some low-level Baath Party official ([[Sami al-Jundi]]) to describe Arab nationalists as racists and supporters of Nazism simply goes against [[WP:Undue]] and [[WP:OR]]. In fact, he wasn't even a party official during the 1930s because the Baath Party wasn't founded until 1947. We're essentially using the assertion of a relative nobody, a random Arab nationalist, to label/describe all Arab nationalists or their collective mood in that particular decade. Why is Jamal al-Husayni's [[Palestine Arab Party]], a largely irrelevant force in the BM of Palestine, even mentioned at all? Because it was apparently inspired by the Nazis and named its youth movement after them? What would that have to do with the development of Arab nationalism? It belongs in the [[Nazi relations with the Arab world]] article or in the articles on Jamal-al-Husayni and the Palestine Arab Party. Finally I'm not sure why you changed line dealing with &quot;the Mufti&quot; becoming friendly with the Nazis to the &quot;[[al-Husayni]] clan&quot; being friendly with the Nazis? That's a false assumption or generalization of the whole family, not that any sort of relations between the family and the Nazis is relevant to this article. --[[User:Al Ameer son|Al Ameer son]] ([[User talk:Al Ameer son|talk]]) 05:58, 3 February 2013 (UTC)
:::::::::You make fair points.  I separated a paragraph and restored the picture of Hitler with the Mufti, but did not remove or insert any more text.  I consider the matter closed.  --[[User:GHcool|GHcool]] ([[User talk:GHcool|talk]]) 23:23, 3 February 2013 (UTC)
::::::::::I forgot about the picture. If we have one picture depicting the Mufti ''and'' Rashid Ali commemorating a major event linked to the growth of Arab nationalism (the 1941 Iraq coup) inside Nazi Germany isn't that much more relevant to that section of the article than a picture depicting the Mufti ''alone'' in a meeting with Hitler whose purpose isn't made known and, more importantly, whose relation to the development of Arab nationalism isn't made known? And of course we don't need two pictures of the Mufti as, once again this article isn't about him or Nazi relations with the Arab world. --[[User:Al Ameer son|Al Ameer son]] ([[User talk:Al Ameer son|talk]]) 23:49, 3 February 2013 (UTC)

http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-13610702 On 1 June 1941, a Nazi-inspired pogrom erupted in Baghdad,  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:InsufferableKnuts|InsufferableKnuts]] ([[User talk:InsufferableKnuts|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/InsufferableKnuts|contribs]]) 20:22, 15 July 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Welcome &quot;new&quot; user. This was discussed and removed by consensus, and if you want to restore it you need to establish a consensus for doing so.You would likely need to show the relevance to the topic of Arab nationalism. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 23:00, 15 July 2013 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
:Again, the material was removed by consensus. Either gain a new one or walk away. Repeated reverts will be reported. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 02:32, 16 July 2013 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;

== Revival ==

Some have argued that the [[Arab Spring]] has triggered a revival of Arab nationalism and Pan-Arabism, as there has been solidarity between the revolutionary movements in all the Arab states and the role of Arab nationalists in the revolutions. [[User:Charles Essie|Charles Essie]] ([[User talk:Charles Essie|talk]]) 21:36, 7 July 2013 (UTC)

== Constitutions ==

The recently approved Egyptian Constitution, along with its predecessors, and constitutions of some other Arab nations such as Jordan and Syria, all prominently state that their country is &quot;part of the Arab nation&quot;. Perhaps this should be mentioned in the article somewhere? --[[User:Yair rand|Yair rand]] ([[User talk:Yair rand|talk]]) 01:04, 28 January 2014 (UTC)

== Arab Nationalism Versus Islamic Fundamentalism ==
 
The decline of Arab Nationalism caused Islam offer the Arabs a genuine ideology, unlike Arab Nationalism and Marxism-Leninism which are imported from European ideas. King Faisal of Saudi Arabia sought to counter the influences of Marxism-Leninism and Arab Nationalism in the region by promoting pan-Islamism as an alternative. He called for the establishment of the Muslim World League, visiting several Muslim countries to advocate the idea. He also engaged in a propaganda and media war with Egypt's pan-Arabist president, Gamal Abdel Nasser.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/62.134.201.14|62.134.201.14]] ([[User talk:62.134.201.14|talk]]) 05:22, 12 June 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Arab nationalism after 1967==
This article features almost no information about Arab nationalism after the [[Six-Day War]]. The ideology did not just cease to exist after that. Arab nationalists continue to hold positions of power in many of the [[Arab states]] today. Arab nationalist groups also played key roles many subsequent conflicts throughout the [[Arab world]] (such as [[Black September in Jordan]], the [[Lebanese Civil War]], the [[Iran–Iraq War]], the [[Gulf War]], the [[Iraq War]], the [[First Intifada|first]] and [[Second Intifada|second intifadas]], the [[Arab Spring]], the [[Syrian Civil War]], the [[Arab Winter]], ect.). Arab nationalism is not dead. It's very much alive. [[User:Charles Essie|Charles Essie]] ([[User talk:Charles Essie|talk]]) 01:54, 4 July 2015 (UTC)

==Islamism==
This article seems to think that Arab nationalism and [[Islamism]] are mutually exclusive which is not true at all. There are many groups and personalities that have advocated a hybrid of Islamism and [[pan-Arabism]] (such as the [[Amal Movement]], the [[Arab Unification Party]], the [[Muslim Brotherhood]], the [[National Congress (Sudan)|National Congress]], ect.). [[Pan-Islamism]] could also be considered an expansion of pan-Arabism (just like [[Turanism]] is often considered and expansion of [[pan-Turkism]].). [[User:Charles Essie|Charles Essie]] ([[User talk:Charles Essie|talk]]) 00:34, 3 March 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>d8enwjv9bp2vk9tp7mg2hi8wdi7chu7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
