<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Kodori Valley</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>5682904</id>
    <revision>
      <id>704492962</id>
      <parentid>235999586</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-02-11T22:33:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cyberbot II</username>
        <id>16283967</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9913">{{WikiProject Abkhazia|class=Start|importance=High}}

Shouldn't something be mentioned about Russian accusations that Georgia is harboring or not stopping Chechen terrorists in this region?--[[User:Eupator|Eupator]] 18:15, 23 June 2006 (UTC)

:You're probably confusing it with the Pankisi gorge. An alleged 2001 Chechen presence in the Kodori valley is discussed in the article on [[Georgian-Abkhaz conflict]].--[[User:Kober|Kober]] 18:19, 23 June 2006 (UTC)
:: Yes you're right.--[[User:Eupator|Eupator]] 19:33, 23 June 2006 (UTC)

==Abkhazia Peaceful?==
I disagree with the definition of Kodori and Gali being two “troublespots” while the rest of Abkhazia is “peaceful.” This is nothing but Abkhzaian POW. First, these two regions are the only two region of Abkhazia that are relatively safe for ethnic Georgians, while the rest of Abkhazia is a real “troublespot” for any Georgian national (Georgians simply get killed if they go outside Gali or Kodori). Second, the rest of Abkhazia is by no means peaceful. People (mostly tourists) get kidnapped there for ransomed all the time. There is virtually no rule of law (quite often the kidnappers have everything worked out with the police), and human slavery is being practiced (mostly on citrus plantations). Thus, while Gali and Kodori are trouble spots for Abkhazians (and possibly Russians), the rest of Abkhazia is a trouble spot for Georgians (as well as other non-Abkhazian nationals). [[User:Irakliy81|Irakliy81]] 15:26, 29 July 2006 (UTC)

:Gamarjoba, Irakliy. Completely agree with you. I justed wanted to restore the context of the passage removed by Rebecca. I think the current version is quite neutral and objective.--[[User:Kober|Kober]] 15:55, 29 July 2006 (UTC)

:: Gamarjoba Kober, I’m glad that the current version has persisted. Thank you very much for maintaining this article. [[User:Irakliy81|Irakliy81]] 19:15, 30 July 2006 (UTC)

:::Kober is the man! [[User:Sosomk|Sosomk]] 02:39, 3 October 2006 (UTC)

== Recent move ==
Dear [[User:Petri Krohn|Petri Krohn]], your recent moves created a mess as the article's title was not in accordance with the text. Upper Abkhazia is a recently created administrative entity, while the Kodori Valley is a purely geographic term without any officially defined administrative boundaries. So I see no POV here. If you wish to have a separate article on the Valley as a geographic area, you are welcome to create it. Thanks, --[[User:Kober|Kober]] 04:55, 30 September 2006 (UTC)
:I have reverted your copy paste move. If you want to rename the article, you should follow the appropriate procedure, and seek a consensus on the talk pages. Doing a copy-paste move destroys the articles edit history, and can be seen as a form of vandalism.
: The &quot;renaming&quot; of Kodori Valley to &quot;Upper Abkhazia&quot; by the so-called [[de-jure Government of Abkhazia]] is a political move intended to undermine the legitimity of the &quot;rebel&quot; govenment of [[Abkhazia]]. Wikipedia should be very critical of such militant POV-pushing. -- [[User:Petri Krohn|Petri Krohn]] 22:19, 30 September 2006 (UTC)
:P.S. I have also redirected [[Upper Abkhazia]] to [[de-jure Government of Abkhazia]]. So far the name is nothing more than a new name the &quot;de-jure&quot; governments uses to refer to itself. If I start hearing the [[BBC]] using it, I might reconsider my possition.
:P.P.S. If you want to expand Wkipedia content, you might write an article on [[Upper Abkhazia]], the political entity, not the geographic valley. I doubt hovewer whether it would survive a without being merged to [[de-jure Government of Abkhazia]]. -- [[User:Petri Krohn|Petri Krohn]] 22:40, 30 September 2006 (UTC)

:: This action by User:Petri Krohn is unacceptable for NPOV compliance. First of all, this region has been officially called Upper Abkhazia as per recognition of Georgian government. This is a separate region of Abkhazia and has nothing to do with de jure government. This was a simple vandalism, which is definitely un-productive and harmful. Do not merge this region into any political entity. And refrain from POV statements and vandalizing the content of this article. Provide sources and references for your claims. Also please review Wikipedia policy on [[NPOV]]. Thanks for your contributions. [[User:Ldingley|Ldingley]] 16:20, 1 October 2006 (UTC)

:Before accusing me of &quot;militant POV-pushing&quot;, please be careful about your own bias. Undermine the &quot;legitimity&quot; of the Abkhaz separatists? Huh! Is this statement not POV? Kodori and other parts of Upper Abkhazia are ''de jure'' and ''de facto'' parts of Georgia, and what you call &quot;the so-called de jure government&quot; is the only internationally recognized authority on Abkhazia's territory. What you are trying here is just an attempt to destroy the content you disagree with. --[[User:Kober|Kober]] 05:06, 1 October 2006 (UTC)

:P.S. For the sake of a compromise, I'll proceed and create a seprate article on [[Upper Abkhazia]]. It is survivable and expandable and please don't destroy it. --[[User:Kober|Kober]] 05:58, 1 October 2006 (UTC)

:P.S.S. Btw, Googling already gives [http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=%22upper+abkhazia%22+-wikipedia 947 hits] for &quot;Upper Abkhazia&quot; -wikipedia.--[[User:Kober|Kober]] 06:08, 1 October 2006 (UTC)

:: Petri, refrain from Personal attacks. I will report to the administrator if you don't ceace to make attacks on other users and stop implementing your POVs on this article. Please review [[Wikipedia:Words to avoid]], [[Wikipedia:NPOV tutorial]] and [[Wikipedia:What is a troll]]. [[User:Ldingley|Ldingley]] 16:24, 1 October 2006 (UTC)

:::Spare people the threats, Ldingley. You were both out of line; Kober has since come up with a suitable compromise. [[User:Rebecca|Rebecca]] 06:32, 2 October 2006 (UTC)

:::: Im not threatening anyone. Please do not make false accusations. Im reminding Wikipedia policies, which you might be interested to. [[User:Ldingley|Ldingley]] 15:43, 2 October 2006 (UTC)

:::::I'm well aware of the appropriate policies. I'm just asking you to take heed of them too, and stop threatening action against other users when you've both been violating the same policies. [[User:Rebecca|Rebecca]] 02:08, 3 October 2006 (UTC)

:::::::Oh, Please what threatening are you guys talking about? Can we define the ''threatening'' first? Ms. Rebecca, if you are that ''experienced'' and ''sophisticated'' user you should be able to tell the difference between the outstanding scholars like LDingley and Vandals, who are just full of crap. In addition, ''WTF?'' is not a language that you should be using in an academical discussion. [[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Georgian-Abkhaz_conflict&amp;action=history]] [[User:Sosomk|Sosomk]] 02:35, 3 October 2006 (UTC)

::::::::Dear Georgian friends, please don't try to wikilawyer an [[WP:ArbCom|arbitrator emeritus]]. Rebecca's efforts at normalizing this discussion are enormously appreciated. --&lt;font color=&quot;FC4339&quot;&gt;[[User:Ghirlandajo|Ghirla]]&lt;/font&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;C98726&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Ghirlandajo|-трёп-]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 07:02, 5 October 2006 (UTC)

:::::::::Calm down guys! The problem has already been resolved and there's no need for arbitration. Since the start of the recent political crisis, many Georgia-related articles have come under repeated POV attacks and I understand the emotions of Luis and Soso. The content of the article as it is now is quite neutral. As for Petri's strange redirects, one should make a distinction among a government ([[de-jure Government of Abkhazia]]), a geographic area ([[Kodori Valley]]) and an administrative entity ([[Upper Abkhazia]]). So all the three articles are needed and potentially expandable. --[[User:Kober|Kober]] 07:22, 5 October 2006 (UTC)

==help me==
Hi I try to translate Kodori Valley into Korean. I should consider it natural to make appropriate title. But are there anyone who can tell me what is the correct pronouciation of Kodori?  I mean, the initiative letter, K is [k] sound or [g] sound? [[User:Pju0353|Pju0353]] ([[User talk:Pju0353|talk]]) 08:22, 3 September 2008 (UTC)
: It's [k] sound. [[User:Alaexis|Alæxis]]&lt;sub&gt;[[User_talk:Alaexis|¿question?]]&lt;/sub&gt; 10:14, 3 September 2008 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:4|one external link|4 external links}} on [[Kodori Valley]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=704492958 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20081024171824/http://www.jamestown.org:80/publications_details.php?volume_id=25&amp;issue_id=2240&amp;article_id=19322 to http://www.jamestown.org/publications_details.php?volume_id=25&amp;issue_id=2240&amp;article_id=19322
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20081026003901/http://www.jamestown.org:80/edm/article.php?article_id=2371309 to http://www.jamestown.org/edm/article.php?article_id=2371309
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20081024171808/http://jamestown.org:80/edm/article.php?article_id=2371315 to http://jamestown.org/edm/article.php?article_id=2371315
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20060821205613/http://www.jamestown.org/edm/article.php?article_id=2371395 to http://jamestown.org/edm/article.php?article_id=2371395

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 22:33, 11 February 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>794yjt8yrwmm5eaej3pik9oe9giii6t</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
