<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Marrakesh</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>4234351</id>
    <revision>
      <id>663068618</id>
      <parentid>585321943</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-05-19T11:22:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>M2545</username>
        <id>9455233</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>timeline</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24526">{{GA|06:01, 13 July 2013 (UTC)|topic=Places|page=1|oldid=564069076}}

{{Vital article|level=4|topic=Geography|class=GA}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Cities|class=GA|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Morocco|class=GA|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Africa|class=GA|importance=Top}}
}}

{{dyktalk|1 November|2012|entry=... that in 2009, when [[Fatima-Zahra Mansouri]] was elected mayor of '''[[Marrakesh|Marrakech]]''', she became only the second woman in [[Morocco]]'s history to be elected mayor of a Moroccan city?|nompage=Template:Did you know nominations/Marrakech}}

==Spelling==
Can somebody please tell me the Wikipedia stance on British/American spellings?  The latest edit here has changed ''Neighbourhoods'' to ''Neighborhoods''.  Not wanting to be petty, I haven't changed it back.  03/[[September|09]]/2006, [[User:Tomkeene|Tomkeene]]

:If the subject of the article has a natural affinity to one variety or the other, use that one. (ie write about an American citizen or city or battleship etc in American English). Otherwise, stick to the variety used by the first major contributor. Often, though I try to replace the word with a spelling-neutral one like ''district'' or ''quarter''. [[User:Roger Davies|&lt;font color=&quot;maroon&quot;&gt;'''R&lt;small&gt;OGER'''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Roger Davies|''TALK'']]&lt;/sup&gt; 08:30, 11 July 2007 (UTC)

==Economy==

Marrakech seems to have hosted a number of international meetings.  Any particular reason?  It would also be nice to have general information about the local economy. -- [[User:Beland|Beland]] ([[User talk:Beland|talk]]) 05:48, 24 September 2008 (UTC)

==Founding?==
Was the city founded in 1062 or 1070? [[User:Hexmaster|Hexmaster]] ([[User talk:Hexmaster|talk]]) 10:36, 22 January 2009 (UTC)


==History==
The end of the history section just fizzles out and reads like an advertisement. Topics that need to be covered include World War II and Independence.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/92.229.244.146|92.229.244.146]] ([[User talk:92.229.244.146|talk]]) 18:52, 21 May 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== English spelling ==

I moved the article to &quot;Marrakesh&quot;. ''Marrakech'' is the French spelling although it's used in English too, but the proper English spelling is &quot;Marrakesh&quot; which was used already in the body of article as many as 29 times prior to the move.
&quot;Marrakesh&quot; not only better reflects the transliteration from broth both Arabic (مراكش‎) and [[Tashelhit]] language, but is also used commonly in English. [[User:Khestwol|Khestwol]] ([[User talk:Khestwol|talk]]) 15:36, 5 October 2012 (UTC)

&quot;Marrakesh&quot; is also used in other Wikipedia articles, like [[Marrakesh-Tensift-El Haouz]]. [[User:Khestwol|Khestwol]] ([[User talk:Khestwol|talk]]) 15:47, 5 October 2012 (UTC)

No, the correct spelling is based on Berber which is with a c. [https://www.google.co.uk/search?q=Marrakech&amp;ie=utf-8&amp;oe=utf-8&amp;aq=t&amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US:official&amp;client=firefox-a#hl=en&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US%3Aofficial&amp;tbm=bks&amp;sclient=psy-ab&amp;q=Marrakech&amp;oq=Marrakech&amp;gs_l=serp.3..0.2839.3122.3.3290.2.1.1.0.0.0.46.46.1.1.0...0.0...1c.1.26iJLiUIOcU&amp;bav=on.2,or.r_gc.r_pw.r_qf.&amp;fp=8dd0d67111f7bdd9&amp;biw=1376&amp;bih=678 787,000] for Marrakech [https://www.google.co.uk/search?q=Marrakech&amp;ie=utf-8&amp;oe=utf-8&amp;aq=t&amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US:official&amp;client=firefox-a#hl=en&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US%3Aofficial&amp;tbm=bks&amp;sclient=psy-ab&amp;q=Marrakesh&amp;oq=Marrakesh&amp;gs_l=serp.3..0i13.50874.51531.4.51686.2.0.2.0.0.0.0.0..0.0...0.0...1c.pk6rFlArNmg&amp;bav=on.2,or.r_gc.r_pw.r_qf.&amp;fp=8dd0d67111f7bdd9&amp;biw=1376&amp;bih=678 295,000] for Marrakesh. I'm moving it back. I intend developing this article shortly.♦ [[User talk:Dr. Blofeld|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:#000&quot;&gt;Dr. Blofeld&lt;/span&gt;]] 15:08, 8 October 2012 (UTC)
:No, ''Marrakech'' is not based on Berber. The city is spelled ''Marrakec'' in the Berber Latin alphabet with a C at the end (not ''Marrakech''). The Berber pronunciation is ''Marrakesh'' because its alphabet uses C for ش (IPA: ʃ). The Arabic name has ش /sh/ at the end too. The English spelling &quot;Marrakesh&quot; is correct and is commonly used in English besides the French spelling. [[User:Khestwol|Khestwol]] ([[User talk:Khestwol|talk]]) 15:48, 8 October 2012 (UTC)

Yes but the real way to decide it is what is most commonly used in reliable sources and its 787,000 for Marrakech vs 295,000 for Marrakesh. I've had similar dilemnas over spelling and always decide it by most hits in google books. Per you could ask User:Al ameer son for input? Anyway I'll dig out my book shortly and begin and expansion. I aim to get this up to GA.♦ [[User talk:Dr. Blofeld|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:#000&quot;&gt;Dr. Blofeld&lt;/span&gt;]] 18:23, 8 October 2012 (UTC)
:This is an issue on the difference between the English and French spellings of Arabic proper names. For Moroccan, Algerian, Tunisian and Lebanese-related articles, there seems to be a tendency to use ''ch'' in lieu of ''sh'' i.e. Cheikh &gt; Sheikh. Personally, I prefer using the English spellings for all articles since this English Wikipedia, but the sources typically trump preference, unless otherwise specified by [[WP:MOS-AR|MoS-Arabic]].  --[[User:Al Ameer son|Al Ameer son]] ([[User talk:Al Ameer son|talk]]) 01:42, 9 October 2012 (UTC)
Having already done much research in preparing this article I think Marrakech is far more commonly used than Marrakesh, even in English publications. Books by the most reputable sources for travel and indeed websites on the city on places such as &quot;the largest club in Africa&quot; spell it Marrakech. There is a case to be made for spelling it Marrakesh, but i think the decision should be based upon the majority of reliable sources and how they spell it; 3 times as many spell it Marrakech.♦ [[User talk:Dr. Blofeld|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:#000&quot;&gt;Dr. Blofeld&lt;/span&gt;]] 08:19, 9 October 2012 (UTC)

:: Hm. That's not a proper g-books search.  Most of those numbers are &quot;ghost-hits&quot; (non-existent).  And you're not even restricting to English language sources.  A quick check (removing both Wikipedia llc, English-only restrictions, placing the cut-off at 1980 and trying to wash out g-hits) shows they're both roughly equal - that is 91 pages-worth of references vs. 100 pages-worth.  And the latter still includes a ''lot'' of French books and French references I couldn't weed out.  So it is not &quot;far more commonly used&quot;. It's pretty much a toss up. Personally, I have a preference for &quot;Marrakesh&quot;, not only for being the English spelling, commonly recognizable and commonly used, but also for yielding a more correct pronunciation in English (&quot;Marrakech&quot; in English will likely end up embarassingly pronounced &quot;Marraketch&quot; by many of the innocent children who will come here.)   Heck, even the official Morocco tourism website lists it as &quot;[http://www.visitmorocco.com/index.php/eng/I-am-going-to/Marrakech/Unmissable Marrakesh]&quot; in English.
:: Also, I have lot more observations and notes on the history section of this article, which I plan to substantially change.  But I will post those later. [[User:Walrasiad|Walrasiad]] ([[User talk:Walrasiad|talk]]) 12:02, 15 October 2012 (UTC)
:::The article is not completed yet but if you want to constructively help build it you are welcome so long as you referenced using sfb notes as I've been doing. I intend to take this to GA at some point. Also needs to mention recent events including the 2011 trouble. Actually Marrakesh spelling by page hits only averages about 300 hits a day, Marrakech gets 2200 odd.♦ [[User talk:Dr. Blofeld|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:#000&quot;&gt;Dr. Blofeld&lt;/span&gt;]] 14:26, 16 October 2012 (UTC)

Not sure what you by hits per day, but I expect a lot of your hits are from French &amp; other sources.  But take a closer examination.  Just going by the English references already contained in the article, most of the general-interest references you cite use &quot;Marrakesh&quot;  - e.g. Bosworth (2010), Clammer (2009), Denby (2004), Gerteiny (1967), Gottreich (2007), Layton (2011), Nanjira (2010), Naylor (2009),  Shillington (2005). 

Marrakech tends to be only used in specialist books which nativize (i.e. Frenchify) ''all'' location spellings (e.g. &quot;Fès&quot; instead of &quot;Fez&quot;), like Davis (2009), Delbecki &amp; co. (2011), Hamilton (2011), Harrison (2012), Hoisington (2004),  Pons (2010) and Venison (2005)  

(Rogerson uses both - esh in 2000, and ech in 2004)

Of the travel guides it is divided: Fodor's (2007), Lonely Planet (Hardy 2005, Mahyew/Dodd, 2004, Bing 2006/11), and Rough Guide (Jacobs, 2010) use Marrakesh, while Frommer's (Christiani, 2010, Humphrys (several)),  Maverick (Searight 1999) and Hedonist (Sullivan) use Marrakech ''but'' the latter also nativize everything (again, Fès instead of Fez, etc.)

(the &quot;further reading&quot; sources you cite I can't verify for degree of nativization, but just from the titles, the selection seems pretty balanced (also some sources repeated, this should be pared)).

More importantly, major news outlets (e.g. BBC,  [http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-13226117], New York Times [http://travel.nytimes.com/travel/guides/africa/morocco/marrakesh/overview.html]), even UNESCO ([http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/331]) and the Moroccan government (e.g. on official tourism site [&quot;[http://www.visitmorocco.com/index.php/eng/I-am-going-to/Marrakech/Unmissable Marrakesh]]), which you'd expect to nativize, actually use &quot;Marrakesh&quot; in their English text.  

Granted it is not always consistent. But you'll hardly ever see the &quot;Marrakech&quot; spelling paired together with English names like &quot;Fez&quot;, but only with French/nativist &quot;Fès&quot;.

In SUM: it's pretty clear Marrakesh is the English spelling, Marrakech is the French spelling.  And those who use English spelling generally use Marrakesh, while those who use French/nativist spelling generally go for Marrakech. 

Given this is a general interest English encyclopedia, for the general public rather than specialists, with a preference for common usage rather than specialized usage, the default should be the common English spelling: &quot;Marrakesh&quot;. If even Cote d'Ivoire is (perplexingly, IMO) is forced to be Ivory Coast here, I don't see why Marrakesh article shouldn't use the English spelling. (And it has the further advantage (as I already noted) of yielding the correct pronounciation for English-speakers, and not letting the children reading -ech slip into &quot;Marraketch&quot; or &quot;Marrakek&quot;.) [[User:Walrasiad|Walrasiad]] ([[User talk:Walrasiad|talk]]) 01:22, 18 October 2012 (UTC)

I disagree. The Collins world map in front of me, Marrakech. My National Geographic atlas which always tries to choose the &quot;most correct&quot; spelling for places spells it Marrakech. The most reputable books on Marrakech and local institutions spell it Marrakech. Where possible we should use the name most popular locally/nationally. Fès instead of Fez seems more appropriate too. A Pronounciation Marrak-esh can be added to the intro, hardly an argument.♦ [[User talk:Dr. Blofeld|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:#000&quot;&gt;Dr. Blofeld&lt;/span&gt;]] 15:15, 18 October 2012 (UTC)
:: Wikipedia is not about &quot;most correct&quot;.  It is about &quot;most common&quot;/&quot;least surprise&quot;.  Maps are a poor guide, since many nativize wholesale.  I got a supposedly English atlas with Munchen and Moskva instead of Munich and Moscow.  Most general English-speakers wouldn't recognize Fès at all. [[User:Walrasiad|Walrasiad]] ([[User talk:Walrasiad|talk]]) 16:27, 18 October 2012 (UTC)

*&quot; It is about &quot;most common&quot;/&quot;least surprise&quot;. True, more sources spell it Marrakech than Marrakesh, fact. 
*&quot;Maps are a poor guide&quot;. Actually, no, they usually try to be politically correct and as accurate as possible. [[National Geographic]] is a fantastic resource for geography and maps, and Collins is one of the world's most reputable institutions on language and spelling and they spell it Marrakech.♦ [[User talk:Dr. Blofeld|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:#000&quot;&gt;Dr. Blofeld&lt;/span&gt;]] 16:31, 18 October 2012 (UTC)
:: I can see with [http://maps.nationalgeographic.com/maps/atlas/europe-geopolitical.html my own eyes] that national Geographic has Munchen and Moskva, Torino and Wien in their Atlas.  That's not most common usage. I can also see with my own eyes that the [http://maps.nationalgeographic.com/maps searchable map] they use on their main map page has &quot;Fez&quot; and Marrakesh&quot;.  Try another angle. [[User:Walrasiad|Walrasiad]] ([[User talk:Walrasiad|talk]]) 16:43, 18 October 2012 (UTC)

You have an answer for everything don't you? Feel free to open an RFC or village pump post about what we should name the article. I'm convinced Marrakech is more popular than Marrakesh, Highbeam research (English language newspapers mainly) also confirms it 5000 odd for Marrakesh [http://www.highbeam.com/Search?searchTerm=marrakesh] 8150 for Marrakech [http://www.highbeam.com/Search?searchTerm=marrakech]  ♦ [[User talk:Dr. Blofeld|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:#000&quot;&gt;Dr. Blofeld&lt;/span&gt;]] 16:52, 18 October 2012 (UTC)

Yet [http://books.google.com/ngrams/graph?content=Marrakesh%2CMarrakech&amp;year_start=1980&amp;year_end=2010&amp;corpus=0&amp;smoothing=2&amp;share= ngram] says it ain't.  Again, I'm not seeing dominance you're claiming in number runs, but pretty much a toss-up, as mentioned before. As a result, I think reasonable expectations should play a larger role in consideration.  A big marker to me is that I simply don't find Marrakech-Fez pairings, but only Marrakesh-Fez or Marrakech-Fès, which indicates to me that Marrakech is used only in English texts which take the extra effort to nativize all spellings.   It is not a huge surprise - the visual difference between Marrakech &amp; Marrakesh is slight and can be glazed over. But the difference between Fez and Fès is huge and the latter would surprise and befuddle most general readers. Given that no Marrakesh/Marrakech spelling dominates it seems to me the pairing issue should be given higher priority, as many Morocco-related articles here naturally contain both cities, and to introduce an inconsistency in spelling that is not found in any text (i.e. no Marrakech-Fez pairings), we'd be introducing a new anomaly. As Marrakesh is English spelling, correct pronunciation, preponderant in general rather than specialist/nativist texts and common enough (even if not overtly dominant), there is little lost and much gained by it. But if you still believe you see some Marrakechi dominance somewhere I don't see, perhaps more eyes should be brought to bear. An RM and/or RFC should indeed be introduced to decide on both articles simultaneously (Marrakesh-Fez), not merely one individually. But it will likely delay approval of the DYK nom.  If you don't mind the delay, that can be done. [[User:Walrasiad|Walrasiad]] ([[User talk:Walrasiad|talk]]) 17:49, 18 October 2012 (UTC)

We could always move it to [[Marrakesh (Marrakech)]]...♦ [[User talk:Dr. Blofeld|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:#000&quot;&gt;Dr. Blofeld&lt;/span&gt;]] 17:52, 18 October 2012 (UTC)
:: That's probably the unhappiest of solutions. I'd be more interested in hearing your positive arguments for Marrakech (outside the number runs, which I hope you agree are inconclusive). That is, what advantages are gained by it. [[User:Walrasiad|Walrasiad]] ([[User talk:Walrasiad|talk]]) 18:35, 18 October 2012 (UTC)
::Believe it or not but the issue does not concern me as much as you think. I'm only going by my gut instinct having already a lot of research for this.♦ [[User talk:Dr. Blofeld|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:#000&quot;&gt;Dr. Blofeld&lt;/span&gt;]] 18:49, 18 October 2012 (UTC)
:::Dr. B asked my opinion, though I can not imagine why he thinks I'm an authority. FWIW, which is very little, the spelling I recognize is Marrakech. English spelling is notoriously not phonetic both for English names and for names in other languages, so proper phonetic transliteration has nothing to do with it. IMO, the best guide to current English spelling is the usage of major newspapers. The NYT &amp; London Times use Marrakesh. The WSJ uses Marrakech. Official sources are also useful. The US Dept. of State uses both, but Marrakech twice as often.  This leaves it completely ambiguous. At least, unlike many naming disputes, this one has no political connotations. '''[[User:DGG| DGG]]''' ([[User talk:DGG| talk ]]) 20:29, 18 October 2012 (UTC)

There are a greater majority of hits for Marrakech in both google book and English language sources in High Beam as well as US Dept of State using Marrakech twice as often. Add to this that most specialist books on it spell it Marrakech and local institutions and Moroccan government seem to recognize it as Marrakech there is a reason why I'm leaning towards Marrakech and I think that justifies this spelling.♦ [[User talk:Dr. Blofeld|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:#000&quot;&gt;Dr. Blofeld&lt;/span&gt;]] 20:42, 18 October 2012 (UTC)

We should trust Google Books [http://books.google.com/ngrams/graph?content=Marrakesh%2CMarrakech&amp;year_start=1950&amp;year_end=2012&amp;corpus=15 Ngram Viewer] which shows &quot;Marrakesh&quot; is used more commonly in English books. [[User:Khestwol|Khestwol]] ([[User talk:Khestwol|talk]]) 21:23, 19 October 2012 (UTC)

: For me its a question of practical experience and convenience in usage. Wikipedia is for general readers, not specialists, and general not specialist books are the guide to nomenclature.  Someone who picks up a dedicated book on Morocco isn't surprised when nativist spellings are thrown at him - he is mentally prepared for it, indeed, he expects it.  But a general reader isn't.  That is, someone who is researching another topic and picks up a book on, say, the general history of Africa, or Portuguese imperialism, or the Italian gold trade, or Medieval art, or Islamic legal schools, or Jewish migration, or textile weaves, or a children's atlas, is not expecting it and will be &quot;surprised&quot; by nativist spellings.  It is exactly for such general readers that Wikipedia is designed.  And it is for this reason the Moroccan government uses &quot;Marrakesh&quot; on its tourist sites.  I write a lot of historical articles, many of which touch on Moroccan history, where surprise spellings can startle and arrest the smoothness of the prose, particularly for a general reader. Marrakesh/Marrakech isn't the worst of them - eyes can glaze over. But Fès/Fez is impossible. Common recognizable phrases like the Maghrawa Kingdom of Fez, the Marinid palace of Fez, the Malikite scholars of Fez, the Ghana-Fez gold route, etc. become unrecognizable and startling when forced into &quot;Fès&quot;.  
: It is without doubt that Marrakesh is English spelling, and Marrakech is French spelling (as Bosworth [http://books.google.com/books?id=tPsUAAAAIAAJ&amp;lpg=PA593&amp;pg=PA588#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false notes]).  The question is whether the French spelling has dominantly displaced the English in common usage in general works.  And I don't see that. I see it displaced only in specialist works, or works which go the extra effort to nativize everything - which is why Marrakech-Fez pairings aren't found, only Marrakech-Fès or Marrakesh-Fez. In my experience, the Marrakesh-Fez pairing is the most common found in general works, simplest, natural and straightforward which won't cause head-scratching and wonder by general audiences.  It is more likely to be used in other Wiki articles and more likely to stay stable - that is, you're likelier to get people changing from &quot;Marrakech&quot; to &quot;Marrakesh&quot; thinking the spelling is a non-English mistake than people changing &quot;Marrakesh&quot; to &quot;Marrakech&quot;. Not only here, but particularly when used in other articles. [[User:Walrasiad|Walrasiad]] ([[User talk:Walrasiad|talk]]) 21:48, 19 October 2012 (UTC)

Actually page views show by far more editors search for Marrakech than Marrakesh..♦ [[User talk:Dr. Blofeld|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:#000&quot;&gt;Dr. ☠ Blofeld&lt;/span&gt;]] 11:41, 28 October 2012 (UTC)


Just in case there anyone failed to follow my note in Dr. Blofeld's talk page upon creation of History of Marrakesh&quot;, let me replicate it here:

:::OK.  But I object to the title. It really has to be &quot;Marrakesh&quot;, not &quot;Marrakech&quot;.  I don't know if you saw my citations in the original article to numerous books clearly and explicitly noting that &quot;Marrakesh&quot; is indeed the common English spelling. To replicate: Cenival (in Bosworth, 1989: [http://books.google.com/books?id=tPsUAAAAIAAJ&amp;lpg=PA593&amp;pg=PA588#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false p.588]), Cornell (1997: [http://books.google.com/books?id=u4X1s7S0ZdgC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PR15#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false p.xv]), Pennel (2000: [http://books.google.com/books?id=o4Ju-uaw49UC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PR34#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false p.xxxiv]), Gottereich (2007: [http://books.google.com/books?id=c6fALw8d9ZoC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PR15#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false p.xv]), Hoffman and Miller (2010: [http://books.google.com/books?id=W-ziBn5HakEC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PP12#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false p.xi]), Schroeter (2002: [http://books.google.com/books?id=ur38Oc3EIs8C&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PR19#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false p.xix-xx]). The French version may be the preference of some authors (and if they're serious authors, they'll note they're making a francophone deviation from the common English spelling, e.g. [http://books.google.com/books?id=Y4bEaUNtkx8C&amp;lpg=PR13&amp;dq=marrakesh%20marrakech%20spelling&amp;pg=PR13#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false]).  But &quot;Marrakesh' is clearly the common English spelling, and the one used in generalist works not narrowly dedicated to Morocco alone. I write a lot of North African-history related articles here, and that is what I've seen, what I've used and what I plan to stick with. So, if you don't object, I'm going to move that to &quot;History of Marrakesh&quot; for now.  We can RM a longer-term resolution later. [[User:Walrasiad|Walrasiad]] ([[User talk:Walrasiad|talk]]) 11:46, 28 October 2012 (UTC)

To summarize: while usage my be mixed in google searches, reliable references explicitly identify &quot;Marrakesh&quot; as the common English spelling.  Final decision can be put up to RM, but a decision had to be made in extracting the &quot;History of Marrakesh&quot; article.  [[User:Walrasiad|Walrasiad]] ([[User talk:Walrasiad|talk]]) 17:36, 28 October 2012 (UTC)

== History spinoff? ==

OK, so I just revamped the history section.  It tapers off horribly at the end - the 20th C. city certainly needs more work.  But I've pooped myself out for the moment and need a break. I still have to paste in the refs, but besides being momentarily tired, before I do so, I'd like to canvass opinion whether this section should be spinned off into its own article.  Looking at it now, it's kinda large for a city article, and I wonder if it should perhaps be moved to a &quot;History of Marrakesh&quot; article?  I am not sure how much to retain here - perhaps reverting back to the older smaller history, or taking a new summary from this one? Or just leave it as it is for now? (+ refs).  [[User:Walrasiad|Walrasiad]] ([[User talk:Walrasiad|talk]]) 23:06, 26 October 2012 (UTC)

Agree.  History section should move into its own article.  The history section in this article should be summarized based on what we currently have rather than reverting back to what was. --[[User:Rosiestep|Rosiestep]] ([[User talk:Rosiestep|talk]]) 02:21, 27 October 2012 (UTC)

Indeed, I'll condense it shortly, splitting done, tremendous work Walras.♦ [[User talk:Dr. Blofeld|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:#000&quot;&gt;Dr. ☠ Blofeld&lt;/span&gt;]] 11:39, 28 October 2012 (UTC)

== Etymology ==
The article says &quot;The probable origin of the name is from the Berber (Amazigh) words mur (n) akush . . . which means &quot;Land of God&quot;. The word mur is used now in Berber mostly in the feminine form tamurt.&quot;  But of the two words, ''mur'' and ''akush'', which means 'land' and which means 'God'?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Linguistatlunch|Linguistatlunch]] ([[User talk:Linguistatlunch|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Linguistatlunch|contribs]]) 11:43, 23 May 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

{{Talk:Marrakesh/GA1}}

== [[Timeline of Marrakesh]] ==
What is missing from the city timeline? Please add relevant content. Thank you. -- [[User:M2545|M2545]] ([[User talk:M2545|talk]]) 11:22, 19 May 2015 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>1po71anzx2ppoqc94i2i22ofcqfo7bf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
