<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:North Staffordshire Railway</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>3013693</id>
    <revision>
      <id>379293491</id>
      <parentid>379293335</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-08-16T22:07:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SineBot</username>
        <id>4936590</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Signing comment by [[Special:Contributions/86.171.23.213|86.171.23.213]] - &quot;/* Diagram is wrong */ new section&quot;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8893">{{ArticleHistory
| action1       = GAN
| action1date   = 16:42, 28 April 2006
| action1link   = Talk:North Staffordshire Railway#G
| action1result = failed
| action1oldid  = 50080509

| action2       = GAN
| action2date   = 00:24, 24 July 2009
| action2link   = Talk:North Staffordshire Railway/GA1
| action2result = listed
| action2oldid  = 303843403

| currentstatus = GA
| topic         = engtech
}}
{{TrainsWikiProject|class=GA|importance=low|UK=yes|UK-importance=Mid|portalSAweek=31, 2009}}
{{BS template|North Staffordshire Railway RDT}}



== Comments ==
Goods traffic from Knutton to Silverdale did start in 1850, even though it was authorised nine years later than this.

Here is my explanation.

Ralph Sneyd owned many ironworks in the Silverdale area. In 1849 he began construction of his own private line which was about 2 miles long - this was not authorised by parliament.

So when the NSR came to build its line in this area it was leased to the NSR for the usual 999 years. However it was not authorised to carry passenger traffic which was done in 1859.

[[User:Aidan Croft|Aidan Croft]]

----
Thanks for your comments [[User:Aidan Croft|Aidan Croft]]. Here are some of my views on this.

When I read that construction from Congleton to Macclesfield was authorised on June 26th 1846, I find it rather odd that the same statement says it opened for goods and passenger traffic '''eight days earlier'''!
Likewise I find it srange that goods traffic from Knutton to Silverdale started in 1850, '''nine years before''' the line was authorised and long before traffic on the section Newcastle to Knutton. I put it to you that if the list is correct then there is a most unusual story to tell and you ought to tell that story rather than just publish an odd list.

On the matter of Cauldon Low, I note that Google manages 1,250 entries for '''Cauldon Lowe''' and a massive 22,300 entries for '''Cauldon Low '''.  I can see there is a variant spelling with some antiquity in its support but there is significantly more local usage of the normal spelling than of the variant.  Basil Jeuda's book '''&quot;The Quarries of Cauldon Low&quot;''' appears to be offered for sale under both names. 

Well of course they were only a few paragraphs whereas I had the temerity to change one word that you had previously changed without asking!  

Concerning Rights and Powers, there is a Wikipedia glossary of railway terminology at http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rail_terminology which makes it clear that 'running powers' is the usual British term as opposed to the American which is actually 'trackage rights'.

Sincerely,  [[User:NoelWalley|NoelWalley]] 16:39, 30 October 2005 (UTC)

&lt;hr /&gt;
Thanks for your comments [[User:NoelWalley|NoelWalley]]. Here are some of my views on this.

I apoligise for deleting those few paragraphs. My reason for doing so '''was''' that I thought it may have been better for it to be in list form (as shown at the bottom of the article) but when I think about it a bit more, I realise that it is useful to have a summary in a few paragraphs as opposed to pure information in a list.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
On Cauldon Lowe, it was changed because that is how it is spelt by people who live in Cauldon Lowe and the area local to that (Staffordshire moorlands), and I propose to change at least this back after receiving some comments on this from you.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;Rights powers&quot;: either will do!!


Conclusion:
* Cauldon Lowe must be changed back pending receipt of comments
* I send my apoligies for mistakes made

[[User:Aidan Croft|Aidan Croft]]


P.S the dates in the list that you pointed out to me are correct - thanks anyway!

&lt;hr /&gt;

In his haste to reorganise a few paragraphs, '''User: 84.64.58.113''' has, inadvertantly I hope, deleted several other paragraphs as follows:


Later branches included lines from Stoke-on-Trent to [[Congleton]] via [[Biddulph]]; Stoke-on-Trent to [[Leek]]; Newcastle to [[Silverdale]], [[Keele]] and [[Market Drayton]] (junction with the [[Great Western Railway]]); [[Alsager]] to [[Audley]], Lycett and Keele, and [[Rocester]] to [[Ashbourne]]. 

The famous Loop Line from [[Etruria,_Staffordshire|Etruria]] via [[Hanley]], Cobridge, [[Burslem]], [[Tunstall]], Pitts Hill, Newchapel &amp; Goldenhill to [[Kidsgrove]] Liverpool Rd. and a junction with the Manchester line was the last of the N.S.R.’s major undertakings.    

Twentieth century construction included a branch from Leek to Caldon Low via Waterhouses from where the nominally independent narrow gauge [[Leek and Manifold Light Railway]] was constructed through the Hamps and Manifold river valleys to Hulme End near [[Hartington]]. Finally in 1910, a very short line was built from Stoke-on-Trent to Trentham Park. The latter was authorised as part of an alternative line to Newcastle-under-Lyme but construction work beyond Trentham was quickly abandoned owing to rising costs.

The Company prospered throughout its seventy-five years of independent ownership and operation, paid its shareholders good dividends (latterly a notable 5%), and successfully resisted repeated take-over bids by the London and North Western Railway Company. 

I propose to reinstate them shortly  [[User:NoelWalley|NoelWalley]] 19:35, 27 October 2005 (UTC)



'''User: 84.65.26.36''' has corrected Leycett for which I thank him. However, I find it difficult to accept his change of 'Cauldon Low' to 'Cauldon Lowe' and unless others tell me he is right, I propose to change it back.

In terms of common usage I see little difference between 'rights' and 'powers', however, 'powers' would appear to be the term most commonly used in Britain and 'rights' in North America (although their law may be different for all I know). I would never deliberately change someone's 'running rights' into 'running powers' and I expect the same consideration from others. Again I propose to reverse this change unless someone advises against it.

I used the full title London, Midland and Scottish Railway in the important statement re amalgamation. LMS needs an explanation which was not provided, and in the context seems trivial. Again I propose to reverse this unless advised.  

I would ask if there is a policy concerning internal linkage. Surely if [[Uttoxeter]] is linked once in the article, that is sufficient.

If user: 84.65.26.36 reads this he will know that I sign my contributions [[User:NoelWalley|NoelWalley]] 20:09, 28 October 2005 (UTC)

==Caldon Low/Cauldon Lowe==
This is known to be controversial, even among locals, of whom I used to be one. Different publications and organisations use different variations e.g. the Ordnance Survey use Caldon Low for the quarries but ''Cauldon Lowe'' for the hill behind the quarries. Cauldon Low is used by several businesses in the area.  Christiansen and Miller use Caldon Low and as most of the references are to the quarry not the hill or the village of Cauldon, I've used Caldon Low.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Nthep|Nthep]] ([[User talk:Nthep|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Nthep|contribs]]) 14:47, 28 April 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Friargate==
I've amended the link to read Derby Friargate (which is due to be written) to distinguish it from the main Midland/LMS station. [[User:213.78.117.229|213.78.117.229]] 17:45, 30 October 2005 (UTC)

==G==

This was [[WP:GA/N|nominated]] for Good Article status, but fails to meet the [[WP:WIAGA|criteria]] on a number of points.  First of all there are no [[WP:CITE|references]].  Second, the History section starts with bullet points rather than prose and so is not well written.  Also large number of one/two sentence paragraphs are not good writing.  Finally, please consider whether the list of lines is really necessary.  If you think it is I'd at least suggest putting it in a nicely formatted table.  [[User:Worldtraveller|Worldtraveller]] 16:42, 28 April 2006 (UTC)

{{Talk:North Staffordshire Railway/GA1}}

== Diagram is wrong ==

The rail diagram used to show the NSR routes should distinguish between open and closed routes. For instance Trentham Gardens has that has been closed since the 1960s, but according to this rail diagram it remains open along with the line that serves it. Wikipedia MoS states that routes that are now closed are marked as such. Besides as a rail enthusiast I want to see what was lost and what remains open. This map, which shows everything is open, does not make it clear and does not help the understanding of the subject.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/86.171.23.213|86.171.23.213]] ([[User talk:86.171.23.213|talk]]) 22:06, 16 August 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;</text>
      <sha1>k4q0sg5dm5hozeqw4980ehmdjx4slsl</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
