<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Valkyrie</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2647964</id>
    <revision>
      <id>701766505</id>
      <parentid>537873971</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-01-26T13:16:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Svehen</username>
        <id>27417027</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Recent television characters */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24837">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=15:54, 9 February 2009
|action1link=Talk:Valkyrie/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=269551920

|action2=FAC
|action2date=21:20, 23 June 2009
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Valkyrie/archive1
|action2result=not promoted
|action2oldid=298139956

|topic=Religion, mysticism and mythology
|currentstatus=GA
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Norse history and culture|class=GA|importance=top}}
{{WikiProject Mythology|class=GA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Death|class=GA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=GA|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Women's History|class=GA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Guild of Copy Editors|user=SMasters|date=May 1, 2010}}
}}

==Vote for move==
Although I see this as a waste of time BUT, [[Valkyrie (disambiguation)|Valkyrie]] can mean a number of things. Just like [[Enterprise]]. --&lt;small&gt; [[User:White Cat/05|Cat]]&lt;/small&gt; &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:White Cat/05|chi?]]&lt;/sup&gt; 17:45, 9 September 2005 (UTC)
*'''Move'''--&lt;small&gt; [[User:White Cat/05|Cat]]&lt;/small&gt; &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:White Cat/05|chi?]]&lt;/sup&gt; 17:46, 9 September 2005 (UTC)
*'''OPPOSE'''. This article should treat the basic meaning of Valkyrie, with a link to a disambiguation page where derived uses are listed.--[[User:Wiglaf|Wiglaf]] 17:49, 9 September 2005 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''' per Wiglaf's reasoning. The Norse term is the primary use from which all the others are derived, so it should be here, with the Starcraft unit and the experimental bomber and such disambiguated appropriately. &amp;#8212;[[User:Mirv|Charles&amp;nbsp;P.]][[User talk:Mirv|&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;(Mirv)&lt;/small&gt;]] 19:08, 9 September 2005 (UTC)
:*I realise that but the Aircraft for instance have little to do with the norse term, nor does the motorcycle or any of the fictional characters in names. It is as related as the Aircraft Carrier Enterpise to Enterprise-D of Star Trek. Hence the need of disambig --&lt;small&gt; [[User:White Cat/05|Cat]]&lt;/small&gt; &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:White Cat/05|chi?]]&lt;/sup&gt; 04:23, 10 September 2005 (UTC)
::*Hence [[Valkyrie (disambiguation)]]. There's an [[Wikipedia:Disambiguation|extensive style guide for this]]. &amp;#8212;[[User:Mirv|Charles&amp;nbsp;P.]][[User talk:Mirv|&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;(Mirv)&lt;/small&gt;]] 14:22, 10 September 2005 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''' per Wiglaf and Mirv. --[[User:Salleman|Salleman]] 21:43, 9 September 2005 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''' per above and note that someone should '''move [[Talk:Valkyrie (Norse mythology)]] back here''' and '''delete [[Valkyrie (Wagner)]]''' which was copied out of the main article. &amp;mdash;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Davenbelle|Davenbelle]] 04:13, September 10, 2005 (UTC)
***I will move the talkpage when this vote is over.--[[User:Wiglaf|Wiglaf]] 08:07, 10 September 2005 (UTC)
** see also move request at [[Talk:Valkyrie (disambiguation)]] &amp;&amp; [[WP:POINT]].  &amp;mdash;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Davenbelle|Davenbelle]] 04:23, September 10, 2005 (UTC)
***[[m:Don't be a dick]] --&lt;small&gt; [[User:White Cat/05|Cat]]&lt;/small&gt; &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:White Cat/05|chi?]]&lt;/sup&gt; 04:24, 10 September 2005 (UTC)
**** see also: [[Wikipedia:Requests for arbitration/Coolcat, Davenbelle and Stereotek/Proposed decision]] &amp;&amp; [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3AValkyrie&amp;diff=22955015&amp;oldid=22954879 this too]. &amp;mdash;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Davenbelle|Davenbelle]] 04:31, September 10, 2005 (UTC)
*****[[m:Don't be a dick]] and dont distupt wikipedia to make a point. --&lt;small&gt; [[User:White Cat/05|Cat]]&lt;/small&gt; &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:White Cat/05|chi?]]&lt;/sup&gt; 04:24, 10 September 2005 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''' per Wiglaf and Mirv. &amp;mdash;[[User:Wahoofive|Wahoofive]] ([[User talk:Wahoofive|talk]]) 20:19, 10 September 2005 (UTC)
*'''Oppose'''. As per Wiglaf. – [[User:AxSkov|AxSkov]] (&lt;big&gt;[[User talk:AxSkov|☏]]&lt;/big&gt;)&lt;small&gt; 06:55, 11 September 2005 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;

:No need to go on IMHO. I shall run from this vote before Valkyrie's come chasing me. ^^ --&lt;small&gt; [[User:White Cat/05|Cat]]&lt;/small&gt; &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:White Cat/05|chi?]]&lt;/sup&gt; 06:17, 11 September 2005 (UTC)

''It was [[wikipedia:requested moves|requested]] that this article be renamed but there was no consensus for it be moved.'' [[User:Dragons flight|Dragons flight]] 00:18, 22 September 2005 (UTC)

==[[WP:POINT]]==
User:Cool Cat, having had your unilateral move undone by [[User:Wiglaf|Wiglaf]], you requested this move again stating at the top of this page that you ''&quot;see this as a waste of time&quot;'' &amp;mdash; and I can only assume you mean the move request, and that you expect the move to not have consensus &amp;mdash; yet you made the move request anyway. This is exactly what [[Wikipedia:Don't disrupt Wikipedia to illustrate a point]] is about. &amp;mdash;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Davenbelle|Davenbelle]] 04:45, September 10, 2005 (UTC)
:You have any idea what the hell you are talking about? You request a move and then get a concensus. Thats why you list it on requested moves. I can suggest a freaking move. There is no bad faith here. Why don't you go pester some other civilisation? Stop following me around AS PER ARBCOM RULING YOU POSTED. Shoo! --&lt;small&gt; [[User:White Cat/05|Cat]]&lt;/small&gt; &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:White Cat/05|chi?]]&lt;/sup&gt; 04:49, 10 September 2005 (UTC)
:: Yes, I do believe that I know what the hell I am talking about. &amp;mdash;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Davenbelle|Davenbelle]] 07:39, September 10, 2005 (UTC)
::: You are plainly an irritating troll to make people discuss views you don't hold. Oppose me on every suggestion, move, and edit I make, go ahead. --&lt;small&gt; [[User:White Cat/05|Cat]]&lt;/small&gt; &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:White Cat/05|chi?]]&lt;/sup&gt; 07:45, 10 September 2005 (UTC)
:::: User:Cool Cat, ''I'' am not a troll, I ''do'' believe what I've said here, and your continued personal attacks are not helping your case any. &amp;mdash;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Davenbelle|Davenbelle]] 07:50, September 10, 2005 (UTC)
::::: So it is a mere coincidence that you are opposing me on a vote for the 5th time out of the 6 votes I was part of in the past 30 days? --&lt;small&gt; [[User:White Cat/05|Cat]]&lt;/small&gt; &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:White Cat/05|chi?]]&lt;/sup&gt; 07:55, 10 September 2005 (UTC)
:::::: I suggest that you make better proposals. &amp;mdash;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Davenbelle|Davenbelle]] 08:00, September 10, 2005 (UTC)
::::::: This will look great on arbcom case. --&lt;small&gt; [[User:White Cat/05|Cat]]&lt;/small&gt; &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:White Cat/05|chi?]]&lt;/sup&gt; 08:06, 10 September 2005 (UTC)

==Valkyries (and norns) as Dísir==
I think that it is wrong to state something which is never explicitly confirmed by the sources – but only an interpretation – as a fact in the lead sentence of the article; namely that the valkyries are dísir. The valkyrjur–dísir–nornir connection should be elaborated on in a section below the statement of facts. --[[User:Salleman|Salleman]] 22:56, 26 September 2005 (UTC)

:Even [[Freya]] was a Dís, and according to the definition that the Dísir were &quot;minor female deities&quot;, there is nothing wrong in it. Nor do I think that it is very controversial either. If you disagree, which is normal on Wikipedia, just change it.--[[User:Wiglaf|Wiglaf]] 05:51, 27 September 2005 (UTC)

::I am, like Salleman, slightly uncomfortable with the wording of the lead. The valkyries, however, are sometimes referred to as ''dísir'' in the ancient sources so it is defensible. Here's an example from [[Krákumál]] (kudos to Wiglaf for writing an article on it).

::Fýsum-k hins at hætta.
::Heim bjóða mér dísir,
::þær's frá Herjans höllu
::hefr Óðinn mér sendar.

::The translation is left as an exercise for the reader. - [[User:Haukurth|Haukurth]] 20:28, 27 September 2005 (UTC)

:::Thanks Haukurth! The term ''dísir'' appears to have been used both for goddesses (Freya was Vanadís), Norns (according to [[Nordisk familjebok]]) and for Valkyries. IMHO, it is sensible to stay with this use of the name ''dís'', since it is all we know about them.--[[User:Wiglaf|Wiglaf]] 20:54, 27 September 2005 (UTC)

==The purpose of Valkyrie in Battle==
This article says:

{{Cquote|  The valkyries' purpose was to choose the most heroic of those who had died in battle and to carry them off to Valhalla where they became einherjar. }}

I believe this is not true. To my best knowledge, the purpose of the Valkyrjur was to choose the fighters who would die in each battle (in old-norse: &quot;kjósa val&quot;, which means to choose casualties), not to choose among the ones who died (all menn who died in battle became einherjar). They shared this role with Odin (sometimes named &quot;Valfaðir&quot;, father of casualties) and Týr, the one-armed wargod. I will change this when I have the original source handy. [[User:BjörnÓmarsson|BjörnÓmarsson]] 09:33, 15 December 2006 (UTC)

== Ibn Fahdlan accounts. Valkyries real people. ==

They were priestesses concerned with human sacrifice in ancient Germanic culture as well, not just mythic minor deities; as has been fairly attested to by the likes of Ibn Fahdlan. &quot;Angels of death&quot; or really as they are translated &quot;Choosers of the slain&quot;, is pretty much the same rendering in meaning. This shouldn't go without mention in the article. [http://www.baldrthebarbarian.com/Ibn.html] [[User:Nagelfar|Nagelfar]] 03:42, 28 December 2006 (UTC)
:Whatever the case may be, surely there's a better site out there hosting the study - that site is just painful. [[User:Bloodofox|:bloodofox:]] 09:47, 28 December 2006 (UTC)
::Also, I remember reading that there was a prohibition against witches and 'valkyries' in a Catholic church restriction. I remember reading of it and the author making the point that if valkyries were a caste of people whose profession was forbidden, then they must have been actual people, possibly another name for a [[Völva]] that was in current use. [[User:207.202.227.125|207.202.227.125]] 01:38, 24 January 2007 (UTC)

== Girls' Soccer Teams ==

I was browsing and came across this page and noticed that there were links to two girls' soccer teams, which seemed inappropriate. I would have said they should be linked or referenced on the disambiguation page. I shall come back to check to see if anyone makes a strong case for keeping them or whether someone who has contributed to this page has moved them or wants to keep them. Otherwise I shall move them at that point. --[[User:Muchado|Muchado]] 15:43, 5 May 2007 (UTC)

== B-71 Valkyrie ==
I can't find any mention on this aircraft anywhere on Wikipedia. Does anyone know anything about this?

:That was a real (experimental) aircraft and it's got a pretty good article here on Wikipedia (if you should happen to still be looking). You have the wrong designation, though, I think; try XB-70? [[User:Archer884|J.M. Archer]] ([[User talk:Archer884|talk]]) 19:45, 10 November 2009 (UTC)

==Freyja==
I move a section where Freyja is said to be a Valkyrie, here:
:&lt;small&gt;In ''[[Gylfaginning]]'' of the [[Prose Edda]] and the poem ''[[Grimnismál]]'' of the [[Poetic Edda]], it is said that [[Freyja]] receives half of the slain heroes in her hall [[Fólkvangr]], however there are no descriptions about life at [[Fólkvangr]]. In ''[[Skáldskaparmál]]'', Freyja is called &quot;Possessor of the Slain&quot; (Eidandi Valfalls), and in [[Njal's Saga]], another title of Freyja is mentioned: ''Valfreyja'' &quot;Mistress of the Chosen&quot; (cf. Valfadir, Valkyrja). Freyja is also called [[Vanadís]], which suggests that she is related to the [[dísir]].&lt;/small&gt;
The main problem here is that none of these facts point to Freyja being a Valkyrie. Dís simply meant &quot;lady&quot; and it appears to have comprised all female supernatural powers, including Freyja and the Valkyries. The fact that Freyja received the slain does not make her a Valkyrie more than it makes Odin a Valkyrie.--[[User:Berig|Berig]] 07:59, 14 October 2007 (UTC)
::Moved it back and gave it a section. Agreed that Freyja is a major goddess and is certainly not a mere minor Vakyrie, but Grimm pointed out in his &quot;German Mythology&quot; that Freyja is maybe Mistress of the Valkyr. Since the Valkyries divided the slain to both Odin and Freyja, it's worth mentioning Freyja and her links to Valkyries in the article. It clearly does not deserve a deletion. [[User:Cryinggirls(T T)|Cryinggirls(T T)]] 07:37, 17 October 2007 (UTC)
I beileived that she married into the valkeries.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/97.123.125.237|97.123.125.237]] ([[User talk:97.123.125.237|talk]]) 02:16, 17 October 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Absurd. Valkyries are female. They are not really classified by the sources we have (which are extremely late in origin) but it's clear they are subordinate to Freyja. Not sure why I responded to this. [[User:Obotlig|Obotlig]] ([[User talk:Obotlig|talk]]) 03:22, 17 October 2011 (UTC)

== Pronunciation ==

How is the word pronounced, both in the original language and in English? [[Special:Contributions/91.107.128.252|91.107.128.252]] ([[User talk:91.107.128.252|talk]]) 22:18, 22 September 2008 (UTC)

I'd like to know this as well.  The proper English pronunciation though , not American. --[[Special:Contributions/59.100.51.1|59.100.51.1]] ([[User talk:59.100.51.1|talk]]) 03:39, 19 December 2008 (UTC)

:I assume it would be written in IPA, which would mean that the pronunciation would be fine in either dialect.  [[Special:Contributions/98.202.165.201|98.202.165.201]] ([[User talk:98.202.165.201|talk]]) 05:01, 1 August 2009 (UTC)

==Picture removal==
Why were these pics [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Valkyrie&amp;diff=258493974&amp;oldid=257762045 removed]?
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Arrival at Valhalla.jpg
File:Valkyrie.jpg
File:U 1163, Drävle (Sigrdrífa).JPG
&lt;/gallery&gt;
I think it is far superior to represent Valkyries with what scholars consider to be contemporary illustrations rather than romanticized pictures from the 19th and the 20th centuries, and I'd appreciate an explanation for their removal.--[[User:Berig|Berig]] ([[User talk:Berig|talk]]) 15:57, 17 December 2008 (UTC)

:Bloodofox is rewriting the article, I bet he plans to put those images back in when he gets to the archaeological attestations. On the other hand maybe one of them should be the lede image. I certainly wouldn't object if you put the Tjängvide stone back in the lede. [[User:Haukurth|Haukur]] ([[User talk:Haukurth|talk]]) 18:18, 17 December 2008 (UTC)

::Haukur is correct. I am rewriting the article from scratch and will be bringing it to GA status (and FA is quite possible from there). I intend to bring in an &quot;archaeological record&quot; section to cover all of the finds. It's nowhere near where it needs to be at the moment, but that will change. [[User:Bloodofox|:bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 20:27, 17 December 2008 (UTC)

::As an update, I am currently away from most of my books at the moment, but will get back to them in a few days or so. I still intend to create said section, and I think we ought to include the images above in a gallery (as they are shown above) located below the section. [[User:Bloodofox|:bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 14:54, 31 December 2008 (UTC)

::I've started the section. I'm on the look out for a references that points out that this is Sigrdrífa. As I noted in a recent edit summary, I hope to be able to get some shots of some more of these silver valkyrie figures in Copenhagen soon (if anyone else is able to, please feel free, as I'll be using a camera unfamiliar to me to do so, unfortunately). [[User:Bloodofox|:bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 14:01, 5 January 2009 (UTC)
:::Have you tried [[Rundata]] as a reference for the Sigrdrífa picture?--[[User:Berig|Berig]] ([[User talk:Berig|talk]]) 14:33, 5 January 2009 (UTC)
::::Good idea. Rundata has &quot;Bild av Sigurd Fafnesbane som sticker sitt svärd genom ormen, dessutom dvärgen Andvare och valkyrian Sigdriva som räcker Sigurd ett dryckeshorn&quot; with the reference $=Larsson 2002:71f (According to Rundata: 2002: Yrrunan. Användning och ljudvärde i nordiska runinskrifter. (Runrön 17), Uppsala.), so we even have a specific mention of Sigrdrífa handing Sigurd a drinking horn. I'll add it. [[User:Bloodofox|:bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 14:56, 5 January 2009 (UTC)

==More valkyrie object images==
After typing this, I realized I had some images on my hard drive from previous visits that we could use. However, as it stands the only reference I have to these objects as being valkyries with me is from the displays at the [[National Museum of Denmark]]. Here are the images.
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Silver figure with hair and silver figure with horse.jpg|Valkyries, according to the National Museum of Denmark.
File:Valkyrie on horse and giving valkyrie.jpg|Another figure on horse, and one of the various &quot;giving&quot; valkyries silver figures.
&lt;/gallery&gt;
Know of any references outside of this that we could use? [[User:Bloodofox|:bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 16:32, 5 January 2009 (UTC)
:I'm afraid that I'm not familiar with the items. The best way might be to ask people at the museum by e-mail.--[[User:Berig|Berig]] ([[User talk:Berig|talk]]) 16:55, 5 January 2009 (UTC)
::Well, if nothing else, I suppose we can cite the museum display captions themselves (which I also photographed), though a printed source would certainly be superior. [[User:Bloodofox|:bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 21:18, 5 January 2009 (UTC)

== Logical quotation ==

I've checked a bit around, and per MoS [[WP:LQ]], we are to use logical quotation, not American quotation, which means that punctuation should be ''outside'' of a quotation if it is not in the quotation in the source. I do not have access to all the sources used here, so I will not perform any change yet, even though I did do so earlier when I put all the punctuation marks ''inside'' the quotation marks, thinking we'd be consistent in use of American grammar and spelling. I do not know if the article followed logical quotation before I went around changing it all, but if it did, I will try to restore it how it was. –[[User:Holt|Holt]]  &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Holt|'''T''']]•[[Special:Contributions/Holt|C]])&lt;/small&gt; 16:26, 1 March 2009 (UTC)

== Only the most heroic warriors ==

Going around all the different Norse afterlife-related pages, it seems that only this one really states that the Valkyries pick the most heroic, as opposed to some kind of arbitrary half and half selection of the dead. Do the unheroic warriors then belong to Freyja? What of warriors [[Death_in_Norse_paganism#Hel|deliberately wounding themselves]] to trick the goddess Hel? Do unheroic warriors somehow also go to Hel as an alternative to both [[Valhalla]] and [[Fólkvangr]]? Can these discrepancies be attributed to the incomplete survival of texts and the destruction suffered from Christian suppression?

I can only imagine how neo-pagans must feel when trying to actually revive portions of this faith. [[User:D Boland|D Boland]] ([[User talk:D Boland|talk]]) 19:03, 18 May 2009 (UTC)
:These details are not found in the surviving source material, and it's worth noting that the feminine aspects of Germanic paganism are poorly represented in the sources. Most of the material that has survived involves kingship and royalty in some way or another, with a heavy emphasis on Odin. Yet, in the sources that do survive, it's revealing that those that die end up in supernatural female possession no matter what; valkyries to Valhalla, Freyja receives half of all those slain in battle in Fólkvangr (a very revealing surviving element of the apparent role of women in Germanic society prior to Christianization), Rán if at sea, and Hel under more vague circumstances. It's also quite unfortunate that more work by female skalds (!) didn't survive. [[User:Bloodofox|:bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 05:15, 10 June 2009 (UTC)

==Indiginous British Residents==
The article states that there is confusion as to whether the Valkyrie was from a Norse background or &quot;Indiginous Anglo-Saxon Pagans&quot; however it must be remembered that the Angles and the Saxons were also of a Germanic and Scandinavian origin. The indiginous occupants of Britain were the Celts (also pagans) so even if there were Anglo-Saxon references to the Valkyrie, they could easily have still come across from Scandinavia with the previous invasions of the few hundred years after the Romans left.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/62.255.136.194|62.255.136.194]] ([[User talk:62.255.136.194|talk]]) 10:32, 2 July 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Yes, you are correct, but I should point out that by the time England was formed by the Anglo-Saxon settlers, the Britons had Christianized. Anyway, the point of the section is that it's unclear whether or not later waves of Norse paganism introduced the concept of the valkyrie among the Anglo-Saxons or that it was a pan-Germanic concept. Certainly, the idisi/dísir were pan-Germanic, and they are clearly closely related to the valkyries—if not at some point one and the same—but we don't know anymore about valkyries in specific among non-Scandinavian Germanic peoples. [[User:Bloodofox|:bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 11:56, 2 July 2010 (UTC)

==name valkerie==
I once read somewhere that the word might have stemmed from val(hall) and the greek ker (spirit). thus hall spirit as in valhala and related to greek keres as an inspirational source to thier mythos.  i can't recall the source and it might just be conjecture. [[Special:Contributions/98.216.6.31|98.216.6.31]] ([[User talk:98.216.6.31|talk]]) 00:57, 14 February 2011 (UTC)
:No the words have straightforward meanings. &quot;hall&quot; and cognates mean hall. &quot;kyrie&quot; means something what it sounds like in English, chooser. It stems from Germanic origins and not via Greek. Val means dead or slain, typically in battle. It and its cognates were a common word. Valkyrie has a straightforward meaning of chooser of the battle-slain. The sound would make sense in Old English as well. wæl-cyrge. cyre means choice from ceosan to choose. Common words in the Germanic languages. [[User:Obotlig|Obotlig]] ([[User talk:Obotlig|talk]]) 02:50, 17 October 2011 (UTC)

==Word order in second sentence==
Shouldn't the sentence have half before among.  As it is now it reads: &quot;Selecting among half of those who die in battle (the other half go to the goddess Freyja's afterlife field Fólkvangr)&quot; meaning a portion of half are chosen by the valkerie rather than an entire half.  Instead: &quot;Selecting half among of those who die in battle (the other half go to the goddess Freyja's afterlife field Fólkvangr)  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/66.30.177.171|66.30.177.171]] ([[User talk:66.30.177.171|talk]]) 22:46, 22 October 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Valkyrie in NTNU ==
Warnning to Valkyrie in NTNU sir,
Do not talk bad-words and whisper with others!  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/114.38.238.199|114.38.238.199]] ([[User talk:114.38.238.199|talk]]) 13:31, 10 November 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Recent television characters ==

I've separated some material on recent television characters by putting them under a new subheading, but should they be here at all? I doubt if the characters are intended to be authentic, but on the other hand they do represent some continuing interest. --[[User:Northernhenge|Northernhenge]] ([[User talk:Northernhenge|talk]]) 22:28, 11 February 2013 (UTC)
:This sort of thing tends to accrue on these articles, and whether or not the information is notable or even if the media directly references the topic at hand is frequently an issue. Norse mythology in modern popular culture is a very interesting topic, but we can't just have a pile of uncited information piling up at the end of this article. If it's not sourced, it should be deleted on sight; see [[WP:PROVEIT]]. [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 23:15, 11 February 2013 (UTC)
::Fair enough. I couldn't really see a way of making the existing dubious material fit anywhere sensibly, so deletion was always a possible outcome. --[[User:Northernhenge|Northernhenge]] ([[User talk:Northernhenge|talk]]) 14:04, 12 February 2013 (UTC)

==Official==
The official Valkyre are 3 sisters, they have the same blonde hair color, they are only 3 of them.--[[User:Svehen|Svehen]] ([[User talk:Svehen|talk]]) 13:16, 26 January 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>8jgl60lqg47octfmy9x5x8k9zxbxxkf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
