<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:The Last Dog on Earth</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>13261161</id>
    <revision>
      <id>565022167</id>
      <parentid>548579561</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-07-20T06:57:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BattyBot</username>
        <id>15996738</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[WP:AWB/GF#Talk page general fixes|Talk page general fixes]] &amp; other cleanup using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (9359)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="4190">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Novels|class=GA|importance=Low|attention=|needs-infobox=|incomp-infobox=|needs-infobox-cover=|listas=Last Dog on Earth, The}}
{{WikiProject Dogs|class=GA|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Guild of Copy Editors|user=Pol430|date=21 December 2010}}
}}{{ArticleHistory
|action1=PR
|action1date=03:10, 7 December 2010
|action1link=Wikipedia:Peer review/The Last Dog on Earth/archive1
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=400984165

|action2=GAN
|action2date=05:03, 19 February 2011
|action2link=Talk:The Last Dog on Earth/GA1
|action2result=listed
|action2oldid=414735125

|currentstatus=GA
|topic=literature
}}
 

{{Talk:The Last Dog on Earth/GA1}}

== Reviews ==

* &quot;Not as funny, but equally gripping is Daniel Ehrenhaft's &quot;The Last Dog on Earth&quot; (234 pages, Delacorte Press, $15.95). All around Logan's town, dogs are getting sick and attacking whoever is nearby. But Logan is too busy to notice. His stepfather has given him a dog and, in spite of his all-consuming anger, Logan meets the challenge, training Jack and growing to love the dog's untamable nature. When Logan gets in trouble can Jack save him even as he struggles to save Jack from dog-hunting vigilantes? A memorable story of self-discovery for ages 9 to 12.&quot; St. Louis Post-Dispatch (Missouri), May 28, 2003. Archived at [[LexisNexis]]
*&quot;This fast-paced thriller set in Oregon blends elements of science fiction and a Gary Paulsen - like survival story with a coming-of-age tale about a rebellious teenager and his dog. Logan, at 14, has not seen his father since he was seven. His stepfather, Robert (&quot;the All-Knowing Dictator of Everything&quot;), wants to send him to Blue Mountain Camp for Boys, a kind of boot camp run by an ex-marine, but opts for a dog instead, to teach Logan &quot;the value of discipline and responsibility.&quot; Choosing Jack, a feral stray, rather than the purebred Robert prefers, gives Logan the upper hand - but not for long. The author makes clear that Logan is not a bad kid; his small acts of rebellion simply tend to escalate. For instance, when Logan takes Jack into a local deli, the deli owner's dog menaces the two and things reel out of control. So it's off to Blue Mountain for the teen. Meanwhile, a mysterious virus begins spreading from dogs to humans, its progress tracked in a series of increasingly ominous e-mail messages, newspaper clippings, faxes, etc., interspersed throughout the narrative. The story's third plot line involves a reclusive scientist, the only one who can create an antidote to the deadly disease - but he requires an immune dog. Ehrenhaft (the Techies series) keeps things moving at a rapid clip, with tension and violence mounting incrementally as the story lines converge. If the bittersweet ending stretches credibility, this is still a smartly written, thoroughly engrossing tale. Ages 9-12. (Feb.)&quot; Publishers Weekly Reviews, January 27, 2003. Archived at [[LexisNexis]]
*&quot;Warning: the dog dies. Actually, most of the dogs on the West Coast die here, victims either of a prion plague (think Mad Cow Disease) that turns them suddenly vicious in its last stages, or of systematic extermination. Worse yet, bitten humans turn out to be susceptible, too. Ehrenhaft, author of entries in the Bone Chillers series, places Logan, an Oregon teenager with family problems, and Jack, a wild dog he's tamed who turns out to be immune to the plague, and therefore the key to a cure, against a backdrop of rising governmental and public panic. The two escape the plague, but not the panic: losing themselves in the woods despite the best efforts of Logan's bad-news stepfather to keep them separately captive, the two fugitives are finally forced to place themselves in the care of Logan's estranged father (a brilliant epidemiologist, forsooth) after Jack is brutally beaten by vigilante exterminators. Though happenstance plays a large role in the plot, and the author has a tendency to trot in typecast characters, then summarily drop them, disaster-tale fans with a taste for the lurid will not be let down by this melodramatic, if predictable, chiller. (Fiction. 11-13)&quot; Kirkus Reviews, December 1, 2002. Archived at [[LexisNexis]]</text>
      <sha1>qnq5uxu84m7bhj4uddh1u8hvrz3kv00</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
