<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Mac Pro</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>5759048</id>
    <revision>
      <id>695058757</id>
      <parentid>669833707</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-12-13T13:59:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ritchie333</username>
        <id>664832</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* NPOV issue: Reception of second-gen Mac Pro */ cmt</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="19707">{{Talk header|noarchive=yes}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=FAC
|action1date=00:11, 12 May 2007
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Mac Pro/archive1
|action1result=not promoted
|action1oldid=129612491

|action2=PR
|action2date=08:21, 31 May 2007
|action2link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Mac Pro/archive1
|action2result=reviewed
|action2oldid=134662417

|action3=GAN
|action3date=01:57, 6 February 2010
|action3link=Talk:Mac Pro/GA1
|action3result=listed
|action3oldid=342212229

|action4=GAR
|action4date=11:06, 2 March 2014
|action4link=Wikipedia:Good article reassessment/Mac Pro/1
|action4result=kept
|action4oldid=596951912

|currentstatus=GA
|topic=engtech
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Apple Inc.|class=GA|importance=high|mac=yes|mac-importance=top}}
{{WikiProject Computing
|class=GA
|importance=mid
|needs-image=no
|hardware=yes
|hardware-importance=High
}}
{{WikiProject Brands|class=GA|importance=low}}
}}
{{archive box|search=yes|
*[[/Archive 1|'''1''' – 2006 → 2009]]
*[[/Archive 2|'''2''' – 2010 → present]]
}}

{{/GA1}}

== Speed? ==

Could someone please add a speed comparison between the machines? Like [[SPECINT]] or something. 

Not sure if we should mention an expected update in June 2010...

THANKS -- [[User:MichaelJanich|Michael Janich]] ([[User talk:MichaelJanich|talk]]) 04:09, 31 May 2010 (UTC)
:Which machines? No, Wikipedia isn't a place for rumors. [[User:Airplaneman|&lt;span style=&quot;color:blue;size=2&quot;&gt;Airplaneman&lt;/span&gt;]][[User talk:Airplaneman|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#33dd44;size=2&quot;&gt;  ✈&lt;/span&gt;]] 04:28, 8 June 2010 (UTC)
::All machines mentioned in the article: all mac pro generations. -- [[User:MichaelJanich|Michael Janich]] ([[User talk:MichaelJanich|talk]]) 02:49, 24 June 2010 (UTC)
:::An interesting idea definitely worth considering. In what format should it be presented (prose, table, etc.)? [[User:Airplaneman|&lt;span style=&quot;color:blue;size=2&quot;&gt;Airplaneman&lt;/span&gt;]][[User talk:Airplaneman|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#33dd44;size=2&quot;&gt;  ✈&lt;/span&gt;]] 05:27, 15 August 2010 (UTC)
::::Isn't table the most obvious? column 1: model name; column 2: specint (or whatever measure). -- THANKS -- [[User:MichaelJanich|Michael Janich]] ([[User talk:MichaelJanich|talk]]) 03:42, 17 September 2010 (UTC)

== Broken Images ==

Hi, I am new to this. There are a few pictures in this page with broken images. I do not feel comfortable enough with copyright to replace them but I am just alerting anyone who wishes to fix this. 
[[User:Yackilote|Yackilote]] ([[User talk:Yackilote|talk]]) 10:17, 24 June 2013 (UTC)

== Congrats! ==

Congrats! I'd just like to tell you that you have way more information in this article as does Apple Support by now. I've just called the official Apple Support line in my Western European country (where the person answering had trouble speaking my language) to ask them about what specific RAM type I need for my first-generation 2006 Mac Pro, and they insistently told me there was no Mac Pro in existence prior to the second-generation Mac Pro 2008 (they even called it &quot;second-generation&quot;), and first tried to tell me that what I have must be the MacBook Pro laptop, and when I told them this is really, really a desktop machine with a huge tower, they insisted that I must have a PowerMac!

Add to that the fact that they were incapable of finding my 2006 e-mail registration with this Mac Pro or any other account to my name. They then told me to remove my &quot;laptop battery&quot; to give them the machine's serial on it, and when I repeated that this is no laptop, they told me to check some &quot;This Mac&quot; window in MacOS, which I couldn't because I'm running Windows on this machine. And when I told them that I'm running Windows on it, they flat-out refused to continue that support call any longer because they said it would be &quot;impossible&quot;. --[[Special:Contributions/93.232.164.99|93.232.164.99]] ([[User talk:93.232.164.99|talk]]) 17:15, 9 July 2013 (UTC)

== 2006 first-gen Mavericks support ==

Obviously, the unofficially highest MacOS that can run on the 2006 first-generation Mac Pro has now been determined to be Mavericks beta, on the very same forum that originally cooked up the hack for Mountain Lion: [http://forum.netkas.org/index.php/topic,1123.780.html]. --[[Special:Contributions/37.80.190.4|37.80.190.4]] ([[User talk:37.80.190.4|talk]]) 04:15, 10 July 2013 (UTC)

:And a link from that thread also claims it's possible to run Win7 64-bit on the 2006 first-gen Mac Pro: http://www.insanelymac.com/forum/topic/126089-howto-boot-macs-with-intel-chipset-in-ahci-win7-vista-xp-linux/page-11 --[[Special:Contributions/37.80.190.4|37.80.190.4]] Something like a workthrough given here:[http://forum.netkas.org/index.php/topic,1123.675.html] ([[User talk:37.80.190.4|talk]]) 04:32, 10 July 2013 (UTC)

You can now download a Boot.efi file that allow the 2006 Mac pro to run 10.9 without the need a a boot loader, such as chameleon.  See http://forums.macrumors.com/showthread.php?t=1598176&amp;page=2  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.210.61.85|24.210.61.85]] ([[User talk:24.210.61.85|talk]]) 04:29, 11 January 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Remove Mac Pro pic ==

The picture used to illustrate the Mac Pro is NOT the current Mac Pro. The picture is of a Mac Pro yet to be released. It should be changed back. [[Special:Contributions/2601:D:480:109:2480:C8DD:E1E:5C9E|2601:D:480:109:2480:C8DD:E1E:5C9E]] ([[User talk:2601:D:480:109:2480:C8DD:E1E:5C9E|talk]]) 17:11, 23 July 2013 (UTC)
:I've updated the caption on the picture, is that sufficient? [[User:DavidAmis|DavidAmis]] ([[User talk:DavidAmis|talk]]) 01:35, 13 September 2013 (UTC)

The new Mac Pro has technically been sold at this point (the RED auction), and the 2012 Mac Pro is no longer available for sale through Apple.  I think we can safely change the picture back to the new Mac Pro now.

== Design Inspiration Section added to GEN 2== 

An unsourced document shows original design concept referring to SR-71 jet engine, extreme cost and &quot;a challenge worth of Apple&quot;  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/211.30.254.6|211.30.254.6]] ([[User talk:211.30.254.6|talk]]) 16:57, 12 November 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Is this 'design inspiration' speculation appropriate for wikipedia? It appears to be one person's imaginative guess at what inspired the design.

It's not a guess ... its the first concept document summary. Maybe it can be cleaned up. I take your point but you could undertake scrutiny of the design process as much as the final product itself. It may surprise you to know that the initial concept was rejected by another computer maker prior to Apple accepting it. Apple was aware of this. &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/211.30.254.6|211.30.254.6]] ([[User talk:211.30.254.6|talk]]) 13:22, 13 November 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Wikipedia upholds its tradition of expanding the human advertisement. A place where nothing outside of the marketing brochure is offered.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/211.30.254.6|211.30.254.6]] ([[User talk:211.30.254.6|talk]]) 00:32, 15 November 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== 64-bit kernel? ==

The table says &quot;Kernel Default Mode: 32-bit in Mac OS X (client), 64-bit in Mac OS X Server&quot; for some models, but isn't this for a specific (and outdated) version of OS X?  It appears by all accounts that my old Mac Pro is running K64 here, even without OS X Server (which is now mostly just some management software, anyway).  Did they switch to K64 for all EFI64 models at some point?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;auto signed&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/67.185.161.246|67.185.161.246]] ([[User talk:67.185.161.246|talk]]) 00:49, 15 November 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Depends on the model. My MP1,1 is 32-bit. [[User:Maury Markowitz|Maury Markowitz]] ([[User talk:Maury Markowitz|talk]]) 16:30, 17 January 2014 (UTC)

== Split G5-styled minitower out ==

Given that the two have very little in common, the article is presently humongous, and that a great deal of information on the older design's intricacies was accrued over the article's lifespan, I think it would be best if pretty much everything related to the pre-2013 systems was split into its own article. [[Special:Contributions/66.133.250.190|66.133.250.190]] ([[User talk:66.133.250.190|talk]]) 05:51, 24 December 2013 (UTC)

*'''Disagree''' - I don't feel like article is exceedingly long. Both machines are sold under the Mac Pro brand and share the same processor family.--[[User:Shivertimbers433|Shivertimbers433]] ([[User talk:Shivertimbers433|talk]]) 04:10, 27 December 2013 (UTC)

*'''Disagree''' - Concur with Shivertimbers433.  The article is not that long.  &amp;nbsp;[[User:Tabanger|&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid #000;font-family:Courier;padding:1px 3px 1px 3px;color:#000;&quot;&gt;Tabanger&lt;/span&gt;]]&amp;nbsp; 08:14, 4 January 2014 (UTC)

*'''Disagree, but...''' - Although I think it's best to keep the article consolidated, I do think the page needs some reorganization. [[User:Not|Not]] ([[User talk:Not|talk]]) 19:08, 29 December 2013 (UTC)
* I think the article should be split, because the new one (2013) is different enough as physical computer build. There are precedents for this. See [[Power Macintosh G3]] vs. [[Power Macintosh G3 (Blue &amp; White)]]. It facilitates clean infoboxes etc. For example this page gives the impression that you can install &quot;OS X 10.4.7 and later&quot; on the 2013 Mac Pro. I bet you can't install 10.4.7 on it. The page is messed up badly enough to be a quickfail for a [[WP:GAR]]. [[User:Someone not using his real name|Someone not using his real name]] ([[User talk:Someone not using his real name|talk]]) 22:44, 12 January 2014 (UTC)

*'''Disagree''' - The article is certainly in need of some work but I do not believe a split as proposed would be helpful in improving it. [[Special:Contributions/50.53.15.59|50.53.15.59]] ([[User talk:50.53.15.59|talk]]) 10:39, 13 January 2014 (UTC)

*'''Oppose:''' The reasons above pretty much cover it. [[User:Maury Markowitz|Maury Markowitz]] ([[User talk:Maury Markowitz|talk]]) 15:52, 13 January 2014 (UTC)

*'''Oppose:''' Agree with the comments above. --[[User:Tooki|tooki]] ([[User talk:Tooki|talk]]) 14:58, 21 January 2014 (UTC)

Should we close this, or re-list for further comments? [[User:Maury Markowitz|Maury Markowitz]] ([[User talk:Maury Markowitz|talk]]) 16:29, 17 January 2014 (UTC)

'''Closing…''' [[User:Maury Markowitz|Maury Markowitz]] ([[User talk:Maury Markowitz|talk]]) 13:02, 24 January 2014 (UTC)

== Production/manufacturing ==
So where is it being produced in the end? In the US? [[User:Nestea Zen|Nestea Zen]] ([[User talk:Nestea Zen|talk]]) 22:35, 18 February 2014 (UTC)

== PCIe SSD ==

Just wondered what type of [[PCIe]] this uses/is? It's not mentioned on the page at all, when I'd have thought it vital to understanding the throughput it can handle in comparison to the rest of the marketplace out there. [[User:Jimthing|Jimthing]] ([[User talk:Jimthing|talk]]) 23:38, 18 March 2014 (UTC)

== New Infobox picture? ==

The dual picture in the infobox is misleading, and it is not to scale.  The new Mac Pro is a tiny fraction of what is shown, if it were shown to scale.  Today I unpacked my own unit, and I took snapshots (no pretense of great photography), but take a look...  https://www.dropbox.com/sh/s2a37jnqt0l28og/AAB0YZ1CLGX6cRp7_PraHJcta?lst --[[User:Mareklug|Mareklug]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Mareklug|&lt;b&gt;talk&lt;/b&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 05:34, 14 June 2014 (UTC)
:If people have objections to the carpet in the picture -- don't understand why, that is an irrational and prejudicial objection -- just ask the Graphic Lab on Commons to skillfully remove the background.  The infobox picture of the actual Mac Pro late 2013 edition on a [[Turkmen rug]] is the only one on Commons, and it is a high-quality, high-resolution image that shows the ports of the machine, and is generally ency, depicting it in daylight, in  an installed setting.  The old infobox picture was misleading, because it juxtaposes two machines not to scale, and is a hand-drawn cartoon, with no information whatsoever, unless you claim a cartoon silhouette without scale information or features drawn in to be a picture worthy of encyclopedia.  Please try to take a rational view, and do not edit-war on this for silly objection reasons that only expose your cultural prejudices (against Turkmen carpets, or whatever). --[[User:Mareklug|Mareklug]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Mareklug|&lt;b&gt;talk&lt;/b&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 18:35, 24 June 2014 (UTC)

=== A message for the reverters of the actual picture of the machine (on the carpet) ===

I am leaving this message on talk pages of the reverters.  Also, see Finnish revert by some Finnish editor who openly asks, why did you revert this?  My point exactly.

''If you don't like the background, surely you can remove it yourself in a derived work, or ask the Graphic Lab on commons to do so. But why do you negate the obviously encyclopedic valors of my image? It is the only one we have a full year into the machine's existence, and one that is sharp, high-resolution, and shows what it looks like with ports in view, and which shows what the machine looks like in a home environment, how it is highly reflective. Clearly if a better backgrounded picture surfaces, let's use it. But in the interim, this is the best picture for the encyclopedic use. Sincerely,''

--[[User:Mareklug|Mareklug]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Mareklug|&lt;b&gt;talk&lt;/b&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 18:46, 24 June 2014 (UTC)
:I think it doesnt need an explanation. The pic. is not good enough to change--[[User:Ayrıntılı Bilgi|Ayrıntılı Bilgi]] ([[User talk:Ayrıntılı Bilgi|talk]]) 19:08, 24 June 2014 (UTC)
::What do you mean, not good enough?  Have you looked at it in full magnification?  It shows the ports very clearly and using the electric power plug, you get scale information. If you don't like the carpet, fix it. --[[User:Mareklug|Mareklug]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Mareklug|&lt;b&gt;talk&lt;/b&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 19:13, 24 June 2014 (UTC)
:The pic. distorted--[[User:Ayrıntılı Bilgi|Ayrıntılı Bilgi]] ([[User talk:Ayrıntılı Bilgi|talk]]) 19:19, 24 June 2014 (UTC)
::What is distorted about it?  It is truthfully depicted from the angle of above and to the side.  That is not distortion, only perspective.  Even if you think that is a fault, it is still the most useful picture we have, as it shows what the machine looks like in real life, AND it gives good close up view of its ports, and using the standard power cable plug used, it gives useful scale information. When a better picture arrives, feel free to use it, but don't put back inferior information depictions like cartoons and not-to-scale comparison shots. --[[User:Mareklug|Mareklug]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Mareklug|&lt;b&gt;talk&lt;/b&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 19:26, 24 June 2014 (UTC)
:{{anchor|marekbattleground}}This is [[WP:BATTLEGROUND]], not a discussion. We have a major and totally unnecessary edit to 29 international wikis in violation of consensus, after having negative reviews on IRC. We have a [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=User_talk:Smuckola&amp;diff=614179543&amp;oldid=613523736 preemptive personal attack and declaration of war] (in abuse of antiabuse policy itself) in response to a simple revert, followed by an actual [[WP:3RR]] global edit war. We have [[WP:OWNER]], [[WP:ICANTHEARYOU]] and I'm pretty sure [[WP:TEND]]. We have an editor who considers any (even perfectly obvious, factually cogent and policy backed) dissent whatsoever about one of the most aesthetically violent and generally unnecessary images possible on a computer article, to be tantamount to a prank, vandalism, and a culturally bigoted insult -- with imaginary personal accusations. Not to mention the fact that he deleted imagery of half the product line. He asserts that it's the incumbent upon the rest of the world to fix his obvious damage and violently prevents them (including obviously ESL editors struggling to keep up in English) from doing so. He got his faux-solicited response, and has blasted a disingenuously faux discussion. And of course this isn't the first time for contentious and aggrandizing behavior. These are egregiously reportable offenses by someone who notoriously knows better, to a well versed community. Other editors are encouraged not to stoop to his level with a [[WP:3RR]] but instead to report the abuse.   — [[User:Smuckola|Smuckola]] &lt;small&gt;[[Special:EmailUser/Smuckola|(Email)]] [[User talk:Smuckola|(Talk)]]&lt;/small&gt; 22:50, 24 June 2014 (UTC)

== question? ==

Why does Apple use a comma in the model identifiers (e.g. Macmini1,1)?
[[Special:Contributions/74.96.73.25|74.96.73.25]] ([[User talk:74.96.73.25|talk]]) 04:07, 24 October 2014 (UTC)

== Intel Kush? ==

&quot;Intel Kush&quot;?

The link in the article seems to go to an unrelated page, and Intel Kush doesn't appear to match anything relevant on Google.

Did Intel really use a variety of pot as a brand name?  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/70.170.121.162|70.170.121.162]] ([[User talk:70.170.121.162|talk]]) 03:28, 21 March 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== NPOV issue: Reception of second-gen Mac Pro ==

When I arrived, this section was littered with &quot;citation needed&quot; notations.  I've removed those, replaced them with a single citation-needed template at the end of the section, and added [[Template:NPOV-section]].  This section sounds like it's written by a fan of second-gen Mac Pros.  I've heard very mixed reviews about the new design, with a lot of valid and significant issues being brought up, none of which are noted in this section.  We're clearly missing at least one side of the story.  —[[User:Zenexer|Zenexer]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;#91;[[User_talk:Zenexer|talk]]&amp;#93; 21:27, 3 July 2015 (UTC)

:Here are some things I've heard, though I haven't verified any of them, except the case issue:
:* The unusual case size/shape makes expansion difficult (for example, with PCIe cards)
:* The PSU is insufficient for power-hungry GPUs
:* The cooling isn't actually all that great (seems particularly subjective)
:* The price doesn't match the hardware
:—[[User:Zenexer|Zenexer]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;#91;[[User_talk:Zenexer|talk]]&amp;#93; 21:33, 3 July 2015 (UTC)

*I took off the &quot;citation needed&quot; tag of the end of the reception for the new &quot;coke can&quot; style &lt;small&gt;(well, that's what I call it) Mac Pro&lt;/small&gt; as there are already two sources there. If you know what's missing a ref, let me know and I'll see what I can dig out. I've recently gone through several teardown videos of Mac Pros (mainly so I can turn a dead one into a working one, which thankfully on a pre-2012 Mac Pro is not ''too'' hard) so i should be able to dig out some sources to fix the other tagged areas. [[User:Ritchie333|&lt;b style=&quot;color:#7F007F&quot;&gt;Ritchie333&lt;/b&gt;]] [[User talk:Ritchie333|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:#7F007F&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/sup&gt;]] [[Special:Contributions/Ritchie333|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:#7F007F&quot;&gt;(cont)&lt;/sup&gt;]] 13:59, 13 December 2015 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>c2j0w2o96scz986zvvdjzo47p5dlj1m</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
