<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Southeast Asia Treaty Organization</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2192992</id>
    <revision>
      <id>665370252</id>
      <parentid>655299130</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-06-03T19:57:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Schwede66</username>
        <id>10689882</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>WPNZ importance reassessment based on page views</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14038">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=10:44, 4 May 2011
|action1link=Talk:Southeast Asia Treaty Organization/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=427279583
|currentstatus=GA
|topic=History
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Southeast Asia|class=GA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Australia|class=GA|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject France|class=GA|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject International relations|class=GA|importance=Mid}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=GA
&lt;!-- B-Class parameters --&gt;
|B-Class-1=no
|B-Class-2=yes
|B-Class-3=yes
|B-Class-4=yes
|B-Class-5=yes
|US-task-force=yes|French-task-force=yes|Korean-task-force=yes|British-task-force=yes|New-Zealand-task-force=yes|Australian-task-force=yes}}
{{WikiProject New Zealand|class=GA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Organizations|class=GA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Pakistan|class=GA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Tambayan Philippines|class=GA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Thailand|class=GA|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject United Kingdom|class=GA|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject United States|class=GA|importance=low}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2012-09-08|oldid1=511192795|date2=2014-09-08|oldid2=624631619}}

==MEMBERSHIP==

ATTENTION:

South Korea, South Vietnam, and Bangladesh were NEVER members of SEATO.

South Vietnam was excluded because of the Geneva Accords, although it along with Laos and Cambodia were designated &quot;areas of interest&quot;.

South Korea was not IN Southeast Asia nor was it a global power that had interest in that region (DESPITE being an intervening power in the Vietnam War.)  

Bangladesh became independent from Pakistan in 1971.  Although Pakistan was a member, and thus technically the territory of Bangladesh was part of SEATO when it was part of Pakistan (&quot;East Pakistan&quot;) Bangladesh *NEVER* joined SEATO.  


[[Special:Contributions/71.199.114.98|71.199.114.98]] ([[User talk:71.199.114.98|talk]]) 15:12, 15 November 2008 (UTC)

Yes South Vietnam was. Can't you see the South Vietnam's flag? The yellow flag with 3 red stripes.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Jasonbourn48|Jasonbourn48]] ([[User talk:Jasonbourn48|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Jasonbourn48|contribs]]) 00:13, 20 April 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Both of the photographs included with this article clearly show the presence of South Vietnam at the meetings!   South Vietnam, Cambodia, and Laos were prohibited from joining any military alliance by the Geneva Accords.  However, protection of those countries was the main reason for SEATO, it being formed right after the Geneva Accords gave North Vietnam to the communists.  Therefore the protection of the alliance was extended to those countries without their having to join the alliance. Thus the spirit but not the letter of the Geneva Accords was violated -- remember that the US did not sign those accords. SEATO was Dulles' &quot;work-around&quot; that enabled Geneva signatories to get involved in the defence of SE Asia, and as the article notes it failed in that mission.  SEATO got involved in non-military activities because a main thrust of US cold war policy was to support economic development in countries that might be susceptible to communist revolution.  The reason for the alliance ceased to exist after 1975 with the fall of Saigon, so it died for lack of interest.  This information can be found in The Pentagon Papers, but my Kindle won't give me useful citations! [[User:Peter9291|TayRuong]] ([[User talk:Peter9291|talk]]) 06:47, 29 January 2012 (UTC)

== Graphic is wrong ==

need to adjust / edit graphic to show all members it is misleading.

== graphic missing Republic of Korea ==

ROK/South Korea should be colored in. &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[Special:Contributions/206.125.57.218|206.125.57.218]] ([[User talk:206.125.57.218|talk]]) 19:30, 11 December 2006 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;

*Done. Also added more info to differentiate between founding members and non founding members, and those that stayed put until '77 and those that didn't.[[User:Paj.meister|Paj.meister]] 12:33, 27 December 2006 (UTC)

*I found a source at http://www.spartacus.schoolnet.co.uk/USAseato.htm wiht some further information. I'll try and find a site with comprehensive information about membership later. [[User:Paj.meister|Paj.meister]] 09:43, 9 January 2007 (UTC)
==Infobox==
I've started an infobox, hopefully something similar to that on [[NATO]]. Any contribution with more (often evasive) info is 0of course welcome! [[User:Paj.meister|Paj.meister]] 09:43, 9 January 2007 (UTC)

{{Infobox Organization &lt;!-- START INFOBOX --&gt;
|name=South East Asia Treaty Organisation 
|image=NonFreeImageRemoved.svg&lt;!-- NonFreeImageRemoved.svg&lt;!-- Seato.gif --&gt; --&gt;
|caption=Flag of SEATO. 
|map=SEATO2.PNG
|mcaption=SEATO countries are in purple.
|headquarters=[[Bangkok]], [[Thailand]]
|membership=9
|language=
|general= 
|formation= 1954
|website= 
}}


I took the liberty of doing a major rewrite of this article.  One thing I altered was the membership list: neither South Vietnam nor South Korea were ever members.  

Also, I am not certain why the Falklands Islands (located in the South Atlantic) were listed as a member of SEATO.  The Falklands are a political dependency of the United Kingdom, and does not have its own foreign policy.  

I used the 1968 Encyclopedia Britannica and several volumes of the World Almanac (1959-1977 as my basic sources.  

Also, at this point, the map is incorrect (re South Vietnam and South Korea.  I am not certain how to change it. 

I also changed the reference to the author of the containment policy from John Foster Dulles to George F. Kennan.  Since the original article correctly noted that the containment policy was an outgrowth of the Truman Doctrine, this was done in the Truman Administration (which included Kennan in the State Department Policy Planning Division); Dulles served as Secretary of State in the Eisenhower Administration.  

I will continue to do research for any additional information that should be inserted in this article.

Sorry, I hit the &quot;send&quot; button too quickly.  The above was written by [[User:NelsonLB|NelsonLB]] 04:25, 23 January 2007 (UTC)
:The Falklands was someone's idea of a joke. However: South Korea I'm not sure about, but I would be almost certain that South Vietnam was a member, I mean the establishment of North Vietnam was the main reason why SEATO was formed. Are you sure we aren't just listing ''founding'' members in the article and ignoring those who joined later? Regards, [[User:Grant65|Grant65]] | [[User talk:Grant65|Talk]] 05:12, 23 January 2007 (UTC)

Ok, let me do some more checking on that![[User:74.134.12.144|74.134.12.144]] 05:24, 23 January 2007 (UTC)

* I've edited the image, so it only has the founding members.[[User:Paj.meister|Paj.meister]] 12:52, 11 February 2007 (UTC)

==WPMILHIST Assessment==
Though perhaps a bit short, it does technically fulfill all the requirements of a B-class article, so congrats. And good work on the map! I'm really not sure how to handle task forces on these types of things, as the subject is far from centrally important to the history/politics of many member countries (UK, US) - if we had a SE Asian task force... [[User:LordAmeth|LordAmeth]] 14:01, 5 February 2007 (UTC)
-----
While doing some earlier changes, I raised the issue of the membership of SEATO not including either South Korea or South Vietnam.  This assertion  was questioned by one of my learned colleagues.  Accordingly, as promised, I did some further research on this point over the last two weeks. 

The reference materials I consulted included the World Almanacs for 1958 (p. 774), 1960 (p. 826), 1965 (pp. 155 and 213), 1967 (p. 682), 1968 (p. 549), 1969 (pp. 316 and 573), 1972 (p. 593), and 1973(p. 631); the Reader's Digest Almanacs for 1967 (p. 904), 1968 (p.60), 1969 (p. 832), and 1971 (p. 312); the Information Please Almanacs for 1958 (p. 60), 1959 (p. 66), 1960 (p. 464 and map on pp 180-181), and 1970 (p. 559 and the map on 242-243); The 1961 American Peoples' Encyclopedia Yearbook for 1960 (p. 826); The Times [of London] Atlas of World History (published 1978) (p. 328); The American Annual for 1958 (pp. 713-714), and the Encyclopedia Britannica Book of the Year for 1966 (p. 693).  I also checked several websites, including the on-line Encyclopedia Britannica.   

(Let me explain that I collect old almanacs, so I had all of these in my basement.)

In every listing about SEATO in these materials the members of the organization listed were the original founding members: France, the United Kingdom, the United States, Pakistan, Thailand, the Philippine Islands, Australia, and New Zealand. In no listing was either South Korea or South Vietnam included as a member. In no listing was there any mention of any other country joining the original eight in the organization.   

Part of the confusion may be that South Korean troops did fight (pursuant to American diplomatic pressure and while being paid for and equipped by the American government)in Vietnam. However, they did so as an American ally, not because of any SEATO membership.  The Allied Forces (as they were called) in Vietnam did not fight under any kind of SEATO command.

South Vietnam was not a member of SEATO as a result of the 1954 Geneva Accords, which forbade it from joining any military alliances.  I do not have a good single citation on this, but I have seen this point referenced several times, and I will find a specific citation to it. 

I submit this to my colleagues as a documented substantiation of the membership list for SEATO, and accordingly will change the listing in the article.  I have a more technically gifted friend who is going to modify the map. Regards,[[User:NelsonLB|NelsonLB]] 04:11, 10 February 2007 (UTC)

Further research resulted in the determination that South Vietnam was prohibited from joining any military alliances (e.g., SEATO) by Article 19 of the Agreement to End Hostilities in Vietnam and Paragraph 5 of the Final Declaration, both of which emerged from the Geneva Conference of 1954. This is the reason that South Vietnam was not a member of SEATO, even though SEATO was created in response to the West's concern about the expansion of communism in southeast Asia.[[User:NelsonLB|NelsonLB]] 08:24, 18 February 2007 (UTC)

My understanding is that South Vietnam was NOT a member.  However, BOTH of the photographs that accompany this article clearly show the Republic of Vietnam's flag, and the caption of one of them lists Ky as a participant.  This is crying out for an explanation!! [[User:Peter9291|TayRuong]] ([[User talk:Peter9291|talk]]) 10:42, 28 January 2012 (UTC)

==Dulles==
Isn't [[John Foster Dulles]] the architect of SEATO? --[[User:Noypi380|Noypi380]] 08:26, 28 February 2007 (UTC)

Yes, I think it is fair to say that Secretary fo State John Foster Dulles (1953-1959)was the main architect of SEATO.  In the original article, Dulles was credited with being the architect of the &quot;containment policy.&quot; This was actually started in the Truman Administration, with the intellectual basis created in 1946, the date of Kennan's famous &quot;Long Telegram&quot; from Moscow.  Do you think the article should mention that Dulles was the lead architect of SEATO (and in a way the architect of the application of the containment policy to southeast Asia)? [[User:NelsonLB|NelsonLB]] 00:56, 19 March 2007 (UTC)
:Yes, Dulles should be mentioned for that. :-) --[[User:Noypi380|Noypi380]] 12:00, 21 March 2007 (UTC)
I haven't done this yet, because I am gathering some other material to add with it, but I will soon. [[User:NelsonLB|NelsonLB]] 05:43, 28 March 2007 (UTC)

== 'Collective Defence' vs 'Collective Security'==
I have today switched a number of references to &quot;collective security&quot; to read &quot;collective defence.&quot; The difference is often confused or overlooked by laymen and is mostly academic anyway, but we may as well be accurate. 
*&quot;collective defence&quot; refers to an agreement by which 2 or more States agree to defend each other against agression by other party(ies) ''external'' to the agreement. NATO, SEATO, CSTO are all collective defence organizations since their primary goal is to prevent and resist aggression from a state ''outside'' the organization. 
*&quot;collective security&quot; is a security arrangement in which the members of the system agree to monitor ''each other''; that is, all agree that all will resist aggression by any single member. Theoretically speaking such an arrangement would lead to the complete isolation of an aggressor. The League of Nations was the first Collective Security organization. 

[[User:Dmhaglund|Dmhaglund]] 12:18, 10 October 2007 (UTC)

== Suriname as member? ==
you must be joking, right?--[[Special:Contributions/88.217.59.90|88.217.59.90]] ([[User talk:88.217.59.90|talk]]) 23:07, 6 August 2009 (UTC)

{{Talk:Southeast Asia Treaty Organization/GA1}}

==File:SEATO2.PNG Nominated for Deletion==
{|
|-
| [[File:Image-x-generic.svg|100px]] 
| An image used in this article, [[commons:File:SEATO2.PNG|File:SEATO2.PNG]], has been nominated for deletion at [[Wikimedia Commons]] in the following category: ''Media without a source as of 5 September 2011'' 
;What should I do?
''Don't panic''; a discussion will now take place over on Commons about whether to remove the file. This gives you an opportunity to contest the deletion, although please review Commons guidelines before doing so.
* If the image is [[WP:NFCC|non-free]] then you may need to upload it to Wikipedia (Commons does not allow fair use)
* If the image isn't freely licensed and there is no [[WP:FUR|fair use rationale]] then it cannot be uploaded or used.

''This notification is provided by a Bot'' --[[User:CommonsNotificationBot|CommonsNotificationBot]] ([[User talk:CommonsNotificationBot|talk]]) 02:17, 5 September 2011 (UTC)
|}</text>
      <sha1>9oy494kj8jsldh2oqgcx6khp197nt38</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
