<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Mezhyhirya Monastery</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>14922651</id>
    <revision>
      <id>701121085</id>
      <parentid>551579895</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-01-22T16:38:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cyberbot II</username>
        <id>16283967</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8254">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=2008-01-11, 21:46:44 
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=183287028

|currentstatus=GA
|dykdate=January 1, 2008
|topic=architecture
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Ukraine|class=GA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Russia|class=GA|importance=High|hist=yes|relig=yes|art=yes|mil=yes|tech=yes}}
{{WikiProject Belarus|class=GA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Architecture|class=GA|importance=}}
}}

==Did you know==
Here are some ideas for a DYK nomination:
*...that at the time of its height, the '''[[Mezhyhirskyi Monastery]]''' in [[Ukraine]] was considered a spiritual center of the [[Zaporozhian Cossacks|Cossacks]]? 
*...that the '''[[Mezhyhirskyi Monastery]]''' in [[Ukraine]] is thought to have included the lost library of [[Yaroslav the Wise]]?
Any more? [[User:DDima|—dima]][[User talk:DDima|'''''/talk/''''']] 19:57, 28 December 2007 (UTC)

:An expansion of the above one, still under 200 characters (with spaces included):

:*...that the '''[[Mezhyhirskyi Monastery]]''' in [[Ukraine]], mentioned in [[Nikolai Gogol|Gogol’s]] novel [[Taras Bulba]], is thought to have included the lost library of [[Yaroslav the Wise]]?

--[[User:Riurik|Riurik]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Riurik|(discuss)]]&lt;/sup&gt; 03:37, 29 December 2007 (UTC)
:Pretty good. Let's nominate it. [[User:DDima|—dima]][[User talk:DDima|'''''/talk/''''']] 04:51, 29 December 2007 (UTC)
::Done [[Template_talk:Did_you_know#Articles_created.2Fexpanded_on_December_26|here]].--[[User:Riurik|Riurik]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Riurik|(discuss)]]&lt;/sup&gt; 04:58, 29 December 2007 (UTC)
:::Thanks. I added a little note stating that it was in my userspace until 28 Dec. Hopefully that will give the article more time for chance to get on DYK. [[User:DDima|—dima]][[User talk:DDima|'''''/talk/''''']] 05:02, 29 December 2007 (UTC)

== Good article review ==

In many ways an outstanding article.  I'd suggest taking it to Featured article status, with a little work.  (BTW, this is my first GAR so if you see anything that looks unusual about it, you are probably correct)

:'''Prose, ... clear language.'''
:I'll guess at least one of the author's speaks English as a second language, but it only shows in spots; e.g. &quot;In 1884, the faience factory was closed down after it failed to bring any profits (except to the factory's founder).&quot;  (Who else is supposed to get the profits?) and &quot;During this period, its location was disclosed from the public.&quot; (What was hidden from the public? or disclosed to the public?).  I think a quick once over from an experienced copyeditor would bring significant improvement.  In general, I think that the quality of the prose is lowered simply because you're trying to fit in too much detail.  A bit of simplification will go a long way.

::* I too think that I tried to include a lot of detail in the article (especially during my last edits to the article).. I will try to copyedit it more, but I probably won't be able to copyedit it as a native speaker of English.. [[User:DDima|—dima]][[User talk:DDima|'''''/talk/''''']] 04:24, 10 January 2008 (UTC)

:'''Formatting and organization''' is fine.  There are 3 red links - you might ask if they will ever be filled in, or is Metropolitan Micheal really notable enough for an English language Wikipedia article? (I don't know).  I was surprised that the 3rd red link [Sviato-Pokrovskyi Monastery] didn't have an article already - maybe under a different spelling?

::*I have cleared one of the red links.. I don't want to start a quick stub on the [[Sviato-Pokrovskyi Monastery]] because there's a lot I could write about it, but will get around to it sometime in the near future. [[User:DDima|—dima]][[User talk:DDima|'''''/talk/''''']] 04:24, 10 January 2008 (UTC)

:'''Referencing''' lots of appearently relevant well formatted references.  But this is the main substantive problem that I see - they are all in Ukrainian or Russian, which makes them pretty hard to evaluate or use for the average English speaker.  I know that you get references from reliable sources where ever you find them, and that foreign language references are not a formal negative for good article status.  Nevertheless if you could find a couple in English (aren't there English language newspapers in Kiev and Moscow?) or even in French, Spanish, or German, it would help a lot of readers (and 1 reviewer).  The OKO site is relied on fairly heavily - it's hard for me to evaluate whether it's reliable, but since there are so many other references .... Under external links, the Noviy Dim link seems to be purely commercial - is my reading correct that they are building cotteges on the site?  If so, something should be mentioned in the article.  The link to Wikicommons is not in the usual format AND there is nothing in Wikicommons on the topic.

::* I understand your concern about the references being in Russian/Ukrainian, but truly, there ''is nothing'' about the monastery in the internet (even less chance of finding anything in books). I Googled different variations of the monastery's name (Mezhyhirya, Mezhgorye, Mezhigorye, and even in German/Polish) and found either something unrelated or a short mention of the name and nothing about the monastery...
::* The Noviy Dim link is commercial, but you're right - they are building cottages on the site of the monastery... I think that it's beneficial to include it... If not, then I'll just remove it. [[User:DDima|—dima]][[User talk:DDima|'''''/talk/''''']] 04:24, 10 January 2008 (UTC)

:::*This is also something that can be adjusted as English language sources become available.  I think in the meantime there are editors available that will be able to verify a reference should one raise questions, etc.  Good job on the GAR, detailed and constructive.--[[User:Riurik|Riurik]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Riurik|(discuss)]]&lt;/sup&gt; 20:41, 10 January 2008 (UTC)

:'''Broadness''' - fine, maybe a bit too detailed.  NPOV. 

:'''Images''' beautiful - all appearently out of copyright.

In short, an informative, beautiful, and fairly well written and referenced article that should go further.  I hope my minor criticisms help it do so.  [[User:Smallbones|Smallbones]] ([[User talk:Smallbones|talk]]) 23:54, 9 January 2008 (UTC)

:I'll go ahead and and pass this as a Good Article.  Please do look for some non-Cyrillic  sources.  It's a bit of a paradox - can something be this notable (and I believe it is), and be recorded in such detail, but there are no mentions of it anywhere in reliable sources in English?
:Keep up the good work
:[[User:Smallbones|Smallbones]] ([[User talk:Smallbones|talk]]) 21:36, 11 January 2008 (UTC)
::Thanks for your great help on reviewing it! It is like a paradox, and the monastery is/was very notable (like second in importance for the Cossacks) but it was destroyed like 80 years prior, and very little/no material was printed about it during the Soviet time.. Since Ukrainian independence in '91, English sources are a lot more common on these forgotten subjects.. but not everything happens at once. Thanks again, [[User:DDima|—dima]][[User talk:DDima|'''''/talk/''''']] 22:06, 11 January 2008 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Mezhyhirya Monastery]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=701121081 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20010226215533/http://poetyka.uazone.net:80/kobzar/chernec.html to http://www.poetyka.uazone.net/kobzar/chernec.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 16:38, 22 January 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>hrlc9gopwnqw4ap1uon60nofk88qcsf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
