<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Elizabeth of Bosnia</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>7054712</id>
    <revision>
      <id>677784427</id>
      <parentid>634620079</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-08-25T14:04:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sadads</username>
        <id>563447</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Assessment: -Women writers ([[User:Kephir/gadgets/rater|assisted]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23999">{{talkheader}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Biography |living=n |class=GA |listas=Elizabeth Of Bosnia |military-work-group=y |military-priority=Low |royalty-work-group=y |royalty-priority=Low}}
{{WikiProject Middle Ages |class=GA |importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Hungary |class=GA |importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Poland |class=GA |importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Bosnia and Herzegovina |class=GA |importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Croatia |class=GA |importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Women's History |class=GA |importance=}}
{{WikiProject Military history |class=GA |Balkan=y |Medieval=y |Biography=y}}
}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=08:08, 18 July 2010 (UTC)
|action1link=Talk:Elizabeth of Bosnia/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=372689387

|action2=PR
|action2date=18:06, 25 June 2012
|action2link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Elizabeth of Bosnia/archive1
|action2result=reviewed
|action2oldid=499316706

|action3=FAC
|action3date=12:09, 3 September 2012
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Elizabeth of Bosnia/archive1
|action3result=not promoted
|action3oldid=509061253

| topic         = Royalty, nobility and heraldry

|action4=FAC
|action4date=10:02, 09 February 2014
|action4link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Elizabeth of Bosnia/archive2
|action4result=not promoted
|action4oldid=594113635
|currentstatus=GA
}}
{{Talk:Elizabeth of Bosnia/GA1}}

== Map ==
Adding a map was a wonderful idea, Kebeta! I considered it myself, but couldn't find a suitable one. However, I think we can find a better map than [[:File:Lands under Louis the Great in the middle of the 14th century.jpg|this one]] - or perhaps someone can create it? I am not sure how one can &quot;order&quot; a map, but I remember ordering an image of a coat of arms from a user who was more than willing to help. The problem with the present map is that is hard to read (for starters, it is not in English). [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 12:38, 15 July 2012 (UTC)
:Thanks. Moving map is ok although Elizabeth's daughters lost some of Louis lands presented in that map. That's way I think map's previous position is better. --[[User:Kebeta|Kebeta]] ([[User talk:Kebeta|talk]]) 13:39, 15 July 2012 (UTC)
::Yes, they did lose some territory, but the caption says that those were the lands they inherited from their father, so it's not really misleading. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 14:02, 15 July 2012 (UTC)

== Recent edits ==
I don't think we should name every [[valet]] that accompanied Elizabeth and Mary. It adds nothing to the article, as the reader won't have a clue who &quot;Paul son of John&quot; was. Imagine naming all Elizabeth's ladies-in-waiting. It's simply trivial. The article should contain relevant information - information about Elizabeth's life. Why would a reader interested in Elizabeth's life want to know where Charles sailed from? That information would be of interest to someone reading about Charles. Let's not wander off topic, please. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 13:29, 15 July 2012 (UTC)
:I don't agree with you on this point. Most of Elizabeths reign was a civil war in Hungary and Croatia. I think it's important to present names of leading nobles, army strenght and other circumstances that could explain to a reader what happened during her reign (which fraction oposed her and which supported her).--[[User:Kebeta|Kebeta]] ([[User talk:Kebeta|talk]]) 13:45, 15 July 2012 (UTC)
::All you said is true. I'd like to emphasise your own words: &quot;names of leading nobles&quot;. &quot;Paul son of John&quot;, a Gregory, an Andrew and others were not leading nobles. The leading nobles were the Garays and the Horvats, all of whom are properly introduced. You are venturing into unneccessary detail and introducing information that is relevant to other articles and not this one. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 13:57, 15 July 2012 (UTC)

Please don't link to irrelevant articles. See [[WP:Context]], which says that links should be created to &quot;relevant connections to the subject of another article that will help readers understand the article more fully&quot;. Linking to the article about Croats creates an impression that all Croats were opposed to Elizabeth, that they were opposed to her ''because'' they were Croats or that their opposition to her had something else to do with their being Croats. Please discuss before reverting again. Please don't revert again without discussion. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 13:57, 15 July 2012 (UTC)
:Please allow me to finish writting so you can get the whole picture. Afterwards if necessary you (we) can remove if something is redundant. Please be patient, and let me write by adding more material into the article.--[[User:Kebeta|Kebeta]] ([[User talk:Kebeta|talk]]) 14:08, 15 July 2012 (UTC)
::Please discuss the contentious material you already added before proceeding to add more of it. I have explained why we shouldn't name every single man in her entourage, yet you keep reinstating the names without addressing my concerns. I have also explained it to you that this article is not the place for the information you're adding. That information should be in the article about [[Charles II of Hungary]]. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 14:14, 15 July 2012 (UTC)
:::I don't link to irrelevant articles. The fact is that Croatian nobles (most of them- all important ones at that time) were at war with Elizabeth and Mary due to many reasons which are not written in this article. Mary's insecure reign is not the only or a main reason for this. So linking Croatian is not irrelevant (or it want be after I present reasons of rebelion). She is a women-lets attack her because she is week...things don't go that way. You don't attack your queen because she is a women. --[[User:Kebeta|Kebeta]] ([[User talk:Kebeta|talk]]) 14:25, 15 July 2012 (UTC)
::::The fact that they were Croatian has nothing to do with their rebellion. They rebelled because they wanted to profit from the turmoil. They did not rebel because they were Croats. That is why the link should not be there. In fact, I replaced the wording with a better one. I am not sure why you insist on using an inferior wording. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 14:34, 15 July 2012 (UTC)

Please cool down...don't jump on every single sentence which I write. Please, [[User:Kebeta|Kebeta]] ([[User talk:Kebeta|talk]]) 14:28, 15 July 2012 (UTC)
:I don't. The map and information about Paul's pawning of church estates were great additions, but you don't seem to understand that this article is '' about Elizabeth'', not ''about Charles'' and ''not about the history of Hungary-Croatia''. This article should contain information about this woman's life. Imagine explaining the entire situation in Hungary ''and'' in Poland. Important events were taking place there as well, such as the formation of centuries-long union between Poland and Lithuania, but this article does not go into detail about that because it is ''about Elizabeth''. You also don't understand that discussing contentious edits is better than blindly reverting them. If a user raises concerns about your edits, discuss rather than revert. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 14:34, 15 July 2012 (UTC)
::I agree with you, but you just don't give me space to finish my edits...how to discuss unfinished text (of course that kindn of text wan't be as good as it should be). But you are doing the same thing for which you acuse me - blindly reverting. Opposite to you, I am trying to expand the article while you simply delete my material - immediately as I write it. --[[User:Kebeta|Kebeta]] ([[User talk:Kebeta|talk]]) 14:42, 15 July 2012 (UTC)
:::We can discuss what you've already inserted. Why not start from there? It's the most sensible thing to do. I have explained it to you that the material you added while expanding the article is out of this article's scope. It is unneccessary detail that reduces the quality of the article. I am sure that your goal is to improve the article, but inserting excessive detail and irrelevant information is not the way to do that. Quality is more important than quantity. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 14:52, 15 July 2012 (UTC)

== A proposal ==
I will stay away from this aricle for the next several days. I hope that during that time you will try to read something which I have wrote above on this talk page, instead of just repeating your self. My intention is (and will be in the future) to expand this article, since this wasn't my first edit on this article as you are awere of. I am doing this so you can cool down since obviously you seem upset. I hope that you will understand that writing some material about Elizabeth something requires explanation, which (I agree) can be a part of some other article as well. I hope that when everybody cools down, we can edit this article normally and discuss in a more friendly way. Regards, [[User:Kebeta|Kebeta]] ([[User talk:Kebeta|talk]]) 15:11, 15 July 2012 (UTC)
:Kebeta, you haven't responded to any of my concerns. I have read and responded to everything you wrote; anyone can see that. You, however, have been merely ignoring my concerns. I applaud your intention to ''improve'' the article, but ''expanding'' it is not neccessarily the same as ''improving'' it. Adding material that does not directly concern ''Elizabeth'' and which is not indispensable for understanding ''Elizabeth's life'' hurts the article. A person reading about Elizabeth would not care about the number of ships Charles had and would not care about Charles' gathering support in an obscure Italian town. Imagine listing every promise made by Jogaila in the [[Act of Kreva]] or describing everything that happened to Hedwig in Poland; such details belong to the articles about Jogaila and Hedwig respectively, just like the information you keep adding belongs to the article about Charles. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 15:25, 15 July 2012 (UTC)
:You reverted a spelling correction several times even though I [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Elizabeth_of_Bosnia&amp;diff=502424784&amp;oldid=502424646 asked you not to]. It proves, if nothing else, that you were blindly reverting my edits and not paying any attention to my edit summaries. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 17:45, 15 July 2012 (UTC)
::I think that I gave you a fair proposal. Why accuse me further if I gave you what you want (I stopped editing the article)? Does this means that you are not interested in my proposal, at all? --[[User:Kebeta|Kebeta]] ([[User talk:Kebeta|talk]]) 18:41, 15 July 2012 (UTC)

::Very well, I will than make now new sections with your concerns. --[[User:Kebeta|Kebeta]] ([[User talk:Kebeta|talk]]) 20:09, 15 July 2012 (UTC)
:::I'm looking forward to the discussion, but please cease reverting. If you don't, I will have no other option but to report you for breaking the [[WP:3RR|three revert rule]], which you have broken several times today while I was begging you to discuss. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 20:49, 15 July 2012 (UTC)
::::I was open for discussion the best I could. I evan wanted to stop writing for several days, but you continued to acuse me and mock to my proposal. I would like to invite some other editors here to help us to resolve this situation, since it's becoming clear that we can't do it alone. You are breaking the [[WP:3RR|three revert rule]], I don't revert you, just adding more material (which apparently you don't like). --[[User:Kebeta|Kebeta]] ([[User talk:Kebeta|talk]]) 21:01, 15 July 2012 (UTC)
:::::How did I mock your proposal? It's quite clear what a revert is, and it what you are doing is disruptive reverting. Why is it so hard to discuss a proposed change if it's obviously contentious? I am going to request a [[WP:3O|third opinion from a neutral user]]. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 21:18, 15 July 2012 (UTC)

== Issues ==
*Lead 
[[Wikipedia:Manual of Style/Lead section]] says that ''&quot;The lead serves as an introduction to the article and a summary of its most important aspects.&quot;'' and ''&quot;The lead should be able to stand alone as a concise overview. It should define the topic, establish context, explain why the topic is notable, and summarize the most important points—including any prominent controversies&quot;'' That is way I expanded the lead. 

I added new info into lead ''(shortly after her death, a big parts of Bosnia and Dalmatia were separated from Hungarian Crown.)'' which breaks (''&quot;Significant information should not appear in the lead if it is not covered in the remainder of the article.&quot;''), but I am planning to add that content into the body of the article (into section 'Death and aftermath'.--[[User:Kebeta|Kebeta]] ([[User talk:Kebeta|talk]]) 20:22, 15 July 2012 (UTC)

''&quot;The lead should normally contain no more than four paragraphs, be carefully sourced as appropriate, and be written in a clear, accessible style with a neutral point of view to invite a reading of the full article.&quot;'' The article had only two paragraphs (which were POV since they didn't reflect on the 'lost lands') before I expanded it. Now it has three.--[[User:Kebeta|Kebeta]] ([[User talk:Kebeta|talk]]) 21:14, 15 July 2012 (UTC)

:Do you honestly think that the information you keep reinserting into the lead makes it a &quot;summary of its most important aspects&quot; and &quot;a concise overview&quot;? I don't. You inserted unneccessary details and simply copy-pasted text from other sections. Anyway, you should really pay more attention to your grammar. I am not a native speaker either, and I know it can be hard, but this article (at Good Article status) should not feature things like &quot;a big parts&quot; and &quot;successfull&quot;. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 20:59, 15 July 2012 (UTC)
::I am sorry about my grammar, but it's hard to focus when I have you on my neck. Yes, I think that the lead is to short and that my addition about 'lost lands' is very important.--[[User:Kebeta|Kebeta]] ([[User talk:Kebeta|talk]]) 21:04, 15 July 2012 (UTC)
:::You cannot blame me for your grammar. You had problems with it before our dispute ([http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Elizabeth_of_Bosnia&amp;diff=502411864&amp;oldid=502411512]). Anyway, what you added to the lead is not even correct. It cannot be said that Elizabeth lost Poland. She did not lose it in any sense. The lead is exactly what you cited: an introduction to the article, a summary of its most important aspects and a concise overview. Please, bear in mind that this article is about a woman, not about the history of Hungary. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 21:25, 15 July 2012 (UTC)
*WL for 'Croatian'
*Expanding vs improving
*Images
There are many images (paintings) in the article-that's why I think that something real thing (like Novigrad Castle) is a good image for this article. I didn't want to delete the image which you added, so I put it with other painting as double image. --[[User:Kebeta|Kebeta]] ([[User talk:Kebeta|talk]]) 21:07, 15 July 2012 (UTC)

Listed four issues for now.--[[User:Kebeta|Kebeta]] ([[User talk:Kebeta|talk]]) 20:13, 15 July 2012 (UTC)

==Ethnicity==
I have a question for anybody who can answer it: what ethnicity was Elizabeta? was she Croatian, Serbian, Hungarian, Bosniak (before Islamization), Polish, etc.? --[[User:DemirBajraktarevic|DemirBajraktarevic]] ([[User talk:DemirBajraktarevic|talk]]) 16:16, 30 December 2012 (UTC)

:It depends on who you ask. The question can only generate pointless disputes. I strongly doubt she'd care, for what it's worth. [[Nationalism]] hardly existed before the 18th century. As you can see, this woman and her contemporaries had bigger problems on their mind. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 16:40, 30 December 2012 (UTC)

I didn't mean for that to sound bad... I was just wondering what she was ... Her name was Elizbeth of Bosnia and she was the Queen of Hungary and daughter of the Ban and Baness of Bosnia, she was also the mother of the Queen of Poland -- kinda confusing especially because I'm not exactly sure how that all works --[[User:DemirBajraktarevic|DemirBajraktarevic]] ([[User talk:DemirBajraktarevic|talk]]) 16:50, 30 December 2012 (UTC)
:It doesn't work. There is no need for it to work. The only certainty is that she was Bosnian, obviously. She was born in Bosnia to a Polish woman and a Bosnian man whose mother was Serbian, and married off as a child to a Hungarian whose father was a French-speaking prince from Naples. God knows what her native language was. What was [[Queen Victoria#Ancestry|Queen Victoria]]'s ethnicity? [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 17:12, 30 December 2012 (UTC)

You're right. jeez louise -- these royals make me dizzy --[[User:DemirBajraktarevic|DemirBajraktarevic]] ([[User talk:DemirBajraktarevic|talk]]) 17:19, 30 December 2012 (UTC)

wait a go getting that in there that ethnicity and race are totally invented and modern concepts. This isn't about nationalism. Ethnicity was formalized later, but cultural identity certainly existed, which is the basis of ethnicity as we define it today. So she had an ethnicity.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/128.12.187.216|128.12.187.216]] ([[User talk:128.12.187.216|talk]]) 16:03, 9 May 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==New category==
Would the category &quot;Bosnian royalty&quot; apply to Elizabeth? --[[Special:Contributions/63.152.96.146|63.152.96.146]] ([[User talk:63.152.96.146|talk]]) 18:32, 25 January 2013 (UTC)
:I am not sure, but I am inclined to say no. Is [[Nicolas Sarkozy]] a Hungarian president? Elizabeth was neither daughter nor wife of a Bosnian king. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 18:50, 25 January 2013 (UTC)

== My comments ==
I've been asked to comment on this article.  In my opinion, it has a lot of potential but needs some work.  Here are some specific and general comments.

::Lede:
:*I dislike one sentence lede paragraphs.  Can't you say what she is best known for?
::Descent
:*&quot;Born around 1339&quot; Around seems a bit informal, perhaps &quot;about&quot;?
:*Do we know when Elizabeth's mother died?
:*&quot;her father refused to consider the proposal&quot;.  It's unclear if you mean that he was OK with the marriage, but did not like the idea of handing over the land as dowry, or if he was against the suitor under any circumstances.
:*&quot;The same year&quot; perhaps &quot;Later that year,&quot;
:*You'd probably be thanked by the non-geneologic reader if you spelled out the relation of the common ancestor to both (i.e., grandfather, great-grandfather, etc.)
::Marriage:
:*Wouldn't Louis's hopes really be his reason for accepting the betrothal?  After all, once they were betrothed, he would be expected to wed, if you understand what I am saying. So possibly his expectations should be moved into the preceding paragraph. Also, given that Elizabeth was about 14, it might be useful to mention Louis's age.
:*&quot;her retinue included the same individuals who had served the queen mother.&quot; perhaps, &quot;her retinue was made up of people who had served the queen mother, and remained loyal to her.&quot;
:*&quot;For a couple of years&quot; perhaps too informal
:*&quot;of at least a small part of the kingdom&quot; Perhaps &quot;of any part of the kingdom&quot;  I'd also strike the word &quot;own&quot; before &quot;maternal uncle&quot;, I don't see what it adds.
Similarly &quot;officially&quot; before heir presumptive, (I imagine in the 14th century, the throne would often go to whoever had the biggest battalions anyway).
:*&quot;Elizabeth is known to have written a book&quot; I'm not sure this sentence fits in well with the rest of the paragraph.
:*With mama-in-law off ruling Poland rather than ruling daughter-in-law, was younger Elizabeth able to break free of control? 
:*&quot;On 17 September 1374, Louis issued the Privilege of Koszyce,&quot; Hm.  Given that his mother was about to (or just had) returned from Poland with a footprint on her rear end, was this thought likely to stick?
:*&quot; and by 1374, it became certain&quot;  Well, no.  They could have all died.
:*Somewhere you should have the link to &quot;arranged marriage&quot;.
::Widowhood and regency
:*&quot;centralizing policy&quot; which has not yet been mentioned, and wouldn't it be up to Elizabeth to decide whether to continue it?
:*&quot;John asked Tvrtko for help, but they were ultimately defeated by Elizabeth's army&quot; Apparently he did more than ask for it, he received it, however ineffectual it was.
:*&quot;the lack of trusted men&quot; perhaps &quot;a lack of men loyal to her&quot;
:*Why was Hedwig more acceptable to the Poles?  Who was her regent?
*&quot;Both Sigismund and Mary's relative, King Charles III of Naples, threatened to invade Hungary; the former intended to marry Mary and become her co-ruler, while the latter intended to depose her.&quot; Multiple issues.  The start of this sentence reads oddly, and who exactly are the former and latter?  
:*&quot;Elizabeth was desperate in 1384&quot; That's a strong term.  Why?
:*&quot; but the marriage turned out to be too late&quot; I imagine for him to claim the throne.  There is a LOT happening in this paragraph, and it begs for more explanations.
::Legacy
:*&quot;Hedwig was disappointed by her mother's procrastinations and inability to make clear decisions, while Mary was most distressed by her endless problems with Croatian nobles and failure to improve the relations with her native Bosnia&quot; I'm not sure you've made all this clear in the article, especially Hedwig's concerns. I'd also strike &quot;the&quot; before relations.
:*You've not previously mentioned stealing the saint's finger.
::General comments:
:*I think it would be helpful if you explained things a bit more, and made sure that the reasons for events are stated more clearly.  People are coming and going and doing things, and you need to be careful about explaining why these things are happening. Continuity, a la the movies, is key to writing a good biographical article.  --[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 09:55, 23 April 2013 (UTC)

Thank you for your time and comments! I've implemented most of your suggestions and here are responses to the rest:
*It is not known when Elizabeth's mother died or what caused her untimely death. [[Oskar Halecki|Halecki]] only says that she died before the marriage of her only child. Apparently, she was last mentioned alive in 1345, but that is very vague.
*I am not sure where to place the two sentences about her book. Would it be better to put them in a paragraph of their own? They are much less relevant to the next paragraph, which describes events that took place after the book was written.
*Elizabeth did break free in 1370 (&quot;Her mother-in-law's influence prevailed until 1370&quot;), but gained substantial influence only after it was settled that her daughter(s) would become queen(s) (&quot;Her influence had grown steadily since she had given her husband three possible heiresses&quot;).
*I am not sure what you mean in regard to the Privilege of Koszyce. Which thought?
*The article already says that Poles only wanted a queen who would reside in their country, so I made it clear that Hedwig moved to Poland once it was settled that she should rule it. Does that answer your question?
*I am not sure what to do about the sentence that introduces Charles III of Naples, except for reminding the reader that Sigismund was Mary's fiancé. Could you please be a bit more specific?
*The legend says that she stole the finger. Since it is only a legend, it should not be mentioned in the preceding sections. I've made it clear that it is a legend. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 23:56, 24 April 2013 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>h8hzikwwevh3zjcn75x7lfyovepi7tt</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
