<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Citizens' Commission to Investigate the FBI</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4448880</id>
    <revision>
      <id>707041033</id>
      <parentid>707040954</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-02-26T17:24:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>68.46.28.103</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */ fixed a spell correction</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10590">The '''Citizens' Commission to Investigate the FBI''' was a [[leftist]] activist group operational in the US during the early 1970s.  Their only known action was breaking into a two-man [[Media, Pennsylvania]] office of the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]] (FBI), and stealing over 1000 classified documents.  They then mailed these documents anonymously to several US newspapers.  Some news outlets refused to publish the information, as it related to ongoing operations and they contended disclosure might have threatened the lives of agents or informants.  
{{external media | width = 210px | align = right | topic = One Veteran's Square, Media, PA | headerimage= [[File:One Vets Sq Media Delco PA.JPG|210px]]| video1 =[http://www.retroreport.org/video/stealing-j-edgar-hoovers-secrets/ Stealing J. Edgar Hoover's Secrets], [[Retro Report]], 13;36, January 7, 2014, New York Times publisher.
}}
&quot;The complete collection of political documents ripped-off from the F.B.I. office in Media, Pa., March 8, 1971&quot; was published for the first time as the March, 1972 issue of WIN Magazine, a journal associated with the [[War Resisters League]]. The documents revealed the [[COINTELPRO]] operation,&lt;ref&gt;Tim Phillips, [http://activistdefense.wordpress.com/2014/01/07/activists-confess-to-breaking-into-federal-bureau-of-investigation-office-more-than-forty-years-ago/ &quot;Activists Confess to Breaking Into Federal Bureau of Investigation Office More Than Forty Years Ago&quot;], Activist Defense, January 7, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; and led to the [[Church Committee]] and the cessation of this operation by the FBI. [[Noam Chomsky]] has stated:

&lt;blockquote&gt;According to its analysis of the documents in this FBI office, 1 percent were devoted to organized crime, mostly gambling; 30 percent were &quot;manuals, routine forms, and similar procedural matter&quot;; 40 percent were devoted to political surveillance and the like, including two cases involving right-wing groups, ten concerning immigrants, and over 200 on left or liberal groups. Another 14 percent of the documents concerned draft resistance and &quot;leaving the military without government permission.&quot; The remainder concerned bank robberies, murder, rape, and interstate theft.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chomsky.info/articles/199909--.htm Noam Chomsky. ''New Political Science'', Volume 21, Number 3 (September, 1999), pp. 303-324]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The theft resulted in the exposure of some of the FBI's most self-incriminating documents, including several documents detailing the FBI's use of postal workers, switchboard operators, etc., in order to spy on black college students and various non-violent black activist groups.

Some forty years after their successful infiltration, some of the perpetrators decided to go public. In 2014, Betty Medsger's book ''The Burglary: The Discovery of J. Edgar Hoover's Secret F.B.I.'' was released, which contains the burglars' description of the burglary, and revealed the identities of five of the eight burglars.&lt;ref name=&quot;book&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=The Burglary: The Discovery of J. Edgar Hoover's Secret F.B.I.|first=Betty|last=Medsger|publisher=Alfred A. Knopf|location=New York|isbn=978-0-307-96295-9|year=2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Filmmaker Johanna Hamilton also made a documentary titled ''[[1971 (2014 film)|1971]]''.

== Members ==
The FBI closed their investigation into the group's burglary on March 11, 1976 without conclusively identifying any of the perpetrators. The group's identity remained a secret until early 2014, when four of its eight members agreed to be interviewed prior to a book on the burglary being published. The members breaking their silence were Keith Forsyth, John C. Raines and Bonnie Raines, and Robert Williamson. [[William C. Davidon]] (the recruiter and informal leader) died in 2013 but had planned to reveal his involvement.&lt;ref name=nytimes2014&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2014/01/07/us/burglars-who-took-on-fbi-abandon-shadows.html|title=Burglars Who Took On F.B.I. Abandon Shadows|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|date=January 7, 2014|first=Mark|last=Mazzetti}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Later that year, Judi Feingold also revealed herself as a member and was interviewed and included in the paperback edition of ''The Burglary''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | url=http://www.thenation.com/article/181878/breaking-43-years-silence-last-fbi-burglar-tells-story-her-years-underground
 | title=Breaking 43 Years of Silence, the Last FBI Burglar Tells the Story of Her Years in the Underground
 | work=The Nation
 | date=2014-10-06
 | accessdate=2015-04-03 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

Keith Forsyth and Robert Williamson were also members of [[The Camden 28]], who broke into a [[draft board]] to destroy documents, in order to impede the war draft and make an anti-war statement.

==Burglary==
[[File:Media PA Delco Courthouse South.JPG|thumb|upright=1.1|Delaware County Courthouse in Media, PA]]
The burglars did extensive surveillance of the FBI office, to ensure they knew when the office was empty. The break-in was perpetrated on the day of [[Joe Frazier]] and [[Muhammad Ali]]'s [[Fight of the Century]], in the hope that any security guards would be glued to their radios.&lt;ref name=&quot;nbc&quot; /&gt;

The picture of the office shown in the New York Times' video corresponds to [https://tools.wmflabs.org/geohack/geohack.php?pagename=Citizens%27_Commission_to_Investigate_the_FBI&amp;params=39_55_8.65_N_75_23_29.92_W_ 1 Veterans Sq, Media, PA].,&lt;ref name=nytimes2014 /&gt; which is just south of the Delaware County Courthouse.

==Statement==
In a 2014 interview, John Raines said that while returning from the burglary early in the morning, the group had stopped at a pay phone, called a Reuters journalist and delivered the following statement:&lt;ref name=democracynow2014&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.democracynow.org/blog/2014/1/8/from_cointelpro_to_snowden_the_fbi|title=From COINTELPRO to Snowden, the FBI Burglars Speak Out After 43 Years of Silence (Part 2)|publisher=[[DemocracyNow]]|date=January 8, 2014|first=Amy|last=Goodman}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;On the night of March 8, 1971, the Citizens' Commission to Investigate the FBI removed files from the Media, Pennsylvania, office of the FBI. These files will now be studied to determine: one, the nature and extent of surveillance and intimidation carried on by this office of the FBI, particularly against groups and individuals working for a more just, humane and peaceful society. Two, to determine how much of the FBI's efforts are spent on relatively minor crimes by the poor and the powerless against whom they can get a more glamorous conviction rate. Instead of investigating truly serious crimes by those with money and influence which cause great damage to the lives of many people—crimes such as war profiteering, monopolistic practices, institutional racism, organized crime, and the mass distribution of lethal drugs. Finally, three, the extent of illegal practices by the FBI, such as eavesdropping, entrapment, and the use of provocateurs and informers.

As this study proceeds, the results obtained along with the FBI documents pertaining to them will be sent to people in public life who have demonstrated the integrity, courage and commitment to democratic values which are necessary to effectively challenge the repressive policies of the FBI.

As long as the United States government wages war against Indochina in defiance of the vast majority who want all troops and weapons withdrawn this year, and extends that war and suffering under the guise of reducing it. As long as great economic and political power remains concentrated in the hands of a small clique not subject to democratic scrutiny and control. Then repression, intimidation, and entrapment are to be expected. We do not believe that this destruction of democracy and democratic society results simply from the evilness, egoism or senility of some leaders. Rather, this destruction is the result of certain undemocratic social, economic and political institutions.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

== Investigation==
FBI had up to 200 agents working on the case, but it was never solved, and the investigation was closed when the five-year statute of limitations ran out.&lt;ref name=&quot;nbc&quot;&gt;http://investigations.nbcnews.com/_news/2014/01/06/22205443-after-43-years-activists-admit-theft-at-fbi-office-that-exposed-domestic-spying?lite&lt;/ref&gt;

==&quot;1971&quot; documentary film==
A [[documentary film]] titled ''[[1971 (2014 film)|1971]]'' was produced by Big Mouth Productions and co-produced by [[Laura Poitras]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Independent Lens&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=1971 Citizens Who Exposed COINTELPRO|url=http://www.pbs.org/independentlens/1971/|website=Independent Lens|publisher=PBS|accessdate=19 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It had its world premiere at the [[Tribeca Film Festival]] on April 18, 2014.

==See also==
* This burglary is one of the historical events fictionalized by [[James Ellroy]] in his [[Underworld USA Trilogy]].
* [[New York Times Co. v. United States]] — the 1971 case regarding publication of the [[Pentagon Papers]] detailing US involvement in the [[Vietnam War]]
* [[Global surveillance disclosures]] - The 2013 whistleblowing leak by Edward Snowden.

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.1971film.com/ 1971 - A film by Johanna Hamilton] - 2014 documentary about the Citizens' Commission to Investigate the FBI
* [[LA Times]] - [http://www.latimes.com/news/opinion/commentary/la-oe-jalon8mar08,0,2280342.story?coll=la-news-comment-opinions A break-in to end all break-ins]
** [http://www.democracynow.org/blog/2014/1/8/from_cointelpro_to_snowden_the_fbi From COINTELPRO to Snowden, the FBI Burglars Speak Out After 43 Years of Silence (Part 2)]
* [[National Public Radio]] [http://www.npr.org/2014/01/07/260302289/the-secret-burglary-that-exposed-j-edgar-hoovers-fbi story The Secret Burglary That Exposed J. Edgar Hoover's FBI], [http://pd.npr.org/anon.npr-mp3/npr/me/2014/01/20140107_me_the_secret_burglary.mp3 audio]; January 7, 2014
* [[New York Times]] - [http://www.nytimes.com/2014/01/07/us/burglars-who-took-on-fbi-abandon-shadows.html Burglars Who Took On F.B.I. Abandon Shadows] mini-documentary by Mark Mazzetti; January 7, 2014
* [[Democracy Now!]] interviews: 
**[http://www.democracynow.org/2014/1/8/it_was_time_to_do_more &quot;It Was Time to Do More Than Protest&quot;: Activists Admit to 1971 FBI Burglary That Exposed COINTELPRO (Part 1)]
* [http://www.warresisters.org/win/ WIN Magazine]
* [http://www.warresisters.org/ War Resisters League]

[[Category:Federal Bureau of Investigation]]
[[Category:American whistleblowers|+]]
[[Category:Whistleblower support organizations]]</text>
      <sha1>dib6kvifnmrhbxkuc9xx0cqbml4a4z1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
