<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Restoration of the Everglades</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>17601830</id>
    <revision>
      <id>535052329</id>
      <parentid>509221145</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-01-26T21:50:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Alan Liefting</username>
        <id>36352</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>assess for WikiProject Environment - importance=low</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14584">{{ArticleHistory|action1=GAN
|action1date=13:15, 2 June 2008
|action1link=Talk:Restoration of the Everglades/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=216616571

|action2=PR
|action2date=23:10, 15 June 2008
|action2link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Restoration of the Everglades/archive1
|action2result=reviewed
|action2oldid=219195525

|action3=FAC
|action3date=02:01, 5 July 2008
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Restoration of the Everglades
|action3result=promoted
|action3oldid=223278250

|action4=FTC
|action4date=16:28, 2 August 2008
|action4link=Wikipedia:Featured topic candidates/The Florida Everglades/archive1
|action4result=failed

|action5=FTC
|action5date=17:34, 6 July 2010
|action5link=Wikipedia:Featured topic candidates/Everglades/archive2
|action5result=promoted

|ftname=Everglades
|dykdate=31 May 2008
|topic=geography
|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=May 8, 2009
|four=yes
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Miami|class=FA |importance=high }}
{{WikiProject Florida|class=FA |importance=mid |listas=Restoration of the Everglades}}
{{WikiProject Environment|class=FA|importance=low}}
}}

== Nitpicky ==

Now as far as I was aware, the ''[[Melaleuca]]'' species in question was only the one, ''[[Melaleuca quinquenervia]]'', so best to just use the species name in the article (?) I may be wrong on this though. Cheers, [[User:Casliber|Casliber]] ([[User talk:Casliber|talk]] '''·''' [[Special:Contributions/Casliber|contribs]]) 13:53, 25 May 2008 (UTC)
:No, you're right. I'll amend the paragraph. --[[User:Moni3|Moni3]] ([[User talk:Moni3|talk]]) 14:14, 25 May 2008 (UTC)

{{Talk:Restoration of the Everglades/GA1}}
==Successful [[Wikipedia:Good articles|good article]] nomination==
I am glad to report that this article nomination for [[WP:GA|good article]] status has been promoted. This is how the article, as of June 2, 2008, compares against the  [[Wikipedia:What is a good article?|six good article criteria]]:

:'''1. Well written?:''' Pass
:'''2. Factually accurate?:''' Pass
:'''3. Broad in coverage?:''' Pass
:'''4. Neutral point of view?:''' Pass
:'''5. Article stability?''' Pass
:'''6. Images?:''' Pass

  If you feel that this review is in error, feel free to take it to [[Wikipedia:Good article reassessment|Good article reassessment]]. Thank you to all of the editors who worked hard to bring it to this status, and congratulations.&lt;!-- Template:PGAN --&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
[[User:Brianboulton|Brianboulton]] ([[User talk:Brianboulton|talk]]) 07:40, 2 June 2008 (UTC)

== Images ==

I am no expert on images, but I took a quick look at all of images to look for obvious problems:
*[[:Image:Three Roseate spoonbills.jpg]] - It would probably be a good idea to add a date to this one, if possible.
The rest look good to me! [[User:Awadewit|Awadewit]] ([[User talk:Awadewit|talk]]) 00:03, 20 June 2008 (UTC)
:I added a bit to the source description, but the source does not include a date for the image. I reflected this in the summary. --[[User:Moni3|Moni3]] ([[User talk:Moni3|talk]]) 19:04, 24 June 2008 (UTC)

== Invasive species ==

I would have thought the she-oaks gained a guernsey here, namely [http://www.csiro.au/science/ps334.html], [http://www.fs.fed.us/database/feis/plants/tree/casspp/all.html]

for the lovely ''[[Casuarina equisetifolia]]'', ''[[Casuarina glauca]]'' and ''[[Casuarina cunninghamiana]]''....Cheers, [[User:Casliber|Casliber]] ([[User talk:Casliber|talk]] '''·''' [[Special:Contributions/Casliber|contribs]]) 03:52, 22 June 2008 (UTC)

:All bluelinked anyway. Cheers, [[User:Casliber|Casliber]] ([[User talk:Casliber|talk]] '''·''' [[Special:Contributions/Casliber|contribs]]) 04:07, 22 June 2008 (UTC)

== Questions from copyediting ==

*The second paragraph of the lead is confusing to someone unfamiliar with the history of the Everglades. Who the CS&amp;F is probably needs to be made clearer - why were they making canals? Etc.

*''A commission appointed by the governor published a report in 1995 stating that South Florida was unable to sustain its growth, and the deterioration of the environment was negatively affecting daily life for residents in South Florida.'' - Which governor?

*''The remaining 25% of the Everglades in its original state are protected in Everglades National Park, but the park was established prior to the C&amp;SF, and it depended upon the actions of the C&amp;SF to release water.'' - I am not really sure what &quot;the remaining 25%&quot; means.

*''Another water quality issue was the discovery of mercury in fish during the 1980s.'' - Could we find a better transition than &quot;another&quot;?

*I think the panther paragraph could be better organized. I worked on it a bit, but the arrangement as it now stands still jumps back and forth between topics.

*''With the sharp rise in human population, the problem of exotic plant and animal species has grown.'' - When? How sharp was it?

*''A plan in 1993 to revamp the property and convert it into a commercial airport was met with enthusiasm from local municipal and commercial entities hoping to recoup $480 million and 11,000 jobs lost in the local community by the destruction and subsequent closing of the base.'' - Is &quot;revamp&quot; encyclopedic?

*''Underground water storage so that 1,600,000,000 US gallons (6,100,000,000 L) a day could be stored in wells or reservoirs in the Floridan Aquifer, to be used later in dry periods, in a method called Aquifer Storage and Recovery (ASR).'' - I feel like a verb is missing at the beginning of this statement.

*''Treatment wetlands used as Stormwater Treatment Areas throughout 35,600 acres (14,400 ha) that would decrease the amount of pollutants in the environment.'' - Another statement missing a verb at the beginningn to match the rest of the list.

*For some reason, the main body text almost touches the quote box in the &quot;Implementation&quot; section. Larger margins need to be set or something.

That's all I have! [[User:Awadewit|Awadewit]] ([[User talk:Awadewit|talk]]) 16:13, 24 June 2008 (UTC)

::Ok. I think I fixed most of your points. As for the issue of 25%: 27% of the Everglades is now the Everglades Agricultural Area, and 38% of the Everglades is contained within the Water Conservation Areas. Approximately 10% was taken by urban expansion. The remaining 25% of the original Everglades is in the park. Do I need to make that clearer? 
::Let me look at how to do cellpadding in quote boxes. It's almost touching the text on my screen as well.
::Thanks again, Awadewit!  --[[User:Moni3|Moni3]] ([[User talk:Moni3|talk]]) 17:30, 24 June 2008 (UTC)

== Future of restoration section ==

Pursuant to your question [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Featured articles/FA-Team/Mission 4|here regarding the McCain issue]], I'm not seeing any [[WP:UNDUE]] problems here. You present both candidates' quotes on the matter and there is only one paragraph on them in a much broader article that explains the context for their views, so I think we are fine. What does everyone else think? [[User:Awadewit|Awadewit]] ([[User talk:Awadewit|talk]]) 16:18, 24 June 2008 (UTC)

== Copyedit questions ==

*&quot;Their last venture was the C-38 canal which straightened the Kissimmee River&quot;: does this need a comma after &quot;canal&quot;?  It would have 20 years ago.  At that time, leaving out the comma would have meant that you're talking about the C-38 canal which did this, as opposed to other C-38 canals which do something else; putting it in would have meant that the clause doesn't help specify the object.  But everyone's style has fewer commas these days, and I don't know if it's time for this one to go. - Dan [[User:Dank55|Dank55]] ([[User talk:Dank55|talk]])([[Special:Contributions/Dank55|mistakes]]) 00:29, 29 June 2008 (UTC)

*&quot;and maintaining roads and handling traffic congestion for half the amount of vehicles would require $26.3 billion over the next 20 years&quot;: I think I'd prefer to leave that out.  I read the source, and I thought it was slightly goofy for them to be assuming that half the &quot;transportation&quot; (did they mean cars?) would disappear.  I also don't think that a 20-year projection made almost 15 years ago (and doubtless wrong) is helpful.  It seems to me that the part before that can stand on its own: &quot;It noted that though the population had increased by 90% over the previous two decades, registered vehicles had increased by 166%&quot;. - Dan [[User:Dank55|Dank55]] ([[User talk:Dank55|talk]])([[Special:Contributions/Dank55|mistakes]]) 03:15, 1 July 2008 (UTC)

*When I look at the box that begins &quot;Though Congress promised...&quot; and ends &quot;The New York Times, November 2007&quot;, I get the impression the whole thing is a quote from the NYT; is it?  Btw, if it's not a quote, I would switch it around to read &quot;Though Congress promised half the funds for restoration, the federal role in CERP was left unfulfilled after the War in Iraq began and two of CERP's major supporters in Congress retired.&quot; - Dan [[User:Dank55|Dank55]] ([[User talk:Dank55|talk]])([[Special:Contributions/Dank55|mistakes]]) 04:02, 1 July 2008 (UTC)

*The US Sugar story at the end feels just a little anticlimactic; could we give it its own paragraph and start it off with something like &quot;in a widely-applauded announcement...&quot; (and maybe give another reference indicating that environmental groups consider it significant?) - Dan [[User:Dank55|Dank55]] ([[User talk:Dank55|talk]])([[Special:Contributions/Dank55|mistakes]]) 04:21, 1 July 2008 (UTC)
:Pardon me for butting in, but &quot;widely applauded announcement&quot; is not NPOV. I would support adding in references showing that environmental groups have supported the move (which is indeed good news for restoration efforts), but we need to find something a little more neutral for the article. '''[[User:Horologium|&lt;font color=&quot;DarkSlateGray&quot;&gt;Horologium&lt;/font&gt;]]''' &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Horologium|(talk)]]&lt;/small&gt; 12:31, 1 July 2008 (UTC)
::I read your suggestions, and I can do them, but my real job - the stupid one - is diverting my attention at the moment. However, I thought about this last one, and I think I was purposely low-key about it because I really did not believe it was going to happen. I still have reservations that it will go through, and it's causing some controversy about how it will be carried out, if Big Sugar will continue to extend deadlines as they have in the past, etc. I certainly don't want it to be such a big finish that people will assume everything will be all right since the article has such a neat and tidy conclusion. --[[User:Moni3|Moni3]] ([[User talk:Moni3|talk]]) 12:40, 1 July 2008 (UTC)

:::Horologium, you're always welcome to butt in.  My feeling is that statements like &quot;widely applauded announcement&quot; are POV unless they're supported by multiple references that support the statement.  I feel they can actually help to reduce POV if the alternative is a long list of &quot;X liked it, Y liked it, Z liked it&quot;.
:::Moni, your responses to my edits and to my questions were great, and I'm done. - Dan [[User:Dank55|Dank55]] ([[User talk:Dank55|talk]])([[Special:Contributions/Dank55|mistakes]]) 15:54, 1 July 2008 (UTC)

== Relevent Everglades News ==

I just want to provide this recent article since it relates to this article. Not sure if there is any updating necessary, just trying to keep editors here informed, sorry if you already knew this - [http://www.miamiherald.com/newsletters/five_min/story/642776.html] [[User:NancyHeise|NancyHeise]] ([[User talk:NancyHeise|talk]]) 00:40, 17 August 2008 (UTC)
:Sorry, Nancy, 404 error. I have full access to the Miami Herald. If you give me the title or some such, I can find it. --[[User:Moni3|Moni3]] ([[User talk:Moni3|talk]]) 12:00, 8 May 2009 (UTC)

== let not precision exceed accuracy ==

: ''Twenty-five percent of the original Everglades are preserved in Everglades National Park.''

Numbers like &quot;25%&quot; make me suspicious; has it really been measured as less than 26% and more than 24% (if indeed the original area of the Everglades can be stated to two [[significant digits]]) or did someone think the mere two syllables of &quot;one-fourth&quot; undignified? —[[User:Tamfang|Tamfang]] ([[User talk:Tamfang|talk]]) 22:42, 9 May 2009 (UTC)

==Propose adding text on National Research Council review of CERP==

Hi,

I'm interested in adding some text to describe a series of reports from the [[U.S. National Research Council]] that review the progress of the CERP (more information here http://dels.nas.edu/search). I'm also proposing adding the same text on the main Everglades page--let me know if I should edit the version that appears here, or perhaps only add this in one place.

:A series of biennial reports from the [[U.S. National Research Council]] have reviewed the progress of CERP. The fourth report in the series, released in 2012, found that little progress has been made in restoring the core of the remaining Everglades ecosystem; instead, most project construction so far has occurred along its periphery.&lt;ref&gt;(http://dels.nas.edu/Report/Progress-Toward-Restoring-Everglades/13422)&lt;/ref&gt; The report noted that to reverse ongoing ecosystem declines, it will be necessary to expedite restoration projects that target the central Everglades, and to improve both the quality and quantity of the water in the ecosystem.&lt;ref&gt;(http://dels.nas.edu/Materials/Report-In-Brief/4296-Everglades)&lt;/ref&gt; 

:To better understand the potential implications of the current slow pace of progress, the report assessed the current status of ten Everglades ecosystem attributes, including phosphorus loads, peat depth, and populations of snail kites, birds of prey that are endangered in South Florida. Most attributes received grades ranging from C (degraded) to D (significantly degraded), but the snail kite received a grade of F (near irreversible damage). The report also assessed the future trajectory of each ecosystem attribute under three restoration scenarios: improved water quality, improved hydrology, and improvements to both water quality and hydrology, which helped highlight the urgency of restoration actions to benefit a wide range of ecosystem attributes and demonstrate the cost of inaction.&lt;ref&gt;(http://dels.nas.edu/resources/static-assets/materials-based-on-reports/reports-in-brief/Everglades2-Report-Brief-Final.pdf)&lt;/ref&gt; 

:Overall, the report concluded that substantial near-term progress to address both water quality and hydrology in the central Everglades is needed to reverse ongoing degradation before it’s too late. 

Any feedback would be appreciated. Best wishes, [[User:Earlgrey101|Earlgrey101]] ([[User talk:Earlgrey101|talk]]) 15:10, 24 July 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>d8xgscua1atho7p4o042kncrqqu165m</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
