<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Anti-tobacco movement in Nazi Germany</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>17716479</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744488930</id>
      <parentid>734487981</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-15T15:24:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot (v1.2.5)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="86895">{{Talk header}}
{{ArticleHistory|action1=GAN
|action1date=02:02, 1 July 2008
|action1link=Talk:Anti-tobacco movement in Nazi Germany/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=222657545

|action2=FAC
|action2date=19:33, 27 August 2008
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Anti-tobacco movement in Nazi Germany
|action2result=promoted
|action2oldid=234521604

|dykdate=6 June 2008
|four=yes
|topic=World history
|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=November 13, 2008
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Germany|class=FA
&lt;!-- 1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points are appropriately cited. --&gt;
|B-Class-1=yes
&lt;!-- 2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2=yes
&lt;!-- 3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;|B-Class-3=yes
&lt;!-- 4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;|B-Class-4=yes
&lt;!-- 5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;|B-Class-5=yes
|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject History|class=FA
&lt;!-- 1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points are appropriately cited. --&gt;
|B-Class-1=yes
&lt;!-- 2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2=yes
&lt;!-- 3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3=yes
&lt;!-- 4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4=yes
&lt;!-- 5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;|B-Class-5=yes
&lt;!-- 6. It is written from a neutral point of view. --&gt;
|B-Class-6=yes|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject Medicine|class=FA|importance=Low}}}}
{{American English}}

== wow ==

This article is very well-written. I've often heard the the anti-tobacco movement in Nazi Germany used as a straw person argument against all anti-smoking campaigns. I'm glad to see that Wikipedia was able to produce a neutral and highly informative article about a subject which is too often only a talking point. [[User:Savidan|Savidan]] 19:34, 6 June 2008 (UTC)
:Thanks, I have studied the subject well before creating this article. Actually it is [[Robert N. Proctor]], he did extensive research on this topic and in his book ''Nazi War on Cancer'' detailed the Nazi anti-tobacco measures very well. As you can see from the article, Nazi Germany was the first nation to identity the link between lung cancer and tobacco and Nazi sponsored anti-smoking movement was the strongest in the 1930s and 1940s until the collapse of the Nazi government. And what you have heard is right that pro-tobacco advocates try to depict the present day anti-tobacco movement as being borrowed from Nazis, thus they label any anti-smoking movement as a Nazi method. [http://www.prisonplanet.com/articles/april2007/250407antismoking.htm Here is an article] which says &quot; Today's Anti-Smoking Purge Is Borrowed From The Nazis&quot;. But it is misrepresentation of historical facts. By that definition, any [[ballistic missile]] will be &quot;Nazi missile&quot; because the [[V-2 rocket]] was world's first ballistic missile. There is no relation between modern anti-smoking movement and Nazi anti-smoking campaign. The tobacco industry try to misrepresent historical facts and apply several logical fallacy to weaken the anti-tobacco movement. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 20:01, 6 June 2008 (UTC)

however, today's anti-smoking advocates actually use some of the same odious techniques utilized by the nazis, depicting smokers as lesser individuals and hopeless addicts. now, today they don't actually say 'subhuman', etc. but the implication is clear. single-minded, bureaucratic, one-issue individuals such as today's rabid anti-smoking advocates are cut from the same cloth as the people that 'just went along' with the nazis. that is why the anti-tobacco people often use that particular argument. big business capitalism (pro-tobacco) vs. big government socialism (anti-tobacco)... neither one is more evil than the other. &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.69.50.94|24.69.50.94]] ([[User talk:24.69.50.94|talk]]) 20:34, 6 June 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;
:Strange, well if we are talking in terms of &quot;evil&quot; then cigarettes are certainly a lot more evil than other addictions/habits. I really don't see how people trying to get others to quit smoking for health benefits are as evil as a billion dollar comapnies getting people addicted (at an early an age as possible) to cigarettes, still if it helps you feel better as you inhale toxic chemicals then feel free.--[[User:EchetusXe|EchetusXe]] ([[User talk:EchetusXe|talk]]) 10:45, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

It is generally accepted that tobacco increases the chances of contracting cancer, bronchitis, heart disease and so on, and there is certainly nothing wrong with helping people to give up if they wish to, nor is there anything wrong with advising on the dangers.  It is the whole &quot;ideological&quot; part of the debate that irritates me; the way that smokers are villified and treated as second class citizens even if they confine their habits to their own homes.  That is where the similarity lies between the Nazis and the current anti smoking &quot;fashion&quot;, and its not the only similarity either.  By the way, I think you'll find you're inhaling toxic chemicals too, unless you live somewhere where nobody uses a petrol or diesel angine, so you can wipe the smug grin off your face too.   (And yes, I did give up.  2006, and it was EASY).  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/217.198.33.252|217.198.33.252]] ([[User talk:217.198.33.252|talk]]) 13:14, 13 November 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Smokers are not subhuman; they are merely polluters, violators of others' rights to clean environment. Their faults are comparable to those using internal-combustion engines in populated areas. Besides, we humans have civic obligations to look after these people when they get ill. So, all these polluters should be fined, until the marginal social cost equals their marginal utility of smoking (or polluting the atmosphere).  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:FetteK|FetteK]] ([[User talk:FetteK|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/FetteK|contribs]]) 18:41, 13 November 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:You basically just said &quot;Smokers aren't subhuman, But they are subhuman&quot;--[[User:BLaafg|BLaafg]] ([[User talk:BLaafg|talk]]) 23:01, 13 November 2008 (UTC)
:Gee FetteK, I certainly don't want to be a Jew if you become Supreme Leader [[Special:Contributions/24.108.11.228|24.108.11.228]] ([[User talk:24.108.11.228|talk]]) 21:51, 14 August 2010 (UTC)

Ummmmm... they ARE fined. Tobacco taxes are huge in many regions (for example, in British Columbia, $40 CAD is paid to the province in tax. Furthermore, the anti-tobacco movement has tried to claim that smokers do not cover their health care cost, but numerous studies discount this fact (Pieter van Baal, an economist at the Netherlands' National Institute for Public Health and the Environment, published in the Public Library of Science Medicine journal). 'Healthy' people actually end up costing the system more because they live longer and require expensive palliative care and pharmaceuticals.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.69.50.94|24.69.50.94]] ([[User talk:24.69.50.94|talk]]) 20:11, 13 November 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Trouble in free health care paradise?--[[User:BLaafg|BLaafg]] ([[User talk:BLaafg|talk]]) 22:45, 17 November 2008 (UTC)
:You know it. Now and always... ;) [[Special:Contributions/24.108.11.228|24.108.11.228]] ([[User talk:24.108.11.228|talk]]) 21:53, 14 August 2010 (UTC)

==Automobiles or streetcars?==
{{resolved}}
The '''Anti-tobacco measures''' section contains the two sentences &quot;''In 1941, tobacco smoking in automobiles was outlawed in Germany's sixty large urban settlements.[25] Smoking on trams was also banned in many cities.[11]''&quot;
However, [http://www.bmj.com/cgi/content/full/313/7070/1450 this online reference] by Proctor says that &quot;''Sixty of Germany's largest cities banned smoking on street cars in 1941.''&quot; Was smoking really banned in automobiles, or was this just a misunderstanding of the meaning of &quot;street car&quot; (tram)? --[[User:DAJF|DAJF]] ([[User talk:DAJF|talk]]) 02:58, 11 June 2008 (UTC)
*It is tram. Fixed. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 04:20, 11 June 2008 (UTC)
{{Talk:Anti-tobacco movement in Nazi Germany/GA1}}

==Tobacco decline during WWII==

Looking at the data, the success of the antismoking policy appears to be confined to the war years. An obvious alternative explanation is that Germany had limited access to imports of tobacco under conditions of wartime blockade. Is there any info on this?[[User:John Quiggin|JQ]] ([[User talk:John Quiggin|talk]]) 10:03, 24 June 2008 (UTC)
:No, because the &quot;alternative explanation&quot; is not supported by any reference. I have added the information exactly what the reference is saying. What Proctor described is that the decline in tobacco consumption in the later years in the military is due to the policies implemented in the military. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 11:58, 24 June 2008 (UTC)
::Actually, I fully concur with John's comment. By the middle of the war Germans were being supplied with [http://books.google.com.au/books?id=ybxiIKH7eLQC&amp;pg=PA9&amp;lpg=PA9&amp;dq=%22ersatz+cigarettes%22&amp;source=web&amp;ots=eH1IpuoNhn&amp;sig=G-TXb9yHGsMeumD4LIYz4tffqRE&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=5&amp;ct=result#PPA9,M1 ersatz cigarettes], which clearly demonstrates that they had insufficient access to tobacco to make real ones. Also, the source is clearly contradictory as it says that of its study group of 1000, 100 soldiers took up smoking during the war as opposed to only seven who quit. The obvious conclusion is that the overall decline in smoking was due primarily to lack of access to the product, not to the alleged effectiveness of the anti-smoking campaign. [[User:Gatoclass|Gatoclass]] ([[User talk:Gatoclass|talk]]) 10:09, 16 July 2008 (UTC)
:::May be lack of access to cigarettes was a catalytic factor behind decline in tobacco smoking. But per [http://www.bmj.com/cgi/content/full/313/7070/1450 this] reference, ''The net effect of these and other measures (for instance, medical lectures to discourage soldiers from smoking) was to lower tobacco consumption by the military during the war years.'' It is necessary to add information according to [[WP:V]] which is done here. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 00:42, 22 July 2008 (UTC)
::::You are right that according to WP:V this data should be included however I am unsure of the wording. A few times in the article it mentions the decline as specifically the result of the anti-smoking legislation and policies. Given that there is the clear potential that this isn't the case it should be said perhaps that &quot;such and such&quot; said that the policies were the cause. Of course until there is a source saying otherwise it shouldn't be said that &quot;such and such&quot; said that the poor quality and lack of tobacco was the cause ... but making a definitive statement based on 1 reference is an a mistake based on the neutrality guidelines.--[[User:Senor Freebie|Senor Freebie]] ([[User talk:Senor Freebie|talk]]) 02:40, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

The article really looks weird without any references at all to the geo-political situation regarding tobacco import.  Maybe it is because I'm European, and remember my grandparents talking about all the imported stuff they didn't have access to during the occupation.  I'm sure coffee consumption was down too.--[[User:Per Abrahamsen|Per Abrahamsen]] ([[User talk:Per Abrahamsen|talk]]) 09:13, 13 November 2008 (UTC)
:You must have to understand that the topic of the article is researched by very few people, this is why there are very few references. As I have repeatedly said, I will be glad to add it if I can find [[WP:RS|reliable source]]. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 09:20, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

== Brilliant ==

This article is like my new favourite article lol, im a smoker of rolleys and i find this at once informative, easy to read and understand and (subtly) funny all in one glorious artcile, '''Top Marks''', especially for the propaganda pic! xD ''':D''' &lt;font color=&quot;Goldenrod&quot;&gt;[[User:Terrasidius|ΤΕΡΡΑΣΙΔΙΩΣ]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;b&gt;(&lt;/b&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;purple&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Terrasidius|Ταλκ]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;big&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;purple&quot;&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/big&gt;&lt;b&gt;)&lt;/b&gt; 08:03, 4 July 2008 (UTC)
:Thanks. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 18:41, 4 July 2008 (UTC)

::Good read, but for the record: beware [[Godwin's law]].  It just needed to be mentioned. --[[User:Bobak|Bobak]] ([[User talk:Bobak|talk]]) 00:42, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

== ecomed-medizin ==

On June 24, 2008, {{user|Dessources}} added [http://www.ecomed-medizin.de/sj/sfp/Pdf/aId/6824 this reference] in the article to support the claim ''The link between lung cancer and tobacco was first proved in Germany before the rise of the Nazis in the 1930s by Prof. Fritz Lickint'' in [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Anti-tobacco_movement_in_Nazi_Germany&amp;diff=221330858&amp;oldid=220927356 this edit]. But there is no mention in the reference that Lickint was the person who first proved the link between lung cancer and tobacco smoking nor there is any mention that the paper &quot;Tobacco and tobacco smoke as aetiological factors for carcinoma&quot; by Lickint was the first to prove this link. The reference is only saying:
{{cquote|Bereits 1930 veröffentlichte Lickint einen Beitrag zum &quot;Tabak und Tabakrauch als ätiologische Faktoren des Carcinoms&quot; in Form eines Übersichtsbeitrages mit 167 Literaturzitaten (Lickint 1930). Aus den Ergebnissen des damaligen Schrifttums und nach seinen Daten kam er zu einer Geschlechterhäufigkeit von 5 : 1 zwischen Männern und Frauen. Er machte den Tabakrauch für diese Veränderungen verantwortlich und wies bereits damals auf seine Gefahren hin.}}
{{cquote|As early as 1930 Lickint published a contribution to the &quot;Tobacco and tobacco smoke as etiological factors for Carcinoms&quot; in the form of an overview with 167 literature citations (Lickint 1930). From the results of the then Literature and according to his data, he came to a Gender frequency of 5: 1 between men and Women. He made the tobacco smoke for these changes responsible and dismissed were already on its dangers.}}

On the other hand both Proctor (pp. 173) and [http://ije.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/34/3/537 Johan P. Mackenbach] clearly mentions that the '''link between lung cancer and tobacco smoking was first proved by Nazi scientists in Nazi Germany'''. Since the claim {{user|Dessources}} added is not supported by [http://www.ecomed-medizin.de/sj/sfp/Pdf/aId/6824 his reference], I am removing the unsourced claim and his reference and mentioning what the two reliable sources, Proctor and Mackenbach, are saying. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 07:06, 31 July 2008 (UTC)

== Table in &quot;Effectiveness&quot; section ==

I see that Otolemur Crassicaudatus has reverted my adjustment of the [[Anti-tobacco movement in Nazi Germany#Effectiveness|table in the effectiveness section]] (with the addition of a brief title). In my opinion, the table should stand alone as useful data, without requiring qualification from the main text.

Here is the current version of the table:-

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center; margin-right:60px&quot;
|+ Comparison of cigarette consumption
!Country
!1930&lt;ref name=&quot;NWC228&quot;/&gt;
!1935&lt;ref name=&quot;NWC228&quot;/&gt;
!1940&lt;ref name=&quot;NWC228&quot;/&gt;
!1944&lt;ref name=&quot;NWC228&quot;/&gt;
|-
|'''Germany'''||490||510||1,022||743
|-
|'''United States'''||1,485||1,564||1,976||3,039
|}

Here is my proposal:-

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center; margin-right:60px&quot;
|+ '''Cigarette consumption per capita per year in Germany &amp; the [[United States]]'''&lt;ref name=&quot;NWC228&quot;/&gt;
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; |
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; | '''Year'''
|-
| '''1930'''
| '''1935'''
| '''1940'''
| '''1944'''
|-
|'''Germany'''||490||510||1,022||743
|-
|'''United States'''||1,485||1,564||1,976||3,039
|}

Problems with the current table:-
# When reading the top row: '''Country''' | '''1935'''  | '''1940''' | '''1944'''
#: It is not immediately obvious why &quot;Country&quot; is followed by a series of numbers. Only when I look down the the left hand column does the purpose of &quot;Country&quot; become clear. Indeed when I see that the column consists of '''Germany''' and '''United States''', the label &quot;Country&quot; becomes redundant. All readers of this article know what &quot;Germany&quot; and &quot;United States&quot; are.
# Every column has an in-line citation, but these citations are all the same. Rather than listing the citation separately for each column, I used a single citation with the table's title, indicating that all the data derives from that source.
# It is not immediately obvious what &quot;1930&quot;, &quot;1935&quot;, &quot;1940&quot; and &quot;1944&quot; refer to. Given the sequence and similarity to the Nazi era, a reader might infer that they are years.
# It is not obvious what the numbers &quot;490&quot;, &quot;510&quot;, etc. refer to. It is necessary to read the text preceding the table to find out. With my version, the preceding text becomes superfluous. [[User:Axl|Axl]] ([[User talk:Axl|talk]]) 08:32, 10 August 2008 (UTC)

:Hi, thanks for discussing. I have no strong opinion here. The table at first had no table caption and since it started with the sentence &quot;Below is a comparison of per capita cigarette consumption rate per year in Germany and the United States from 1930 to 1944&quot;, I though it will be unnecessary to give a table caption. You have a good point here about the reference and column issue, so I am reverting it back to your version. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 09:51, 10 August 2008 (UTC)
::Thank you. :-) [[User:Axl|Axl]] ([[User talk:Axl|talk]]) 11:14, 10 August 2008 (UTC)

== Consensus for [[:Image:AntiSmokingNaziGermany.jpg]] ==
{{archivetop}}
{{resolved|Consensus is for inclusion of the image. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 07:53, 27 August 2008 (UTC)}}
There is a disagreement over the inclusion of the [[:Image:AntiSmokingNaziGermany.jpg]] in [[Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Anti-tobacco movement in Nazi Germany]]. So it will be better to seek a consensus if the image should be included or not. I have informed the involved users. The arguments for the inclusion of the image are:

*The image gives the reader a picture of a Nazi anti-tobacco magazine
*''Reine Luft'' was the main Nazi anti-tobacco magazine.

Arguments against the inclusion of the image is it does not mention the fair use rationale clearly and the image is unnecessary to describe Nazi anti-tobacco movement.

Lets seek a consensus to solve this problem. &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|Otolemur crassicaudatus]] ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Otolemur crassicaudatus|contribs]]) 14:29, 18 August 2008  (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

===People for inclusion of the image===
*I am for the inclusion of this image, as long as the fair use rationale is strengthened. To do this, the &quot;main points&quot; phrase needs to be specified. What main points does the image convey to the reader? Why is this image necessary? Why won't words suffice? This needs to be explained in the fair use rationale. [[User:Awadewit|Awadewit]] ([[User talk:Awadewit|talk]]) 14:37, 18 August 2008 (UTC)
* I agree with Awadewit. The rationale needs to be clearer, but fair use is justifiable. For what it's worth, the main image on that page is public domain anyway, although I realise that doesn't help. Is there actually a copyright holder for Nazi stuff? [[User:Jimfbleak|jimfbleak]] ([[User talk:Jimfbleak|talk]]) 14:49, 18 August 2008 (UTC)
*'''Include''' The image directly depicts what the article is about and shows Nazi attittudes towards smoking, and you don't have to read German to tell this. This is precisely what FU is for. &lt;span style=&quot;font-family: verdana;&quot;&gt; — [[User:Rlevse|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#060;&quot;&gt;'''''R''levse'''&lt;/span&gt;]] • [[User_talk:Rlevse|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#990;&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/span&gt;]] • &lt;/span&gt; 18:37, 18 August 2008 (UTC)
*: I see an image of a lobster, an image of a joker (possibly malevolent), and (I think) an image of a medieval knight. I can guess that the caption next to the lobster says &quot;Tobacco and crabs&quot;. [[User:Axl|Axl]] ([[User talk:Axl|talk]]) 18:55, 18 August 2008 (UTC)

===People against inclusion of the image===
: '''Remove'''. I can't read German. Hence the picture doesn't add to my understanding of the article's topic. However I expect that this picture might be helpful in the analogous article in German Wikipedia. [[User:Axl|Axl]] ([[User talk:Axl|talk]]) 17:23, 18 August 2008 (UTC)
: '''Remove'''. I agree with Axl. I can read German somewhat, but the picture does not enhance my understanding, unlike the lead one. --I'm an '''''[[Special:Contributions/Editorofthewiki|Editor]][[User:Editorofthewiki|of]][[User talk:Editorofthewiki|the]][[Special:Random|wiki]]'''''&lt;sup&gt;[[Wikipedia:Editor review/Editorofthewiki|[''citation needed'']]]&lt;/sup&gt; 17:42, 18 August 2008 (UTC)
::A translation in the caption could solve this problem. [[User:Awadewit|Awadewit]] ([[User talk:Awadewit|talk]]) 19:22, 18 August 2008 (UTC)

===Discussion===
'''Note:''' I have given the detailed rationale in [[:Image:AntiSmokingNaziGermany.jpg]]. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 15:14, 18 August 2008 (UTC)
*It might be helpful to discuss the imagery in more detail (if only in the image summary).  The crustacean  representing cancer (''Krebs'' means both crustacean and cancer in German) and the devil singing &quot;''so appetitlich frisch'' (ca. so deliciously fresh) as &quot;Propaganda&quot; (this is a reference to a Bergmann cigarette slogan/jingle/advertisement, btw).  I'm forced to wonder, also, if reading the German is unnecessary, why we are using such a high resolution (742x1,080)?  I'm able to read and see everything in the right column (the meaningful one) at my 200px thumbnail preference; see [[WP:NFCC]]#3B.  Also, if we're dotting Is and crossing Ts for FAC, the copyright holder should be attributed (NFCC#10A). [[User:elcobbola|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;'''ЭLСОВВОLД'''&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sub&gt;[[User talk:elcobbola|talk]]&lt;/sub&gt; 19:47, 19 August 2008 (UTC)
::Resolution is unrelated to German language. The purpose of the image is that readers can understand how a Nazi anti-tobacco journal looked like. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 05:19, 23 August 2008 (UTC)
:::However I will say I do not have any strong opinion here, and if other editors think the image is inappropriate, I will remove it after a consensus is achieved. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 07:05, 23 August 2008 (UTC)

Ok, the consensus seems to be for keeping the image. Hence I am closing the discussion. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 07:52, 27 August 2008 (UTC)
{{archivebottom}}

== &quot;Consensus&quot;? ==

I accept that the &quot;Keep&quot; !voters present good arguments. However three good quality &quot;keeps&quot; vs. two good quality &quot;opposes&quot; does not represent &quot;[[WP:CON|consensus]]&quot;. Rather this discussion should have closed as &quot;no consensus&quot;. [[User:Axl|Axl]] ([[User talk:Axl|talk]]) 19:31, 28 August 2008 (UTC)

== Last lead sentence ==

&quot;The world's first public anti-smoking campaign was more powerful and serious than the anti-tobacco movement in Germany at the end of the 20th century.&quot;

:Perhaps I'm simply not fully awake, but this is hard to read. I understand it to mean the Nazi anti-smoking campaign was better than the modern anti-smoking movement in Germany. This should be said another way, such as &quot;The current anti-smoking movement in Germany is not as forceful/powerful/effective/visible as the Nazi anti-tobacco movement.&quot; - [[User:RoyBoy|Roy]][[User talk:RoyBoy|'''Boy''']] 18:24, 7 September 2008 (UTC)
::I have reworded the sentence &quot;The anti-smoking movement in Germany even at the end of the 20th century was not as powerful as the Nazi anti-smoking campaign&quot;. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 07:02, 9 September 2008 (UTC)

== Hitler Image ==

Is is reasonable to discuss replacing the image of Hitler, or removing it altogether?   Do we really need an image of AH in this article, first of all, and, if we decide we do, does it have to be so,  -well- iconic?  Isn't there a photo of him picking his nose or something somewhere on the web?
I would suggest that the image adds nothing to the article.   And, as this is a neutral article, with regards to the Party itself, it may be less than fully appropriate to have an image of the Party leader that is clearly complimentary.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.114.81.205|76.114.81.205]] ([[User talk:76.114.81.205|talk]]) 01:15, 13 November 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:The purpose of the image is to illustrate the article. It is added in a relevant section [[Anti-tobacco_movement_in_Nazi_Germany#Hitler.27s_attitude_towards_smoking|Hitler's attitude towards smoking]]. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 01:37, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

Alright, accepted as valid that there should be an image of AH.
My final point was:  does it have to be such a complimentary one?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.114.81.205|76.114.81.205]] ([[User talk:76.114.81.205|talk]]) 02:41, 13 November 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:::Why does there have to be an uncomplimentary? That would be POV-pushing.... [[User:SGGH|SGGH]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:SGGH|speak!]]&lt;/sup&gt; 15:44, 13 November 2008 (UTC)
::::In Proctor's book (to mention him again) there is an image of Hitler (also iconic) with a text in it praising the Führer as a non-smoker. This would be a more apt image, however somebody would have to scan it and the question of copyright would have to be solved. --[[User:Alex1011|Alex1011]] ([[User talk:Alex1011|talk]]) 11:08, 14 November 2008 (UTC)
:::::You are probably talking about [http://www.bmj.com/cgi/content/full/313/7070/1450/F15 this image]. It is a fair use image. The article already has two fair use images and we cannot include fair use image any more. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 13:40, 15 November 2008 (UTC)
::::::Yes, that is the image. --[[User:Alex1011|Alex1011]] ([[User talk:Alex1011|talk]]) 19:35, 15 November 2008 (UTC)

==Still no mention of supply==

I find it disappointing that this article still has no mention whatever of the fact that Germany was unable to ''access'' tobacco through the war years because of the naval war, and consequently had to substitute the atrocious ersatz-tobacco instead. That, along with the difficulty in actually supplying troops with even their basic needs, let alone luxuries like cigarettes, could surely account for the drop in consumption, but this article stills naively asserts it was all due to the Nazi propaganda campaign. [[User:Gatoclass|Gatoclass]] ([[User talk:Gatoclass|talk]]) 01:35, 13 November 2008 (UTC)
:You are asking this question for the second time. I have answered to your question, see [[Talk:Anti-tobacco_movement_in_Nazi_Germany#Tobacco_decline_during_WWII|this thread]]. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 01:38, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

::Yes, I know, but you only have one reference which says that, and that reference itself admits that little research has been done into the Nazi program. People do make mistakes you know. I note that article also says French consumption declined even more sharply during the years of occupation than in Nazi Germany. Was the Nazi anti-tobacco campaign also extended to France? Or is the more likely explanation, as for the decline in Germany, lack of access?

::I accept that you have a reference to support the statement in the article, but I do think this article is incomplete without at least some discussion of the shortage of tobacco and the difficulties in supplying troops. I mean, German soldiers on the Eastern Front were literally ''starving'' at times. The war led to all kinds of shortages. [[User:Gatoclass|Gatoclass]] ([[User talk:Gatoclass|talk]]) 01:55, 13 November 2008 (UTC)
:::I do understand your argument, you have raised a good point and a thought provoking question. But right now I have nothing to do because almost all the [[WP:RS|reliable sources]] available on this topic are included within the article and none of them discusses this fact. Very few people have researched this topic, this is why there are very few references on it. The only reference on this particular issue (i.e. effectiveness) I have is Proctor. If I can find any reliable source which discusses the issue of effectiveness and its relation with war-time lack of supply, I will add it. Otherwise it will be [[WP:OR|original research]]. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 02:08, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

== its not the first ==

Murad IV, sultan of the Ottoman Empire 1623-40 was among the first to attempt a smoking ban by claiming it was a threat to public moral and health. see the [[Smoking]] page &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/195.174.9.35|195.174.9.35]] ([[User talk:195.174.9.35|talk]]) 03:17, 13 November 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;

:I think the qualifier &quot;in modern history&quot; makes this still fine. There were other bans historically, but this was the first serious attempt in the past few hundred years. --[[User:Delirium|Delirium]] ([[User talk:Delirium|talk]]) 06:56, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

::It's not up to you to decide, when [[modern history]] started. The introduction is simply POV. --[[User:Hans-Jürgen Hübner|Hans-Jürgen Hübner]] ([[User talk:Hans-Jürgen Hübner|talk]]) 11:18, 13 November 2008 (UTC)
:::Read the article [[Modern history]], there is a definition of Modern history. Modern history refers to the history of the Modern Times, the era after the Middle Ages. I completely failed to understand on what basis you are saying &quot;The introduction is simply POV&quot;. The fact is supported by a reliable source ''Science in the Third Reich'' by Margit Szöllösi-Janze, professor of history at the [[University of Salzburg]]. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 11:26, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

::::Apparently there were quite a few tobacco prohibitions during this period of the seventeenth century - China, Russia, New York, Bhutan among others.[http://www.tobacco.org/resources/history/Tobacco_History17.html]  I could scarcely imagine that such an unpleasant and addictive drug could have gained such popularity without them. [[User:Mike Serfas|Mike Serfas]] ([[User talk:Mike Serfas|talk]]) 07:35, 15 November 2008 (UTC)

:::::The online source you cited is a personal website of an independent anti-tobacco activist, blogger and Internet writer named Gene Borio and in no sense is more reliable than a scholarly book written by a professor of history at the [[University of Salzburg]]. The online source also does not site any reference for most of the information with only a few exceptions like the information on Nazi Germany where it cites Proctor. Another point, &quot;movement&quot; and &quot;prohibition&quot; are not same. Movement not only means law enforcement, but includes mobilization of the public, use of the mass media, publication of relevant literature and education for the masses. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 12:59, 15 November 2008 (UTC)

==First Two Sentences Contradictory==
As noted in the second sentence of the article, there were public anti-tobacco movements from the start of the 20th C, for example in Illinois in 1907. The first sentence claims that Nazi Germany led the ''first'' campaign. Nazi Germany, under any history I have seen, did not exist then. Possibly this should be ammended to 'first successful public' or similar? [[User:Mharward|Mharward]] ([[User talk:Mharward|talk]]) 03:18, 13 November 2008 (UTC)
&lt;br /&gt;
:The first sentence is not saying it was the first anti-smoking campaign, the first sentence is saying it was the first '''public''' anti-smoking campaign. The campaign by Nazi Germany was characterized by attempt to influence the public (through the use of almost all government-public interaction means), not only by implementing laws. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 09:37, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

==Did it help lose the war?==
Can't seem to find the source that said this. Anyone seen it?[[User:Research Method|Peas &amp;amp; Luv]] ([[User talk:Research Method|talk]]) 05:04, 13 November 2008 (UTC)
:I would have thought attacking the Soviet Union and declaring war on the USA would have lost them the war, any source that says the anti-tobacco movement lost the Nazis the war isn't worth referencing.--[[User:EchetusXe|EchetusXe]] ([[User talk:EchetusXe|talk]]) 10:47, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

== repulse ==

i must say, looking at a picture of Adolph Hitler on the main page of wikipedia... is of such great repulse at this times of history... In an article, where the inhumanity of Nazi facts is not at first hand mentioned. I am deeply sorry some people condemn cigarette or any other kind of drug or even petty vice abuse. But, im afraid every nation and human rights defender person has a right on this matter. We cannot allow any issues defended under the nazi flag. Any, for that matter. It's inmoral, it's repulsive. This will be taken to the higher levels of Wikipedia, i so hope. Maybe tomorrow we will feature an article on the dissapearing of Roma, Iranian or whichever race or habit by nazi standars. Im enraged at this, and this, should be answered by ethical standars of Holocaust denial. I might have missed the whole point of the article, yet it doesnt look so clear, nor does Adolph Hitler's picture in the main page ([[User:Abestrobi|Abestrobi]] ([[User talk:Abestrobi|talk]]) 08:56, 13 November 2008 (UTC))
:Sorry, what is your objection? This is an article on the 'Anti-tobacco movement in Nazi Germany', anything repulsive the Nazis did isn't particularly relevant to the article, even so you will notice their anti-semitism is mentioned in the article as the Nazis used Jews in this propaganda piece as was their custom.--[[User:EchetusXe|EchetusXe]] ([[User talk:EchetusXe|talk]]) 10:51, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

:Abestrobi, I think, as you yourself say, that you &quot;might have missed the whole point of the article&quot;! This article is not the place to condemn the terrible things done by the Nazis. There are plenty of relevant pages in wikipedia for that. I'm sure it must be hard to accept by some people that evil/totalitarian regimes actually managed to do some good/useful things (even if for the wrong reasons and even if vastly outweighed by the bad things they did) but facts are facts. So if the Nazis were the first to do a major anti-smoking campaign, it has to be recognized, no? (They were also the first to build modern motorways were they not?) --[[User:BodegasAmbite|BodegasAmbite]] ([[User talk:BodegasAmbite|talk]]) 12:08, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

::When a member of the Yehudim faith opens wikipedia this is how they are to be greeted?!?!?! A picture of the evil aryan races number 1 :@:@:@:@ THIS IS DISGUSTING!!! Anyone who advocates an article which PRAISES ANY FORM OF NAZISM/ARYAN PRIDE IS A NAZI AND MUST BE SOUGHT OUT AND NAMED AND SHAMED!!! :@:@:@:@ '''We cannot allow any issues defended under the nazi flag'''!!! I will be taking this further, anyone who supports or supported this pathetic excuse for an article will get theirs!!![[Special:Contributions/58.107.179.146|58.107.179.146]] ([[User talk:58.107.179.146|talk]]) 12:20, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

:::You seem to forget that Wikipedia is NPOV, and thus does not advocate or support anything. This article does not approve of either the Nazis or their anti-tobacco campaign. [[User:Brutannica|Brutannica]] ([[User talk:Brutannica|talk]]) 13:25, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

Before you react in such an enraged way, you should maybe give some things a second philosophical thought. What should somebody think who sees today's featured picture about work on an &quot;A-31 Vengeance dive bomber&quot; and whose siblings and mother burned to death because of the allied attacks. Thousands of children were deliberately burned to death in the allied bombing raids against civilians. &lt;br&gt;
So what it ends up to today is the following – mankind is divided in absolutely good on the one side and absolutely evil on the other – therefore ALL actions are looked upon not according to the nature of the action but who was the actor.
What do Americans know about the hundreds of thousands of girls and women – mothers, sisters, and daughters who were raped after &quot;the good side&quot; won? Who knows about the millions of Germans and East Europeans who were butchered after &quot;the good side&quot; won? If it ever enters articles it's downplayed because of the modern commandment not to relativize the guilt of &quot;the evil side&quot;. &lt;br&gt;
It's not in the media and you're not close to personally told stories. &lt;br&gt;
Sadly the world stays the same – just count the murdered and the wars since 1945 or before 1900. &lt;br&gt;
Greetings, [[Special:Contributions/217.236.224.46|217.236.224.46]] ([[User talk:217.236.224.46|talk]]) 13:54, 13 November 2008 (UTC)
:::Wikipedia is NPOV, saying that Hitler is &quot;disgusting and evil&quot; is POV, not to mention one-dimensional. [[User:SGGH|SGGH]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:SGGH|speak!]]&lt;/sup&gt; 15:46, 13 November 2008 (UTC)
::::Oh, and incidentally, I echo the sentiments from further up the page, this article is an excellent job :) [[User:SGGH|SGGH]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:SGGH|speak!]]&lt;/sup&gt; 15:48, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

:::Enjoy your time, many nazis did until THEY WERE HUNG!!! :@[[Special:Contributions/58.107.172.142|58.107.172.142]] ([[User talk:58.107.172.142|talk]]) 05:58, 14 November 2008 (UTC)

::::You sure have humane feelings, gallows in your backyard and have to be an enjoyable person.[[Special:Contributions/217.236.218.226|217.236.218.226]] ([[User talk:217.236.218.226|talk]]) 13:24, 16 November 2008 (UTC)

Thanks for the thoughts, I ''still'' have the nasty memory and feel the same rejection when i look at that ''Wikipedia front page with an image of Hitler and an article that talks about Nazi life protection policy''. It's so ironic, isnt it? seems almost a joke. For my (IP only) friend up here... that links Nazism with the Aryan race... you are SO mistaken!! Nazis killed aryans as well, starved many to death. The aryan race as all races, but not just one, is to be praised. Yet it's sad you consider this party... that only benefited itself with its policies (under puny racial claims) the savior of aryan races.
:I saw below, someone also claimed the nazi's had '''welfare''' programs for german citizens. Yes they did, but to THEIR definition of german citizens (defenders of the regime). Germans that were political opponents were not considered or treated as citizens, no matter their race.
::And yes, i can indulge to say Hitler is a disgusting an evil political figure, that is completely POV. '''&quot;Discussion&quot; page is exactly for that, expose and share personal POV concerns'''.([[User:Abestrobi|Abestrobi]] ([[User talk:Abestrobi|talk]]) 22:05, 16 November 2008 (UTC))
::: From the banner at the top of this page: &quot;'''This is the talk page for discussing improvements to the [[Anti-tobacco movement in Nazi Germany]] article.... This is not a forum for general discussion about the article's subject.''' [[User:Axl|&lt;font color=&quot;#808000&quot;&gt;'''Axl'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;font color=&quot;#3CB371&quot;&gt;¤&lt;/font&gt; &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Axl|&lt;font color=&quot;#6B8E23&quot;&gt;[Talk]&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/small&gt; 22:19, 16 November 2008 (UTC)
::::Agree with Axl. The person who started this thread is [[WP:NOTFORUM|using the talk page as a forum]]. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 09:45, 17 November 2008 (UTC)

== Restrictions on rationing ==

Just thought I'd mention, since it's on the Main Page, that:

:''The Nazis also imposed restrictions on tobacco advertising, tobacco rationing for women, and smoking in public spaces, and they regulated restaurants and coffeehouses.''

...isn't a featured-quality sentence. Does someone want to fix? [I'm not watching this page]. [[User:AndyJones|AndyJones]] ([[User talk:AndyJones|talk]]) 09:45, 13 November 2008 (UTC)
:What is your alternative suggestion? '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 09:48, 13 November 2008 (UTC)
::Dunno. How about:

:::''The Nazis also imposed restrictions on tobacco advertising and smoking in public spaces, introduced tobacco rationing for women, and regulated restaurants and coffeehouses.''

::...? I think the problem with the original is pretty obvious. [[User:AndyJones|AndyJones]] ([[User talk:AndyJones|talk]]) 09:56, 13 November 2008 (UTC)
::::Err, the Nazis actually '''prohibited''' tobacco rationing for women, not &quot;'''introduced''' tobacco rationing for women&quot;. The structure of your alternative suggestion, which is not so different from the previous structure, is ok except the tobacco rationing for women part, I will add this removing that particular part. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 10:06, 13 November 2008 (UTC)


Another point: &quot;Pregnant women and women below the age of 25 and over the age of 55 were not given tobacco ration cards during World War II.&quot; Shouldn't that be '''over 25''' and '''under 55'''? I don't think there would have been many pregnant women over 55. &lt;font style=&quot;bold italic&quot; color=&quot;7C0500&quot;&gt;Harry the Dog &lt;/font&gt;[[User_talk:Harry the Dirty Dog|&lt;font color=&quot;0000FF&quot;&gt;WOOF&lt;/font&gt;]] 12:01, 13 November 2008 (UTC)
:No. The Nazis targeted two groups:

:#Pregnant women
:#Non-Pregnant women

:Actually  the sentence means pregnant women were not given tobacco ration cards during World War II; women who were not pregnant were also not given tobacco ration cards during World War II. In case of women who were not pregnant, the age structure was below the age of 25 and over the age of 55. The age structure only applies for women who were not pregnant, not for pregnant women. All pregnant women, regardless of their age, were not given tobacco ration cards. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 12:07, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

:I get it now! My misreading. Thanks! &lt;font style=&quot;bold italic&quot; color=&quot;7C0500&quot;&gt;Harry the Dog &lt;/font&gt;[[User_talk:Harry the Dirty Dog|&lt;font color=&quot;0000FF&quot;&gt;WOOF&lt;/font&gt;]] 12:13, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

== most influential vs. not effective ==

I think it is contradictory to claim, that the campaign was the most influential of 20th century, and on the other side to claim, that it was not effective. That smoking declined during war time has probably something to do with the war. Proctor himself writes, if I remember correctly, that the NS government stopped or interrupted the campaign during the war in order to enhance public morale. --[[User:Alex1011|Alex1011]] ([[User talk:Alex1011|talk]]) 12:24, 13 November 2008 (UTC)
:Powerful movement does not mean it have to be completely effective. According to Proctor, it was the most powerful movement during the 1930s and early 1940s, but it was not as effective as expected. It is wrong to claim the movement was completely ineffective, it had some degree of effect. The Nazi anti-tobacco campaign was also more powerful than the present day anti-smoking movement in Germany. This means there is an anti-tobacco movement in Germany, but the campaign the Nazis started was more expensive and larger (in terms of government expense, use of the mass media, legislation effort, propaganda etc.) than the present day movement; the Nazi campaign involved the mass media and almost all government machineries, see the [[Anti-tobacco_movement_in_Nazi_Germany#Anti-tobacco_measures|measures]] section. It was not so effective does not mean it was not larger in size than other contemporary movements and the present day movement in Germany. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 12:40, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

Gee, the way you guys talk, we should all worship The Proctor. When did he die? I want to stop referring to the year as 2008 and start referring to it as 46 AP or something because HE IS GOD!  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.69.50.94|24.69.50.94]] ([[User talk:24.69.50.94|talk]]) 20:39, 13 November 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Hitler Youth Division ==

I'd have to find the reference, but I believe the 12th SS &quot;HitlerJugend&quot; Division - made up largely of underage teenagers from the Hitler Youth movement - were denied tobacco rations and were actually given additional hard candy rations in lieu, a fact often mentioned in their divisional histories. In the context of this article (great article, by the way - this is why we have Featured Articles, I think, for I had no idea this existed) - it makes even more sense, now.[[Special:Contributions/139.48.25.60|139.48.25.60]] ([[User talk:139.48.25.60|talk]]) 15:35, 13 November 2008 (UTC)
:It is a good information. I have added the reference properly. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 16:23, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

The reference for the information on [[12th SS Panzer Division Hitlerjugend]], ''The 12th SS: The History of the Hitler Youth Panzer Division'' by Hubert Meyer, 2005, ISBN 9780811731980, published by Stackpole Books, states:
{{cquote|Efforts by departments at home to provide additional rations were unsuccessful. The troops were supplied with the regular provisions by the supply offices of the Heer. However, the recruits were not issued with tobacco products but received candy instead.}}

I have reworded the information properly as per the reference. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 16:35, 13 November 2008 (UTC)
::Great job.[[Special:Contributions/139.48.25.60|139.48.25.60]] ([[User talk:139.48.25.60|talk]]) 18:32, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

==Translation?==

By way of comment: odd that such an excellent article does not have a counterpart on the German Wikipedia. --'''[[User:Legis|Legis]]''' &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Legis|talk]] - [[Special:Contributions/Legis|contribs]])&lt;/small&gt; 16:21, 13 November 2008 (UTC)
:If I have time, I shall do it. By the way, Proctor's book itself is not yet translated into German. There were some reviews of this English book in German newspapers, which were, however, not very enthusiastic. At a time, when Europe-wide and in Germany there are strong efforts to regulate smoking, mainstream media are not amused to get reminded, that there had already been a [[mutatis mutandis]] similar effort in NS times. Another possible point for controversy is Proctor's claim that experiments with living people in concentration camps did provide medical results. That the Nazis passed a law very early [[Animal welfare in Nazi Germany|to prohibit experiments with animals]] in the chemical and pharmaceutical industry might be another taboo. That this policy measure was derided in a cartoon - against Goering - in a left wing news paper, although Hitler was already in power, still another. Finally, Proctor was so impolite to bring world attention to &quot;the world's biggest swastika&quot;, a wood near Berlin planted in the form of a huge swastika, which had survived unnoticed in GDR territory, till it was found by aeroplane passengers after the fall of the wall. That wood was then, reluctantly, cut down by the authorities. There are still other taboo themes in Proctor's book. --[[User:Alex1011|Alex1011]] ([[User talk:Alex1011|talk]]) 20:06, 15 November 2008 (UTC)

== Intro paragraph: &quot;associated with antisemitism and racism&quot;? ==

From the intro: ''&quot;...and this campaign was associated with both antisemitism and racism.&quot;'' Does this seem extremely vague and weaselwordy to anyone else? Isn't everything in nazi Germany &quot;associated with antisemitism and racism&quot;? Is there a better way to phrase this statement? Thoughts? [[User:AdRem|AdRem]] ([[User talk:AdRem|talk]]) 17:00, 13 November 2008 (UTC)
:It is an important fact and should be mentioned in the lead to summarize the entire article and for the purpose of NPOV. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 17:04, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

My fist association is with the Körperkultur, the association between tobacco and anti-semitism/racism isn't an obvious one and might need a few words to help the reader &quot;see it&quot;.
[[User:Dugodugo|Dugodugo]] ([[User talk:Dugodugo|talk]]) 18:27, 13 November 2008 (UTC)
:It is not association between tobacco and antisemitism/racism, it is association between '''Nazi anti-tobacco movement''' and antisemitism/racism. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 18:38, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

== [[Anti-smoking movement]] ==
I've added a link to [[anti-smoking movement]] to the top of the article: it's remarkable that we have an article about the Nazi anti-tobacco movement, but not to the wider topics of the (entirely non-Nazi) anti-tobacco movement in general. -- [[User:The Anome|The Anome]] ([[User talk:The Anome|talk]]) 17:17, 13 November 2008 (UTC)
:Yes, but at present please remove this link since the article does not exist. It will be ok to link when the article is created. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 17:19, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

::No, that's not how Wikipedia works: ''relevant'' red-links are not only permitted, but actively encouraged. See [[Wikipedia:Red link]] and [[Wikipedia:Wikipedia is a work in progress]]. -- [[User:The Anome|The Anome]] ([[User talk:The Anome|talk]]) 17:23, 13 November 2008 (UTC)
:::Then try to improve the article [[Anti-smoking movement]]. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 17:30, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

==Related traits==
It might be well to mention that in addition to being a nonsmoker, Hiter was a teetoaler and a vegetarian. It's one of the weird ironies of history that the most infamous mass murderer of all time was, if one may use the phrase, a &quot;clean liver.&quot; According to some of his biographers, he may have been obsessed with personal cleanliness and hygiene, and was a fastidious dresser.

Stalin, by contrast, was a heavy smoker and drinker.

I never knew that Hitler had once been a heavy smoker. Very nicely crafted article.  [[User:Sca|Sca]] ([[User talk:Sca|talk]]) 20:39, 13 November 2008 (UTC)
::It is possibly more relevant at his own article, and I'm sure it is included there. While it is ironic we wouldn't ideally want the article to comment on such irony off its own bat. [[User:SGGH|SGGH]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:SGGH|speak!]]&lt;/sup&gt; 21:35, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

:::I was only commenting on the irony for this talk page. I just think it would be relevant and interesting to note in passing. ''Hitler, also a teetotaler and vegetarian, blahblahblah....''  [[User:Sca|Sca]] ([[User talk:Sca|talk]]) 22:01, 13 November 2008 (UTC)
::::The information on Hitler's vegetarianism will be better suited in the article [[Adolf Hitler]]. We have an article titled [[Vegetarianism of Adolf Hitler]]. This article only mentions the information which is relevant to the anti-smoking movement. The fact here is that Hitler was a heavy smoker in his early life, but later gave up the habit and encouraged others to do the same. In his later life, he had a hostile attitude towards smoking and it was a catalytic factor behind the Nazi anti-tobacco campaign. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 22:29, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

:::::To clarify: His ''abstinence'' from alcohol and meat is relevant to his parallel ''abstinence'' from tobacco and abhorrence of same.  [[User:Sca|Sca]] ([[User talk:Sca|talk]]) 23:26, 13 November 2008 (UTC)

==Featured Article???==

How did this piece of trash ever make it as an FA? A feeble attempt to link the Nazis with measures intended to improve people's health. Well done smokers! I'm sure when you're breathing your last through that hole in your neck you'll be able to think (you'll certainly not be able to vocalise) &quot;We really showed it to those non-smokers!&quot; Absolutely pathetic. [[User:Halmyre|Halmyre]] ([[User talk:Halmyre|talk]]) 19:43, 14 November 2008 (UTC)

[[Image:DoNotFeedTroll.svg|frame|A &quot;Do not feed the troll&quot; image (don't encourage trolls by reacting to them)]]

:[http://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/What_is_a_troll%3F Never feed the troll]. --'''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 20:21, 14 November 2008 (UTC)

== Irony ==

[[#repulse|Some people]] are outraged at this article because it seems to praise the Nazis (since of course smoking is bad). And then [[#Featured Article???|some people]] are outraged because it seems to defend smoking (since of course the Nazis are bad). Wherever we discuss a historical irony like this (where two evils are in temporary conflict), we will naturally get such complaints. Meanwhile Wikipedia marches onward with [[WP:NPOV|neutrality of point of view]].

Praise to all who wrote this fine and interesting article! —[[User:Toby Bartels|Toby Bartels]] ([[User talk:Toby Bartels|talk]]) 04:28, 15 November 2008 (UTC)
:It neither praise the Nazis, nor defend smoking. There is nothing POV to mention a historical fact, if the Nazis implemented anti-tobacco measures, there is nothing POV to mention it. And if Nazis opposed X, then X will be good, it is a [[logical fallacy]]. Nazis were bad and they opposed smoking does not mean smoking is good, those who claim this, they apply a logical fallacy known as '''''[[Reductio ad Hitlerum]]'''''. I have created another article [[Animal welfare in Nazi Germany]]. The Nazis implemented strict restrictions on animal experimentation. See the [[Animal_welfare_in_Nazi_Germany#Measures|measures the Nazis implemented for their animal welfare campaign]]. Does this mean those who support animal rights are like Nazis? Does this mean those who support unnecessary testing of animals are good? The Nazis also [[Nazi_Germany#Social_Welfare|focused on insuring a minimal living standard for German citizens]]. So by using ''Reductio ad Hitlerum'' one can say any government which provides its citizens with minimal standard of living is evil government. The Nazis did both good and bad, but their bad overwhelms their good. That does not mean the good they did will also be bad, it is ''Reductio ad Hitlerum''. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 07:34, 15 November 2008 (UTC)

It could be claimed as well that investing in the development and promotion of featured articles related to something of great social approval that links to the nazi party is vindication of crime or historical rehabilitation of such party and government. It seems interesting there was so much legislation and policy about the protection of life in nazi Germany, isnt it? Some say they enforced restrictions on animal experimentation... yet history well recalls they performed the most horrid experiments in humans. How can we talk about life-protection policy when the magnitude of the atrocities is such? Some also say nazi social welfare campaigns focused on &quot;insuring a minimal living standard for German citizens&quot;... that i must also criticize since that notion of &quot;citizen&quot; is the one of the nazis. The welfare programs didnt apply to the enemies of the reich, though they were indeed german citizens (socialists, comunists, jews, gays, pro-anglo, etc.) In summary... we cannot say the sun is dark because it has small blackish spots, many in fact, but not enough. This is the logic of my thought here not a reductionism, but a claim and doubt that seeking rehabilitation is a possible objective of this article. ([[User:Abestrobi|Abestrobi]] ([[User talk:Abestrobi|talk]]) 21:39, 16 November 2008 (UTC))
::If you believe there is any problem with this article, you can always AfD it. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 11:10, 17 November 2008 (UTC)
:And yet we have an article on [[sunspot]]s. How far does your analogy carry? --[[User:Stephan Schulz|Stephan Schulz]] ([[User talk:Stephan Schulz|talk]]) 21:51, 16 November 2008 (UTC)

::Yes we do. Oh, lets feature it Stephan! Maybe in time and with enough promotion... we can make people think the sun is actually a dark planet... that oh, well happens to emight some light. ([[User:Abestrobi|Abestrobi]] ([[User talk:Abestrobi|talk]]) 22:13, 16 November 2008 (UTC))
:::The talk page banner says '''This is not a forum for general discussion about the article's subject.''' '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 09:46, 17 November 2008 (UTC)

== &quot;Claim&quot; was correct ==

This article states that a Nazi official &quot;claimed&quot; that a tobacco smoker's breast milk contains nicotine.  I pointed out that this claim was in fact correct, but was reverted 14 hours later by someone claiming [[WP:SYN]] (although my sources &quot;explicitly reach the same conclusion&quot;).[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Anti-tobacco_movement_in_Nazi_Germany&amp;diff=251590114&amp;oldid=251588847]  I believe that &quot;claim&quot; is a word discouraged by [[WP:WTA]], and that it is within our purview to mention whether past scientific beliefs were upheld by further research. [[User:Mike Serfas|Mike Serfas]] ([[User talk:Mike Serfas|talk]]) 07:20, 15 November 2008 (UTC)
:Hi, thanks for discussing it. The article is about the Nazi viewpoint. The sources you provided are modern research. No one is denying the fact that tobacco smoker's breast milk contains nicotine. I am agree with you on the issue of wording. I will change the word &quot;claim&quot; to &quot;said&quot;. Again, the article describes what the Nazis did and what the Nazis said, ''not'' what people in modern times are saying. So even what the Nazis said is proved to be correct in modern research, we cannot include the modern research in this article. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 07:32, 15 November 2008 (UTC)
::I have used the structure &quot;Werner Huttig of the Nazi Party's Rassenpolitisches Amt (Office of Racial Politics) said that a smoking mother's breast milk contained nicotine, a claim that is proved to be correct in modern research.&quot; '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 07:42, 15 November 2008 (UTC)
:::Thanks - that works. [[User:Mike Serfas|Mike Serfas]] ([[User talk:Mike Serfas|talk]]) 08:16, 15 November 2008 (UTC)
:I've just come across this article. You who contribute will need to be wary of anti-tobacco contributors. In general the anti-tobacco movement does not like attention being drawn to the Nazi Germany campaign against tobacco, partly because (in the UK at least) those who campaign for smoking bans are often termed &quot;Health Nazis&quot;. I think the referencing of four articles to show that nicotine is present in breast milk is unnecessary. I'm sure this wasn't a very difficult chemical analysis. Why not find the earliest reference? I suspect that the inclusion of the reference to a 2008 paper about the effect on heart beats is an attempt to get the author's views on smoking onto the page. Unless the Nazis performed similar tests, I don't see its relevance. If you want to know who the anti-tobacco wikipedia contributors are, go to the Passive Smoking page.[[User:Otis66|Otis66]] ([[User talk:Otis66|talk]]) 13:20, 29 December 2008 (UTC)

== Nazi &gt; National Socialist  ==

I changed the word &quot;Nazi&quot; to &quot;National Socialist&quot; in two sentences in the lead to avoid repetitive use of the same word [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Anti-tobacco_movement_in_Nazi_Germany&amp;diff=251764590&amp;oldid=251754849]. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 13:00, 17 November 2008 (UTC)

== Consensus for translation of the word &quot;Genussgifte&quot; ==

There is a problem on translation of the German word &quot;Genussgifte&quot; in the sentence &quot;Articles advocating nonsmoking were published in the magazines Die Genussgifte...&quot; in the [[Anti-tobacco_movement_in_Nazi_Germany#Anti-tobacco_measures|Anti-tobacco measures]] section. {{user|Tshb}} suggested &quot;Poisons&quot; is a better translation [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Anti-tobacco_movement_in_Nazi_Germany&amp;diff=251781874&amp;oldid=251764590], while {{user|Future Perfect at Sunrise}} suggested &quot;drugs for enjoyment&quot; is better translation [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Wikipedia%3AFeatured_article_candidates%2FAnti-tobacco_movement_in_Nazi_Germany&amp;diff=231845743&amp;oldid=231832831]. Actually previously the word &quot;Genussgifte&quot; was translated as &quot;The Benefit Poisons&quot; [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Anti-tobacco_movement_in_Nazi_Germany&amp;oldid=223708836#Anti-tobacco_measures], during the FA nom, Future Perfect suggested the translation &quot;drugs for enjoyment&quot; in place of &quot;The Benefit Poisons&quot; and I believe Future Perfect's suggestion was better. But now there are two possible translated wordings:

#The Drugs for Enjoyment
#The Poisons for Enjoyment

A consensus is necessary to determine which is the better translation. I do not have any strong opinion here. I have temporarily removed the word &quot;Drugs&quot; from the translation because it resulted in a first bracket within a first bracket i.e. ''Die Genussgifte'' (The Poisons (Drugs) for Enjoyment), which I changed to ''Die Genussgifte'' (The Poisons for Enjoyment) [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Anti-tobacco_movement_in_Nazi_Germany&amp;diff=251784133&amp;oldid=251781874]. I am seeking opinion which translation is better: &quot;The Drugs for Enjoyment&quot; or &quot;The Poisons for Enjoyment&quot;. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 14:43, 17 November 2008 (UTC)

:Actually, I now find that Collins German Dictionary [http://dictionary.reverso.net/german-english/Genussgift] translates the term as &quot;social drug&quot;. Never heard of that term, so I can't really judge. [http://www.babylon.com/definition/Genussgift/English This] online dictionary has ''&quot;stimulant, excitant, substance which excites&quot;'' [[User:Future Perfect at Sunrise|Fut.Perf.]] [[User talk:Future Perfect at Sunrise|☼]] 14:50, 17 November 2008 (UTC)
::Google translate and [http://translation2.paralink.com/ this translator] translates the term as &quot;Enjoyment poisons&quot; and &quot;Pleasure poisons&quot; respectively. But after seeing the dictionaries you cited, &quot;drug&quot; will be a better translation, IMO. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 15:09, 17 November 2008 (UTC)
::: I'd certainly prefer &quot;drug&quot; over &quot;poison&quot;. The German term is meant to refer to things like caffeine, tobacco and alcohol, after all. [[User:Future Perfect at Sunrise|Fut.Perf.]] [[User talk:Future Perfect at Sunrise|☼]] 16:31, 17 November 2008 (UTC)

::::[[de:Genussgift]] redirects to [[de:Genussmittel]] and claims that this is a specific German concept (akin to &quot;Schadenfreude&quot; and &quot;Weltschmerz&quot;, neither of which has a good translation). &quot;Social drugs&quot; captures only some of the aspects, as coffee and tea are only drugs in a very limited interpretation. &quot;Recreational substances&quot;? &quot;Recreational stimulants&quot;? &quot;Pleasure poisons&quot; is a literal translation and has a nice alliteration, but is not really encyclopedic. &quot;Social stimulants&quot; might work. --[[User:Stephan Schulz|Stephan Schulz]] ([[User talk:Stephan Schulz|talk]]) 17:13, 17 November 2008 (UTC)
::::: &quot;Recreational stimulants&quot; sounds good. [[User:Future Perfect at Sunrise|Fut.Perf.]] [[User talk:Future Perfect at Sunrise|☼]] 17:19, 17 November 2008 (UTC)
:::::: How about &quot;The Stimulants for Enjoyment&quot;? Keep the present structure, just replace &quot;drug&quot; with &quot;stimulant&quot;. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 17:26, 17 November 2008 (UTC)
::::::: Actually &quot;The Stimulants for Enjoyment&quot; and &quot;The Recreational Stimulants&quot; will mean the same. The later suggests the same meaning in a shorter form, thus better. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 17:31, 17 November 2008 (UTC)
::::::::The first is not good, it has a very different connotations. If you like the structure, the best I can come up with is &quot;Stimulants for Enjoyment&quot; (note plural and no article - the English definite article is more definite than the German), but I still like either &quot;Social stimulants&quot; or &quot;Recreational stimulants&quot; better. --[[User:Stephan Schulz|Stephan Schulz]] ([[User talk:Stephan Schulz|talk]]) 17:41, 17 November 2008 (UTC)
::::::::: To Otolemur: we shouldn't be trying to be too literal with that translation, including the definite article and all that (which sounds decidedly unidiomatic in English, and rather old-fashioned in German.) The translation is only meant to give an idea of what that journal title was about. Just &quot;Recreational stimulants&quot; fits the bill. [[User:Future Perfect at Sunrise|Fut.Perf.]] [[User talk:Future Perfect at Sunrise|☼]] 17:47, 17 November 2008 (UTC)
::::::::::Ok, agree. I think we have found the solution. I am changing it per Stephan Schulz's suggestion. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 17:50, 17 November 2008 (UTC)
:::::Sorry to be a latecomer to the discussion, but &quot;recreational drugs&quot; is a more common phrase in English. For something like this, a sort of &quot;guilty pleasure,&quot; it seems more apt than &quot;stimulants.&quot; [[User:Sca|Sca]] ([[User talk:Sca|talk]]) 18:39, 17 November 2008 (UTC)
::::::&quot;Recreational drugs&quot; typically includes all drugs not taken for medical reasons, i.e. Marihuana, eXtasy, cocaine. Those are not included in the German term. --[[User:Stephan Schulz|Stephan Schulz]] ([[User talk:Stephan Schulz|talk]]) 20:22, 17 November 2008 (UTC)
::::Literally &quot;pleasure poisons&quot;. --[[User:Alex1011|Alex1011]] ([[User talk:Alex1011|talk]]) 19:18, 17 November 2008 (UTC)
:::::Actually I believe Stephan Schulz's suggestion is the best. As he pointed out, ''Genussgift'' is redirecting to ''Genussmittel'' in German Wikipedia. And ''Genussmittel'' means stimulant. The word &quot;drug&quot; will not apply for coffee and tea. Per [http://www.babylon.com/definition/Genussgift/English this] dictionary definition provided by Future perfect, ''Genussgift '' is stimulant, excitant, substance which excites. Thus &quot;Recreational Stimulant&quot; is the best translation. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 19:35, 17 November 2008 (UTC)
::::::But &quot;Gift&quot; is poison, and the people who use that word, mean it. Otherwise they would say Genussreizmittel or something like that. Maybe you cannot translate that word, if there was no political movement in the anglophone world to describe stimulants, drugs etc. as &quot;poison&quot;. The word Genussgift is polemical. Is &quot;recreational stimulant&quot; polemical? --[[User:Alex1011|Alex1011]] ([[User talk:Alex1011|talk]]) 19:52, 17 November 2008 (UTC)
:::::::You have a point. The word is &quot;Genussgifte&quot;. &quot;Genuss&quot; means enjoyment and &quot;gifte&quot; means toxin. Your argument that the word &quot;Genussgifte&quot; is polemical has a point, not sure if the present English translation polemical or not. I know very little German, and have almost no opinion on this translation issue. Waiting for input from Stephan Schulz and Future perfect, and others who know good German. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 14:22, 18 November 2008 (UTC)
::::::::As I pointed out, this is something that likely does not have a proper translation, since it has a number of connotation specific to the time and society that simply do not work in English. If we want to capture most of it, what about a parenthesized, or footnoted version? ''Die Genussgifte (&quot;Recreational Stimulants&quot;, lit. &quot;pleasure poisons&quot;)''? --[[User:Stephan Schulz|Stephan Schulz]] ([[User talk:Stephan Schulz|talk]]) 16:41, 18 November 2008 (UTC)
:::::::::Yeah, the footnote is a good idea. The current translation &quot;Recreational stimulants&quot; is fine, so keep it as it is. A footnote can be added detailing the various translations. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 17:03, 18 November 2008 (UTC)
::::::::::I would suggest &quot;pleasurable poisons.&quot; Hope I am not too late. This is one of the best-written articles I have seen on Wikipedia. [[User:Rumiton|Rumiton]] ([[User talk:Rumiton|talk]]) 14:10, 28 November 2008 (UTC)

== Section title ==

I am waiting for a consensus for the title of [[Anti-tobacco_movement_in_Nazi_Germany#Prelude|this]] section. This section was previously titled '''&quot;Prelude to Nazi anti-tobacco campaign&quot;''' [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Anti-tobacco_movement_in_Nazi_Germany&amp;oldid=252400237] when the article was promoted to featured status and appeared in main page. {{User|Ingolfson}} in [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Anti-tobacco_movement_in_Nazi_Germany&amp;diff=252736106&amp;oldid=252400237 this edit] changed the section title to '''&quot;Prelude&quot;'''. Which is better title, '''&quot;Prelude&quot;''' or '''&quot;Prelude to Nazi anti-tobacco campaign&quot;'''? A consensus is necessary. '''[[User:Otolemur crassicaudatus|&lt;font color=&quot;002bb8&quot;&gt;Otolemur crassicaudatus&lt;/font&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Otolemur crassicaudatus|talk]]) 10:00, 25 December 2008 (UTC)

* &quot;'''Prelude'''&quot; is better. From [[WP:HEAD|the manual of style]], &quot;Section names should not explicitly refer to the subject of the article.&quot; [[User:Axl|&lt;font color=&quot;#808000&quot;&gt;'''Axl'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;font color=&quot;#3CB371&quot;&gt;¤&lt;/font&gt; &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Axl|&lt;font color=&quot;#6B8E23&quot;&gt;[Talk]&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/small&gt; 10:57, 25 December 2008 (UTC)
*How about '''background'''? ~&lt;strong&gt;'''''[[User:Editorofthewiki|&lt;font color=&quot;#F900&quot;&gt;EDDY&lt;/font&gt;]]'' &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Editorofthewiki#top|&lt;font color=&quot;Green&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/Editorofthewiki|&lt;font color=&quot;Green&quot;&gt;contribs&lt;/font&gt;]]/[[Wikipedia:Editor review/Editorofthewiki|&lt;font color=&quot;Green&quot;&gt;editor review&lt;/font&gt;]])&lt;/sup&gt;'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;~ 15:58, 25 December 2008 (UTC)

== This is a brilliant article! ==

It should required reading for all the current Anti Fun Crew who want to ban all sources of pleasure and who are currently in the ascendant at the moment. [[User:SmokeyTheCat|&lt;span style=&quot;border:2px solid Red;padding:2px;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color:Black;background:Red&quot; size=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;SmokeyTheCat&amp;nbsp;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:SmokeyTheCat|&lt;font color=&quot;Red&quot; size = &quot;0&quot;&gt;•TALK•&lt;/font&gt;]] 19:09, 12 October 2009 (UTC)
:The greatest source of pleasure is ignorance, which is hard to either ban or suppress. Enjoy. And yes, this article is excellent, but I don't see it how it can be discouraging to the so-called &quot;Anti Fun Crew&quot;. --[[Special:Contributions/69.121.51.151|69.121.51.151]] ([[User talk:69.121.51.151|talk]]) 03:28, 27 June 2010 (UTC)

== Chronological inconsistency ==

Hello,

How the Nazis could start their anti-tobacco campaign &quot;After German doctors became the first to identify the link between smoking and lung cancer&quot; (very first sentence of the article) when the very first reference link points to a document dating back to 1940 only. The Nazi (or German) did not start their anti-tobacco campaign for this reason (&quot;fighting&quot; lung cancer) as it is chronologicaly impossible (the campaign started before 1940). The very first sentence in the article should be changed as it leads readers to think the anti-tobacco campaign in Germany was based upon lung cancer scientific materials, which can't be true from the first refence in the article.

Thank you.
[[User:WangTzu|WangTzu]] ([[User talk:WangTzu|talk]]) 15:40, 27 May 2010 (UTC)

: I do think it is consistent: the cited source, from 1940, cites earlier sources - for example: &quot;This is described in detail in the publication “The development of carcinoma in a smoking rabbit” (4) (1931).&quot; Poor rabbit. Thereby the cited source does back the claim that they made the connection at the beginning of the 1930's already.
: --[[User:Hugovdm|Hugovdm]] ([[User talk:Hugovdm|talk]]) 01:06, 2 November 2010 (UTC)

::The rest of the article demonstrates (among other sources) that the campaign started before 1930' too, so the &quot;fighing lung cancer anti-tobacco campaign&quot; idea as suggested by the very first sentence of the article is just wrong. The prelude contradicts the first sentence (hence Chronological inconsistency).  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/194.250.65.104|194.250.65.104]] ([[User talk:194.250.65.104|talk]]) 10:25, 4 March 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Fake or anachronistic cartoon? Filtered cigarettes not generally available until the 1950s ==

I would suggest that the cartoon is either a fake or was not from the Nazi Era. If you check Wikipedia's own article on Cigarette Filters you will find that although they were experimented with as early as 1927 there were very few of them available until the 1950s and even so the machine capable of producing them was in the UK, hardly a source of German Cigarettes - and definitely not during the Second World War. I feel that the cartoon is not authentic Nazi propaganda material, as it clearly depicts a filter cigarette. Thus there would be little point in centering the entire cartoon on an object which would be alien to the intended audience of the 1930s or early 1940s. A reliable source or citation should be provided. May I suggest that the cartoon could be from the 1950s - post Nazi - when austerity measures were still being encouraged in Germany? --[[User:MichaelGG|MichaelGG]] ([[User talk:MichaelGG|talk]]) 06:17, 4 October 2010 (UTC)

== How is this article necessary? Why is it ranking #2 under google search for &quot;anti-tobacco campaign history&quot;? ==

I find it highly offensive that this article attempts to link the anti-tobacco public health efforts to Nazi-ism and Hitler racism, anti-semitism, etc.

Why would there be such an effort to write something so pro-tobacco/smoking like this unless it's on behalf of big tobacco?

This does not reflect well on Wikipedia at all--especially since Wikipedia has deemed it as &quot;one of its best articles.&quot;

I request that you either remove this article, or at least stop promoting it on Google as associated with the general anti-tobacco public health campaigns.
[[User:Nikki 121212|Nikki 121212]] ([[User talk:Nikki 121212|talk]]) 22:49, 20 November 2010 (UTC)

:Shockingly, there are things (e.g. the Autobahn) which the Nazis did that were not crimes against humanity.  The Nazi program, its hypocrisy, dubious motivation, and its failure, are a major part of the early history of anti-smoking campaigns, and it's a perfectly valid topic for an encyclopedia article, and [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8973234 scholarly research] for that matter.  Honestly, the Nazis were pretty awful people, but an article about education in Nazi Germany wouldn't be seen as a polemic against education in general.  This article is no different.  [[User:SDY|SDY]] ([[User talk:SDY|talk]]) 08:41, 21 November 2010 (UTC)

Simply because the anti-tobacco movement are Nazi's, trying to impose THEIR ideals on the population, if people want to smoke, by all means let them, let's stop inflicting our own personal beliefs on others. [[User:Trumpy|Trumpy]] ([[User talk:Trumpy|talk]]) 12:02, 8 December 2010 (UTC)

&quot;Trumpy&quot;: &quot;Simply because the anti-tobacco movement are Nazi's&quot;... I couldn't have worded the bias agenda of this article any better. You are such an idiot and so is whoever wrote this article.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/71.23.38.90|71.23.38.90]] ([[User talk:71.23.38.90|talk]]) 01:04, 8 July 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Cigarette rationing ==

Why the article does not mention at all influence of wartime cigarette rationing on tobacco consumption? Wasn't cigarette rationing used as a tool of limiting civilian tobacco consumption too? (And certainly potentially much powerful one than propaganda) I'm not German, but I remember family stories, how my grandfather (on territory under German occupation) had been given (in 1941) an official ration of 25 cigarettes per week, which makes stories about percentage of people smoking 30 cigarettes per day a complete pipe-dream. The article is sorely missing any background information on German tobacco consumption in general, but it would certainly be helpful to give some general info on effects of wartime cigarette rationing. [[Special:Contributions/78.128.177.136|78.128.177.136]] ([[User talk:78.128.177.136|talk]]) 11:01, 22 April 2011 (UTC)

== Suppression of the anti-smoking cause ==

No German was executed for opposition to tobacco use. Sure, some of the major Nazi figures executed for war crimes (slave-trafficker Fritz Sauckel was one of them) were in the anti-smoking movement, but attributing their silencing by hanging to their opposition to tobacco is like saying that many of the executed Nazis were fans of classical music.

It is more significant that two of the victorious powers, the UK and the USA, had lucrative tobacco industries and of course wanted Germany to be a market for their lucrative tobacco industries. The full hazard of tobacco use may have been better known in Nazi Germany than in Britain or America, but by the 1960s the American medical profession had surpassed Nazi knowledge of the harmful effects of smoking upon health.[[User:Pbrower2a|Pbrower2a]] ([[User talk:Pbrower2a|talk]]) 02:42, 28 May 2011 (UTC)
:It took them only 20 years? Whow, ´murrica! [[Special:Contributions/89.204.135.52|89.204.135.52]] ([[User talk:89.204.135.52|talk]]) 23:45, 28 October 2015 (UTC)

== Present day tobacco industry context ==

A little context would be nice. This article should make some mention of how the events described are being used today by tobacco companies. &quot;The use of Nazi and health fascism rhetoric can be regarded as part of an institutionalised practice of the tobacco industry and its front groups to discredit tobacco control activities and prevent the introduction of effective policies.&quot;  http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2736555/  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/66.131.131.83|66.131.131.83]] ([[User talk:66.131.131.83|talk]]) 20:07, 23 July 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:: I looked briefly at the sources, but I don't really there is anything there beyond the term 'nazi' (and 'fascist') being used as synonyms for the overly controlling nanny state.  (Cf. Seinfeld's &quot;soup nazi&quot;). As it stands, the sentence is just confusing, and not notable enough - certainly not to warrant a place in the introductory section.  I'll just remove it - if you disagree, I suggest you add something clearer about it in a more appropriate section further down. [[User:Ketil|Ketil]] ([[User talk:Ketil|talk]]) 05:43, 27 April 2014 (UTC)

== Translation of Reichsstelle für Rauschgiftbekämpfung ==

I think that the person that tried to translate this term misread Rausch for Rauch and thus translated Rauschgift to smoke poisoning instead of (narcotic) drug. Or is there an error in the German term?
[[Special:Contributions/85.233.28.60|85.233.28.60]] ([[User talk:85.233.28.60|talk]]) 13:37, 29 June 2016 (UTC)

:Better now. Would [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Anti-tobacco_movement_in_Nazi_Germany&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=727536676&amp;oldid=727213682 that] be close enough?[[User:TracyMcClark|--TMCk]] ([[User talk:TracyMcClark|talk]]) 16:54, 29 June 2016 (UTC)

== Astelling The Truth ==

I'm  incredibly impressed by this article, being both an English and German speaker and kudos to the editor(s) for managing to produce such a balanced article. It must be an incredibly difficult task, steering a rational, NPOV, historical fact driven course between the pseudo-scientific claims &amp; vested interests of all sides of the argument both historical and modern etc.

One thing does however need some attention I think: &quot;at the University of Jena, headed by Karl Astel&quot;. I would suggest it be made clear that not only was KA 'rector' at Jena but also primarily a &quot;Racial Scientist&quot;. Not mentioning that fact might lead any reader to assume that KA was a serious scientist, not the man who gave the Nazis the 'Scientific' justification for the Holocaust. Perhaps something like &quot;headed by KA, the Reich's foremost Racial Scientist&quot; (yeah I would personally put 'scientist' in speech marks too but that's POV I guess) ? Also I haven't checked but wasn't the Jena Uni the 'SS-Uni' by that time?[[Special:Contributions/31.48.13.249|31.48.13.249]] ([[User talk:31.48.13.249|talk]]) 14:21, 14 August 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Anti-tobacco movement in Nazi Germany]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=744488924 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20081014053354/http://www.environmentaloncology.org/files/file/secrethistorysupport/Chapt%203%20References/REF%207%20proctor.pdf to http://environmentaloncology.org/files/file/secrethistorysupport/Chapt%203%20References/REF%207%20proctor.pdf

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 15:24, 15 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>79mixufntbx2bapo8zl29mgssue2fqy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
