<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Hoover Dam</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>80682</id>
    <revision>
      <id>724074654</id>
      <parentid>724032364</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-06-07T00:17:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lowercase sigmabot III</username>
        <id>17518500</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Archiving 2 discussion(s) to [[Talk:Hoover Dam/Archive 1]]) (bot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7908">{{Talk header}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=PR
|action1date=14:04, 23 June 2010
|action1link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Hoover Dam/archive1
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=369723368
|action2=FAC
|action2date=17:10, 2 July 2010
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Hoover Dam/archive1
|action2result=promoted
|action2oldid=371404635
|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=30 September 2010
}}
{{Vital article|level=4|topic=Technology|class=FA}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject National Register of Historic Places|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Nevada|class=FA|importance=High|Las Vegas=yes|Las Vegas-importance=top}}
{{WikiProject Energy|class=FA|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Dams|class=FA|importance=top}}
{{WikiProject Arizona|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject National Archives|importance=Mid|class=FA}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2004-04-20|oldid1=3262364|date2=2012-03-01|oldid2=479681988|date3=2016-03-01|oldid3=707706555}}
{{Wikipedia CD selection}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{atnhead|noredlinks=y}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 1
|minthreadsleft = 4
|algo = old(100d)
|archive = Talk:Hoover Dam/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Archive box|auto=long|search=yes|bot=MiszaBot I|age=100}}

== Image, revisited ==

I got there today.  I'm unclear how I can get to the area south of the bridge without getting arrested.  Help?  I intended to be there all day tomorrow, or until I got the image(s) I want, but now I wonder if today's drive was a waste of time. - [[User:Denimadept|Denimadept]] ([[User talk:Denimadept|talk]]) 05:41, 19 April 2014 (UTC)
:I don't know.  I saw nothing obvious when I was there.  Let us know you're OK please.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 21:33, 19 April 2014 (UTC)
::You were able to get to the area south of the bridge?  How? - [[User:Denimadept|Denimadept]] ([[User talk:Denimadept|talk]]) 03:00, 20 April 2014 (UTC)
:::No, I men, I saw no obvious way to get there.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 04:42, 20 April 2014 (UTC)
::::I think I just figured it out.  If you're going to the dam from US93, you get off at the obvious place.  If you're going south, there's a 4-way intersection at the bottom of the ramp.  Left goes to the dam.  Straight gets back on US93.  RIGHT... goes to something called the [[Gold Strike Hot Springs Trail]] Head (no article, dammit).  I'll try that on my way through tomorrow morning.  Google Maps shows a trail (maybe) to where I'm talking about.  Volcanism near the Colorado River?  By the dam?  Really??  If you're going north on US93, go LEFT at the bottom of the ramp, straight under the overpass, and straight.  Hm, maybe not something to do in a few minutes: [https://plus.google.com/105086258450855638290/about?hl=en&amp;gl=us Gold Strike Hot Springs Trail reviews] says it may take 6 hours round trip.  Also, the driving may be trouble for normal cars.  Sounds like something to do with a buddy, lots of water, and a good amount of time.  So the reason the Hoover Dam people don't know about it would be because it's outside of their purview. - [[User:Denimadept|Denimadept]] ([[User talk:Denimadept|talk]]) 07:06, 20 April 2014 (UTC)

== Largest reservoir ==

The department of interior says that is is the largest by volume. [http://www.usbr.gov/pmts/eco_research/eco5.html] I tend to believe them. If someone has an [[reservoir]] that is larger by volume in the US when we can discuss. Based on edit summaries one key point here is that a lake is not a reservoir. The [[WP:RS]] clearly states that it is the largest. Note also [[List of reservoirs by volume]] has Lake Mead as the largest. Lets use [[WP:BRD]]. I have reverted back to what the original source says for now. [[User:XFEM Skier|XFEM Skier]] ([[User talk:XFEM Skier|talk]]) 17:32, 29 August 2014 (UTC)
:That was my point in the initial revert.  As far as I know, Lake Meade is the largest reservoir.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 17:45, 29 August 2014 (UTC)

== Role in irrigation and water supply ==

I came here to learn how the dam contributes to agriculture.  All the article says about that is &quot;Water released from the Hoover Dam eventually reaches the All-American Canal for the irrigation of over 1,000,000 acres (400,000 ha) of land. Water from the lake serves 8 million people in Arizona, Nevada and California.&quot;  On one hand it does not say whether the dam supplies much or all or just a little of the water in the All-American canal, nor does it say whether all or much or only a little part of the water from the dam reaches that canal.  Does the dam supply other major water distribution systems?  The environmental impact section never describes the environmental impact of watering those 1,000,000 acres.  The article says very little about the economic effects of the irrigation.  I do not know about these things.  But the talk page shows some people do, and I think those topics deserve more attention. [[User:Colin McLarty|Colin McLarty]] ([[User talk:Colin McLarty|talk]]) 13:29, 15 October 2015 (UTC)
:There's a section at the bottom of the article called &quot;See also&quot; I'm adding [[Water_in_California]]. There is a link to the [[All-American_Canal]], not sure if that will answer your questions. In Arizona there's the [[Central Arizona Project]] that delivers water to Phoenix, Tucson and farms. And, I'm sure if you looked at articles on California, Nevada and Arizona there would be details about agriculture. There has recently been a lot of news about the salty run-off from the farms served by the All American Canal and lower Colorado River around Yuma AZ and what to do with it and also allowing [[Colorado_River]] water to reach Mexico and the [[Colorado River Delta|gulf/delta]] ecosystem. If you want to add anything to the articles, please use a reference. I watch most of these articles so if you make a mistake, I can help correct it. [[User:Raquel Baranow|Raquel Baranow]] ([[User talk:Raquel Baranow|talk]]) 13:54, 15 October 2015 (UTC)
::The reason there isn't much detail is because the Hoover Dam is upstream of much of the canals. Two major canals, the [[Central Arizona Project]] (water to Arizona) and the [[Colorado River Aqueduct]] (mostly drinking water to Southern California) come off [[Lake Havasu]], created by [[Parker Dam]]. [[Colorado_River#Engineering_and_development|This section of the Colorado River article]] explains it all pretty well. I do agree there should be more detail, or w/ls to guide readers to the info. I did add some detail on the three major canals with links to the article. Hopefully that satisfies the need. I don't think the environmental impacts of that irrigation should be included in Hoover Dam but rather the respective articles on those projects and dams.--[[User:NortyNort|NortyNort]]  &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:NortyNort|(Holla)]]&lt;/small&gt; 12:10, 16 October 2015 (UTC)

== Post-2017 power allocations ==

For planning purposes, I was looking into when the contracts will go into force under the modified power allocation regime that is to begin in 2017 (apparently in October).  Per [http://crc.nv.gov/2017hooverallocation/files/20140826-28%20WAPA%20BCP%20Post%202017%20Proposed%20Allocations-PIF.PDF this], there seem to be some 58 successful applicants in addition to the existing ones, and so the power allocation table is going to get very long.  Do we want to keep it in the article, collapse it when it gets long, move it to another page (possibly [[List of entities contracting for power from Hoover Dam]]) or something else?  Or just wait until 2017?--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 17:30, 6 June 2016 (UTC)
:Could combine the ones with less than 1%, etc. [[User:Raquel Baranow|Raquel Baranow]] ([[User talk:Raquel Baranow|talk]]) 18:28, 6 June 2016 (UTC)
That makes sense.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 18:49, 6 June 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>k4k8f73eknxuhirm904s7w2iqc7nkcf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
