<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>1946 Pilbara strike</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5297713</id>
    <revision>
      <id>740531219</id>
      <parentid>738283343</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-21T17:05:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Working conditions for Aboriginal pastoral workers */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14686">{{more footnotes|date=February 2013}}

The '''1946 Pilbara strike''' was a landmark [[Strike action|strike]] by [[Indigenous Australian]] pastoral workers in the [[Pilbara]] region of [[Western Australia]] for [[human rights]] recognition and payment of fair wages and working conditions. The strike involved at least 800 Aboriginal pastoral workers walking off the large Pastoral Stations in the Pilbara on 1 May 1946, and from employment in the two major towns of [[Port Hedland, Western Australia|Port Hedland]] and [[Marble Bar, Western Australia|Marble Bar]]. The strike did not end until August 1949 and even then many indigenous Australians refused to go back and work for white station owners.&lt;ref name=CP&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.creativespirits.info/aboriginalculture/politics/1946-pilbara-strike-australias-longest-strike|title=1946 Pilbara strike - Australia’s longest strike|year=2012|accessdate=27 July 2014|publisher=Creative Spirits}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is regarded as one of the longest industrial strikes in Australia, and a landmark in indigenous Australians fighting for their human rights, [[cultural rights]], and [[Native title]].

==Working conditions for Aboriginal pastoral workers==

For many years Aboriginal pastoral workers in the Pilbara were denied cash wages and were only paid in supplies of tobacco, flour and other necessities.&lt;ref name=CP/&gt; The pastoral stations treated the Aboriginal workers as a cheap slave labour workforce to be exploited. If they tried to leave the station, they were found and brought back by the police, according to McLeod.

European attacks and brutal shootings of whole family groups of indigenous Australians are part of the history of the region, though often not well documented. One attack took place at [[Skull Creek]] near [[Barrow Creek, Northern Territory|Barrow Creek]] in the 1870s, which resulted in the bleached bones and thus the name for the place &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?isbn=1876756152|title=Daughters of the Dreaming|author=Diane Bell|year=2002|accessdate=13 January 2014|publisher=Spinifex Press|ISBN=9781876756154}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is a well documented report of a massacre in 1926 by a police party on the Forrest River Mission (now the Aboriginal community of [[Oombulgurri Community, Western Australia|Oombulgurri]]), in the [[Kimberley region of Western Australia|East Kimberleys]]. Though there was a [[Royal commission]] into the reported killing and burning of Aborigines in East Kimberley, the police allegedly involved were  brought to trial and acquitted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Of Massacres, Missionaries, Myths and History Wars|url=http://aiatsis.gov.au/asp/docs/Contents%20Sample%20Chaps%20Index/loos/LoosSamplechapter.pdf|publisher=Aboriginal Studies Press|accessdate=13 January 2014|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140114105702/http://aiatsis.gov.au/asp/docs/Contents%20Sample%20Chaps%20Index/loos/LoosSamplechapter.pdf|archivedate=14 January 2014|format=PDF|year=2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;
(see [[List of massacres of indigenous Australians]]).

As well as proper wages and better working conditions, Aboriginal lawmen sought natural justice arising from the original Western Australian colonial Constitution. As a condition for self-rule in the colony, the British Government insisted that once public revenue in WA exceeded 500,000 pounds, 1 per cent was to be dedicated to &quot;the welfare of the Aboriginal natives&quot; under Section 70 of the Constitution.[http://www.treaty.murdoch.edu.au/Conference%20Papers/Steven%20Churches.htm] Succeeding colonial and state Governments legislated to remove the funding provisions for 'native welfare'. Aboriginal plaintiffs from Strelley Station finally commenced an action in the State Supreme Court in 1994 [https://web.archive.org/web/20080324000105/http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/journals/AboriginalLB/1996/54.html], seeking a declaration that the 1905 repeal was invalid. In 2001, after protracted litigation, the High Court held that the 1905 repeal had been legally effective [http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/high_ct/2001/47.html]{{dead link|date=June 2015}}.

==The strike==

The strike was coordinated and led by Aboriginal lawmen [[Dooley Bin Bin]] and [[Clancy McKenna]]; and Don McLeod, an active unionist&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.greenleft.org.au/node/33993|title=Pilbara: Australia's longest strike|date=6 May 2006|accessdate=27 July 2014|publisher=Green Left Weekly}}&lt;/ref&gt; and member of the [[Communist Party of Australia]] for a short period. According to McLeod in his book, ''How the West was Lost'' self-published in 1984, the strike was planned at an Aboriginal law meeting in 1942 at [[Skull Creek|Skull Springs]] (east of [[Nullagine, Western Australia|Nullagine]]), where a massacre had previously occurred. The meeting was attended by an estimated 200 senior Aboriginal law men representing twenty three language groups from much of the remote north west of Australia. Discussions were protracted with the meeting lasting six weeks. McLeod was given the task of chief negotiator. The strike was postponed until after the Second World War had ended.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://yamatjimarlpa.blogspot.com.au/2011/07/naidoc-profile-pilbara-pastoral-workers.html|title=NAIDOC profile: the Pilbara pastoral workers' strike|date=7 July 2011|accessdate=27 July 2014|publisher=Yamatji Marlpa Aboriginal Corporation}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Crude calendars were taken from one station camp to another in early 1946 to organise the strike. The efforts, if noticed by the white people present, were dismissed and laughed at. When 1 May 1946 occurred hundreds of Aboriginal workers left the pastoral stations and setup strike camps.

The strike was most effective in the Pilbara region. Further afield in [[Broome, Western Australia|Broome]] and [[Derby, Western Australia|Derby]] and other inland northern towns, the strike movement was harshly suppressed by police action and was more short lived. Over the three years, occasionally strikers went back to work, while others joined or rejoined the strike.

At the commencement of the strike in 1946, Don McLeod was an [[Australian Workers' Union]] delegate at Port Hedland wharf who motivated support by the [[Australian labour movement]]. The Western Australian branch of the [[Maritime Union of Australia|Seamen's Union of Australia]] eventually put a blackban on the shipment of wool from the Pilbara. Nineteen unions in Western Australia, seven federal unions and four Trades and [[Labour council]]s supported the strike. The strike stimulated support from the [[Woman's Christian Temperance Union]], who helped establish the [[Committee for the Defense of Native Rights]]. This organisation raised funds for and publicised the strike in Perth including organising a public meeting in the Perth Town Hall attended by 300 people.

Many of the Aboriginal strikers served time in jail; some were seized by police at revolver point and put into chains for several days. At one stage in December 1946 Don McLeod was arrested in Port Hedland during the strike for 'inciting Aborigines to leave their place of lawful employment'; the Aboriginal strikers marched on the jail and McLeod was freed. McLeod was gaoled a total of seven times during the period, three times for being within five [[Chain (unit)|chains]] (100 m) of a congregation of natives, three times for inciting natives to leave their lawful employment, and once for forgery.

In one incident during the strike, two policemen were sent out to the Five Mile Camp near Marble Bar. When they arrived they commenced shooting the people's dogs, even when they were chained up between their legs. Shooting the dogs of Aborigines was considered by some frontier Europeans as a sport. On this occasion the endangering of human life angered the strikers who quickly disarmed the two policeman. The local strike leader, Jacob Oberdoo, and other strikers held the policemen until they had regained some composure and then arranged their own arrests insisting they be taken into custody.

Jacob Oberdoo was jailed three or four times and suffered humiliations and deprivations of many kinds during the strike, but maintained his dignity and solidarity for the length of the strike. In 1972 he was awarded the [[British Empire Medal]] but turned it down. McLeod described Oberdoo's reply to the Prime Minister rejecting the medal:
: &quot;he was unable to do business with, or accept favours from Law-carriers in bad standing. &quot;You pin medals on dogs&quot; was how he explained the real message underlying the award.&quot;

The strikers were forced to sustain themselves by their traditional bush skills, hunting kangaroos and goats for both meat and skins. They also developed some cottage industry which brought some cash payment such as selling buffel grass seed in Sydney, the sale of pearl shell, and in surface mining.

Wages and conditions were eventually won by the strikers on Mt. Edgar and Limestone Stations. These two became a standard, with the strikers declaring that any station requiring labour would have to equal or better the rates of pay and conditions operating on these two.

By August 1949, the Seamen's Union had agreed to blackban wool from stations in the Pilbara onto ships for export. On the third day after the ban had been applied, McLeod was told by a government representative that the strikers' demands would be met if the ban was lifted. A week after the strike ended and the ban was lifted, the government denied making any such agreement.

After the strike concluded many Aborigines refused to go back to working in their old roles in the pastoral industry. Eventually they pooled their funds from surface mining and other cottage industry to buy or lease stations, including some they had formerly worked on, to run them as cooperatives.

==Legacy==

The poet [[Dorothy Hewett]] visited Port Hedland in 1946 and wrote the poem ''Clancey and Dooley and Don McLeod'' about the strike,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://unionsong.com/u399.html|title=Clancy and Dooley and Don McLeod|first=Dorothy|last=Hewett|authorlink=Dorothy Hewett|work=Union Songs|accessdate=7 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; which was subsequently put to music by folk musician Chris Kempster and recorded by [[Roy Bailey (folk singer)|Roy Bailey]]. The 1959 documentary novel ''Yandy'' by [[Donald Stuart (novelist)|Donald Stuart]] deals with the strike.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Stuart|first=Donald|authorlink=Donald Stuart (novelist)|title=Yandy|url=http://trove.nla.gov.au/work/9512152?selectedversion=NBD2268207|accessdate=7 February 2013|year=1959|publisher=Georgian House|location=Melbourne}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1987 a documentary film was made about the strike by director David Noakes, titled ''How the West was Lost''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aso.gov.au/titles/documentaries/how-west-was-lost/clip1/|title=How the West was Lost (1987)|accessdate=27 July 2014|publisher=[[National Film and Sound Archive]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Kangkushot, The Life of Nyamal Lawman Peter Coppin'', by Jolly Read and Peter Coppin, tells the story of Kangku's life including his leadership in the strike and after in setting up Yandeyarra station which still runs today. It was shortlisted for the 1999 [[Western Australian Premier's Book Awards]].

Yandy, a play written by Jolly Read, commissioned by Black Swan State Theatre Company, tells the story of the strike and its leaders and families. It won the 2004 Western Australian Premier's Book Award for best script and is published in Collection #6 by the Australian Script Centre.

Four streets in the [[Canberra, Ausralia|Canberra]] suburb of [[Bonner, Australian Capital Territory|Bonner]] were named after the strike leaders in 2010. Clancy McKenna Crescent, Dooley Bin Bin Street, Peter Coppin Street and Don McLeod Lane were all named after the men instrumental in organizing the strike.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wangkamaya.org.au/pilbara-history-and-culture/01-the-1946-strike|title=The 1946 Strike|year=2014|accessdate=27 July 2014|publisher=Wangka Maya Pilbara Aboriginal Language Centre}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
* McLeod, D. W.(1984) ''How the West was lost : the native question in the development of Western Australia'' Port Hedland, W.A. The author.
* Roberts, Janine (1978) ''From Massacres to Mining'' ISBN 0-905990-05-6

==Further reading==
*{{cite book|title=The Black Eureka|first=Max|last=Brown|first2=Dorothy|last2=Hewett|publisher=Australasian Book Society|location=Sydney|year=1976|ISBN=0909916764|url=http://trove.nla.gov.au/work/9523853?versionId=45252079|accessdate=7 February 2013}}

==External links==
* [http://www.greenleft.org.au/node/33993 Pilbara: Australia's longest strike] Green Left Weekly
* [http://www.reasoninrevolt.net.au/biogs/E000282b.htm Pilbara Strike (1946 - 1949)] - Brief description
* [http://www.abc.net.au/message/tv/ms/s1335203.htm Peter Coppin, Pilbara elder and lawman] ABC TV ''Messagestick'' program broadcast 1 April 2005
* [http://www.strelleynomadgroup.com/photos.html Photos of the Strike Leaders] Strelley Nomad Group
* [http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/other/IndigLRes/car/1997/3/speeches/seminar1/george.htm The role of unions in the dispute] - Jennie George, ACTU President
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20050315030844/http://home.vicnet.net.au/~aar/mcleod.htm Rebel of the Pilbara] newspaper article transcribed from [[the Age]] 2 May 1996
* [http://www.austlii.edu.au/cgi-bin/sinodisp/au/cases/cth/HCATrans/1996/406.html?stem=0&amp;synonyms=0&amp;query=Judamia Aboriginal Citizens and the Western Australian Constitution: Judamia &amp; Ors v State of Western Australia]
* [http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/high_ct/2001/47.html Yougarla v Western Australia (2001) HCA 47 (9 August 2001)]{{dead link|date=June 2015}}
* [http://www.treaty.murdoch.edu.au/Conference%20Papers/Steven%20Churches.htm The Story of a Promise made to Western Australia's Aborigines] Dr Steven Churches, Barrister and Senior Lecturer in Law, University of Adelaide
* [http://www.roninfilms.com.au/video/0/135/1832181.html How the West was Lost] (1987) Ronnin Films

{{Portal|Organized labour}}
{{Indigenous Australians}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:1946 Pilbara Strike}}
[[Category:1946 labor disputes and strikes|Pilbara Strike, 1946]]
[[Category:1947 labor disputes and strikes]]
[[Category:1948 labor disputes and strikes]]
[[Category:1949 labor disputes and strikes]]
[[Category:1946 in Australia|Pilbara strike]]
[[Category:Indigenous Australian politics]]
[[Category:Labour disputes in Australia]]
[[Category:History of Western Australia]]
[[Category:Pilbara]]
[[Category:Agriculture and forestry strikes]]
[[Category:20th century in Western Australia]]

{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2013}}</text>
      <sha1>85kv50bnnpggawxxwhdfm5x342g6evq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
