<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>3D Systems</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4234010</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745310212</id>
      <parentid>745310060</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-20T11:57:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Helleba</username>
        <id>1103650</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="28652">{{ infobox company
|name             = 3D Systems Corporation
|logo             = 3D Systems Logo.png
|type             = [[Public company|Public]]
|traded_as        = {{NYSE|DDD}}
|industry         =
|foundation       = [[Valencia, California|Valencia]], [[California]], [[United States|U.S.]] ({{Start date|1986}})
|location_city    = [[Rock Hill, South Carolina|Rock Hill]], [[South Carolina]]
|location_country = U.S.
|area_served      = [[World]]wide
|key_people       = [[Vyomesh Joshi]] (VJ)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;([[President]] &amp; [[Chief executive officer|CEO]])&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[Chuck Hull]] &lt;small&gt;([[Chief technology officer|CTO]])&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[Andrew Johnson]] &lt;small&gt;(Chief Legal Officer)&lt;/small&gt;
| products = [[3D Printing|3D Printers]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Stereolithography|Stereolithography Systems]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Selective laser sintering|Sintering Systems]]&lt;br /&gt;Engineered Materials

| caption = Manufacturing Innovation
| num_employees = 2,100
| revenue = {{profit}} [[United States Dollar|US$]]666.2 million &lt;small&gt;(2015)&lt;/small&gt;
| operating_income = {{loss}} [[United States Dollar|US$]]641.9 million &lt;small&gt;(2015)&lt;/small&gt;
| net_income     = {{loss}} [[United States Dollar|US$]]655.492 million &lt;small&gt;(2015)&lt;/small&gt;
| assets     = {{decrease}} [[United States dollar|US$]]893.3 million &lt;small&gt;(2015)
| equity     = {{decrease}} [[United States dollar|US$]]654.6 million&lt;small&gt;(2015)&lt;/small&gt;
| market cap = US$1.61 billion &lt;small&gt;10/20/2016&lt;/small&gt;
| homepage = {{url|www.3dsystems.com}}
}}

'''3D Systems''', headquartered in [[Rock Hill, South Carolina]], is a company that engineers, manufactures and sells [[3D printer]]s. [[Chuck Hull]], currently the CTO and former president, invented [[stereolithography]] in 1986.&lt;ref&gt;[[U.S. Patent]] [http://www.google.com/patents/US4575330 4,575,330] (“Apparatus for Production of Three-Dimensional Objects by Stereolithography”)&lt;/ref&gt;  3D Systems creates product concept models, precision and functional [[prototype]]s, master patterns for tooling, as well as production parts for [[direct digital manufacturing]].  3D Systems uses proprietary processes to fabricate physical objects using input from [[computer-aided design]] and manufacturing software, or [[3D scanner|3D scanning]] and [[Digital sculpting|3D sculpting]] devices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.3dsystems.com/about-us | title=About 3D Systems | publisher=3D Systems | accessdate=23 November 2014 | deadurl=no&lt;!--present in archive.org--&gt; }}&lt;/ref&gt;

3D Systems' technologies and services are used in the design, development and production stages of many industries, including aerospace, automotive, architecture, health care, dental, entertainment, recreation and consumer goods.  3D Systems offers professional- and production-grade 3D printers, in addition to a line of personal 3D printers and 3D-printed consumer products, supported by the affiliated online forum Cubify.  3D Systems is notable within the [[3D printing]] industry for developing [[stereolithography]] and the [[STL (file format)|STL]] file format.

== History ==
3D Systems was founded in [[Valencia, California]], by [[Chuck Hull]], the inventor and patent-holder of the first [[stereolithography]] (SLA) [[rapid prototyping]] system.  Prior to Hull's introduction of SLA rapid prototyping, concept models required extensive time and money to produce.  The innovation of SLA to reduce these resource expenditures while increasing the quality and accuracy of the resulting model. Early SLA systems were complex and costly, however, and required extensive redesign before achieving commercial viability.  Primary issues concerned hydrodynamic and chemical complications.  In 1996 the introduction of [[solid-state laser]]s permitted Hull and his team to reformulate their materials.  Engineers in transportation, health care and consumer products helped fuel early phases of 3D Systems' rapid prototyping research and development.  These industries remain key followers of 3D Systems' technology.

In 2003, Hull was succeeded by Avi Reichental.  Both Reichental and Hull are listed among the top twenty most influential people in rapid technologies by TCT Magazine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=Staff | title=The TCT Top 20 | work=TCT Magazine | publisher=Rapid News Publications | location=United Kingdom | url=http://www.tctmagazine.com/TCTTop20 | accessdate=23 November 2014 | deadurl=no&lt;!--present in archive.org--&gt; }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Hull remains an active member of 3D Systems' board and serves as the company's Chief Technology Officer and Executive Vice President.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.google.com/finance?q=ddd&amp;ei=RYueU7iuIummigLIroCwDQ | title=3D Systems Corporation: NYSE:DDD quotes &amp; news | website=[[Google Finance]] | at=Officers and Directors |publisher=Google | accessdate=23 November 2014 | deadurl=no&lt;!--present in archive.org--&gt; }}&lt;/ref&gt;  3D Systems relocated its headquarters to Rock Hill, South Carolina, citing a favorable business climate, a sustained lower cost of doing business, and significant investment and tax benefits as reasons for the move.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author=Staff | title=California 3D-Technology Firm To Relocate Headquarters to Rock Hill, SC | date=5 November 2005 | url=http://wraltechwire.com/business/tech_wire/news/story/1163149/ | work=WRAL TechWire | publisher=[[Capitol Broadcasting Company]] | location=United States | subscription=yes | deadurl=no&lt;!--entry page found in archive.org--&gt; }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2015, Reichental stepped down as the president and CEO of 3D Systems, Inc. and was replaced, on an interim basis, by the company's Chief Legal Officer Andrew Johnson.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release | publisher=3D Systems | via=3D Systems | url=http://www.3dsystems.com/press-releases/3d-systems-announces-departure-president-and-ceo | title=3D Systems Announces Departure of President and CEO | date=29 October 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 4th, 2016, the 3D Systems board appointed Vyomesh Joshi (VJ) as President and CEO.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release | publisher=3D Systems | via=3D Systems | url=http://www.3dsystems.com/press-releases/printing-innovator-and-leader-vyomesh-joshi-takes-helm-3d-systems-chief-executive | title=Printing Innovator and Leader, Vyomesh Joshi Takes Helm as 3D Systems' Chief Executive Officer | date=4 April 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Growth ==
In late 2001 3D Systems began an acquisitions program that expanded the company's technology through ownership of software, materials, printers and printable content, as well as access to the skills of engineers and designers.  The rate of 3D Systems' acquisitions (16 in 2011) raised some eyebrows with regard to the task facing the company's management team.  Other onlookers point to the encompassing scope of the acquisitions as indicating calculated steps by 3D Systems to consolidate the 3D printing industry under one roof and logo, to become a comprehensive one-stop-shop capable of servicing each link in the scan/create-to-print chain.&lt;ref name=&quot;pfeifle2012&quot;&gt;{{cite web | last=Pfeifle | first=Sam | date=10 October 2012 | website=Head in the Point Clouds (blog) | title=A brief history of 3D Systems acquisitions | url=https://www.sparpointgroup.com/Blogs/Head-in-the-Point-Clouds/A-brief-history-of-3D-Systems-acquisitions/ | publisher=[[SPAR Point Group]] | deadurl=yes | archivedate=14 March 2013 | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130314023900/https://www.sparpointgroup.com/Blogs/Head-in-the-Point-Clouds/A-brief-history-of-3D-Systems-acquisitions/ }}{{unreliable source?|date=November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

3D Systems now employs over 2400 people in 25 offices worldwide.  Through its acquisitions, 3D Systems has achieved a strong and growing presence in Asia-Pacific (China, Korea, Japan) and Europe (France, Germany, Switzerland, Italy, the United Kingdom), in addition to expanding its brand of print materials, printers, industrial and professional CAD software, on-demand custom parts services, data capture and scanning technologies, and customizable, ready-to-print consumer collections.  3D Systems' corporate statements indicate the company's desire to facilitate user creation and &quot;remove expert/user friction between content creation and print.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author=Johnson, Cory | authorlink=Cory Johnson | title=Printing in 3D | date=25 April 2012 | url=http://www.bloomberg.com/video/90540409-3d-systems-ceo-shows-model-printing-technology.html | work=[[Bloomberg West]] | publisher=[[Bloomberg Television]] | location=United States | format=Video | deadurl=no&lt;!--video not retained in archive.org, but abstract text is--&gt; }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2011, 3D Systems transferred from [[NASDAQ]] (TDSC) to the [[New York Stock Exchange]] (DDD).  Company stock has risen with general consistency since its entry to the exchange, as have company revenues and profits.  In 2012, a Gray Wolf Report predicted 3D Systems' rate of growth to be unsustainable, pointing to inflated impressions from acquisitions as a corporate misstatement of organic growth.  3D Systems responded to this article on November 19, 2012, claiming it to &quot;contain materially false statements and erroneous conclusions that we believe defamed the company and its reputation and resulted in losses to our shareholders.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SA Transcript&quot;&gt;{{cite web | author=Staff | title=3D Systems' CEO Hosts Recent Articles Discussion Conference (Transcript) | url=http://seekingalpha.com/article/1018051-3d-systems-ceo-hosts-recent-articles-discussion-conference-transcript | date=19 November 2012 | publisher=[[Seeking Alpha]] | location=United States | subscription=yes | deadurl=no&lt;!--present in archive.org--&gt; }}  ''Note: the first page of the 9 page transcript is available without registration.''&lt;/ref&gt;  One offending article was removed as a result.  Sequential increases in earnings from actual sales and steady climbs in stock price per share provide reasonable cause for skepticism towards this report.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=Staff | title=3D Systems Earnings Smash Short Theory For Now | url=http://seekingalpha.com/article/964021-3d-systems-earnings-smash-short-theory-for-now | publisher=[[Seeking Alpha]] | date=31 October 2012 | subscription=yes }}  ''Note: the first of two pages is available without registration.''&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2014 it was announced that 3D Systems had acquired the Burbank, Ca-based collectibles company Gentle Giant LTD.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.actionfigureinsider.com/3d-systems-acquires-gentle-giant-studios/&lt;/ref&gt; Gentle Giant Ltd. designs, develops, and manufactures three-dimensional representations of characters from a variety of franchise properties with worldwide name recognition, including [[Star Wars]], [[The Matrix]], [[Harry Potter (film series)|Harry Potter]], [[The Simpsons]], Hellboy Animated, Disney Dragonkind, Animated Pirates of the Caribbean, Lord of the Rings, Red Star, Terminator, Charlie and the Chocolate Factory and Corpse Bride. Gentle Giant Ltd. produces a wide range of products including mini busts, statues, Bust-Ups, action figures, 12&quot; figures and models. Gentle Giant Ltd.'s products are manufactured using the highest quality of polyresin, resin, plastic, PVC and ABS. Utilizing the most advanced laser-scanning techniques and a team of incredibly talented artisans, Gentle Giant digitally captures the likenesses of actors, props, and scenery to accurately recreate these images for fans and collectors everywhere.

In July 2014, 3D Systems announced an acquisition of Israeli [[medical imaging]] company Simbionix for {{currency|120000000|US}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Weinreb, Gali |url=http://www.globes.co.il/en/article-3d-systems-acquires-simbionix-for-120m-1000959570 |title=3D Systems acquires Simbionix for $120m |work=[[Globes]] |date=31 July 2014 |location=Israel |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140802025133/http://www.globes.co.il/en/article-3d-systems-acquires-simbionix-for-120m-1000959570 |archivedate=August 2, 2014 }}&lt;!-- not productively archived in archive.org --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2014, 3D Systems acquired the Belgian company LayerWise. The terms of the acquisition were not disclosed by the companies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release | url=http://www.3dsystems.com/press-releases/3d-systems-acquires-layerwise-extending-its-global-leadership-advanced-metal-3d | publisher=3D Systems | title=3D Systems Acquires LayerWise, Extending its Global Leadership in Advanced Metal 3D Printing, On-Demand Parts Manufacturing Services and Personalized Medical Devices | date=3 September 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The company is based in Leuven, a town in Belgium close to Brussels. It is a principal provider of services in the area of direct metal 3D printing and manufacturing.  The company was a spin-off of the University of Leuven.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.layerwise.com/home/company/ | title=Company | publisher=LayerWise | accessdate=17 January 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The takeover adds Belgium to the list of countries where 3D Systems has active locations.

In January 2015, 3D Systems acquired the 3D printer manufacturer botObjects, the first company to commercialize a printer using the [[fused deposition modeling]] technique.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release | publisher=3D Systems | via=Desktop Engineering (Peerless Media) | url=http://www.deskeng.com/de/3d-systems-acquires-botobjects/ | title=3D Systems Acquires botObjects | date=13 January 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2015, 3D Systems announced it acquired the Easyway Group of companies in China, creating 3D Systems China. Easyway is a Chinese 3D printing sales and service provider with key operations in Shanghai, Wuxi, Beijing, Guangdong and Chongqing.&lt;ref&gt;By Chris Lange, 24/7 Wall St. “[http://247wallst.com/technology-3/2015/04/06/3d-systems-hopes-acquisition-in-china-will-help/ 3D Systems Hopes Acquisition in China Will Help].” April 6, 2015. April 6, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Technology ==
3D Systems manufactures stereolithography (SLA), selective laser sintering (SLS) color-jet printing (CJP), fused deposition modeling (FDM), multi-jet printing (MJP) and direct metal sintering (DMS).  Each technology takes digital input from three-dimensional data to create three-dimensional parts through an additive, layer-by-layer process.  The systems vary in their materials, print capacities and applications.

* [[Stereolithography]], or SLA, was invented by 3D Systems’ founder Chuck Hull.  Stereolithography describes the method and apparatus for making solid objects in a vat of liquid photopolylmer using ultraviolet curable material and a laser to trace the digital design.  SLA systems print with supports and are advantageous due to the speed and possible size of prints (size depends on the build volume of the particular machine).  SLA systems can also rapidly manufacture parts of different geometries at the same time and are designed to produce prototypes, patterns or end-use parts of versatile sizes and applications.  SLA parts are strong enough to be machined and can be used as master patterns for [[injection moulding|injection molding]], [[thermoforming]], [[blow molding]] and various metal casting processes.
* [[Selective laser sintering]], or SLS, is an additive manufacturing technique that uses a high power laser to fuse small particles together.  Material options are wide, including plastic, metal, ceramic, nylon, polystrene or glass powders.  In many cases, SLS is an efficient process because large numbers of parts can be printed in one session.  SLS does not require any support structures, as parts are surrounded by unsintered powder at all times.
* Color jet printing uses inkjet technology to deposit a liquid binder across a bed of powder.  Powder is released and spread with a roller to form each new layer.  This technology was originally developed by [[Z Corporation]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.3dscentral.3dsystems.com&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Fused deposition modeling]] is handled by 3D Systems' hobbyist level printer line.  These printers use a heated extruder to deposit a thermoplastic along complex toolpaths, one layer at a time.  A good visual model of this is using a hot glue gun to build a 3d model.  The hot glue gun (a hand powered extruder) would have to build things one layer at a time, depositing a string roughly the width of the extruder orifice.  Once a layer has cooled and hardened, the next layer can be built until the model is complete.  FDM limitations include time (it must travel along complex toolpaths), color (only one color can be printed at a time), and durability (inter-layer adhesion is analogous to a cold solder).  This is generally the least expensive type of printer available.
*Multi-Jet printing refers to the process of depositing liquid [[photopolymer]]s onto a build surface using inkjet technology.  High resolution is attainable with a support material that can be easily removed in post processing.  Unlike FDM, these parts are generally too brittle for snap-fits.  However, lower durometer (softer) parts are possible with newer model MJP printers.  This allows the user to create rubbery or hard plastic parts for more diverse applications.
* [[Direct metal laser sintering|Direct Metal Sintering]] refers to the 3D Systems metal printing process.  This process spreads fine powders of diverse metal alloys out onto a printbed, and fuses geometries together using an overhead laser beam.  This technology is used primarily in medical and aerospace applications, where low volumes of unique and complex models are needed.

== Products and patents ==
As part of 3D Systems' effort to consolidate 3D printing under one logo, its products span a range of 3D printers and print products to target all potential consumers of its technologies.  The three branches of printers offered by 3D Systems are personal, professional, and production.  Though production-grade printers formed the early backbone of the company, 3D Systems' extension to professional and personal printers follows the company's reported desire to &quot;level the playing field&quot; in manufacturing and open up access to the resources that have traditionally been reserved for deep-pocketed companies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=3D Printing's Future|url=http://www.wired.com/video/3d-printings-future/1651267404001|publisher=Wired|format=Video}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In addition to printers, 3D Systems offers content creation software to consumers unversed in CAD, with the expressed hope of making content creation &quot;as simple and intuitive as a video game.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=3D Systems CEO Shows Model Printing Technology|url=http://bloom.bg/HP2yYQ#ooid=UycDlnNDoEPWvRekWu9UhH2jhj6X00lp|publisher=Bloomberg|format=Video}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Following a razors and blades business model, 3D Systems offers more than one hundred materials to be used with its printers, including waxes, rubber-like materials, metals, composites, plastics and nylons.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Next Big Thing: 3D Printing&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=The Next Big Thing: 3D Printing|url=http://video.cnbc.com/gallery/?video=3000074927|publisher=CNBCFast Money|format=Video}}&lt;/ref&gt;

3D Systems is a closed-source company, relying on in-house innovation for product development and improvement, and a protective shield of patents to advantage its technologies over competitors'.  Critics of the closed-source model have blamed seemingly slow development and innovation in 3D printing not on a lack of technology, but on a lack of open information sharing within the industry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=How Patents Have Held Back 3D Printing|url=http://www.techdirt.com/articles/20120130/16535017591/how-patents-have-held-back-3d-printing.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Supporters of the closed source model argue that the right to patents inspires and motivates higher-quality innovations, leading to a better and more impressive final product.

In November 2012, 3D Systems filed a lawsuit against prosumer 3D printer company [[Formlabs]] and the [[Kickstarter]] crowdfunding website over Formlabs attempt to fund a printer which it claimed infringed its patent on “Simultaneous multiple layer curing in stereolithography.”&lt;ref&gt;Rob Giseburt, [http://blog.makezine.com/2012/11/21/3d-systems-suing-formlabs-and-kickstarter-for-patent-infringement/ 3D Systems Suing Formlabs and Kickstarter for Patent Infringement], Make:, 21 November 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

3D Systems has applied for patents for the following innovations and technologies: the rapid prototyping and manufacturing system and method; radiation curable compositions useful in image projection systems; compensation of actinic radiation intensity profiles for 3D modelers; apparatus and method for cooling part cake in laser sintering; radiation curable compositions useful in solid freeform fabrication systems; apparatus for 3D printing using imaged layers; compositions and methods for selective deposition modeling; edge smoothness with low resolution projected images for use in solid imaging; elevator and method for tilting solid image build platform for reducing air entrapment and for build release; selective deposition modeling methods for improved support-object interface; region-based supports for parts produced by solid freeform fabrication; additive manufacturing methods for improved curl control and sidewall quality; support and build material and applications.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=TDSC - 3D Systems Corp. patents|url=http://stks.freshpatents.com/TDSC-sym.php|publisher=Fresh Patents}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Applications and industries ==
3D Systems’ products and services are used across industries to assist, either in part or in full, the design, manufacture and/or marketing processes.  3D Systems' technologies and materials are used for prototyping and the production of functional end-use parts, in addition to fast, precise design communication.  Current 3D Systems-reliant industries include automotive, aerospace and defense, architecture, dental and healthcare, consumer goods and manufacturing.

Examples of industry-specific applications include:
* ''Aerospace'', for the manufacture and tooling of complex, durable and lighter-weight flight parts
* ''Architecture'', for structure verification, design review, client concept communication, reverse structure engineering, and expedited scaled modeling
* ''Automotive'', for design verification, difficult visualizations, and new engine development
* ''Defense'', for lightweight flight and surveillance parts and the reduction of inventory with on-demand printing
* ''Dentistry'', for restorations, molds and treatments. [[Invisalign]] orthodontics uses 3D Systems' technologies
* ''Education'', for equation and geometry visualizations and art schools and design initiatives
* ''Entertainment'', for the manufacture and prototyping of action figures, toys, games and game components; printing of sustainable guitars and basses, multifunction synthesizers, etc.
* ''Healthcare'', for customized hearing aids and prosthetics, improved medicine delivery methods, respiratory devices, therapeutics, and flexible endoscopy and laparoscopy devices for improved procedures and recovery times
* ''Manufacturing'', for faster product development cycles, mold production, prototypes, and design trouble-shooting

For industries such as aerospace and automotive, 3D Systems' technologies have reduced the time needed to incorporate design drafts and enabled the production of more efficient parts of lighter weight.  Because 3D printing builds layer-by-layer according to design, it does not need to accommodate the traditional manufacturing tools of subtractive methods, often resulting in lighter parts and more efficient geometries.

== Facilities and employees ==
In 2007, the company consolidated its offices, operations, and research and development functions into a new global headquarters in Rock Hill, South Carolina, US. About half of the headquarters’ {{convert|80000|sqft|m2}} consist of research and development laboratories with an {{convert|18000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} Rapid Manufacturing Center (RMC) with 3D Systems’ [[rapid prototyping]], [[rapid manufacturing]] and [[3D printing]] systems at work.&lt;ref&gt;[http://desktop3dprinters.us/3d-print/3d-systems/ 3D Systems]&lt;/ref&gt;

With customers in 80 countries, 3D Systems has over 2100 employees in 25 worldwide locations, including [[San Francisco]], [[France]], [[Germany]], [[Italy]], [[Switzerland]], the [[United Kingdom]], [[China]], Korea and [[Japan]]. The company has more than 359 U.S. and foreign [[patent]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://3dsystems.com/company/patents/index.asp |title=Company Patents |work= |publisher=3Dsystems.com |date= |accessdate=2006-06-10 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060422033639/http://www.3dsystems.com/company/patents/index.asp |archivedate=April 22, 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Community involvement and partnerships ==
3D Systems is involved in a multi-year agreement with the [[Smithsonian Institution]] as part of a Smithsonian-wide effort to strengthen collections' stewardship and increase collection accessibility through 3D representations.  This partnership is part of the company's attempt to broadcast the capabilities and applications of 3D printing while increasing &quot;the visibility and accessibility of our national treasures.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=3D Systems Partners With the Smithsonian on Landmark 3D Digitization Project|url=http://finance.yahoo.com/news/3d-systems-partners-smithsonian-landmark-130000639.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2012, 3D Systems began partnering with the 90-year-old Scholastic Art &amp; Writing Awards in the Future New category.  For this branch of the Scholastic Awards, students will be challenged to express bold and innovative ideas using new technologies.  3D Systems will offer students free 3D design software to facilitate their creations and will award three winners with a $1000 scholarship.  This money is in addition to the prizes and recognition granted winners by the Scholastic Awards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Future New - Scholastic Art &amp; Writing Award New Category|url=http://connect.nwp.org/nwp-makes/blog/22349/future-new-scholastic-art-writing-award-new-category|publisher=NWP.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

3D Systems is a corporate underwriter of the National Children's Oral Health Foundation: America's ToothFairy® (NCOHF). NCOHF provides community programs to deliver educational, preventative and treatment oral health services to children in at-risk populations.  3D Systems contributes its 3D content-to-print solutions and Cubify capabilities to the NCOHF effort.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=3D Systems Joins NCOHF: America’s ToothFairy|url=http://dentistrytoday.com/industry-news/7819-3d-systems-joins-ncohf-americas-toothfairy-|publisher=Dentistry Today}}&lt;/ref&gt;

3D Systems has contributed two production-grade 3D printers to the [[National Network for Manufacturing Innovation#Pilot institute|National Additive Manufacturing Innovation Institute]] (NAMII) in Youngstown, Ohio, the first center of a federal initiative to enhance the competitiveness of US industry.  The Youngstown institute is just one regional hub of the [[National Network for Manufacturing Innovation]] (NNMI), which aspires to build &quot;world-class centers for applied research, technology incubation and commercialization&quot; to re-localize manufacturing and strengthen US competitiveness.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=3D Systems Invests In U.S. Government’s Additive Manufacturing Institute|url=http://www.tctmagazine.com/articles/3d-systems-amii/|publisher=TCT Magazine}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On February 18 of 2014, [[Ekso Bionics]] debuted the first ever 3D printed hybrid exoskeleton robotic suit, in collaboration with 3D Systems.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.3dsystems.com/sites/www.3dsystems.com/files/2_18_2014_3d_systems_partners_with_ekso_bionics_to_3d_print_robotic-hybrid_exoskeleton_8.37.48_am.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://eksobionics.com/pressrelease |title=Press Releases - Ekso Bionics Holdings, Inc. (EKSO) |publisher=Eksobionics.com |date= |accessdate=2014-08-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[3D printing]]
* [[Chuck Hull]]
* [[Fused deposition modeling]]
* [[List of 3D printer manufacturers]]
* [[Selective laser sintering]]
* [[Stereolithography]]
* [[STL (file format)|STL]]

== References ==
{{reflist|33em}}

==External links==
* {{Official website|http://www.3dsystems.com}}

[[Category:1986 establishments in California]]
[[Category:Companies listed on the New York Stock Exchange]]
[[Category:3D printer companies]]
[[Category:Computer-aided design]]
[[Category:Companies based in South Carolina]]
[[Category:Companies established in 1986]]
[[Category:Multinational companies headquartered in the United States]]
[[Category:Publicly traded companies of the United States]]
[[Category:Technology companies of the United States]]
[[Category:Fused filament fabrication]]</text>
      <sha1>c961lcif4sgh6e014t8p2txs2s6cu7f</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
