<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.28.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2600" case="first-letter">Topic</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Blasphemy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>90469</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745575713</id>
      <parentid>745575547</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-21T23:35:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TechBear</username>
        <id>421630</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Restoring more deleted material.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="57909">{{Other uses}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2011}}
[[File:Brooklyn Museum - The Execution of Mansur Hallaj From the Warren Hastings Album.jpg|thumb|Sufi teacher [[Mansur Al-Hallaj]] was executed in Baghdad for blasphemy in 922. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Avery|first1=Kenneth|title=Psychology of Early Sufi Sama: Listening and Altered States|date=2004|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0415311069|page=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
'''Blasphemy''' is the act of insulting or showing contempt or lack of [[Deference|reverence]] to a [[deity]], to religious or holy persons or [[sacred]] things, or toward something considered [[sacred]] or [[Sanctity of life|inviolable]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = On blasphemy|last = Miriam Díez Bosch and Jordi Sànchez Torrents|publisher = Blanquerna Observatory on Media, Religion and Culture|year = 2015|isbn = 978-84-941193-3-0|location = Barcelona}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/blasphemy |title=Blasphemy |publisher=Random House Dictionary |accessdate=12 January 2015|quote=Quote: impious utterance or action concerning God or sacred things.; the crime of assuming to oneself the rights or qualities of God.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/blasphemy Blasphemy] Merriam Webster (July 2013); 1. great disrespect shown to God or to something holy&lt;br&gt;2. irreverence toward something considered sacred or inviolable&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Blasphemies'', in Webster's New World College Dictionary, 4th Ed,&lt;br&gt;1. profane or contemptuous speech, writing, or action concerning God or anything held as divine.&lt;br&gt;2. any remark or action held to be irreverent or disrespectful&lt;/ref&gt;

Some religions consider blasphemy as a religious crime.&lt;ref name=wsj&gt;[http://www.wsj.com/articles/blasphemy-divide-insults-to-religion-remain-a-capital-crime-in-muslim-lands-1420673864 Blasphemy Divide: Insults to Religion Remain a Capital Crime in Muslim Lands] The Wall Street Journal (January 8, 2015)&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2012, anti-blasphemy laws existed in 32 countries, while 87 nations had hate speech laws that covered defamation of religion and public expression of hate against a religious group.&lt;ref name=pewres&gt;[http://www.pewforum.org/2012/11/21/laws-penalizing-blasphemy-apostasy-and-defamation-of-religion-are-widespread/ Laws Penalizing Blasphemy, Apostasy and Defamation of Religion are Widespread] Pew Research (November 21, 2012)&lt;/ref&gt; Anti-blasphemy laws are particularly common in Muslim-majority nations, such as those in the Middle East and North Africa,&lt;ref name=pewres/&gt; although they are also present in some Asian and European countries.

=={{Anchor|History}}Etymology==
The word &quot;blasphemy&quot; came via [[Middle English]] ''blasfemen'' and [[Old French]] ''blasfemer'' and [[Late Latin]] ''blasphemare'' from [[Greek language|Greek]] βλασφημέω, from βλάπτω &quot;injure&quot; and φήμη &quot;utterance, talk, speech&quot;. From ''blasphemare'' also came Old French ''blasmer'', from which English &quot;[[blame]]&quot; came. Blasphemy: 'from Gk. blasphemia &quot;a speaking ill, impious speech, slander,&quot; from blasphemein &quot;to speak evil of.&quot;'&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?allowed_in_frame=0&amp;search=blasphemy |title=Online Etymology Dictionary – Blasphemy |publisher=Etymonline.com |accessdate=10 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;In the sense of speaking evil of God this word is found in Ps. 74:18; Isa. 52:5; Rom. 2:24; Rev. 13:1, 6; 16:9, 11, 21. It denotes also any kind of calumny, or evil-speaking, or abuse (1 Kings 21:10 [[Septuagint|LXX]]; Acts 13:45; 18:6, etc.).&quot;&lt;ref&gt;(from Easton's Bible Dictionary) {{bibleref2|Romans.2:24||9}} – {{bibleref2|Revelation.13:1;Rev.13:6;Rev.16:9;Rev.16:11;Rev.16:21||9}} – {{bibleref2|1Kings.21:10;Acts.13:45;Acts.18:6||9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Blasphemy laws==
[[File:Blasphemy laws worldwide.svg|thumb|right| {{legend|#f9dc36|Local restrictions}} {{legend|#ec8028|Fines and restrictions}} {{legend|#e73e21|Prison sentences}} {{legend|#800000|Death sentences}}]]
{{Main article|Blasphemy law}}
In [[Blasphemy law|some countries]] with a [[state religion]], blasphemy is outlawed under the criminal code.  Such laws have led to the persecution, lynchings, murder or arrest of minorities and dissident members, after flimsy accusations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.economist.com/news/asia/21635070-pakistans-blasphemy-laws-legitimise-intolerance-bad-mouthing Bad-mouthing: Pakistan’s blasphemy laws legitimise intolerance] The Economist (November 29, 2014)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sources of claims:
* [http://www.religiouswatch.com/rwworld.htm World of Intolerance] ''Religious Watch''. Retrieved 5 October 2011
&lt;!-- Multiple MALWARE threats 5Oct2011, this URL disabled: h*t*t*p://www.christianpost.com/article/20091113/100-groups-oppose-u-n-defamation-of-religions-proposals/index.html --&gt;
* [http://www.iheu.org/united-nations-will-violate-human-rights-says-new-report-religious-freedoms United Nations will violate Human Rights] ''International Humanist and Ethical Union''. Retrieved 5 October 2011
* {{cite web
| url = http://www.heraldmalaysia.com/news/Muslim-scholar-says-Scrap-blasphemy-laws-which-bring-shame-on-Islam-and-Pakistan-2058-1-1.html
| title = Muslim scholar says Scrap blasphemy laws
| date = 11 August 2009
| work = Herald Malaysia Online
| accessdate = 5 October 2011
}}
* [http://www.uscirf.gov/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=1414&amp;Itemid=1 Annual Report of the U.S. Commission on International Religious Freedom] May 2009 (Pakistan, etc.). Retrieved 5 October 2011
* [http://www.unhchr.ch/Huridocda/Huridoca.nsf/TestFrame/af783bb51170854380256739004faac4?Opendocument A call upon states to work toward abolishing the juvenile death penalty] U.N. January 1999. Retrieved 5 October 2011
* [http://report2009.amnesty.org/en/regions/asia-pacific/indonesia Indonesia – Amnesty International Report 2009] ''Amnesty International''. Retrieved 5 October 2011
&lt;/ref&gt;

As of 2012, 33 countries had some form of anti-blasphemy laws in their legal code.&lt;ref name=pewres/&gt; Of these, 20 were Muslim-majority nations – Afghanistan, Algeria, Bahrain, Egypt, Indonesia, Iran, Jordan, Kuwait, Malaysia, the Maldives, Morocco, Oman, Pakistan, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Somalia, Sudan, Turkey, the UAE and the Western Sahara. The other twelve nations with anti-blasphemy laws in 2012 were Denmark, Finland, Germany, Greece, India, Ireland, Italy, Lebanon, Malta, the Netherlands (abolished in 2014), Nigeria, Poland and Singapore.&lt;ref name=pewres/&gt; Blasphemy was treated as a [[capital crime]] (death penalty) in many Muslim nations.&lt;ref name=wsj/&gt;

Other countries have removed the ban of blasphemy. France did so in 1881 to allow freedom of religion and freedom of the press and blasphemy was abolished or repealed in Sweden in 1970, Norway with Acts in 2009 and 2015, the Netherlands in 2014, Iceland in 2015, and Malta in 2016.

Where blasphemy is banned, it can be either some laws which directly punish religious blasphemy,&lt;ref&gt;See [[Blasphemy law]]&lt;/ref&gt; or some laws that allow those who are offended by blasphemy to punish blasphemers. Those laws may condone penalties or retaliation for blasphemy under the labels of [[blasphemous libel]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web  | last = Kerr  | first = ine  | title = Libel and blasphemy bill passed by the Dail  |work=The Irish Independent  | date = 9 July 2009  | url = http://www.independent.ie/national-news/libel-and-blasphemy-bill-passed-by-the-dail-1813479.html  | accessdate = 17 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; expression of opposition, or &quot;vilification,&quot; of religion or of some religious practices,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/legis/qld/consol_act/aa1991204/s124a.html |title=ANTI-DISCRIMINATION ACT 1991 – SECT 124A 124A Vilification on grounds of race, religion, sexuality or gender identity unlawful |publisher=Austlii.edu.au |accessdate=10 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.police.vic.gov.au/content.asp?document_id=23370 |title=Victoria Police – Racial and religious vilification |publisher=Police.vic.gov.au |accessdate=10 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; religious insult,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://merlin.obs.coe.int/redirect.php?id=11512 |title=European Commission for Democracy through Law (Venice Commission), '&amp;#39;Report on the relationship between freedom of expression and freedom of religion: the issue of regulation and prosecution of blasphemy, religious insult and incitement to religious hatred'&amp;#39;, 17–18 October 2008, Doc. No. CDL-AD(2008)026 |publisher=Merlin.obs.coe.int |accessdate=10 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; or [[hate speech]].&lt;ref&gt;See [[Blasphemy law]] and [[Hate speech]].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Christianity==
{{anchor|Blasphemy in Christianity}}

[[Christian theology]] condemns blasphemy. It is spoken of in [[Gospel of Mark|Mark]] [[s:Bible (World English)/Mark#3:29|3:29]], where blaspheming the [[Holy Spirit]] is spoken of as unforgivable—the [[eternal sin]]. However, there is dispute over what form this blasphemy may take and whether it qualifies as blasphemy in the conventional sense; and over the meaning of &quot;unforgivable&quot;. In 2 Kings 18, the [[Rabshakeh]] gave the word from the king of Assyria,{{Clarify|reason=unclearly phrased|date=September 2015}} dissuading trust in the Lord, asserting that God is no more able to deliver than all the gods of the land.

In {{bibleref2|Matthew|9:2-3}}, Jesus told a paralytic &quot;your sins are forgiven&quot; and was accused of blasphemy.

Blasphemy has been condemned as a serious, or even the most serious, sin by the major creeds and Church theologians ([[apostasy]] and [[infidel]]ity [unbelief] were generally considered to be the gravest sins, with [[heresy]] a greater sin than blasphemy, cf. Thomas Aquinas' ''Summa Theologiae'').&lt;ref&gt;ST II-II q10a3, q11a3, q12. Q11A3: &quot;With regard to heretics two points must be observed: one, on their own side; the other, on the side of the Church. On their own side there is the sin, whereby they deserve not only to be separated from the Church by excommunication, but also to be severed from the world by death. For it is a much graver matter to corrupt the faith which quickens the soul, than to forge money, which supports temporal life. Wherefore if forgers of money and other evil-doers are forthwith condemned to death by the secular authority, much more reason is there for heretics, as soon as they are convicted of heresy, to be not only excommunicated but even put to death.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Thomas Aquinas]] says that “[if] we compare murder and blasphemy as regards the objects of those sins, it is clear that blasphemy, which is a sin committed directly against God, is more grave than murder, which is a sin against one's neighbor. On the other hand, if we compare them in respect of the harm wrought by them, murder is the graver sin, for murder does more harm to one's neighbor, than blasphemy does to God.”&lt;ref&gt;Thomas Aquinas: [http://www.newadvent.org/summa/3013.htm#article3 ''Summa Theologica''] 2:2, q. 13.&lt;/ref&gt;
*The [[Book of Concord]] calls blasphemy “the greatest sin that can be outwardly committed”.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bookofconcord.org/lc-3-tencommandments.php ''The Book of Concord''] ''The Large Catechism,'' §55.&lt;/ref&gt;
*The ''[[Baptist Confession of Faith]]'' says: “Therefore, to swear vainly or rashly by the glorious and awesome name of God…is sinful, and to be regarded with disgust and detestation. …For by rash, false, and vain oaths, the Lord is provoked and because of them this land mourns.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spurgeon.org/~phil/creeds/bcof.htm#part23 The Baptist Confession of Faith] Ch. 23, §2–3.&lt;/ref&gt;
*''The [[Heidelberg Catechism]]'' answers question 100 about blasphemy by stating that “no sin is greater or provokes God's wrath more than the blaspheming of His Name”.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wts.edu/resources/heidelberg.html The Heidelberg Catechism] Q. 100.&lt;/ref&gt;
*The ''[[Westminster Confession of Faith|Westminster Larger Catechism]]'' explains that “The sins forbidden in the third commandment are, the abuse of it in an ignorant, vain, irreverent, profane...mentioning...by blasphemy...to profane jests, ...vain janglings, ...to charms or sinful lusts and practices.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reformed.org/documents/wlc_w_proofs/WLC_091-150.html Westminster Larger Catechism] Q. 113.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Jean Calvin|Calvin]] found it intolerable “when a person is accused of blasphemy, to lay the blame on the [[wiktionary:ebullition|ebullition]] of passion, as if God were to endure the penalty whenever we are provoked.”&lt;ref&gt;Jean Calvin: ''[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/calvin/calcom06.ii.xvii.html Harmony of the Law]'' vol. 4. Lev. 24:10.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Catholic prayers and reparations for blasphemy===
In the Catholic Church, there are specific prayers and devotions as [[Acts of Reparation]] for blasphemy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://catholicism.about.com/od/prayers/qt/Reparation_HN.htm Act of Reparation for Blasphemies Uttered Against the Holy Name, Righting Wrongs Through Prayer] By Scott P. Richert, About.com&lt;/ref&gt; For instance, [[The Golden Arrow Holy Face Devotion (Prayer)]] first introduced by Sister [[Marie of St Peter]] in 1844 is recited &quot;''in a spirit of reparation for blasphemy''&quot;. This devotion (started by Sister Marie and then promoted by the Venerable [[Leo Dupont]]) was approved by Pope [[Leo XIII]] in 1885.&lt;ref&gt;* Dorothy Scallan. The Holy Man of Tours. (1990) ISBN 0-89555-390-2&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Raccolta]]book includes a number of such prayers.&lt;ref&gt;Joseph P. Christopher et al., 2003 ''The Raccolta'', St Athanasius Press ISBN 978-0-9706526-6-9&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Five First Saturdays]] devotions are done with the intention in the heart of making reparation to the Blessed Mother for blasphemies against her, her name and her holy initiatives.

The [[Holy See]] has specific &quot;Pontifical organizations&quot; for the purpose of the reparation of blasphemy through [[Acts of Reparation to Jesus Christ]], e.g. the ''Pontifical Congregation of the [[Benedictine Sisters of the Reparation of the Holy Face]].''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/letters/2000/documents/hf_jp-ii_let_20001021_riparatrici_en.html Letter for 50th anniversary of the Benedictine Sisters of Reparation of the Holy Face, 2000] Vatican archives&lt;/ref&gt;

===Punishment===
The most common punishment for blasphemers was [[capital punishment]] through hanging or stoning, justified by the words of {{bibleref2|Leviticus|24:13-16}}. 
{{quote|Then the Lord spoke to Moses, saying, “Bring out of the camp the one who cursed, and let all who heard him lay their hands on his head, and let all the congregation stone him. And speak to the people of Israel, saying, Whoever curses his God shall bear his sin. Whoever blasphemes the name of the Lord shall surely be put to death. All the congregation shall stone him. The sojourner as well as the native, when he blasphemes the Name, shall be put to death.&quot;}}

The last person hanged for blasphemy in Great Britain was [[Thomas Aikenhead]] aged 20, in Scotland in 1697. He was prosecuted for denying the veracity of the Old Testament and the legitimacy of Christ's miracles.&lt;ref name=truth&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www25.uua.org/uuhs/duub/articles/thomasaikenhead.html |title=Thomas Aikenhead |publisher=5.uua.org |accessdate=10 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Blasphemy (and [[blasphemous libel]]) [[Blasphemy law in the United Kingdom|remained a criminal offence]] in England &amp; Wales until the passing of the [[Criminal Justice and Immigration Act 2008]], but was last successfully prosecuted in the case of ''[[Whitehouse v Lemon]]'' (1977), where the defendant was fined £500 and given a nine-month suspended prison sentence (the publisher was also fined £1,000).

==Islam==
[[File:Salman-Rushdie-1.jpg|thumb|Writer [[Salman Rushdie]] was accused of blasphemy and subject of a ''[[fatwā]]'' issued by [[Ayatollah]] [[Ruhollah Khomeini]], the [[Supreme Leader of Iran]], in February 1989.]]
{{Main article|Islam and blasphemy}}
In Islamic literature, blasphemy is of many types, and there are many different words for it: ''sabb'' (insult) and ''shatm'' (abuse, vilification), ''takdhib'' or ''tajdif'' (denial), ''iftira'' (concoction), ''la`n'' or ''la'ana'' (curse) and ''ta`n'' (accuse, defame).&lt;ref&gt;See:
*Siraj Khan, Blasphemy against the Prophet, in Muhammad in History, Thought, and Culture (ed: Coeli Fitzpatrick Ph.D., Adam Hani Walker), ISBN 978-1610691772, pp. 59-67;
*Hassner, R. E. (2011). Blasphemy and Violence. International Studies Quarterly, 55(1), pages 23-4;
*Lewis, Bernard. &quot;Behind the Rushdie affair.&quot; ''The American Scholar'' 60.2 (1991), pages 185-196;
*Stanfield-Johnson, R. (2004). The tabarra'iyan and the early Safavids. Iranian Studies, 37(1), pages 47-71&lt;/ref&gt; In Islamic literature, the term blasphemy sometimes also overlaps with [[infidel]] (''kufr'', disbeliever), ''fisq'' (depravity), ''isa'ah'' (insult), and ''ridda'' (apostasy).&lt;ref&gt;Talal Asad, in Hent de Vries (Ed.), Religion: Beyond a Concept, Fordham University Press (2008), ISBN 978-0823227242; pages 589-592&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=lw/&gt; There are a number of [[sura]]h in Qur'an and [[sunnah]] in hadith relating to blasphemy, from which Quranic verses 5:33-34 and 33:57-61 have been most commonly used in Islamic history to justify and punish blasphemers.&lt;ref name=khan&gt;Siraj Khan, Blasphemy against the Prophet, in Muhammad in History, Thought, and Culture (ed: Coeli Fitzpatrick Ph.D., Adam Hani Walker), ISBN 978-1610691772, pp. 59-67&lt;/ref&gt; For example,&lt;ref name=khan/&gt;

{{quote|The only punishment of those who wage war against Allah and His Messenger and strive to make mischief in the land is that they should be murdered, or crucified, or their hands and their feet should be cut off on opposite sides, or they should be imprisoned. This shall he a disgrace for them in this world, and in the Hereafter they shall have a grievous chastisement. Except those who repent before you overpower them; so know that Allah is Forgiving, Merciful.|[[Qur'an]]|{{quran-usc|5|33|end=34}}||}}

{{quote|Those who annoy Allah and His Messenger - Allah has cursed them in this World and in the Hereafter, and has prepared for them a humiliating Punishment. Truly, if the Hypocrites, and those in whose hearts is a disease, and those who stir up sedition in the City, desist not, We shall certainly stir thee up against them: Then will they not be able to stay in it as thy neighbours for any length of time: They shall have a curse on them: whenever they are found, they shall be seized and slain (without mercy).|[[Qur'an]]|{{quran-usc|33|57|end=61}}||}}

A variety of actions, speeches or behavior can constitute blasphemy in Islam. Some examples include insulting or cursing Allah, or Muhammad; mockery or disagreeable behavior towards beliefs and customs common in Islam; criticism of Islam's holy personages. [[Apostasy in Islam|Apostasy]], that is, the act of abandoning Islam, or finding faults or expressing doubts about Allah (''ta'til'') and Qur'an, rejection of Muhammed or any of his teachings, or leaving the Muslim community to become an atheist is a form of blasphemy. Questioning religious opinions (fatwa) and normative Islamic views can also be construed as blasphemous. Improper dress, drawing offensive cartoons, tearing or burning holy literature of Islam, creating or using music or painting or video or novels to mock or criticize Muhammad are some examples of blasphemous acts.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aicp.ca/islamic-lessons/english/youth/the-islamic-education-series-book-5/chapter-of-belief/lesson-13-the-types-of-blasphemy-and-blasphemers/ Association of Islamic Charitable Projects, ''The Types of Blasphemy'' (2010)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lawton, D. (1993). Blasphemy. Univ of Pennsylvania Press&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;CW Ernst, in Eliade (Ed), ''Blasphemy - Islamic Concept'', The encyclopedia of religion, New York (1987)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Marshall and Shea (2011), ''Silenced'', Oxford University Press, ISBN 978-0199812288&lt;/ref&gt; In the context of those who are non-Muslims, the concept of blasphemy includes all aspects of [[infidel]]ity (kufr).

===Blasphemy in different Islamic schools of jurisprudence===
{{Main article|Blasphemy in Islam|Islamic criminal jurisprudence}}
The [[Quran]] does not explicitly mention any worldly punishment for blasphemy (''sabb allah'' or ''sabb al-rasul''), as it does for [[Apostasy in Islam|apostasy]] (''riddah''). Islamic jurisprudence ([[fiqh]]) of Sunni and Shia [[madhab]]s have declared different punishments for the religious crime of blasphemy, and they vary between schools. These are as follows:&lt;ref name = &quot;Saeed&quot;&gt;{{Cite book  | last = Saeed  | first = Abdullah  |author2=Hassan Saeed  | title = Freedom of Religion, Apostasy and Islam  | publisher = Ashgate Publishing Company  | year = 2004  | location = Burlington VT  | pages = 37–39  | isbn = 978-0-7546-3083-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wiederhold, Lutz. &quot;Blasphemy against the Prophet Muhammad and his companions (sabb al-rasul, sabb al-sahabah): The introduction of the topic into shafi'i legal literature and its relevance for legal practice under Mamluk rule.&quot;Journal of semitic studies 42.1 (1997): 39-70.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Saeed, Abdullah. &quot;AMBIGUITIES OF APOSTASY AND THE REPRESSION OF MUSLIM DISSENT.&quot; The Review of Faith &amp; International Affairs 9.2 (2011): 31-38.&lt;/ref&gt;

:[[Hanafi]] – views blasphemy as synonymous with apostasy, and therefore, accepts the repentance of apostates. Those who refuse to repent, their punishment is death if the blasphemer is a Muslim man, and if the blasphemer is a woman, she must be imprisoned with coercion (beating) till she repents and returns to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;
*Abu al-Layth al-Samarqandi (983), Mukhtalaf al-Riwayah, vol. 3, pp.&amp;nbsp;1298–1299
*Ahmad ibn Muhammad al-Tahawi (933), Mukhtasar Ikhtilaf al-Ulama, vol. 3, p.&amp;nbsp;504
*Ali ibn Hassan al-Sughdi (798); Kitab al-Kharaj; Quote: “أيما رجل مسلم سب رَسُوْل اللهِ صَلَّى اللهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ أو كذبه أو عابه أوتنقصه فقد كفر بالله وبانت منه زوجته ، فإن تاب وإلا قتل ، وكذلك المرأة ، إلا أن أبا حنيفة قَالَ: لا تقتل المرأة وتجبر عَلَى الإسلام”; Translation: “A Muslim man who blasphemes the Messenger of Allah, denies him, reproaches him, or diminishes him, he has committed apostasy in Allah, and his wife is separated from him. He must repent, or else is killed. And this is the same for the woman, except Abu Hanifa said: Do not kill the woman, but coerce her back to Islam.”&lt;/ref&gt; If a non-Muslim commits blasphemy, his punishment must be a [[tazir]] (discretionary, can be death, arrest, caning, etc.).&lt;ref&gt;Ahmad ibn Muhammad al-Tahawi (933), Mukhtasar Ikhtilaf al-Ulama, vol. 3, p. 504&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;P Smith (2003), Speak No Evil: Apostasy, Blasphemy and Heresy in Malaysian Syariah Law, UC Davis Journal Int'l Law &amp; Policy, 10, pp. 357-373;
*N Swazo (2014), The Case Of Hamza Kashgari: Examining Apostasy, Heresy, And Blasphemy Under Sharia, The Review of Faith &amp; International Affairs, 12(4), pp. 16-26&lt;/ref&gt;
:[[Maliki]] – view blasphemy as an offense distinct from, and more severe than apostasy. Death is mandatory in cases of blasphemy for Muslim men, and repentance is not accepted. For women, death is not the punishment suggested, but she is arrested and punished till she repents and returns to Islam or dies in custody.&lt;ref&gt;[[Qadi Ayyad|Qadi 'Iyad ibn Musa al-Yahsubi]] (1145), Kitab Ash-shifa (كتاب الشفاء بتعريف حقوق المصطفى), pp. 373-441 (Translated in English by AA Bewley, {{oclc|851141256}}, (Review Contents in [http://data.nur.nu/Kutub/English/Qadi-Iyad_Shifa_Aisha-Bewley-Table-of-Contents.pdf Part 4], Read [http://www.masud.co.uk/ISLAM/misc/alshifa/pt4ch1sec4.htm Excerpts from Part 4], Accessed on: January 10, 2015)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;D Jordan (2003), Dark Ages of Islam: Ijtihad, Apostasy, and Human Rights in Contemporary Islamic Jurisprudence, The. Wash. &amp; Lee Race &amp; Ethnic Anc. Law Journal, Vol. 9, pp. 55-74&lt;/ref&gt; A non-Muslim who commits blasphemy against Islam must be punished; however, the blasphemer can escape punishment by converting and becoming a devout Muslim.&lt;ref&gt;Carl Ernst (2005), &quot;Blasphemy: Islamic Concept&quot;, Encyclopedia of Religion (Editor: Lindsay Jones), Vol 2, Macmillan Reference, ISBN 0-02-865735-7&lt;/ref&gt;
:[[Hanbali]] – view blasphemy as an offense distinct from, and more severe than apostasy. Death is mandatory in cases of blasphemy, for both Muslim men and women, and repentance is not accepted.&lt;ref&gt;Abdullah Saeed and Hassan Saeed (2004), Freedom of Religion, Apostasy and Islam, Ashgate Publishing, ISBN 978-0754630838&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
*[[Ibn Taymiyyah]] (a [[Salafi]], related to Hanbali school), ''al-Sārim al-Maslūl ‘ala Shātim al-Rasūl'' (Translation: A ready sword against those who insult the Messenger), Published in 1297 AD in Arabic, Reprinted in 1975 and 2003 by Dar-ibn Hazm (Beirut)&lt;/ref&gt;
:[[Shafi’i]] – recognizes blasphemy as a separate offense from apostasy, but accepts the repentance of blasphemers. If the blasphemer does not repent, the punishment is death.&lt;ref name=lw&gt;L Wiederhold L, Blasphemy against the Prophet Muhammad and his companions (sabb al-rasul, sabb al-sahabah) : The introduction of the topic into Shafi'i legal literature, Jrnl of Sem Studies, Oxford University Press, 42(1), pp. 39-70&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;P Smith (2003), Speak No Evil: Apostasy, Blasphemy and Heresy in Malaysian Syariah Law, UC Davis Journal Int'l Law &amp; Policy, 10, pp. 357-373;
*F Griffel (2001), Toleration and exclusion: al-Shafi ‘i and al-Ghazali on the treatment of apostates, Bulletin of the School of Oriental and African Studies, 64(3), pp. 339-354&lt;/ref&gt;
:[[Ja'fari jurisprudence|Ja'fari]] (Shia) – views blasphemy against Islam, the Prophet, or any of the Imams, to be punishable with death, if the blasphemer is a Muslim.&lt;ref&gt;Ayatullah Abu al-Qasim al-Khoei (1992), Minhaj al-Salihin, vol. 2, pp. 43-45;
*Ali ibn Ahmad al-Amili al-Thani (1602), Sharh al-Luma al-Dimashqiya, vol. 9, pp. 194-195;
*Muhammad ibn al-Hassan al-Tusi (1067), Al-Nihaya, pp. 730-731 and Tadhib al-Ahkam,  vol. 10, p. 85;
*Ali ibn al-Hussein “Sharif al-Murtada” (1044). Al-Intisar, pp.&amp;nbsp;480–481;
*Ali ibn Babawaih al-Qummi al-Saduq (991), Al-Hidaya fi al-Usul wa al-Furu, pp.&amp;nbsp;295–297&lt;/ref&gt; In case the blasphemer is a non-Muslim, he is given a chance to convert to Islam, or else killed.&lt;ref&gt;Ali ibn al-Hussein al-Murtada (1044), Al-Intisar, pp. 480-481&lt;/ref&gt;

Some jurists suggest that the sunnah in [[hadith]]&lt;ref&gt;{{hadith-usc|usc=yes|Bukhari|3|45|687}}, {{hadith-usc|usc=yes|Bukhari|5|59|369}}&lt;/ref&gt; provide a basis for a death sentence for the crime of blasphemy, even if someone claims not to be an apostate, but has committed the crime of blasphemy. Some&lt;ref&gt;Declan O'Sullivan (2001), The Interpretation of Qur'anic Text to Promote or Negate the Death Penalty for Apostates and Blasphemers, Journal of Qur'anic Studies, 3(2), pp. 63-93&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/jan/20/islam-ghamidi-pakistan-blasphemy-laws Islamic scholar attacks Pakistan's blasphemy laws] Guardian 20 January 2010. Retrieved 23 January 2010&lt;/ref&gt; modern Muslim scholars contest that Islam supports [[blasphemy law]], stating that [[Ulama|Muslim jurists]] made the offense part of [[Sharia]].

The Islamic law considers blasphemy against Muhammad a more severe offense than blasphemy against God. Repentance can lead to forgiveness by God when God is blasphemed, however since Muhammad is no longer alive, forgiveness is not possible when Muhammad is blasphemed, and the Muslim community must punish his blasphemy by avenging blasphemer's death.&lt;ref name = &quot;Saeed&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jordan, David A. &quot;Dark Ages of Islam: Ijtihad, Apostasy, and Human Rights in Contemporary Islamic Jurisprudence, The.&quot; Wash. &amp; Lee Race &amp; Ethnic Anc. LJ 9 (2003): 55.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kamali, Mohammad Hashim. Freedom of expression in Islam. Cambridge: Islamic Texts Society, 1997.&lt;/ref&gt;

In Islamic jurisprudence, Kitab al [[Hudud]] and [[Tazir|Taz'ir]] cover punishment for blasphemous acts.&lt;ref&gt;Peters, R. (2005). Crime and punishment in Islamic Law: Theory and practice from the Sixteenth to the Twenty-First Century (Vol. 2). Cambridge University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://islaminstitut.de/uploads/media/Apostasy2.pdf|format=PDF|last=Schirrmacher|first=C.|year=2008|title= Defection from Islam: A Disturbing Human Rights Dilemma|website=islaminstitut.de}}&lt;/ref&gt; The penalties for blasphemy can include fines, imprisonment, flogging, amputation, hanging, or beheading.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.islamicvoice.com/April2006/QuestionHour-DrZakirNaik/ |title=Islamic Voice |publisher=Islamic Voice |accessdate=10 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many nations prescribe and carry out the death penalty for [[Apostasy in Islam|apostasy]], a similarly motivated action, and Pakistan and Egypt demand execution for some [[blasphemy law|blasphemers]]. Muslim clerics may call for revenge against an alleged blasphemer by issuing a [[fatwa]] (legal ruling), or simply provide guidelines on behaviors and lifestyle that is blasphemous. For example, in Malaysia, Islamic scholars issued a fatwa declaring [[yoga]] as blasphemous, because yoga is a form of spiritual practice in Hinduism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.welt.de/english-news/article2766685/Muslims-warned-to-avoid-blasphemous-yoga.html|title=Malaysia: Muslims warned to avoid blasphemous yoga - DIE WELT|date=22 November 2008|work=DIE WELT}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Holike, C. (2011), in  Andrea Fleschenberg, Claudia Derich (Eds), THE STATE OF ISLAM–NEGOTIATING DEMOCRACY, MUSLIM WOMEN’S RIGHTS AND MORALITY IN INDONESIA AND MALAYSIA, ''Women and Politics in Asia: A Springboard for Democracy?'', LIT Verlag (Zurich), 15, page 71-80&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2012/04/09/nyregion/in-queens-seeking-to-clear-a-path-between-yoga-and-islam.html?pagewanted=all New York Times, Seeking to clear a path between yoga and islam (April 8 2012)]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Notable cases and debate on blasphemy===
As of 2011, all Islamic majority nations, worldwide, had criminal laws on blasphemy. Over 125 non-Muslim nations worldwide did not have any laws relating to blasphemy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pewforum.org/Government/Laws-Penalizing-Blasphemy,-Apostasy-and-Defamation-of-Religion-are-Widespread.aspx|title=Laws Penalizing Blasphemy, Apostasy and Defamation of Religion are Widespread|date=21 November 2012|work=Pew Research Center's Religion &amp; Public Life Project}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rehman, Javaid. &quot;THE SHARI ‘AH, INTERNATIONAL HUMAN RIGHTS LAW AND THE RIGHT TO HOLD OPINIONS AND FREE EXPRESSION: AFTER BILOUR’S FATWA.&quot; Islam and International Law: Engaging Self-Centrism from a Plurality of Perspectives (2013): 244.&lt;/ref&gt; In Islamic nations, thousands of individuals have been arrested and punished for blasphemy of Islam.&lt;ref&gt;Forte, David F. &quot;Apostasy and Blasphemy in Pakistan.&quot; Conn. J. Int'l L. 10 (1994): 27.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Silence. How Apostasy and Blasphemy Codes Are Choking Freedom Worldwide. By Paul Marshall and Nina Shea. New York: Oxford University Press, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, several Islamic nations have argued in the United Nations that blasphemy against Muhammad is unacceptable, and that laws should be passed worldwide to proscribe it. In September 2012, the [[Organisation of Islamic Conference]] (OIC), who has sought for a universal blasphemy law over a decade, revived these attempts. Separately, the Human Rights Commission of the OIC called for &quot;an international code of conduct for media and social media to disallow the dissemination of incitement material&quot;. Non-Muslim nations that do not have blasphemy laws, have pointed to abuses of blasphemy laws in Islamic nations, and have disagreed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worldaffairsjournal.org/article/radical-islam’s-global-reaction-push-blasphemy-laws Michael Totten, Radical Islam's global reaction: the push for blasphemy laws (January/February 2013)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/09/19/us-protests-religions-blasphemy-idUSBRE88I1EG20120919|title=Islamic states to reopen quest for global blasphemy law|work=Reuters}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.humanrightsfirst.org/wp-content/uploads/Blasphemy_Cases.pdf|format=PDF|title=Blasphemy Laws Exposed - The Consequences of Criminalizing Defamation of Religions |year=2012|website=humanrightsfirst.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:A_Brief_History_of_Blasphemy.jpg|thumb|left|[[Richard Webster (British author)|Richard Webster]]'s ''[[A Brief History of Blasphemy]]'' criticized unrestricted freedom of speech and was widely praised in the immediate aftermath of the [[The Satanic Verses controversy|Rushdie Affair]].]]Notwithstanding, controversies raised in the non-Muslim world, especially over depictions of [[Muhammad]], questionning issues relating to the [[religious offense]] to minorities in secular countries. A key case was the 1989 fatwa against English author [[Salman Rushdie]] for his 1988 book entitled ''[[The Satanic Verses]]'', the title of which refers to an account that Muhammad, in the course of revealing the Quran, [[Satanic Verses|received a revelation from Satan and incorporated it therein]] until made by Allah to retract it. Several translators of his book into foreign languages have been murdered.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rushdie&quot;&gt;{{cite web| title = Blasphemy Salman Rushdie| publisher = Constitutional Rights Foundation| year = 2009| url = http://www.crf-usa.org/america-responds-to-terrorism/blasphemy-salman-rushdie.html| accessdate = 10 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the UK, many supporters of Salman Rushdie and his publishers advocated unrestricted freedom of expression and the abolition of the [[Blasphemy law in the United Kingdom|British blasphemy laws]]. As a response, [[Richard Webster (British author)|Richard Webster]] wrote ''[[A Brief History of Blasphemy]]'' in which he discussed freedom to publish books that may cause distress to minorities.

==== Notable cases in Muslim countries ====
In September 2007, Bangladeshi cartoonist [[Arifur Rahman]] depicted in the daily ''[[Prothom Alo]]'' a boy holding a cat conversing with an elderly man. The man asks the boy his name, and he replies &quot;Babu&quot;. The older man chides him for not mentioning the name of Muhammad before his name. He then points to the cat and asks the boy what it is called, and the boy replies &quot;Muhammad the cat&quot;. Bangladesh does not have a blasphemy law but groups said the cartoon ridiculed Muhammad, torched copies of the paper and demanded that Rahman be executed for blasphemy. As a result, Bangladeshi police detained Rahman and confiscated copies of ''Prothom Alo'' in which the cartoon appeared.

In November 2007, British schoolteacher [[Gillian Gibbons]], who taught middle-class Muslim and Christian children in Sudan,&lt;ref name= guardian1&gt;{{cite news|last= Day|first= Elizabeth|title= 'I was terrified that the guards would come in and teach me a lesson'|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2007/dec/09/world.schoolsworldwide|accessdate=15 September 2012|newspaper=Guardian|date=8 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; was convicted of insulting Islam by allowing her class of six-year-olds to name a teddy bear &quot;Muhammad&quot;. On 30 November, thousands of protesters took to the streets in Khartoum,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2007/nov/30/uk.schoolsworldwide|title= Jailed teddy row teacher appeals for tolerance | publisher = [[The Guardian]]|date=30 November 2007|accessdate=9 December 2009 | location=London | first=Allegra | last=Stratton}}&lt;/ref&gt; demanding Gibbons's execution after imams denounced her during [[Jumu'ah|Friday prayers]]. Many Muslim organizations in other countries publicly condemned the Sudanese over their reactions&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://commisceo-global.com/blog/muhammad-the-teddy-bear-a-case-of-intercultural-incompetence|title = Muhammad &amp; the teddy bear: a case of intercultural incompetence|date=29 November 2007|accessdate=1 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; as Gibbons did not set out to cause offence.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/7123517.stm | title = Sudanese Views differ in Teddy Row | publisher = BBC | newspaper = News | place = [[United Kingdom|UK]]}}.&lt;/ref&gt; She was released into the care of the British embassy in Khartoum and left Sudan after two British Muslim members of the [[House of Lords]] met President [[Omar al-Bashir]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/7124447.stm Teddy row teacher freed from jail], ''BBC World Service'', 3 December 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/22076390/ Teddy bear&quot; teacher leaves Sudan after pardon]&quot;, ''MSNBC''&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Salmaan Taseer October 29, 2009 Lahore.jpg|thumb|140px|right|[[Salmaan Taseer]] was assassinated for supporting Asia Bibi and for opposing Pakistan's blasphemy laws.]]In January 2011, talking about the [[Asia Bibi blasphemy case]], Pakistani politician [[Salmaan Taseer]] expressed views opposing the country's [[Blasphemy law in Pakistan|blasphemy law]]. He was then killed by one of his bodyguards, Malik Mumtaz Qadri. After the murder, hundreds of clerics voiced support for the crime and urged a general boycott of Taseer's funeral.&lt;ref&gt;R. Upadhyay, [http://www.eurasiareview.com/28012011-barelvis-and-deobandhis-%E2%80%9Cbirds-of-the-same-feather%E2%80%9D/ Barelvis and Deobandhis: &quot;Birds of the Same Feather&quot;]. Eurasia Review, courtesy of the South Asia Analysis Group. 28 January 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; However, hundreds of people turned up for his funeral.&lt;ref name=&quot;sana&quot;&gt;Sana Saleem, [http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/belief/2011/jan/05/salman-taseer-murder-pakistan &quot;Salmaan Taseer: murder in an extremist climate&quot;], ''[[The Guardian]], 5 January 2011. Retrieved 2011-01-07.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC-SA&quot;&gt;Aleem Maqbool and [[Orla Guerin]], [http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-south-asia-12116764 &quot;Salman Taseer: Thousands mourn Pakistan governor&quot;]: &quot;One small religious party, the Jamaat-e-Ahl-e-Sunnat Pakistan, warned that anyone who expressed grief over the assassination could suffer the same fate. 'No Muslim should attend the funeral or even try to pray for Salman Taseer or even express any kind of regret or sympathy over the incident,' the party said in a statement. It said anyone who expressed sympathy over the death of a blasphemer was also committing blasphemy.&quot; ''BBC News South Asia'', 5 January 2011. Retrieved 2011-01-07.&lt;/ref&gt; Supporters of Mumtaz Qadri blocked police attempting to bring him to the courts and some showered him with rose petals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Demonstrators Prevent&quot;&gt;{{cite news
| url= http://www.voanews.com/english/news/asia/south/Disruptions-Mark-Remand-of-Alleged-Pakistani-Assassin-113016474.html
| title= Demonstrators Prevent Court Appearance of Alleged Pakistani Assassin
| publisher= [[Voice of America]]
| date= 6 January 2011
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In October, Qadri was sentenced to death for murdering Taseer.

Minority Affairs Minister [[Shahbaz Bhatti]] said that he was first threatened with death in June 2010 when he was told that he would be beheaded if he attempted to change the blasphemy laws.&lt;ref name=price&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-south-asia-11930849 | title = Pakistani Christian Asia Bibi 'has price on her head' | last = Guerin  | first = Orla |date = 6 December 2010 | work = [[BBC]] | accessdate = 6 December 2010| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20101207044430/http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-south-asia-11930849| archivedate= 7 December 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 2 March 2011, he was shot dead by gunmen, presumably because of his position on the blasphemy laws. Some expressed concerns that the assassinations of Taseer and Bhatti may dissuade other Pakistani politicians from speaking out against the blasphemy laws.

====Protests against depicting Muhammad====
In December 1999, the German news magazine ''[[Der Spiegel]]'' printed on the same page pictures of “moral apostles” Muhammad, [[Jesus]], [[Confucius]], and [[Immanuel Kant]]. Few weeks later, the magazine received protests, petitions and threats against publishing depictions of Muhammad. The Turkish TV-station [[Show TV]] broadcast the telephone number of an editor who then received daily calls.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spiegel.de/spiegel/print/d-15613871.html Terror am Telefon], ''Spiegel'', February 7, 2000&lt;/ref&gt; A picture of Muhammad had been published by the magazine once before in 1998 in a special edition on Islam, without evoking similar protests.&lt;ref&gt;''Spiegel Special'' 1, 1998, page 76&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, several Muslims protested against the inclusion of Muhammad's depictions in the [[English Wikipedia]]'s ''Muhammad'' article.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,328966,00.html |title=Muslims Protest Wikipedia Images of Muhammad |publisher=[[Fox News]] |date=2008-02-06 |accessdate=2008-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NY&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/02/05/books/05wiki.html |title=Wikipedia Islam Entry Is Criticized |author=Noam Cohen |publisher=New York Times |date=2008-02-05 |accessdate=2008-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; An online petition opposed a reproduction of a 17th-century Ottoman copy of a 14th-century [[Ilkhanate]] manuscript image depicting Muhammad as he prohibited [[Nasīʾ]].&lt;ref&gt;MS Arabe 1489. The image used by Wikipedia is hosted on [[Wikimedia Commons]] ([[Media:Maome.jpg|upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/0d/Maome.jpg]]). The reproduction originates from the website of the [[Bibliothèque nationale de France]] [http://expositions.bnf.fr/livrarab/pedago/grands/0_01.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; Jeremy Henzell-Thomas of ''The American Muslim'' deplored the petition as one of &quot;these mechanical knee-jerk reactions [which] are gifts to those who seek every opportunity to decry Islam and ridicule Muslims and can only exacerbate a situation in which Muslims and the Western media seem to be locked in an ever-descending spiral of ignorance and mutual loathing.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theamericanmuslim.org/tam.php/features/articles/wikipedia_and_depictions_of_the_prophet_muhammad_the_latest_inane_distracti/0015659 Wikipedia and Depictions of the Prophet Muhammad: The Latest Inane Distraction], 10 February 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

====The Muhammad cartoons crisis====
[[File:Flemming_Rose_at_the_2015_European_Students_For_Liberty_Conference_in_Berlin.jpg|thumb|200px|''[[Jyllands-Posten]]'' editor [[Flemming Rose]] was responsible for the [[Jyllands-Posten Muhammad cartoons controversy|controversial publication of the Muhammad cartoons in Denmark]] and has been since a free speech advocate.]]In September 2005, in the tense aftermath of the assassination of Dutch film director [[Theo van Gogh (film director)|Theo van Gogh]], killed for his views on Islam, Danish news service [[Ritzau]] published an article discussing the difficulty encountered by the writer [[Kåre Bluitgen]] to find an illustrator to work on his children's book ''The Qur'an and the life of the Prophet Muhammad'' (Danish:''Koranen og profeten Muhammeds liv'').&lt;ref name=hansen&amp;hundevadt&gt;{{cite book|last=Hansen|first=John|title=Provoen og Profeten: Muhammed Krisen bag kulisserne|year=2006|publisher=Jyllands-Postens Forlag|location=Copenhagen|isbn=87-7692-092-5|first2=Kim |last2=Hundevadt|language=Danish}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Bluitgen|first=Kåre|title=Koranen og profeten Muhammeds liv|year=2006|publisher=Høst &amp; Søn/Tøkk|isbn=978-87-638-0049-5|page=268|url=http://www.digibutik.dk/?ID=250&amp;GroupID=250&amp;ProductID=PROD1179&amp;pgid=GROUP249&amp;qq=8D7SR65SK7TUB%2048D9LG6B%20L7T|others=Anonymous illustrator|language=Danish}}&lt;/ref&gt; He said that three artists declined his proposal, which was interpreted as evidence of self-censorship out of fear of reprisals, which led to much debate in Denmark.&lt;ref name=&quot;dybangst&quot;&gt;{{cite news|date=17 September 2005|title=Dyb angst for kritik af islam (&quot;Profound anxiety about criticism of Islam&quot;)|newspaper=Politiken|url=http://politiken.dk/kultur/boger/ECE123660/dyb-angst-for-kritik-af-islam/|accessdate=19 March 2013|language=Danish}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;whyipub&quot;&gt;{{cite news|date=19 February 2006|title=Why I Published Those Cartoons |newspaper=The Washington Post|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/02/17/AR2006021702499.html|first=Flemming|last=Rose|accessdate=16 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Jyllands-Posten]]'' editor [[Flemming Rose]] invited professional illustrators to depict Muhammad, as an experiment to see how much they felt threatened. One cartoon by [[Kurt Westergaard]] depicted Muhammad with a bomb in his turban, which resulted in withdrawal of the ambassadors of Libya, Saudi Arabia and Syria from Denmark, as well as consumer boycotts of Danish products in a number of Islamic countries.

Reviewing the experiment, Danish scholar [[Peter Hervik]] wrote that it disproved the idea that self-censorship was a serious problem in Denmark, because the overwhelming majority of cartoonists had either responded positively or refused for contractual or philosophical reasons.&lt;ref name=IMER&gt;{{cite journal|last=Hervik|first=Peter|title=The Danish Muhammad Cartoon Conflict|journal=Current Themes in IMER Research|year=2012|volume=13|url=http://www.mah.se/upload/Forskningscentrum/MIM/CT/CT%2013.pdf|accessdate=20 October 2012|publisher=Malmö Institute for Studies of Migration, Diversity and Welfare (MIM)|issn=1652-4616}}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, the Danish newspaper ''Politiken'' stated that they asked Bluitgen to put them in touch with the artists who reportedly declined his proposal, so his claim that none of them dared to work with him could be proved, but that Bluitgen refused, making his initial claim impossible to confirm.&lt;ref&gt;Politiken 12. Februar 2006 &quot;''Muhammedsag: Ikke ligefrem en genistreg''&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Commenting the cartoon that initiated the diplomatic crisis, American scholar [[John E. Woods (historian)|John Woods]] expressed worries about Westergaard-like association of the Prophet with terrorism, that was beyond satire and offensive to a vast majority of Muslims.&lt;ref name=explaining&gt;{{cite news|title=Explaining the outrage|url=http://articles.chicagotribune.com/2006-02-08/news/0602080383_1_prophet-muhammad-cartoons-muslims|date=2006-02-08|work=[[Chicago Tribune]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hervik also deplored that the newspaper's &quot;desire to provoke and insult Danish Muslims exceeded the wish to test the self-censorship of Danish cartoonists.&quot;&lt;ref name=IMER/&gt;

An online caricature competition was announced in support of ''Jyllands-Posten'' in Sweden but foreign minister [[Laila Freivalds]] pressured the provider to shut the page down. In 2006, her involvement was revealed to the public and she had to resign.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.alertnet.org/thenews/newsdesk/L21470789.htm |title=Swedish foreign minister resigns over cartoons |work=Reuters AlertNet |accessdate=2006-03-21 |archiveurl =https://web.archive.org/web/20060322184626/http://www.alertnet.org/thenews/newsdesk/L21470789.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 22 March 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; In France, satirical magazine ''[[Charlie Hebdo]]'' republished the ''Jyllands-Posten'' cartoons of Muhammad and was taken to court by Islamic organisations under [[Hate speech laws in France|French hate speech laws]]; it was ultimately acquitted of charges that it incited hatred.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveque&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Leveque|first=Thierry|title=French court clears weekly in Mohammad cartoon row|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2007/03/22/industry-france-cartoons-trial-dc-idUSL2212067120070322|accessdate=10 June 2013|agency=Reuters|date=22 March 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2007, art galleries in Sweden declined to show drawings of artist [[Lars Vilks]] depicting Muhammad as a [[roundabout dog]]. While Swedish newspapers had published them already, the drawings gained international attention after the newspaper ''[[Nerikes Allehanda]]'' published one of them on August 18 to illustrate an editorial on the &quot;right to ridicule a religion&quot;.&lt;ref name=na&gt;{{cite news |first=Lars |last=Ströman |title=Rätten att förlöjliga en religion |url=http://www.na.se/artikel.asp?intId=1209627 |publisher=[[Nerikes Allehanda]] |language=Swedish |date=2007-08-18 |accessdate=2007-08-31 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070906190721/http://www.na.se/artikel.asp?intId=1209627 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-09-06}}&lt;br/&gt;English translation: {{cite news |first=Lars |last=Ströman |title=The right to ridicule a religion |url=http://www.na.se/artikel.asp?intId=1209676 |publisher=[[Nerikes Allehanda]] |date=2007-08-28 |accessdate=2007-08-31 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070830163657/http://www.na.se/artikel.asp?intId=1209676 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; This particular publication led to official condemnations from Iran,&lt;ref name=iran&gt;{{cite news |title=Iran protests over Swedish Muhammad cartoon |url=http://www.thelocal.se/8305/20070827/ |publisher=[[Agence France-Presse]] |date=2007-08-27 |accessdate=2007-08-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pakistan,&lt;ref name=pakistan&gt;{{cite press release |title=PAKISTAN CONDEMNS THE PUBLICATION OF OFFENSIVE SKETCH IN SWEDEN |publisher=[[Pakistan Ministry of Foreign Affairs]] |date=2007-08-30 |url=http://www.mofa.gov.pk/Press_Releases/2007/Aug/PR_234_07.htm |accessdate=2007-08-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; Afghanistan,&lt;ref name=afghanistan&gt;{{cite news |first=Sayed |last=Salahuddin |title=Indignant Afghanistan slams Prophet Mohammad sketch |url=http://in.reuters.com/article/SouthAsiaNews/idINIndia-29281220070901 |publisher=Reuters |date=2007-09-01 |accessdate=2007-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Egypt&lt;ref name=egypt&gt;{{cite news |first=Gwladys |last=Fouché |title=Egypt wades into Swedish cartoons row |url=http://media.guardian.co.uk/presspublishing/story/0,,2161595,00.html |publisher=The Guardian |date=2007-09-03 |accessdate=2007-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Jordan,&lt;ref name=jordan&gt;{{cite news |title=Jordan condemns new Swedish Mohammed cartoon |url=http://news.yahoo.com/s/afp/20070903/wl_mideast_afp/jordanswedenislam_070903124623 |publisher=[[Agence France-Presse]] |date=2007-09-03 |accessdate=2007-09-09}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; and by the inter-governmental Organisation of the Islamic Conference.&lt;ref name=oic&gt;{{cite press release |title=The Secretary General strongly condemned the publishing of blasphemous caricatures of prophet Muhammad by Swedish artist |publisher=[[Organisation of the Islamic Conference]] |date=2007-08-30 |url=http://www.oic-oci.org/press/English/2007/08/caricatur.htm |accessdate=2007-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006, the American comedy program ''[[South Park]]'', which had previously depicted Muhammad as a superhero (&quot;[[Super Best Friends]])&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode | title = Super Best Friends | episodelink = Super Best Friends | series = South Park | serieslink = South Park | airdate = 2001-07-04 | season = 5 | number = 68}}&lt;/ref&gt; and has depicted Muhammad in the opening sequence since then,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tvsquad.com/2006/04/15/south-parks-been-showing-muhammad-all-season/ |title=Ryan j Budke. &quot;South Park's been showing Muhammad all season!&quot; TVSquad.com; April 15, 2006 |publisher=Tvsquad.com |date= |accessdate=2013-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; attempted to satirize the Danish newspaper incident. They intended to show Muhammad handing a salmon helmet to ''[[Family Guy]]'' character [[Peter Griffin]] (&quot;[[Cartoon Wars Part II]]&quot;). However, [[Comedy Central]] who airs the series rejected the scene and its creators reacted by satirizing [[double standard]] for broadcast acceptability. In April 2010, animators [[Trey Parker]] and [[Matt Stone]] planned to make episodes satirizing controversies over previous episodes, including Comedy Central's refusal to show images of Muhammad following the 2005 Danish controversy. After they faced Internet death threats, Comedy Central modified their version of the episode, obscuring all images and bleeping all references to Muhammad. In reaction, cartoonist Molly Norris created the [[Everybody Draw Mohammed Day]], claiming that if many people draw pictures of Muhammad, threats to murder them all would become unrealistic.

==Judaism==
{{See also|List of capital crimes in the Torah}}
{{bibleref2|Leviticus|24:16|NKJV}} states that he that blasphemes the [[Tetragrammaton|name of the LORD]] &quot;shall surely be put to death&quot;. In [[Halakha|Jewish law]] the only form of blasphemy which is punishable by death is blaspheming the [[Tetragrammaton|Ineffable Name]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/3354-blasphemy|title=BLASPHEMY - JewishEncyclopedia.com|work=jewishencyclopedia.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Seven Laws of Noah]], which Judaism sees as applicable to all people, prohibit blasphemy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewishvirtuallibrary.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/Judaism/The_Seven_Noahide_Laws.html|title=The Seven Noachide Laws - Jewish Virtual Library|publisher=Jewishvirtuallibrary.org|accessdate=8 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==The United Nations==
{{Main article|Blasphemy and the United Nations}}
In the early 21st century, blasphemy became an issue in the United Nations. The [[United Nations]] passed several resolutions which called upon the world to take action against the &quot;defamation of religions&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;U.N. Resolutions:
*[http://daccess-ods.un.org/access.nsf/Get?Open&amp;DS=A/RES/60/150&amp;Lang=E A/RES/60/150]
*[http://daccess-ods.un.org/access.nsf/Get?Open&amp;DS=A/60/PV.64&amp;Lang=E Vote on 16 December 2005 (A/60/PV.64)]
&lt;/ref&gt;

The campaign for worldwide criminal penalties for the &quot;defamation of religions&quot; had been spearheaded by [[Organisation of Islamic Cooperation]] on behalf of the United Nations' large Muslim bloc. The campaign ended in 2011 when the proposal was withdrawn in Geneva, in the Human Rights Council because of lack of support, marking an end to the effort to establish worldwide blasphemy strictures along the lines of those in Pakistan, Saudi Arabia, and Iran. This resolution had passed every year since 1999, in the United Nations, with declining number of &quot;yes&quot; votes with each successive year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationalreview.com/article/263450/anti-blasphemy-measure-laid-rest-nina-shea An Anti-Blasphemy Measure Laid to Rest] Nina Shea, National Review (MARCH 31, 2011)&lt;/ref&gt;

In July, 2011, the [[UN Human Rights Committee]] released a 52-paragraph statement, General Comment 34 on the [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]] (ICCPR) 1976, concerning freedoms of opinion and expression.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/hrc/docs/GC34.pdf General Comment 34]&lt;/ref&gt; Paragraph 48 states: 
{{quote|Prohibitions of displays of lack of respect for a religion or other belief system, including blasphemy laws, are incompatible with the Covenant, except in the specific circumstances envisaged in article 20, paragraph 2, of the Covenant. Such prohibitions must also comply with the strict requirements of article 19, paragraph 3, as well as such articles as 2, 5, 17, 18 and 26. Thus, for instance, it would be impermissible for any such laws to discriminate in favor of or against one or certain religions or belief systems, or their adherents over another, or religious believers over non-believers. Nor would it be permissible for such prohibitions to be used to prevent or punish criticism of religious leaders or commentary on religious doctrine and tenets of faith.}}

==Colloquial usage==
In contemporary language, the notion of blasphemy is often used [[hyperbole|hyperbolically]]. This usage has garnered some interest among linguists recently, and the word 'blasphemy' is a common case used for illustrative purposes.&lt;ref&gt;
Recanati, F. (1995) The alleged priority of literal interpretation. Cognitive Science 19: 207–32.
:[[Robyn Carston|Carston, R.]] (1997) Enrichment and loosening: complementary processes in deriving the proposition expressed? Linguistische Berichte 8: 103–127.
:Carston, R. (2000). Explicature and semantics. UCL Working Papers in Linguistics 12: 1–44. Revised version to appear in Davis &amp; Gillon (forthcoming).
:Sperber, D. &amp; D. Wilson (1998) The mapping between the mental and the public lexicon. In Carruthers &amp; Boucher (1998: 184–200).
:Glucksberg, S. (2001) Understanding Figurative Language: From Metaphors to Idioms. Oxford: Oxford University Press.
:Wilson, D. &amp; D. Sperber (2002) Truthfulness and relevance. Mind 111: 583–632.
&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Apostasy]]
* [[Blasphemy Day]] is a holiday in which individuals and groups are encouraged to openly express their criticism of, or even disdain for, religion.
* [[Blasphemy law]]
* [[Blasphemous libel]]
* [[Heresy]]
* [[Impiety]]
* [[Minced oath]]
* [[Profanity]]
* [[Gerard Reve]]
* [[Sacrilege]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* ''[[Maledicta]]: The International Journal of Verbal Aggression''  (ISSN US 0363-3659)
*Levy, L. ''Blasphemy''. Chapel Hill, 1993.
* [http://www.brentonpriestley.com/writing/blasphemy.htm Comprehensive academic study comparing global legal approaches to blasphemy in light of the Jyllands-Posten controversy]
*Dartevelle, P., S Borg, Denis, Ph., Robyn, J. (eds.). Blasphèmes et libertés. Paris: CERF, 1993
*Plate, S. Brent ''Blasphemy: Art that Offends'' (London: Black Dog Publishing, 2006) ISBN 1904772536

==External links==
{{commons category|Blasphemy}}
*The Rational Response Squad: [http://www.blasphemychallenge.com The Blasphemy Challenge]
*[http://www.channel4.com/more4/news/news-opinion-feature.jsp?id=559 A More4 news film report on how insulting the prophet Mohammed in Pakistan is a capital offence, and defiling the Koran carries life imprisonment].
*[http://www.caslon.com.au/blasphemyprofile.htm review of laws relating to blasphemy and sacrilege in various jurisdictions]
*{{CathEncy|wstitle=Blasphemy|author=John Webster Melody}}
*[http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=1119&amp;letter=B&amp;search=Blasphemy Jewish Encyclopedia] – Blasphemy
*{{Cite Americana|wstitle=Blasphemy |short=x}}
{{Blasphemy law}}
{{Ten Commandments}}

[[Category:Blasphemy| ]]
[[Category:Religious terminology]]</text>
      <sha1>fwvenxjqd0s0salr1g680baixkbhpja</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
