<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Diepkloof Rock Shelter</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>26433872</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746939497</id>
      <parentid>746939197</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-30T13:25:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Waitabout</username>
        <id>5637166</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* top */ Increased photo size</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11120">{{EngvarB|date=May 2013}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2013}}
{{Infobox cave
| name = Diepkloof Rock Shelter
| other_name =

| photo = Diepkloof-general-view.JPG|
| photo_width = 
| photo_caption = General view of Diepkloof Rock Shelter

| map = Western Cape
| map_width = 
| map_caption = 
| map_alt = 
| location = Verlorenvlei, [[Western Cape]]
| coords = &lt;!-- {{coord|32|23|12|S|18|27|10|E|type:landmark_region:ZA|display=title}} --&gt;
| lat_d = 32| lat_m = 23|lat_s = 12| lat_NS = S 
| long_d = 18| long_m = 27 | long_s = 10| long_EW = E
| coords_ref = 
| land_registry_number =
| grid_ref_UK = 
| grid_ref_Ireland = 
| grid_ref =

| depth = 
| length = 
| height_variation =
| elevation = 
| discovery = 
| geology = [[Quartzite|Quartzitic Sandstone]]
| entrance_count = 
| entrance_list = 
| difficulty = 
| hazards = 
| access = 
| show_cave = 
| show_cave_length = 
| lighting = 
| visitors = 
| features = 
| survey = 
| survey_format = 
| website = 
}}

[[File:Diepkloof-excavation-2009.JPG|300px|thumb|General view of the excavation during 2009 field season]]
[[File:Diepkloof-excavation-2009-detail.JPG|300px|thumb|Excavation of the upper part of the deposit]]
'''Diepkloof Rock Shelter''' is a [[rock shelter]] in [[Western Cape]], South Africa in which has been found some of the earliest evidence of the human use of [[symbol]]s, in the form of patterns engraved upon [[ostrich]] eggshell water containers. These date around 60,000 years ago.&lt;ref name=&quot;Texier&quot;&gt;Texier PJ, Porraz G, Parkington J, Rigaud JP, Poggenpoel C, Miller C, Tribolo C, Cartwright C, Coudenneau A, Klein R, Steele T, Verna C. (2010). &quot;A Howiesons Poort tradition of engraving ostrich eggshell containers dated to 60,000 years ago at Diepkloof Rock Shelter, South Africa&quot;. ''Proceedings of the National Acadademy of Science'' U S A. 107: 6180–6185. {{doi|10.1073/pnas.0913047107}}  PMID 20194764&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Tribolo&quot;/&gt;

The symbolic patterns consist of lines crossed at right angles or oblique angles by hatching. It has been suggested that &quot;by the repetition of this motif, early humans were trying to communicate something. Perhaps they were trying to express the identity of the individual or the group.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Amos&quot;&gt;Amos, J. (2010). [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/sci/tech/8544332.stm Etched ostrich eggs illustrate human sophistication.] BBC News&lt;/ref&gt;

==Site description==

The cave is about {{convert|17|km}} from the shoreline of the [[Atlantic]] in a semi-arid area, near [[Elands Bay]] about {{convert|150|km}} north of [[Cape Town]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Tribolo&quot;&gt;Tribolo, C. Mercier, N., Valladas, H. Joron J.L., Guibert P., Lefrais Y., Selo M., Texier P.-J., Rigaud J.-Ph., Porraz G., Poggenpoel C., Parkington J., Texier J.-P., Lenoble A.. (2009) &quot;Thermoluminescence dating of a Stillbay–Howiesons Poort sequence at Diepkloof Rock Shelter (Western Cape, South Africa)&quot;. ''Journal of Archaeological Science'', 36: 730–739. {{doi|10.1016/j.jas.2008.10.018}}&lt;/ref&gt; It occurs in [[Quartzite|quartzitic sandstone]] in a [[butte]] that overlooks in an east direction {{convert|100|m}} above the [[Verlorenvlei River]]. It contains one of &quot;most complete and continuous later [[Middle Stone Age]] sequences in southern Africa&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Texier&quot;/&gt; stretching from before 130,000 BP to about 45,000 BP and encompassing pre-Stillbay, [[Stillbay]], [[Howiesons Poort]], and post-Howiesons Poort periods. It is about {{convert|25|m}} wide and {{convert|15|m}} deep. Research is based upon finds discovered in a trench excavated within it that is {{convert|16|m}} across and {{convert|3.6|m}} in depth. The deposits consist of burnt and nonburnt organic residues and ash that came from hearths, ash dumps and burnt bedding.&lt;ref name=&quot;Texier&quot;/&gt;

It was first excavated in 1973 by [[John Parkington]] and Cedric Poggenpoel.&lt;ref&gt;Parkington, J., Poggenpoel, C. (1987). &quot;Diepkloof Rock Shelter&quot;. In: Parkington, J., Hall, M. (Eds.), ''Papers in Prehistory of the Western Cape, South Africa'', vol. 332. BAR International, pp. 269–293. ISBN 978-0-86054-425-8&lt;/ref&gt; Since 1999 it has been researched in a collaboration between the Department of Archaeology at the [[University of Cape Town]] and the Institute of Prehistory and Quaternary Geology at the [[University of Bordeaux]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Tribolo&quot;/&gt;

At Diepkloof Rock Shelter (DRS), from 70-74 ka bifaces and bifacial points are present while less complex forms such as backed artifacts occur from 70 ka through 60 ka and are subsequently replaced with unifacial points. Quartz and quartzite predominate the earliest unit with few occurrences of silcrete. During 70-74 ka unit, silcrete has replaced quartz while quartzite is still fairly dominant. From 65-70 ka quartz becomes dominant again with quartzite also being present.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Mackay|first1=Alex|last2=Marwick|first2=Ben|title=Keeping your Edge: Recent Approaches to the Organisation of Stone Artefact Technology|date=2011|chapter=Costs and benefits in technological decision making under variable conditions: examples from the late Pleistocene in southern Africa}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Engraved ostrich eggshell containers==

270 fragments of ostrich eggshell containers have been found covered with engraved geometric patterns. The fragments have a maximum size of 20–30&amp;nbsp;mm, though a number have been fitted into larger 80 × 40&amp;nbsp;mm fragments. It is estimated that fragments from 25 containers have been found. Eggshell fragments have been found throughout the period of occupation of the cave but those with engraving are found only in several layers within the [[Howiesons Poort]] period. These occur across 18 stratigraphic units, particularly those with the stratigraphic names Frank and Darryl. This suggests the tradition of engraving lasted for several thousand years.&lt;ref name=&quot;Texier&quot;/&gt;

The engraving consists of abstract linear repetitive patterns, including a hatched band motif. One fragment has two parallel lines that might have been circular around the container.

It has been suggested that they form &quot;a system of symbolic representation in which collective identities and individual expressions are clearly communicated, suggesting social, cultural, and cognitive underpinnings that overlap with those of modern people.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Texier&quot;/&gt; Moreover, they show &quot;the development of a graphic tradition and the complex use of symbols to mediate social interactions. The large number of marked pieces shows that there were rules for composing designs but having room within the rules to allow for individual and/or group preferences.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Texier&quot;/&gt;

Earlier finds exist of symbolism, such as the 75,000-year-old engraved ochre chunks found in the [[Blombos cave]], but these are isolated and difficult to tell apart from meaningless doodles.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amos&quot;/&gt;

The engravings are found on ostrich eggshells that were used as water containers. Ostrich eggshells have an average volume of 1 litre. They may have had drinking spouts, holes to enable them to be strung as a [[canteen (bottle)|canteen]] for easier carrying, and seem to have been part of &quot;daily [[hunter-gatherer]] life&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Texier&quot;/&gt; They involved skill to make, with one of the researchers involved noting &quot;Ostrich egg shells are quite hard. Doing such engravings is not so easy.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Amos&quot;/&gt;

==Local flora==

The preservation of organic matter such as wood, grass, seeds and fruits at the site has been described as &quot;exceptional&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tribolo&quot;/&gt; Pollen remains allow the identification of the local animals and plants. The Howiesons Poort period shows evidence for thicket or [[shrubland]] vegetation now usually found in gorges, such as [[Diospyros]], [[Cassine peragua]], [[Maytenus]], [[Rhus]], and [[Hartogiella schinoides]]. [[Afromontane]] trees found in the area, include [[Ficus]], ''[[Kiggelaria africana]]'', ''[[Podocarpus elongatus]]'', and ''[[Celtis africana]]''. This suggests a more diversely wooded riverine environment than now present in the area.&lt;ref name=&quot;Texier&quot;/&gt;

==Animal remains==
Animal remains include those of [[mammal]]s, [[tortoise]]s and [[intertidal]] marine shells. Most bones found in the cave come from [[rock hyrax]], [[hare]]s, [[Bathyergus suillus|cape dune mole-rat]]s, [[steenbok]] and [[Raphicerus|grysbok]]. Animals from rocky environments are also found including [[klipspringer]], and [[Pelea capreolus|vaalribbok]]. There is also evidence of local grasslands, with remains of zebras, [[wildebeest]] and [[hartebeest]]. Hippopotamus and [[southern reedbuck]] came from the local river. The sea coast seems to have moved up the river, as there are fragments from [[black mussel]]s, [[Cymbula granatina|granite limpet]]s, and [[Cape fur seal]]s. Though there are ostrich-shell remains, no ostrich bones have been found.&lt;ref name=&quot;Texier&quot;/&gt;

Tortoise bones are mostly those of the [[Chersina angulata|angulate tortoise]] that is still found in the area. These are noted to have been &quot;remarkably large compared with their Late Stone Age counterparts, suggesting different intensities of predation between MSA and Late Stone Age populations&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Texier&quot;/&gt;

==Provincial Heritage Site==
[[File:Provincial Heritage Site Marker, Diepkloof Rock Shelter, Elands Bay.jpg|right|300px|thumb|Badge indicating that the Diepkloof Rock Shelter is a provincial heritage site]]
Diepkloof Rock Shelter was declared a provincial heritage site by [[Heritage Western Cape]] on the 23 September 2014 in terms of Section 27 of the National Heritage Resources Act.&lt;ref&gt;Provincial Notice 253/2014, Province of the Western Cape Provincial Gazette Extraordinary, No. 7310, Cape Town: 23 September 2014&lt;/ref&gt; This gives the site Grade II status and provides it with protection under South African heritage law.

In 2015, the South African government submitted a proposal to add the caves to the list of [[World Heritage Site]]s and it has been placed on the UNESCO list of tentative sites as a potential future 'serial nomination' together with [[Blombos Cave]], [[Pinnacle Point]], [[Klasies River Caves]], [[Sibudu Cave]] and [[Border Cave]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Emergence of Modern Humans: The Pleistocene occupation sites of South Africa|url=http://whc.unesco.org/en/tentativelists/6050|website=UNESCO|accessdate=3 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{commons category|Diepkloof rock shelter}}

==External links==
* [http://www.diplomatie.gouv.fr/en/france-priorities_1/archaeology_2200/archaeology-notebooks_2202/africa-arabia_2240/south-africa-diepkloof-project_6554/index.html South Africa – Diepkloof Project ]
*[http://www.diplomatie.gouv.fr/en/france-priorities_1/archaeology_2200/archaeology-notebooks_2202/africa-arabia_2240/south-africa-diepkloof-project_6554/the-archaeological-site-and-its-history_11840.html Diepkloof Project – The Archaeological site and its history]

{{Prehistoric technology|state=expanded}}
{{The Emergence of Modern Humans}}

{{Navbox prehistoric caves}}

[[Category:Archaeological sites in South Africa]]
[[Category:Paleolithic]]
[[Category:Middle Stone Age]]
[[Category:Paleoanthropological sites]]
[[Category:Rock shelters]]</text>
      <sha1>h0bqb1ick4uq9mtk2vewz7m67tv9i4j</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
