<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.28.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2600" case="first-letter">Topic</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Temnothorax albipennis</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>31263971</id>
    <revision>
      <id>739568921</id>
      <parentid>739568481</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-15T13:32:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>137.222.174.181</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7136">{{italic title}}
{{Taxobox
| image = Temnothorax albipennis casent0173192 profile 1.jpg
| image_caption = ''Temnothorax albipennis''
| regnum = [[Animal]]ia
| phylum = [[Arthropod]]a
| classis = [[Insect]]a
| ordo = [[Hymenoptera]]
| subordo = [[Apocrita]]
| superfamilia = [[Vespoidea]]
| familia = [[Formicidae]]
| subfamilia = [[Myrmicinae]]
| genus = ''[[Temnothorax]]''
| species = '''''T. albipennis'''''
| binomial = ''Temnothorax albipennis''
| binomial_authority = [[John Curtis (entomologist)|Curtis]], 1854
| synonyms = ''T. tuberointerruptus''
}}

'''''Temnothorax albipennis''''' is a [[species]] of small ant in the subfamily [[Myrmicinae]]. It occurs in Europe and builds simple nests in rock crevices.

==Description==
This species has the typical ant body pattern of head, [[mesosoma]] and [[metasoma]], with the first two segments of the metasoma forming a distinct waist. It is light brown and has a few short pale coloured hairs. The antennae are elbowed and there are a pair of compound eyes and three [[Simple eye in invertebrates#Ocelli|ocelli]].

==Biology==
[[image:Temnothorax albipennis casent0178236 head 1.jpg|thumb|180px|left|View of head from above]]
[[File:Temnothorax albipennis workers performing a tandem run.jpg|thumb|left|Temnothorax albipennis workers performing a tandem run]]
As with other ants, there is a single, relatively large [[Ant#Development and reproduction|queen]] that lays eggs in the [[Ant colony|nest]] and a large number of workers. These are all non-breeding females and leave the nest to forage and collect building materials for its construction and repair.&lt;ref name=MN&gt;[http://myrmecologicalnews.org/cms/images/pdf/volume6/mn6_9-12_non-printable.pdf Myrmecologische Nachrichten]&lt;/ref&gt;

''T. albipennis'' builds simple nests in cracks in rocks, enclosed by walls built from tiny pebbles and grains of sand. In an experiment where two sizes of sand grain were offered to ants that were foraging for building materials, the ants always chose the smaller grains although this was wasteful in terms of building efficiency.&lt;ref&gt;[http://iussi.confex.com/iussi/2006/techprogram/P1205.HTM Building behaviour in ''Temnothorax albipennis'']&lt;/ref&gt; ''T. albipennis'' scouts show behavioural lateralization when exploring unknown nest sites, showing a population-level bias to prefer left turns. One possible reason for this is that its environment is partly maze-like and consistently turning in one direction is a good way to search and exit mazes without getting lost.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal  |vauthors=Hunt ER, etal | year=2014 |title=Ants show a leftward turning bias when exploring unknown nest sites|journal=[[Biology Letters (journal)|Biology Letters]] |volume=10 |issue=12 |pmid=25540159 |doi=10.1098/rsbl.2014.0945}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another experiment examined the division of labour in ant colonies and found that there tended to be a few high performance workers in small colonies which performed tasks considerably more efficiently than the other workers. This was not the case in larger colonies, and in both cases, there were a high proportion of inactive workers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://beheco.oxfordjournals.org/content/20/5/922.abstract Larger colonies do not have more specialized workers in the ant ''Temnothorax albipennis'']&lt;/ref&gt;

Ants are one of the most successful insects on the planet and there is a long-held view that this is because of the [[division of labour]] and the way certain workers specialise in certain tasks. An experiment was carried out to examine whether these specialist ants actually performed the task better than other workers. The ants were marked with drops of paint and then were videotaped while they performed such tasks as foraging, transporting the brood and nest building. The conclusions were that, though some ants performed a range of jobs and others specialised in a single task, the latter were found not to be any more efficient at their selected tasks than were the generalists. However the specialists did put in more time on the job than the other ants so the colony overall benefited from their specialisation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2008/11/081117203826.htm Can an ant be employee of the month?]&lt;/ref&gt; Research tracking ''T. albipennis'' movements found that they move in similar ways both outside and inside the nest, suggesting that workers are principally generalists equipped to do multiple tasks. The duration of each new ant movement appears to be predetermined to some degree (this is known as motor planning), which may make navigating their complex society easier.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal  |vauthors=Hunt ER, etal | year=2016 |title=Ants determine their next move at rest: motor planning and causality in complex systems|journal=[[Royal Society Open Science]] |volume=3 |page=150534 |doi=10.1098/rsos.150534}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another behaviour exhibited by colonies of this species is the ability to react to predator attacks as a single unit. It has been shown that colonies will respond differentially to predation events dependent on their location within the colony, and workers will withdraw or disperse appropriately to enable effective mitigation of mortality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal  |vauthors=O'Shea-Wheller TA, etal | year=2015 |title=Differentiated Anti-Predation Responses in a Superorganism|journal=[[PLOS ONE]] |volume=11 |page=e0141012 |doi=10.1371/journal.pone.0141012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ants of this species have been observed teaching each other through a process known as [[tandem running]]. An experienced forager leads a naive nest-mate to a newly discovered resource such as food or an empty nest site. The follower obtains knowledge of the route by following in the footsteps of the tutor, maintaining contact with its [[Antenna (biology)|antennae]]. Both leader and follower are aware of the progress made by the other with the leader slowing when the follower lags and speeding up when the follower gets too close.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Franks NR, Richardson T| year=2006 |title=Teaching in tandem-running ants|journal=[[Nature (journal)|Nature]] |volume=439 |issue=7073 |page=153|pmid=16407943 |doi=10.1038/439153a}}&lt;/ref&gt; Depending on how far away a new resource is, colonies will modulate the number of tandem runs that they perform, with a greater number of tandem runs occurring when the desired resource is more distant.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=O'Shea-Wheller TA, etal |year=2016 |title=Migration control: a distance compensation strategy in ants|journal=[[The Science of Nature]] |volume=103 |issue=66 |doi=10.1007/s00114-016-1386-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, the relative contribution that workers make to this process differs widely among individuals, with certain ants attempting many more tandem runs than others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=O'Shea-Wheller TA, etal |year=2016 |title=A social mechanism facilitates ant colony emigrations over different distances|journal=[[Journal of Experimental Biology]] |doi=10.1242/jeb.145276}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Commons category|Temnothorax albipennis}}
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Myrmicinae]]
[[Category:Hymenoptera of Europe]]
[[Category:Insects described in 1854]]</text>
      <sha1>joc4tj1l2qf072epueyvbmuip8t1xoj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
