<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Bani Zeid</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>16476365</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746350114</id>
      <parentid>746093638</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-26T21:39:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>207.173.24.28</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Notable people */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="57428">{{For|the nearby Palestinian villages|Bani Zeid al-Sharqiya|Qarawat Bani Zeid}}
{{good article}}
{{Infobox Palestinian Authority municipality
|name        = Bani Zeid
|image       = 
|caption     = 
|arname      = بني زيد
|meaning     = &quot;[the] Zaid Tribe&quot;
|founded=
|type=munc
|typefrom=
|altOffSp    = Bani Zeid al-Gharbiyya
|altUnoSp    = Bani Zayd &lt;br&gt; Bani Zaid &lt;br&gt; West Bani Zeid
|governorate = rb
|latd=32|latm=02|lats=28|latNS=N
|longd=35 |longm=06|longs=6|longEW=E
|palgrid     = 159/161
|population  = 5,515
|population_footnotes = &lt;ref name=&quot;PCBS2007&quot;/&gt;
|popyear     = 2007
|area=
|areakm=
|mayor       = Abdel Karim Abu Aql
|website=
}}

'''Bani Zeid''' ({{lang-ar|&lt;big&gt;بني زيد&lt;/big&gt;}}) is a [[Palestinian people|Palestinian]] town in the [[Ramallah and al-Bireh Governorate]] in the north-central [[West Bank]], located {{convert|27|km|mi|sp=us}} northwest of [[Ramallah]], about 45 kilometers northwest of [[Jerusalem]] and about {{convert|6|km|mi|sp=us}} southwest of [[Salfit]]. A town of over 5,500 inhabitants,&lt;ref name=&quot;PCBS2007&quot;/&gt; Bani Zeid was founded when the villages of '''Deir Ghassaneh''' and '''Beit Rima''' merged to form a municipality in 1966 during [[Jordan]]ian rule.&lt;ref name=&quot;PACE&quot;&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20070811215036/http://www.pace.ps/publications/site.html Bani Zeid: Excerpt] Palestinian Association for Culture Exchange&lt;/ref&gt; The town owes its name to the [[Arab tribe]] that was granted the area as a [[fief]] by the [[Ayyubid dynasty|Ayyubid]] sultan [[Saladin]] in the 12th century for having served in the Muslim army during the first [[Crusades]]. It was settled by members of the tribe alongside the native ''[[fellahin]]'' (&quot;peasantry&quot;) during the reign of [[Mamluk Sultanate (Cairo)|Mamluk]] sultan [[Baibars]] in the mid-13th century. During [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] rule, the area of Bani Zeid served as a [[sheikdom]] with some administrative capacity. It consisted of several villages with Deir Ghassaneh as its [[throne village|center]]. During that time, the [[Barghouti]] family dominated the sheikdom.

During the [[1936–39 Arab revolt in Palestine|1936–39 Arab revolt]] against [[Mandatory Palestine|British Mandate]] rule, Deir Ghassaneh was the scene of rebel gatherings and British military raids. In 1967, Bani Zeid was occupied by [[Israel]] during the [[Six-Day War]], but it was transferred to full [[Palestinian National Authority|Palestinian]] security and administrative control in 2000. The next year it became the first Palestinian-controlled town to be the site of major operation by Israeli forces during the [[Second Intifada]]. When Fathiya Barghouti Rheime was elected mayor in 2005, Bani Zeid became the first Palestinian locality with a woman as head of the municipality, in concurrence with nearby Ramallah. The current mayor is Abdel Karim Abu Aql, elected in 2012.

Historically, Bani Zeid's economy was dependent on the [[olive]] crop, which was supplied to [[Nabulsi soap|soap factories]] in [[Nablus]]. Until the present day, olive trees cover most of the town's cultivable land. However, the residents of Bani Zeid today largely derive their income from employment in the civil service and private business. There are a number of archaeological sites in Bani Zeid, including the old town of Deir Ghassaneh, the manor of Sheikh Salih al-Barghouti and the ''[[Mazar (mausoleum)|maqam]]'' (&quot;saintly person's tomb&quot;) of Sheikh al-Khawwas.

==History==

===Early history===
Deir Ghassaneh has been identified as the ancient Saredah (also spelled ''Zeredah''), hometown of [[Jeroboam]]. According to some sources, it was settled by the [[Ghassanids]], an [[Arab Christian]] tribal confederation, after it was abandoned by the [[Israelite]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharon36&quot;/&gt; English orientalist [[Edward Henry Palmer]] (1840–1882) thought the name meant &quot;The monastery of the Ghassaneh [Ghassanids]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Palmer, 1881, p. [https://archive.org/stream/surveyofwesternp00conduoft#page/228/mode/1up 228]&lt;/ref&gt; However, according to [[Moshe Sharon]] (b. 1937), Israeli professor of Islamic history and civilisation, this claim has been dismissed by a number of researchers since the Ghassanids did not have a history of settlement in [[Samaria]], the modern-day northern West Bank.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharon36&quot;/&gt; Sharon suggests that the name of the village is related to the [[Arabic language|Arabic]] word ''ghassaneh'' which means &quot;very handsome&quot; or suggests &quot;youth and beauty&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharon36&quot;/&gt; Byzantine ceramics have been found in Deir Ghassaneh,&lt;ref name=Dauphin821&gt;Dauphin, 1998, p. 821&lt;/ref&gt; and on the north side of Beit Rima.&lt;ref&gt;Dauphin, 1998, p. 823&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, small fragments of a marble column were found in Deir Ghassaneh.&lt;ref name=Dauphin821/&gt; In Beit Rima, [[sherd]]s from the [[Iron Age#Near East timeline|Iron Age I]] and IA II, [[Achaemenid Empire|Persian]], [[Hellenistic period|Hellenistic]], [[Roman Empire|Roman]], [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine]], [[Crusader states|Crusader]]/[[Ayyubid dynasty|Ayyubid]], [[Mamluk Sultanate (Cairo)|Mamluk]] and Early Ottoman remains have been found.&lt;ref&gt;Finkelstein and Lederman, 1997, p. 279&lt;/ref&gt; In Deir Ghassaneh, sherds from all of the same periods, except Persian, have also been found.&lt;ref&gt;Finkelstein and Lederman, 1997, p. 281&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Sharon, there is no mention of Deir Ghassaneh or Beit Rima&lt;ref&gt;Meaning &quot;The house of Rima&quot;, see Palmer, 1881, p. [https://archive.org/stream/surveyofwesternp00conduoft#page/226/mode/1up 226]&lt;/ref&gt; in early Arabic sources, although it is known that Deir Ghassaneh was inhabited during the [[Mamluk Sultanate (Cairo)|Mamluk]] period due to the many houses there that have preserved elements of Mamluk architecture. Specific examples include the use of the ''[[ablaq]]'' technique of alternating stones of different colors, particularly red and white, that decorate the facades and gates of some houses.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharon36&quot;/&gt;

===Establishment of Bani Zeid tribe in Palestine===
The modern town of Bani Zeid receives its name from the [[Tribes of Arabia|Arab tribe]] of [[Banu Zayd|Bani Zeid]], who settled in Palestine during the [[Ayyubid dynasty|Ayyubid]] period in the late 12th century. They formed part of the [[Bedouin]] units of [[Saladin]]'s army that hailed from the [[Hejaz]]. After the [[Siege of Jerusalem (1187)|Siege of Jerusalem]] in 1187, Saladin's forces captured the city and the Ayyubid army was garrisoned there.&lt;ref name=&quot;PACE&quot;/&gt; The Bani Zeid temporarily resided in Jerusalem and a street, located near the present-day al-Sa'idia Street, was named after them, but has since been renamed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Singer&quot;/&gt;

In order for Saladin to persuade the Hejazi Arab tribes that joined his army to remain in Palestine, he offered each tribe a cluster of villages captured from the [[Crusades|Crusader]]s as ''[[iqta']]'' ([[fief]]s) to settle in and control. The Bani Zeid were granted the villages of Deir Ghassaneh and Beit Rima, as well as the nearby towns of [[Kafr Ein]] and [[Qarawat Bani Zeid|Qarawa]]. However, it was not until 1293, after the [[Bahri dynasty|Bahri Mamluk]]s under Sultan [[Baibars]] conquered the coastal strip of Palestine and expelled the last of the Crusaders, that the Bani Zeid tribe settled in those villages.&lt;ref name=&quot;PACE&quot;/&gt;

A Mamluk-era (1260–1516) stone inscription belonging to an unidentified building in Deir Ghassaneh dating from 1330 describes a two-story &quot;felicitous palace&quot; with a garden. The palace was apparently an asset of the Sultan [[al-Nasir Muhammad]] and was inspected by Isa Muhammad al-Qaymari, a low-ranking ''[[emir]]'' from the [[Mosul]] region in charge of overseeing the personal assets of the sultan.&lt;ref&gt;Sharon, 2004, pp. [https://books.google.com/books?id=01ogNhTNz54C&amp;pg=PA46 46]-47.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1480 Deir Ghassaneh-based tribesmen from the Bani Zeid attacked Jerusalem as retaliation for the governor's execution of some of its members who had been accused of revolting against the [[Burji dynasty|Burji Mamluk]] authorities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Singer&quot;&gt;Singer, 1994, p. [https://books.google.com/books?id=mrsAw_mk1d0C&amp;pg=PA179 179]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Early Ottoman era===
During the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] era in Palestine, the area where the Bani Zeid tribe settled became the ''[[nahiya]]'' (subdistrict) of Bani Zeid, part of the larger ''[[sanjak]]'' (district) of Quds (Jerusalem). The ''nahiya'' contained over 20 towns and villages and had jurisdiction over a part of [[Salfit]].&lt;ref&gt;The 20 villages were [['Atara]], [[Ajjul]], [[Bani Zeid al-Sharqiya|'Arura]], Beit Rima, [[Deir Dibwan]], Deir Ghassaneh, [[Ein Siniya]], [[Yabrud, Ramallah|Yabrud]], [[Jifna]], Jiljiliya, [[Kafr Ein]], [[Kafr Aqab]], [[Qarawat Bani Zeid|Qarawa]], [[Kafr 'Ana]], [[Bani Zeid al-Sharqiya|Mazari]], [[al-Mazra'a ash-Sharqiya]], [[Nabi Salih]], [[Deir as-Sudan]], [[Kobar]], [[Surda, Ramallah|Surda]]. See Singer, 1994, p. [https://books.google.com/books?id=mrsAw_mk1d0C&amp;pg=PA77 77].&lt;/ref&gt; While these villages were registered and organized like other villages in the Jerusalem Sanjak, they were also treated as a group. Each village was led by a ''ra'is'' (local chief) and the entire Bani Zeid Nahiya was headed by a [[sheikh]] (paramount chief).&lt;ref name=&quot;Singer76-8&quot;/&gt; The Bani Zeid [[sheikdom]] would serve as a political-administrative unit for the purposes of tax collection and army mobilization.&lt;ref&gt;Amiry, 1987, p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1556 the sheikdom was led by Sheikh Abu Rayyan bin Sheikh Manna, who was succeeded by Sheikh Muhammad Abu Rabban in 1560. [[Olive oil]] was the primary commodity that Bani Zeid Nahiya produced and the product was sold to local Ottoman officials and [[Nabulsi soap|soap factories in Nablus]]. The Ottomans imposed taxes on olive oil, wheat and barley, and the sheikh was responsible for paying the revenues of collected taxes to the Ottoman authorities. In addition, Bani Zeid was required to finance a ''[[waqf]]'' (religious endowment) to the [[al-Aqsa Mosque]] in Jerusalem and the [[Cave of the Patriarchs|Ibrahimi Mosque]] in [[Hebron]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Singer76-8&quot;&gt;Singer, 1994, pp. [https://books.google.com/books?id=mrsAw_mk1d0C&amp;pg=PA76 76]-78.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1596 both Deir Ghassaneh and Beit Rima appeared in Ottoman [[daftar|tax registers]] and both villages paid taxes on wheat, barley, olive trees, fruit trees, vineyards, goats and/or beehives.&lt;ref&gt;Hütteroth and Abdulfattah, 1977, p. 120-121&lt;/ref&gt; Deir Ghassaneh had a population of 76 households, all Muslim,&lt;ref&gt;Hütteroth and Abdulfattah, 1977, p. 120.&lt;/ref&gt; while Beit Rima had 54 Muslim households and 14 Christian households.&lt;ref&gt;Hütteroth and Abdulfattah, 1977, p. 121.&lt;/ref&gt; During the course of the 16th century, most of Beit Rima's Christian inhabitants had emigrated from the village to Jerusalem, [[Ramla]] and [[Gaza City|Gaza]], although the Christian population that remained continued to grow.&lt;ref&gt;Singer, 1994, p. [https://books.google.com/books?id=mrsAw_mk1d0C&amp;pg=PA180 180]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Nineteenth century===
In the 19th century Bani Zeid was one of 21 sheikdoms in the central highlands of Palestine. While its exact borders varied from time to time, it was generally marked by the Wadi al-Dilb stream to the south, which separated it from the Bani Harith al-Shamali sheikdom, and the Wadi Nattif stream to the north that separated it from [[Jamma'in|Bilad Jamma'in]]. The Bani Zeid sheikdom contained the highest slopes and the largest concentration of mountain faults of all the highland sheikdoms. About two-thirds of its villages were situated on relatively wide hilltops while the remainder were built along slopes. None were located in the valleys or the foothills.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amiry44&quot;&gt;Amiry, 1987, p. 44.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1838 English biblical scholars [[Edward Robinson (scholar)|Edward Robinson]] and [[Eli Smith]] noted that the Bani Zeid Nahiya consisted of 18 inhabited localities and four ''[[khirba]]s'' (abandoned or ruined villages). They classified Deir Ghassaneh and Beit Rima as inhabited by Muslims.&lt;ref&gt;Robinson and Smith, 1841, vol 3, 2nd appendix, pp. [https://archive.org/stream/biblicalresearch03robiuoft#page/124/mode/1up 124]-125. The 18 inhabited villages of the Bani Zeid District were listed as [[Deir Abu Mash'al]], [[Deir Nidham|Deir ad-Dam]], [[Aboud|Abud]], Beit Rima, Deir Ghusaneh, [[Kafr Ein|Kafr Iyan]], [[Qarawat Bani Zeid|Kurawa]], [[Deir as-Sudan]], [[Bani Zeid al-Sharqiya#Mazari al-Nubani|al-Mezari'a]], [[Bani Zeid al-Sharqiya|'Arura]], [[Ajjul]], [[Jiljilia]], [['Atara]], [[Abwein]], Umm Safa, [[Burham, Ramallah|Burham]], Jibiya and [[Kobar]]. The four ''khirba''s are [[Nabi Salih]], Khirbet Ibrahim, Artubba and Rashaniya.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early 19th century, the paramount sheikhs of Bani Zeid were Sheikh Marif al-Barghouti and Sheikh 'Asi al-Rabbah Barghouti.&lt;ref name=&quot;PEF355&quot;/&gt; They belonged to the wealthy noble family of [[Barghouti|al-Barghouti]], a sub-clan of the Bani Zeid tribe that traditionally provided the leaders of the sheikdom.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bussow114&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharon41&quot;/&gt; Its members were generally referred to as ''Baraghithah'' and the clan consisted of nine branches whose collective power extended beyond the Bani Zeid sheikdom to the coastal plain of Palestine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bussow113&quot;/&gt; During the period of [[Muhammad Ali Dynasty|Khedivate Egyptian]] rule in the [[Levant]] (1832–1840), Sheikh 'Abd al-Jabir al-Barghouti, a nephew of Sheikh Marif,&lt;ref name=&quot;PEF355&quot;&gt;Macalister and Masterman, 1905, p. [https://archive.org/stream/quarterlystateme37pale#page/355/mode/1up 355]&lt;/ref&gt; served as the chief of the Bani Zeid.&lt;ref name=&quot;PEF355&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Amiry45&quot;&gt;Amiry, 1987, p. 45.&lt;/ref&gt; Sheikh 'Abd al-Jabir belonged to the al-Zahir branch of the family which was based in Deir Ghassaneh.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bussow113&quot;/&gt; Deir Ghassaneh served as the sheikdom's ''qaryat al-kursi'' ([[throne village]] or capital).&lt;ref name=&quot;Amiry44&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bussow114&quot;/&gt; During the early part of Egyptian rule, Governor [[Ibrahim Pasha of Egypt|Ibrahim Pasha]] had Sheikh 'Abd al-Jabir executed.&lt;ref name=&quot;PEF355&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Amiry45&quot;/&gt; He was succeeded by Sheikh Ali al-Rabbah, another leading Barghouti sheikh and a son of Sheikh Asi. The latter was also subsequently executed on the orders of Ibrahim Pasha.&lt;ref name=&quot;PEF355&quot;/&gt; Both sheikhs and their peasant fighters had fought against Egyptian rule during the [[Peasants' Revolt of 1834 (Palestine)|1834 Peasants' Revolt]] that spread throughout Palestine.&lt;ref&gt;Macalister and Masterman, 1906, p. [https://archive.org/stream/quarterlystateme38pale#page/39/mode/1up 39]&lt;/ref&gt; During the last years of Egyptian control, Sheikh Musa Ahmad al-Sahwil of [[Abwein]] became the paramount sheikh of the Bani Zeid and continued to exercise great influence over the sheikdom when the Egyptian military withdrew from Palestine in 1841.&lt;ref name=&quot;PEF355&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Amiry45&quot;/&gt;

In the second half of the 19th century Bani Zeid was officially ruled by Sheikh Salih al-Barghouti,&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharon41&quot;&gt;Sharon, 2004, p. [https://books.google.com/books?id=01ogNhTNz54C&amp;pg=PA41 41]&lt;/ref&gt; although he struggled to maintain full authority over the sheikdom, having to contend with his Abwein-based rival Sheikh Musa and his family, al-Sahwil.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amiry45&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bussow112&quot;&gt;Bussow, 2011, p. [https://books.google.com/books?id=crPPX99rjYUC&amp;pg=PA112 112]&lt;/ref&gt; The latter controlled seven villages in the eastern part of the sheikdom, while the Barghouti maintained control over twelve villages in the western part. The two domains were separated by a ''[[wadi]]'' (seasonal stream).&lt;ref name=&quot;Amiry45&quot;/&gt; Nonetheless, Sheikh Salih enjoyed high political and social status, holding the official title of ''sheikh al-nahiya'' (chief of the subdistrict) and was also referred to locally as ''sheikh al-mashayikh'' (chief of the chieftains).&lt;ref name=&quot;Bussow112&quot;/&gt; The title ceased to be recognized by the [[Sublime Porte|Istanbul-based central government]] in 1864, but locally the title continued to demonstrate the guise of official authority.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bussow113&quot;/&gt; As ''sheikh al-nahiya'', Sheikh Salih was tasked with the nomination and dismissal of ''[[mukhtar|makhatir]]'' (village headmen) and maintaining order through local custom.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bussow112&quot;/&gt; He also served as the ''[[Iltizam|multazim]]'' (tax collector) of the Bani Zeid sheikdom on behalf of the Ottoman authorities, despite the ban on tax-farming in 1853. This role in particular enabled the Barghouti clan to acquire vast wealth and property either forcefully or through legal transfer.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bussow113&quot;/&gt; During previous inter-family disputes, members of the clan had begun to settle in the surrounding villages of Beit Rima, [[Kobar]] and [[Deir Nidham]].&lt;ref name=&quot;PEF355&quot;/&gt;

As members of the [[Qais]] tribo-political faction, in [[Qays and Yaman tribes|opposition to the Yaman faction]], the Barghouti aligned themselves with Qaisi-affiliated [[Bedouin]] tribes and other prominent families, including the Khalidi clan of Jerusalem, the 'Amr, [[Bayt Jibrin#Ottoman rule and the 'Azza family|'Azza]] and 'Amla clans of the Hebron area and the Samhan clan of the [[Lajjun#Ottoman era|Bani Harith]] ''nahiya'' to the north.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bussow113&quot;&gt;Bussow, 2011, p. [https://books.google.com/books?id=crPPX99rjYUC&amp;pg=PA113 113]&lt;/ref&gt; In 1855–1856 tensions between Sheikh Salih and the leading families of [[Nablus]] broke out into fierce clashes. Sheikh Salih was eventually able to compel the Ottoman authorities to take the local rulers of Nablus to task.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bussow128&quot;/&gt; The restive sheikhs of the Jerusalem and Hebron regions were called to [[Damascus]] to conclude a lasting peace, but all were condemned to exile in [[Trabzon]], northern [[Anatolia]], with the exception of Sheikh Salih who apparently impressed the governor and was allowed to return to Deir Ghassaneh.&lt;ref&gt;Bussow, 2011, pp. [https://books.google.com/books?id=crPPX99rjYUC&amp;pg=PA129 129]-130.&lt;/ref&gt; The Barghouti clan would later support the Dar Hammad tribe against the Dar Hamid, both of which were engaged in a feud in nearby [[Silwad]]. In one day of fighting, 20 men were killed, prompting Sureya Pasha, the governor of Jerusalem, to personally intervene with a detachment of Ottoman troops which forced both factions to withdraw.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bussow128&quot;&gt;Bussow, 2011, p. [https://books.google.com/books?id=crPPX99rjYUC&amp;pg=PA128 128]&lt;/ref&gt;

French explorer [[Victor Guérin]] visited both Deir Ghassaneh and Beit Rima in 1863. He noted that the former had a population of roughly 900 and was built on a mountain overlooking hills filled with &quot;magnificent&quot; olive groves. Beit Rima had a smaller population of 350, and was situated on a high plateau covered with olive and fig groves. The houses of both villages were constructed from red and white stone masonry and the [[mosque]] in Deir Ghassaneh, which Guérin regarded as noteworthy, was built from black and white stone. The home of Deir Ghassaneh's sheikh, who maintained a level of sovereignty over about 15 villages and hamlets in the area, and the members of his family, were particularly large and sturdily built.&lt;ref&gt;Guérin, 1875, p. [https://archive.org/stream/descriptiongogr04gugoog#page/n175/mode/1up 150] ff.&lt;/ref&gt; According to Sharon, the sheikh Guérin had referred to was Sheikh Salih.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharon41&quot;/&gt; It was around this time, in the late 1860s, that the prominent [[al-Husayni]] clan of Jerusalem unsuccessfully attempted to form an alliance with the Barghouti clan, initially through diplomatic means. Afterward, they commissioned their allies in Istanbul to launch a propaganda campaign against the Barghouti clan, accusing them of undermining the sultan. This allegation was evidenced by the disruption of Jerusalem's water supply by the peasant fighters of the Bani Zeid led by Sheikh Salih, who closed off the aqueduct from [[Solomon's Pools]] to the south of [[Bethlehem]].&lt;ref&gt;Bussow, 2011, pp. [https://books.google.com/books?id=crPPX99rjYUC&amp;pg=PA128 128]-129.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1887 census the Bani Zeid sheikdom consisted of 24 villages with an estimated collective population of 7,700, including 400 [[Arab Christians|Christian]]s. According to the census, Deir Ghassaneh had 1,200 inhabitants living in 196 households, making it significantly larger than the surrounding localities. There were nine elite households, each of whose family head was recognized by the census as a sheikh.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bussow114&quot;&gt;Bussow, 2011, p. [https://books.google.com/books?id=crPPX99rjYUC&amp;pg=PA114 114]&lt;/ref&gt; The local imam, Muhammad Shams al-Din al-Shaykh Hanafi, was [[Egypt]]ian and one of five men in Deir Ghassaneh born outside the village.&lt;ref&gt;Bussow, 2011, p. [https://books.google.com/books?id=crPPX99rjYUC&amp;pg=PA115 115]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Palestine Exploration Fund]]'s ''Survey of Western Palestine'' (''SWP'') in the late 19th century stated Deir Ghassaneh was &quot;a village on a ridge, with springs in the valley below. It is of moderate size, built of stone and has olives beneath it.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SWP290&quot;&gt;Conder and Kitchener, 1882, p. [https://archive.org/stream/surveyofwesternp02conduoft#page/290/mode/1up 290]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharon37&quot;/&gt; The ''SWP'' described Beit Rima as &quot;a small village on the summit of a ridge with wells to the west&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;SWP290&quot;/&gt;

===Modern era===
[[File:Bani_Zeid.JPG|thumb|right|Mosque of Bani Zeid, 2012]]
Sheikh Salih was succeeded by his son Umar Salih al-Barghouti, who aligned Bani Zeid with the [[Nashashibi]] clan of Jerusalem against the al-Husayni clan in the contest for political dominance in Palestine during the [[British Mandate for Palestine|British Mandate]] period.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharon41&quot;/&gt; In 1936, during the [[1936–39 Arab revolt in Palestine|Arab revolt in Palestine]], the [[Royal Air Force|British Air Force]] struck a group of 400 local [[militia]]men gathered outside of Deir Ghassaneh, killing about 130 of the fighters.&lt;ref&gt;Probert, 2006, p. 82.&lt;/ref&gt; Later, in September 1938, the local rebel leadership held a meeting in the village where it was decided that [[Abd al-Rahim al-Hajj Muhammad]] and [[Arif Abd al-Raziq]] would each serve as general commander of the revolt on a rotational basis. Deir Ghassaneh was subsequently attacked by British forces backed by fighter planes when they were informed of the conference. A rebel commander, Muhammad al-Salih, was killed in the ensuing firefight.&lt;ref&gt;LeVine, Sonia Nimr, 2012, pp. 150-151.&lt;/ref&gt; The British Mandate Antiquities Authority noted in a January 1947 report that Deir Ghassaneh was &quot;built on a medieval site,&quot; and on a hill {{convert|500|m|ft|sp=us}} west of the village was a two-domed shrine dedicated to a Sheikh Khawas.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharon37&quot;/&gt;

Deir Ghassaneh and Beit Rima were merged and granted municipal status in February 1966 during [[Occupation of the West Bank and East Jerusalem by Jordan|Jordanian rule]], partially due to the efforts of [[Kassim al-Rimawi]], the rural affairs minister at the time and a native of Beit Rima. Its first mayor, Adib Mohammed Rimawi, was appointed by [[Hussein of Jordan|King Hussein]].&lt;ref name=&quot;PMCM&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://west-bzm.org/about1.htm |title=About Municipality |publisher=Municipality of West Bani Zaid |language=Arabic |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080311164407/http://west-bzm.org/about1.htm |archivedate=March 11, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The municipality building is located in Beit Rima.&lt;ref name=&quot;ARIJ&quot;/&gt; In June 1967 [[Israel]] occupied the [[West Bank]] after defeating Arab forces in the [[Six Day War]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ARIJ&quot;/&gt; In 1972 the first municipal polls were held and Fa'eq Ali Rimawi was elected.&lt;ref name=&quot;PMCM&quot;/&gt; In 1978 Bani Zeid was one of several Palestinian localities to append its municipal seal to the ''Memorandum from the masses and the institutions of the West Bank to the Executive Committee of the Palestine Liberation Organization'' in a display of unity with the [[Palestine Liberation Organization]] (PLO). The memorandum was a rejection of any solution, regardless of its origin, not containing a clear recognition of the right of the [[Palestinian people]] to self-determination and to establishing an independent [[Palestinian state|Palestinian national state]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://domino.un.org/UNISPAL.NSF/db942872b9eae454852560f6005a76fb/9b11c5aab7c1709785256fd30059a947!OpenDocument UN Doc] A/33/165 of 5 July 1978&lt;/ref&gt; In 2000 Bani Zeid was incorporated into [[Area A]] giving the [[Palestinian National Authority]] (PNA), the Palestinian governing body established after the [[Oslo Accords|Oslo Agreements]] with Israel in 1993, full control over security and civilian affairs in the town.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.poica.org/editor/case_studies/view.php?recordID=204 The Israeli Army Ravages Beit Rima] Applied Research Institute - Jerusalem. 2001-11-05.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the late night hours of 24 October 2001, during the [[Second Intifada]], the [[Israel Defense Forces|Israeli Army]] (IDF) launched an incursion into Beit Rima in what became the first major Israeli military raid into Palestinian-controlled territory, according to [[Human Rights Watch]] (HRW).&lt;ref name=&quot;HRW&quot;&gt;[[Human Rights Watch]]. [https://books.google.com/books?id=5pENcHhOmiMC&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s Israel, the Occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip, and the Palestinian Authority Territories]. '''14''':2. April 2002. pp. 9-10.&lt;/ref&gt; The IDF stated the intent of the raid was to capture the alleged killers of Israeli Tourism Minister [[Rehavam Ze'evi]], who was shot dead by members of the [[Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine]] (PFLP) in retaliation for Israel's assassination of the party's leader [[Abu Ali Mustafa|Mustafa Zibri]] (Abu Ali Mustafa) in August.&lt;ref name=&quot;ChTribune&quot;/&gt; About 50 people from Beit Rima were detained and brought to the Israeli settlement of [[Halamish]] for interrogation. Most were released before the day's end, but eleven men remained in Israeli custody, two of whom Israel alleged to be directly involved in Ze'evi's assassination. In the course of the raid, Israeli forces killed six Palestinians, including three members of the [[Palestinian National Security Forces]] and two officers from the Civil Police, and wounded seven others. The Palestinian authorities in Beit Rima stated they had not received prior warning from the IDF and their slain men had been resting in an olive grove near the local police station,&lt;ref name=&quot;HRW&quot;/&gt; while Israeli military officials stated all those killed had either fired on Israeli forces or approached them threateningly and all were members of various armed groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNN&quot;&gt;Hanna, Mike. [http://edition.cnn.com/2001/WORLD/meast/10/25/hanna.otsc/index.html  Hanna: Beit Rima clashes]. ''CNN''. 2001-10-25.&lt;/ref&gt; The HRW stated that the [[Red Crescent]] was prevented from treating the injured men until 7:00 am, a delay that resulted in the death of two of the police officers.&lt;ref name=&quot;HRW&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ChTribune&quot;&gt;Dellios, Hugh.[http://www.chicagotribune.com/entertainment/movies/chi-0110250272oct25,0,2998582.story?page=2 Israel raids village to pursue assassins] ''[[Chicago Tribune]]''. 2001-10-05. pp. 1-2.&lt;/ref&gt; Israeli forces also demolished three homes in the town, alleging that they belonged to family members of Ze'evi's killers.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNN&quot;/&gt;

==Geography==
Bani Zeid is situated in the central highlands of the West Bank, off the southwestern cliffs of the mountainous spine that runs from the [[Hebron Hills]] to [[Jenin]]. It has an average elevation of {{convert|510|m|ft|sp=us}} above sea level.&lt;ref name=&quot;PACE&quot;/&gt; The northern part of the town (Deir Ghassaneh) is built on a hilltop with an elevation of roughly 450 meters above sea level. It overlooks the Wadi al-Saredah stream {{convert|1|km|mi|sp=us}} to the north.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharon36&quot;&gt;Sharon, 2004, p. [https://books.google.com/books?id=01ogNhTNz54C&amp;pg=PA36 36]&lt;/ref&gt; Bani Zeid is located {{convert|17.5|km|mi|sp=us}} north of [[Ramallah]] and less than {{convert|45|km|mi|sp=us}} northwest of Jerusalem.&lt;ref name=&quot;ARIJ&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Maraqa&quot;&gt;Maraqa, Hania Nabil. [http://arizona.openrepository.com/arizona/bitstream/10150/190208/1/azu_etd_mr0020_sip1_m.pdf Palestinians; From Village Peasant to Camp Refugees: Analogies and Disparities in the Social Use of Space]. University of Arizona-Faculty of the School of Architecture. 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; Nearby localities include [[Kafr ad-Dik]] and [[Bruqin]] to the north, [[Qarawat Bani Zeid]] to the northeast, [[Kafr Ein]] to the east, [[Nabi Salih]] to the southeast, [[Deir Nidham]] and the [[Israeli settlement]] of [[Halamish]] to the south, [[Aboud]] to the southwest, [[al-Lubban al-Gharbi]] and the settlement of [[Beit Aryeh]] to the west and the settlement of [[Peduel]] to the northwest.&lt;ref name=&quot;ARIJ&quot;/&gt;

Bani Zeid had a total land area of 22,249 [[dunam]]s in 1945, of which 90 dunams were classified as built-up areas (Deir Ghassaneh was larger than Beit Rima) and 8,400 dunams were planted with olive or fig groves.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hadawi&quot;/&gt; Today the Bani Zeid municipality has a jurisdiction of over 21,979 dunams, of which 80.6% is cultivable land. today Beit Rima is the larger village. The built-up areas of the town constitute 918 dunams, 832 of which is geared towards residential areas while the remaining 86 is used for commercial, industrial and transportation purposes.&lt;ref name=&quot;ARIJ&quot;/&gt; The town is surrounded by olive groves,&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharon36&quot;/&gt; which Bani Zeid is well known for, and 14,505 dunams are planted with olive trees.&lt;ref name=&quot;ARIJ&quot;/&gt; The old village center of Deir Ghassaneh consists of three quarters: Harat al-Barghouti (Harat al-Fauqa), Harat al-Shu'aibi and Harat al-Tahtani.&lt;ref&gt;Amiry, 1987, p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt;

The average annual rainfall in the town is {{convert|592.9|mm|in|sp=us}} and average annual humidity is roughly 62%. Average temperature is {{convert|17.4|°C|°F}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;ARIJ&quot;/&gt;

==Demographics==
Ottoman village statistics from 1870 showed that &quot;Der Ghassana&quot; had 164 houses and a population of 559,&lt;ref&gt;Socin, 1879, p. [https://archive.org/stream/zeitschriftdesde01deut#page/152/mode/1up 152]&lt;/ref&gt; while &quot;Bet Rima&quot; had 60 houses and a population of 220, though in both cases the population count included only men.&lt;ref&gt;Socin, 1879, p. [https://archive.org/stream/zeitschriftdesde01deut#page/147/mode/1up 147]&lt;/ref&gt; In the Ottoman census of 1887, Deir Ghassaneh's population of 196 households (roughly 1,200 people) was homogeneous, everyone being Muslim, and with the exception of five individuals, all the males had been born in the village. The estimated 9% of the inhabitants who were born outside the village were almost exclusively women, with one fifth of all females hailing primarily from other villages in the Bani Zeid ''nahiya'' such as Beit Rima, Abwein, [[Kobar]] and [[Kafr Ein]] and about 14 women originating from other parts of Palestine, particularly [[Ashkelon|al-Madjal Ascalon]]. Several men from Deir Ghassaneh settled in the surrounding villages, namely Beit Rima, [[Deir Nidham]] and Nabi Salih.&lt;ref&gt;Bussow, 2011, pp. [https://books.google.com/books?id=crPPX99rjYUC&amp;pg=PA116 116]-117.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[1922 census of Palestine]], conducted by the British Mandatory authorities, &quot;Dair Ghassaneh&quot; had a population of 625, while &quot;Bait Rema&quot; had a population of 555, all Muslims.&lt;ref&gt;Barron, 1923, Table VII, Sub-district of Ramallah, p.  [https://archive.org/stream/PalestineCensus1922/Palestine%20Census%20%281922%29#page/n18/mode/1up  16]&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[1931 census of Palestine|1931 census]] Deir Ghassaneh had 181 occupied houses and a population of 753,&lt;ref name=&quot;Census1931&quot;&gt;Mills, 1932, p. [https://archive.org/details/CensusOfPalestine1931.PopulationOfVillagesTownsAndAdministrativeAreas 48].&lt;/ref&gt; while Beit Rima had had 175 occupied houses and a population of 746, still all Muslim.&lt;ref&gt;Mills, 1932, p. [https://archive.org/details/CensusOfPalestine1931.PopulationOfVillagesTownsAndAdministrativeAreas 47].&lt;/ref&gt; In a land and population survey by [[Sami Hadawi]] in 1945 both villages had a total population of 1,810. Beit Rima had a slightly larger population, but Deir Ghassaneh had a larger land area.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hadawi&quot;&gt;Government of Palestine, Department of Statistics. ''Village Statistics, April, 1945.'' Quoted in Hadawi, 1970, p. [http://www.palestineremembered.com/download/VillageStatistics/Table%20I/Ramallah/Page-064.jpg 64]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=1945p26&gt;Department of Statistics, 1945, p. [http://cs.anu.edu.au/~bdm/yabber/census/VSpages/VS1945_p26.jpg  26]&lt;/ref&gt; In a 1961 census by Jordanian authorities, Deir Ghassaneh's population reached 1,461, but it declined drastically after more than half of the residents fled during the Six-Day War in June 1967. In 1982 there were 892 inhabitants in the town. Beit Rima had 2,165 inhabitants in 1961 and unlike Deir Ghassaneh, the population continued to grow, reaching 3,451 in 1987.&lt;ref name=&quot;PR&quot;&gt;[http://www.palestineremembered.com/GeoPoints/Bayt_Rima_882/index.html Bayt Rima Statistics] and [http://www.palestineremembered.com/GeoPoints/Dayr_Ghassana_963/index.html Dayr Ghassana Statistics] British Mandate censuses via PalestineRemembered.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the first census taken by the [[Palestinian Central Bureau of Statistics]] (PCBS) in 1997, Bani Zeid had a population of 4,351 inhabitants. The gender make-up was 51.8% male and 49.2% female. More than half of the population was under the age of 20 (51.1%), while 27.7% were between the ages of 20 and 39, 15% between the ages of 40 and 64, and the remainder of the population being 65 or older (6%). [[Palestinian refugee]]s made up 6.8% of the residents in 1997.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pcbs.gov.ps/Portals/_pcbs/phc_97/ram_t1.aspx Palestinian Population by Locality, Sex and Age Groups in Years]&lt;br&gt;[http://www.pcbs.gov.ps/Portals/_pcbs/phc_97/ram_t6.aspx Palestinian Population by Locality and Refugee Status] Results of 1997 Census by the [[Palestinian Central Bureau of Statistics]] (PCBS) for the [[Ramallah and al-Bireh Governorate]].&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the PCBS census of 2007, Bani Zeid had a population of 5,515, of which 49% were males and 51% females. There were 1,176 housing units and the average size of a household was five family members.&lt;ref name=&quot;PCBS2007&quot;&gt;[http://www.pcbs.gov.ps/Portals/_PCBS/Downloads/book1487.pdf 2007 PCBS Census]. [[Palestinian Central Bureau of Statistics]]. p. 112.&lt;/ref&gt; The town's principal clans are al-Rimawi, [[Barghouti|al-Barghouti]], al-Shu'aibi, al-Ramahi and Mashaal, although there are also a number of smaller families. Today, there are three [[mosque]]s in the town, the Bani Zeid Mosque, the Abu Bakr al-Siddiq Mosque and the Omar ibn al-Khattab Mosque.&lt;ref name=&quot;ARIJ&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Bani Zeid Town Profile|url=http://vprofile.arij.org/ramallah/pdfs/vprofile/Bani_Zeid_TP_en.pdf|year=2012|publisher=[[Applied Research Institute-Jerusalem]] (ARI)|accessdate=2013-02-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Economy and education==
Historically, Deir Ghassaneh depended primarily on olive cultivation,&lt;ref&gt;Carter (ed), 1996, p. [https://books.google.com/books?id=jvzkoJHe2h0C&amp;pg=PA394 394]&lt;/ref&gt; and until the present day most of Bani Zeid's cultivable land is covered by olive orchards. The cultivation of other fruit trees is significantly lower, with [[almond]]s being a distant second at 240 [[dunam]]s. Other crops grown include grains which cover 135 dunams and onions, dry legumes and [[forage|fodder]] to a lesser degree. Only 1% of the town's residents own livestock and according to the Palestinian Ministry of Agriculture, there were 1,880 goats, 268 sheep, 12 cows and 281 beehives in Bani Zeid in 2009. Agriculture currently accounts for 10% of labor in the town.&lt;ref name=&quot;ARIJ&quot;/&gt;

Today, employment by the [[Palestinian National Authority|Palestinian government]] and private businesses is the dominant economic activity in Bani Zeid, making up around 70% of the town's workforce. The trade sector accounts for 10% of the labor force, followed by the industrial sector which makes up 8%. Work in the Israeli labor market employs around 2% of the working population. Unemployment in the town was at 20% in 2011. According to the Bani Zeid Municipality, there are 26 grocery stores, 26 public service venues, 11 workshops, a bakery, a butchery and two [[olive oil]] presses in the town.&lt;ref name=&quot;ARIJ&quot;/&gt;

A school was founded in Deir Ghassaneh in 1925.&lt;ref&gt;Amiry, 1986, p. 241.&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to the British Mandate period, boys would normally receive education in a ''[[Maktab|kuttab]]'', an elementary-type school with Islamic law and tradition having a major influence on the curriculum.&lt;ref&gt;Amiry, 1986, p. 195.&lt;/ref&gt; Today, there is one elementary school (Bani Zeid Elementary School) and one secondary school (Bashir al-Barghouti Secondary School) in the town of Bani Zeid, both run by the government. According to the Palestinian Ministry of Education and Higher Education, in the 2010-2011 academic year there were 26 classes occupied by 691 students, both male and female. There was 45 teaching staff. There are no kindergartens in Bani Zeid. The closest institution for higher learning is [[Birzeit University]] in the village of [[Bir Zeit]] to the southeast.&lt;ref name=&quot;ARIJ&quot;/&gt;

According to the PCBS, in 2007 94.5% of the population over the age of 10 was literate. Of that demographic segment, 21.7% received elementary education, 24.8% received primary education and 20.2% had secondary education. Over 15% had completed some form of higher education (617 persons), with 248 attaining associate degrees, 324 attaining bachelor's degrees and 45 obtaining higher diplomas.&lt;ref name=&quot;ARIJ&quot;/&gt;

==Governance==
Bani Zeid is governed by a [[Municipality (Palestinian Authority)|municipal council]] of 13 members, including the chairman (mayor) and vice-chairman, under the name Municipality of West Bani Zaid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://west-bzm.org/munmembers.htm |title=Current Municipal Council of West Bani Zaid |publisher=Municipality of West Bani Zaid |language=Arabic |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080311164555/http://west-bzm.org/munmembers.htm |archivedate=March 11, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In normal circumstances the town holds election every four years. In the [[Palestinian local elections, 2004–2005|2005 elections]], the [[Hamas]]-affiliated party won five municipal seats, including the post of mayor, which was won by a female candidate Fathiya Barghouti Rheime who, along with [[Janet Mikhail]] of Ramallah, became the first woman to hold the post of a Palestinian municipality head. The [[Fatah]] list won five seats, the [[Palestinian People's Party]] (PPP) list won one, and a socialist party won the remaining seat.&lt;ref&gt;Moore, Molly.[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A45603-2005Jan28.html Democracy's New Face: Radical and Female Palestinian Mayor Embodies Both Tradition and Change in Middle East] ''Washington Post Foreign Service''. Washington Post Company. 2005-01-29.&lt;/ref&gt;

During an Israeli raid in Bani Zeid in 2007, two Hamas party members in the municipal council were arrested by Israeli authorities along with dozens of other Palestinian mayors, parliament members and ministers belonging to Hamas throughout the West Bank. The arrest of the two put the number of [[Palestinian prisoners in Israel|incarcerated]] West Bani Zeid Municipality Hamas members to three (member 'Ala Rimawi was elected to his post while serving a prison sentence.)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalresearch.ca/index.php?context=va&amp;aid=5755 Israeli forces arrest Palestinian minister of education, former minister of public works, mayors and PLC members] Ma'an News Agency. 2007-05-24.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the most [[Palestinian local elections, 2012|recent polls]] in 2012, Abdel Karim Abu Aql was elected mayor on a leftist alliance list as were the other 12 people elected to the council. The elections were boycotted by Hamas.&lt;ref name=&quot;WAFA&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wafainfo.ps/pdf/ramallah9.pdf|title=2012 Local Elections: West Bani Zeid|work=Palestine Central Elections Commission|publisher=[[Wafa]]|year=2012|accessdate=2013-04-24|language=Arabic}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bani Zeid has had six mayors since the establishment of the municipality in 1966.&lt;ref name=&quot;PMCM&quot;/&gt;

The municipal council takes part in the international [[town twinning]] scheme, and have twinned with [[Bezons]] in France.&lt;ref&gt;Leon, Eli. [http://www.israelhayom.com/site/newsletter_article.php?id=7895 Paris suburb honors Palestinian assassin of Israeli minister]. ''[[Israel Hayom]]''. 2013-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aljazeera.com/news/middleeast/2013/03/2013311133544283976.html French town honours Israeli minister 'killer']. ''[[Al Jazeera English]]''. 2013-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Religious sites==
One of the notable characteristics of Deir Ghassaneh was the concentration of 16 local Muslim shrines or saintly-person tombs (''maqam'', pl. ''maqamat'') in its vicinity which served as visitation sites for the pre-20th-century Palestinian community. According to author and ethnographer Johann Bussow, their locations near Jerusalem also &quot;contributed to the image of an Islamic Holy Land,&quot; which brought further prosperity to the inhabitants of the villages of Bani Zeid who benefited from providing services to pilgrims. The Barghouti family served as patrons for the various religious sheikhs who oversaw the shrines. The ''maqamat'' were dedicated either to prophets (''[[prophets in Islam|anbah]]'') recognized by the [[Qur'an]] or saintly-persons known as ''[[wali|wely]]s'', whom locals believed had been &quot;close to God.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bussow123-4&quot;&gt;Bussow, 2011, pp. [https://books.google.com/books?id=crPPX99rjYUC&amp;pg=PA123 123]-124.&lt;/ref&gt; The veneration of the ''welys'' tombs, a common feature in peasant life, did not derive from the [[Sunni Islam|orthodox Islam]] which was practiced more strictly in the urban centers, and was rooted in local pre-Islamic, including Christian, tradition.&lt;ref&gt;Maraqa, 2004, p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt;

All the ''maqamat'' of Bani Zeid were designed differently, with some being rustic tombstones and others built more elaborately. The latter types consisted of a domed mausoleum known as a ''qubba'', a shelter known as a ''makan nawm'', a garden, a well and either a distinguishable olive or [[oak]] tree. Most of the upkeep of the buildings was provided by ''[[waqf|awqaf]]'' (&quot;religious endowments&quot;). One of the shrines was considered by the local peasantry to be a place to safeguard firewood and outside the reach of potential thieves.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bussow123-4&quot;/&gt; The ''maqamat'' were also divided by status, with some bearing significance only to an individual village or clan and some collectively revered by the residents of the sheikhdom.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amiry208&quot;&gt;Amiry, 1987, p. 208.&lt;/ref&gt; Of all the sites in the Bani Zeid sheikhdom, the most venerated shrine was that of [[Nabi Salih]], dedicated to the prophet (''nabi'') [[Salih]], which held special significance beyond Bani Zeid.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bussow123-4&quot;/&gt;

===Maqam al-Khawwas===
One of the notable ''maqamat'' close to the modern town of Bani Zeid is Maqam al-Khawwas (var. ''Khawassi'', ''Khawwas'' and ''Kawas''), a double-domed building situated on a hilltop 500 meters west of Deir Ghassaneh,&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharon37&quot;&gt;Sharon, 2004, p. [https://books.google.com/books?id=01ogNhTNz54C&amp;pg=PA37 37]&lt;/ref&gt; in an isolated area.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amiry211&quot;&gt;Amiry, 1987, p. 211.&lt;/ref&gt; Along with the ''maqamat'' of al-Rifa'i or al-Majdoub, Maqam al-Khawwas was a shrine of major importance for the Bani Zeid villages, collectively.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amiry208&quot;/&gt; The ''maqam'' honored what was locally considered to be the meditation site of al-Khawass, believed to be a [[Sufi]] holy man (''wely'') from Egypt who often visited the residents of the area.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amiry211&quot;/&gt;

It contained a ''[[mihrab]]'' (&quot;niche indicating direction towards [[Mecca]].&quot;)&lt;ref name=&quot;Maraqa59&quot;/&gt; The ''maqam'' was noted by Guérin in 1863.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharon37&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Guérin, 1875, p. [https://archive.org/stream/descriptiongogr04gugoog#page/n176/mode/1up 151]&lt;/ref&gt; Its eastern dome was constructed by the residents of Deir Ghassaneh, while local legend holds the western dome was completed by angels. The interior of the domes were simple and typical of most ''maqamat'' domes, lacking cross-vault roofing which was a common feature for most of Deir Ghassaneh's buildings.&lt;ref&gt;Amiry, 1987, p. 212.&lt;/ref&gt; The sanctuary had a two-door entrance on its northern end. The interior walls were [[whitewash]]ed, reflecting the Muslim tradition of heavenly light and spirit in the color white. A few verses from the Qur'an were written on parts of the walls. The tomb of al-Khawwas was covered in white cloth. A small [[niche (architecture)|niche]] on the western wall was fitted for an oil lamp.&lt;ref&gt;Amiry, 1987, p. 213.&lt;/ref&gt;

An important feature that distinguished Maqam al-Khawwas from the Deir Ghassaneh mosque was that it acted primarily as a women's domain whereas the mosque had largely been a male domain. In the pre-British Mandate era, it was frequented by women on a daily basis and during a seasonal pilgrimage for women known as ''mawsim al-banat''. During this pilgrimage, which coincided with the Nabi Salih pilgrimage, a largely male affair, large groups of women and children from the villages of Bani Zeid would visit the Khawwas [[mausoleum]] to celebrate festivities, socialize with other women and pray.&lt;ref name=&quot;Maraqa59&quot;&gt;Maraqa, 2004, p. 59.&lt;/ref&gt; According to Palestinian architecture expert [[Suad Amiry]], Maqam al-Khawwas's isolation and the ritual of having to travel uphill to reach the sanctuary added to the tranquil feeling of the visit.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amiry211&quot;/&gt;

==Manor of Salih al-Barghouti==
The late 19th-century chief of the Bani Zeid sheikhdom, Sheikh Salih al-Barghouti, resided in a large palace-like manor in Deir Ghassaneh. The first floor and portions of the second floor were originally built in 1602.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharon40&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Amiry103&quot;&gt;Amiry, 1987, p. 103.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1862-63 Sheikh Salih renovated the [[Seraglio|manor]] which became known locally as &quot;Saraya al-Sheikh Salih al-Barghouti&quot; and built the remainder of the second floor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharon40&quot;&gt;Sharon, 2004, p.  [https://books.google.com/books?id=01ogNhTNz54C&amp;pg=PA40 40]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Amiry103&quot;/&gt; The building was divided into three main components, namely the ''salamlek'', the ''khazeen'' and the ''[[harem|haramlek]]''. The ''salamlek'' included a reception area, dining halls and a guesthouse while the ''khazeen'' consisted of workshops, food depots and horse stables. The ''haramlek'', on the second floor, served as the living quarters for women and servants. Above the living quarters hung the ''sheikh's''' retreat and leisure area from which he could view his estates.&lt;ref&gt;Tamari, 2002, pp. 29-30.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Amiry, Sheikh Salih's manor, along with other Barghouti family palace compounds, &quot;was strongly influenced by urban architecture&quot; in light of its &quot;majestic scale, ornate fine stone work and the introverted spatial organisation.&quot; The manor, which has a rectangular ground plan, roughly measures 23 meters by 34 meters.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amiry103&quot;/&gt; An open courtyard occupied the central position of the manor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amiry104&quot;&gt;Amiry, 1987, p. 104.&lt;/ref&gt; The courtyard was mostly enclosed by four partially open [[Arcade (architecture)|arcade]]s known as ''[[riwaq (arcade)|riwaq]]s'' which either serves as stables or storage.&lt;ref&gt;Amiry, 1987, p. 108.&lt;/ref&gt;

The main gate of the palace consists of two [[arch]]es, with one being built within the other. According to Sharon, while this gate structure was common among village [[Manor house|manor]]s in the area, the gate of Sheikh Salih's palace was &quot;particularly monumental&quot; as the arch was pointed and contained one [[Keystone (architecture)|keystone]]. The entire arch was constructed in the ''ablaq'' style with alternating black and white stone. A large, heavy and decorated wooden door is fitted into the gate and it was used to receive vehicles or large loads while a smaller door for personal use was built in the center of the larger door.&lt;ref&gt;Sharon, 2004, p. [https://books.google.com/books?id=01ogNhTNz54C&amp;pg=PA42 42]&lt;/ref&gt; A smaller secondary entrance was located at the building's northern side, vertically parallel of the main entrance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amiry104&quot;/&gt;

==Notable people==

Members of the [[Barghouti]] clan come from the [[Ramallah and al-Bireh Governorate]], which includes Bani Zeid;&lt;ref&gt;Tamari, 2008, p. [https://books.google.com/books?id=tfz6YsgKGKAC&amp;pg=PA134 134]&lt;/ref&gt; notable members of the clan include [[Bashir Barghouti]], a Palestinian Communist leader and journalist;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.passia.org/palestine_facts/personalities/alpha_b.htm|title=Palestinian Personalities|work=passia.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Abdullah Barghouti]], a convicted [[Hamas]] bomber,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url= https://books.google.com/books?id=FgWvDadmRMwC&amp;pg=PA38&amp;dq=#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|page=38|title=This Burning Land: Lessons from the Front Lines of the Transformed Israeli-Palestinian Conflict|author=Greg Myr|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|date= 8 Mar 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Mourid Barghouti]] a poet and writer. Other notable people born in Bani Zeid include [[Abdullah Rimawi]], head of the [[Ba'ath Party]] in [[Jordan]] in the 1950s,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.beitreema.com/rimawi1.html|title=From Beit Reema|work=beitreema.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kassim al-Rimawi]], prime minister of Jordan in 1980,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZhwfAQAAMAAJ&amp;q=Kassim+al-Rimawi+Beit+Rima&amp;dq=|page=956|title=The Middle East and North Africa, Volume 28|publisher=Europa Publications|date= 1981}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Mahmoud al-Rimawi]], a journalist and author.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arabicfiction.org/author/4.html|title=Mahmoud al-Rimawy|work=arabicfiction.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;[[Asaad Barghouti]],PLO parliament member,activist 1934-2009

==References==
{{reflist|25em}}

==Bibliography==
{{refbegin}}
*{{citation|first=Suad|last=Amiry|authorlink=Suad Amiry|title=Space, Kinship and Gender: The Social Dimension of Peasant Architecture in Palestine|url=http://www.era.lib.ed.ac.uk/handle/1842/6987 |publisher=University of Edinburgh-Faculty of Social Sciences|year=1987}}
*{{cite book |editor= Barron, J. B. |title= Palestine: Report and General Abstracts of the Census of 1922 |url=https://archive.org/details/PalestineCensus1922 |publisher= Government of Palestine |year= 1923}}
*{{cite book|first=Johann|last=Bussow|title=Hamidian Palestine: Politics and Society in the District of Jerusalem 1872-1908|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=crPPX99rjYUC&amp;dq=Deir+Ghassaneh&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s|publisher=BRILL|year=2011|isbn=9004205691}}
*{{cite book|editor=Carter, Charles Edward |year=1996|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=jvzkoJHe2h0C&amp;dq=Deir+Ghassana&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s|title=Community, Identity, and Ideology: Social Science Approaches to the Hebrew Bible|publisher=Eisenbrauns|ISBN=1575060051}}
*{{cite book|last1=Conder|first1=Claude Reignier|authorlink1=Claude Reignier Conder|last2=Kitchener|first2=H. H.|authorlink2=Herbert Kitchener, 1st Earl Kitchener|year=1882|url=https://archive.org/details/surveyofwesternp02conduoft|title=The Survey of Western Palestine: Memoirs of the Topography, Orography, Hydrography, and Archaeology|location=London|publisher=[[Palestine Exploration Fund|Committee of the Palestine Exploration Fund]]|volume=2}}
*{{cite book | last= Dauphin |first= Claudine | title = La Palestine byzantine, Peuplement et Populations |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=FC1mAAAAMAAJ |volume = III : Catalogue | series = BAR International Series 726 | year = 1998 | publisher = Archeopress | location = Oxford|language =French|isbn= 0-860549-05-4}} 
*{{cite book|title=Village Statistics, April, 1945 |url=http://web.nli.org.il/sites/nli/Hebrew/library/Pages/BookReader.aspx?pid=856390|author=Department of Statistics|year=1945|publisher=Government of Palestine}}
*{{cite book|editor1=Finkelstein, Israel | editor1-link= Israel Finkelstein|editor2=Lederman, Zvi|year=1997|title=Highlands of many cultures|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=_rraQgAACAAJ |location=[[Tel Aviv]]|publisher= Institute of Archaeology of Tel Aviv University Publications Section| isbn = 965-440-007-3}}
*{{cite book |last1= Hütteroth |first1=Wolf-Dieter |first2=Kamal |last2= Abdulfattah |title= Historical Geography of Palestine, Transjordan and Southern Syria in the Late 16th Century |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=wqULAAAAIAAJ | year = 1977 |publisher= Erlanger Geographische Arbeiten, Sonderband 5. Erlangen, Germany: Vorstand der Fränkischen Geographischen Gesellschaft |isbn= 3-920405-41-2}}  
*{{cite book|last=Guérin|first=Victor|authorlink=Victor Guérin|title=Description Géographique Historique et Archéologique de la Palestine|url=https://archive.org/details/descriptiongogr04gugoog|volume=2: Samarie,  pt. 2|year=1875|publisher= L'Imprimerie Nationale|location=Paris|language=French}} 
*{{cite journal | author1 = Macalister, R. A. Stewart | author2 = Masterman, E. W. G. | authorlink1= R. A. Stewart Macalister |title= Occasional Papers on the Modern inhabitants of Palestine, part I &amp; part II| journal= Quarterly statement - Palestine Exploration Fund |volume= 37 |pages= 343–356 |url= https://archive.org/details/quarterlystateme37pale |year= 1905}} 
*{{cite journal |author1= Macalister, R. A. Stewart |author2= Masterman, E. W. G. |authorlink1=  R. A. Stewart Macalister| title = Occasional Papers on the Modern inhabitants of Palestine, part III |journal= Quarterly statement - Palestine Exploration Fund |volume= 38 |pages= 33–50 |url= https://archive.org/details/quarterlystateme38pale |year= 1906}} 
*{{cite book |editor= Mills, E. |title= Census of Palestine 1931. Population of Villages, Towns and Administrative Areas | url= https://archive.org/details/CensusOfPalestine1931.PopulationOfVillagesTownsAndAdministrativeAreas |publisher= Government of Palestine |location= Jerusalem |year= 1932}}
*{{cite book| last= Palmer |first= E. H. |authorlink= Edward Henry Palmer |year= 1881 |url= https://archive.org/details/surveyofwesternp00conduoft |title= The Survey of Western Palestine: Arabic and English Name Lists Collected During the Survey by Lieutenants Conder and Kitchener, R. E. Transliterated and Explained by E.H. Palmer |publisher= [[Palestine Exploration Fund|Committee of the Palestine Exploration Fund]]}}
*{{cite book|last= Probert|first= Harry |year= 2006 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=94z34NxGHjQC&amp;pg=PA82&amp;dq=Deir+Ghassana&amp;ei=twbsSLWkEZHaMb2Q0AI&amp;sig=ACfU3U1N_Ga3M93qOV6u_cjG4sUmwkyb3Q#PPA82,M1 |title= Bomber Harris: His Life and Times |publisher= MBI Publishing Company |ISBN= 1-85367-691-8}}
*{{cite book|last1= Robinson |first1= Edward |authorlink1= Edward Robinson (scholar) |last2= Smith |first2= Eli |authorlink2= Eli Smith |year= 1841 |url= https://archive.org/details/biblicalresearch03robiuoft |title= Biblical Researches in Palestine, Mount Sinai and Arabia Petraea: A Journal of Travels in the year 1838 |location= Boston |publisher= [[Crocker &amp; Brewster]] |volume=3}}   
*{{cite book|title= Corpus Inscriptionum Arabicarum Palaestinae, D-F |volume= 3 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=01ogNhTNz54C |first1= Moshe |last1= Sharon |year= 2004 |publisher= BRILL |isbn= 90-04-13197-3}}
*{{cite book|last=Singer|first=Amy|year=1994|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=mrsAw_mk1d0C&amp;pg=PA76&amp;dq=Bani+Zayd+Ottoman&amp;ei=Z9PrSK20IpfMMo-H7egP&amp;sig=ACfU3U1r1NPomW6RCDQedJMz8c37K3ergg&amp;hl=en#PPA77,M1|title=Palestinian Peasants and Ottoman Officials: Rural Administration Around Sixteenth-Century Jerusalem|publisher=Cambridge University Press|ISBN=0-521-47679-8}}
*{{cite journal|author= Socin, A. |title= Alphabetisches Verzeichniss von Ortschaften des Paschalik Jerusalem |journal= Zeitschrift des Deutschen Palästina-Vereins |volume= 2 |pages= 135–163 |url= https://archive.org/details/zeitschriftdesde01deut |year= 1879}}
*{{citation| last= Tamari |first= Salim |authorlink= Salim Tamari |date= Autumn 2002 |volume= 85 |url= http://www.palestine-studies.org/jq/fulltext/78012 |title= The Last Feudal Lord in Palestine |publisher= Revue d'études palestiniennes |work= Jerusalem Quarterly |deadurl= yes |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20150622224600/http://www.palestine-studies.org/jq/fulltext/78012 |archivedate= June 22, 2015 }}
*{{cite book|last= Tamari |first= Salim |authorlink= Salim Tamari |title= Mountain Against the Sea: Essays on Palestinian Society and Culture |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=tfz6YsgKGKAC&amp; |year= 2009 |publisher= University of California |location= Berkley and Los Angeles |isbn= 978-0-520-25129-8}} 
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Bani Zeid}}
*[http://www.beitreema.com Official Website beitreema]
*Survey of Western Palestine, Map 14:   [http://www.iaa-archives.org.il/zoom/zoom.aspx?folder_id=93&amp;type_id=6&amp;id=8376   IAA], [http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Survey_of_Western_Palestine_1880.14.jpg Wikimedia commons]
*[http://vprofile.arij.org/ramallah/pdfs/vprofile/Bani_Zeid_TP_en.pdf Bani Zeid Town profile], ARIJ
*[http://vprofile.arij.org/ramallah/images/english/Bani%20Zeid_ap_en.jpg Bani Zeid aerial photo], ARIJ
*[http://www.palestineremembered.com/GeoPoints/Bayt_Rima_882/index.html Welcome To Bayt Rima]
*[http://www.palestineremembered.com/GeoPoints/Dayr_Ghassana_963/index.html Welcome To Dayr Ghassana]

{{Ramallah and al-Bireh Governorate}}

[[Category:Bani Zeid| ]]
[[Category:Towns in the West Bank]]
[[Category:Throne villages]]</text>
      <sha1>2w56w39z95s6xvfphjnaddfg5hsod7w</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
