<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.28.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2600" case="first-letter">Topic</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Church of St. Polyeuctus</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>22521791</id>
    <revision>
      <id>740783433</id>
      <parentid>734467793</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-23T07:47:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Sources */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16832">[[File:Anicia Juliana.jpg|thumb|right|Marble bust of [[Anicia Juliana]], from the [[New York City|New York]] [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]].]]
The '''Church of St. Polyeuctus''' ({{lang-el|{{lang|grc|Ἅγιος Πολύευκτος}}}}, ''Hagios Polyeuktos'') was an ancient [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine]] church in [[Constantinople]] (now [[Istanbul]], [[Turkey]]) built by the noblewoman [[Anicia Juliana]] and dedicated to [[Saint Polyeuctus]]. Intended as an assertion of Juliana's own [[Theodosian dynasty|imperial lineage]], it was a lavishly decorated building, and the largest church of the city before the construction of the [[Hagia Sophia]]. It introduced the large-scale use of [[Sassanid Persia]]n decorative elements, and may have inaugurated the new architectural type of [[dome]]d [[basilica]], perfected in the later Hagia Sophia. 

Little is known of the church's history after its construction. The building survived until the 11th century, after which it fell into decay, while several architectural elements were removed and reused in Constantinople and other cities. After being built over in the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman period]], the site of the church was rediscovered during excavations in the 1960s. The area, directly opposite the Istanbul Metropolitan Municipality City Hall, is now a preserved archaeological site open to visitors, although the sculptures have been removed to the [[Istanbul Archaeological Museum]].

== History ==
[[File:St. Polyeuktos niche with epigram 1.JPG|thumb|right|Fragment from the church's [[entablature]], containing the beginning of the 31st line of the epigram celebrating the foundation of the church. Discovered ''in situ'' during the 1960 excavations.]]
[[File:San Marc Pilastri Acritani 1.jpg|thumb|right|The ''Pilastri Acritani'' in Venice, taken from the Church of St. Polyeuctus.]]
The church was commissioned by the noblewoman [[Anicia Juliana]], [[Theodosian dynasty|descendant]] of several [[Western Roman Empire|Western]] emperors, and was constructed between 524 and 527, during the reign of [[Justin I]] (r. 518–527). It was meant to replace an earlier church, built by [[Aelia Eudocia|Eudocia]], wife of [[Theodosius II]] and Juliana's great-grandmother, to enshrine the relic skull of [[Saint Polyeuctus]].&lt;ref&gt;Walter (2003), p. 236&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ODB&quot;&gt;Kazhdan (1991), p. 1696&lt;/ref&gt; The new church was thought to have been the largest in Constantinople before the building of the [[Hagia Sophia]] by Justin's nephew and heir, [[Justinian I]] (r. 527–565).&lt;ref&gt;Cameron, Ward-Perkins, Whitby (2000), p. 961&lt;/ref&gt;

In a laudatory 76-line [[epigram]] inscribed on the walls of the church and preserved in its entirety (''[[Anthologia Graeca]]'', I.10), Juliana compares herself to past emperors [[Constantine I]] and [[Theodosius II]] as a monumental builder, and claims to have surpassed [[Solomon]]'s [[Temple of Solomon|Temple]], on whose proportions the new church was allegedly based. The building constituted thereby a direct challenge to the prestige and authority of the low-born [[Justinian Dynasty|reigning dynasty]], and it may have been one of the reasons for the massive scale of Justinian's reconstruction of the [[Hagia Sophia]] a few years later.&lt;ref&gt;Mitchell (2007), p. 317; Maas (2005), pp. 364–365; Canepa (2006), pp. 14–15&lt;/ref&gt; In light of this rivalry, it is perhaps no coincidence that Justinian too, when he beheld the completed Hagia Sophia, is said to have cried out: &quot;Solomon, I have surpassed thee.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Maas (2005), p. 365; Harrison (1989), pp. 36–41&lt;/ref&gt; The importance of the Solomonic allusions is however questioned by some scholars, who see the church more as a statement of the imperial prestige of the [[Rome|Old Roman]] aristocracy, from which Juliana descended, and of [[Chalcedonian]] orthodoxy, which she had championed during the reign of the [[Monophysite]] emperor [[Anastasius I (emperor)|Anastasius I]] (r. 491–518).&lt;ref&gt;Canepa (2006), pp. 12–14&lt;/ref&gt; A further aspect of the antagonism with Justinian however is evidenced by a tale recorded by [[Gregory of Tours]]: shortly after his accession, Justinian called upon the aged Juliana to contribute a part of her large fortune to the state treasury. After stalling for time, she had her gold melted down and fashioned into plates, with which she adorned the interior of the roof of the newly built church of St. Polyeuctus, thus preserving it from the emperor's avarice.&lt;ref name=&quot;DOAK&quot;&gt;Mango &amp; Ševčenko (1961), pp. 243–247&lt;/ref&gt;

The church survived until the 11th century, when it was abandoned. Thereafter it was liberally plundered for sculptures and other architectural elements ([[spolia]]) by both the Byzantines and, after the [[Siege of Constantinople (1204)|sack of the city]] in 1204, by the [[Fourth Crusade|Crusaders]]. Several pieces from St. Polyeuctus were reused in the Monastery of Christ Pantokrator (the modern [[Zeyrek Mosque]]),&lt;ref&gt;Ousterhout, Ahunbay &amp; Ahunbay (2000), p. 268&lt;/ref&gt; and various pieces such as [[Capital (architecture)|capitals]] were spread to places as far as [[Venice]], [[Barcelona]] and [[Vienna]],&lt;ref name=&quot;EHW&quot;/&gt; including the so-called ''Pilastri Acritani'' (&quot;Pillars of [[Acre, Israel|Acre]]&quot;) in [[St Mark's Basilica]], Venice.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODB&quot;/&gt;

The site of the church, in the Saraçhane quarter (the ancient Constantinianae), was gradually occupied by houses and a mosque in the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman period]]. In 1940, the area was leveled, and in 1960, during construction of the intersection of the Șehzadebași Caddesi and Atatürk Bulvari roads, excavations began.&lt;ref name=&quot;EHW&quot;/&gt; [[Brick]] vaults and pieces of [[Proconnesian]] marble sculpture were discovered, among them fragments of the monumental epigram adorning the church. These fragments, in conjunction with references to the approximate location of church in Byzantine texts concerning the imperial processions on the [[Mese (Constantinople)|Mese]] avenue, allowed a secure identification.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODB&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DOAK&quot;/&gt; The site was extensively excavated between 1964 and 1969 by archaeologists under the direction of Dr. Nezih Firatli from the [[Istanbul Archaeological Museum]] and Roy Michael Harrison of the [[Dumbarton Oaks Institute]].&lt;ref name=&quot;EHW&quot;/&gt; The area, directly opposite the Istanbul Metropolitan Municipality City Hall, is now a preserved archaeological site open to visitors, although the sculptures have been removed to the [[Istanbul Archaeological Museum]].&lt;ref name=&quot;DOAK&quot;/&gt;

== Description ==
[[File:St Polyeuctus interior reconstruction.jpg|thumb|right|Conjectural reconstruction of the interior by R.M. Harrison. The ''exedrae'' are visible on the left, the ambon and altar in the lower picture.]]
Despite its architectural prominence, very little is known of the church's history and its precise architecture. Most of the information on the church's original appearance is derived from the epigram in honour of Juliana and her family, which was inscribed in pieces in various parts of the church.&lt;ref name=&quot;DOAK&quot;/&gt; The epigram claims that the church was laid out as a [[Replicas of the Jewish Temple|replica of the ancient Jewish Temple]] with the precise proportions given in the Bible for the [[Temple of Solomon]], and using the [[royal cubit]] as a unit of measure, as in its model.&lt;ref&gt;Hamblin &amp; Seely (2007), p. 109&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Solomon&quot;&gt;Harrison (1989), pp. 137–144&lt;/ref&gt; Richard Martin Harrison, the site's chief excavator, has reconstructed the church as a roughly square [[basilica]], ca. 52 m long on the sides, with a central nave and two side [[aisle]]s, fronted by a [[narthex]] and preceded by a large [[Atrium (architecture)|atrium]] of 26 m length. To the north of the atrium, remains of another building have been identified as either the church's [[baptistery]] or Juliana's palace.&lt;ref name=&quot;EHW&quot;/&gt; An oval substructure in the building's center indicates the position of the [[Ambon (liturgy)|ambon]], while strong foundations throughout the building indicate, according to Harrison, the presence of a [[dome]], bringing the estimated height of the building to over 30 m. The area of the [[altar]] was not sufficiently excavated, and its shape remains unknown.&lt;ref&gt;Harrison (1985), pp. 406–411&lt;/ref&gt; The possible presence of a dome, although not universally accepted, is of major importance, since it would mean that it was St. Polyeuctus, and not Justinian's churches ([[Saints Sergius and Bacchus (Istanbul)|Saints Sergius and Bacchus]] and the Hagia Sophia), which first combined the traditional [[basilica]] with a dome.&lt;ref name=&quot;EHW&quot;/&gt; From the epigram, we know that the interior featured two storeys with colonnades and galleries. Based on the epigram and the substructures, Harrison also posited the existence of a pair of two-storey [[exedra]]e, composed of three niches with a pier in between, on the northern and southern sides of the ambo. The spaces around the domed western [[Bay (architecture)|bay]] would have been covered with [[barrel vault|barrel]] or [[cross vault|cross-vaults]].&lt;ref&gt;Harrison (1985), pp. 407–408; Cameron, Ward-Perkins, Whitby (2000), p. 963&lt;/ref&gt;

The interior decoration was extraordinarily rich.&lt;ref name=&quot;EHW&quot;&gt;Fiolitaki (2008)&lt;/ref&gt; The walls were decorated with marble, the roof was gilded, while the [[narthex]] featured a depiction of the baptism of [[Constantine the Great]].&lt;ref name=&quot;DOAK&quot;/&gt; Fragments of ivory, amethyst, gold and colored glass, originally inlaid in the marble sculptures, have also been found at the site, as well as fragments of [[mosaics]].&lt;ref name=&quot;EHW&quot;/&gt; The deliberate evocation of the Solomonic Temple was further reinforced by the preponderance of motifs such as [[palm tree]]s, [[pomegranate]]s and [[lily|lilies]] in the church's decoration.&lt;ref name=&quot;Solomon&quot;/&gt; A notable characteristic, which has not been attested before in Constantinopolitan art and architecture, is the extensive use of [[Sassanid Empire|Sassanid Persian]] decorative motifs such as friezes of running palmette and pomegranate leaves or symmetric geometric and vegetal patterns. Persian motifs became increasingly popular in the 6th century, and were also used in the decoration of the Hagia Sophia.&lt;ref&gt;Canepa (2006), pp. 6–19&lt;/ref&gt; Another exceptional find are ten relief plaques bearing the images of [[Christ]], the [[Virgin Mary]] and the [[Apostles]]; such images are very rare due to the destruction of human representations in the [[Byzantine Iconoclasm|Iconoclasm]] of the 8th and 9th centuries.&lt;ref&gt;Harrison (1985), pp. 414–418&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the largest decorative marble remains of the site is the niche-head pieces. These massive pieces of marble consist of a concave segment with a large frontal peacock carved in the center, tail fanned out proud. The epigram runs along the semicircle of the carving. Surrounding the peacocks are the spandrels filled with grape vines and leaves.&lt;ref&gt;&amp; Ševčenko (1961), pp. 243-245&lt;/ref&gt; The inscription's letters are raised 11&amp;nbsp;cm high, and surrounded by realistic grape vines. The detail involved in every individual leaf is remarkable. Each leaf has visible veins, some edges of the leaves are frayed and torn, and the artist even took the time to layer the design, pulling some leaves forward, and carving others in the background, giving the sense of depth.&lt;ref&gt;Harrison (1989), p. 81&lt;/ref&gt; Martin Harrison notes that this workmanship is all done by the artist’s eye, and with no use of a constant measure, as indicated by the marks made by the chisel, minute irregularities, and slight bends in the lattice work. This area was originally painted  in vibrant colors. The primary colors used were blues, greens, and some purples. These colors are difficult to find or make and show Anicia Juliana’s power in the decorative aspect of the structure. The background to vines and letters was a bright blue. The peacocks—associated with the goddess [[Hera]] and royalty in Antiquity and symbolizing renewal and rebirth for Christians&lt;ref name=&quot;Connor109&quot;&gt;Connor (2004), p. 109&lt;/ref&gt; —adorned with carved necklaces, were painted in blues, greens and gold. Due to the empty cavities in the eyes of the remaining bird head pieces, green glass was used for the pupils.&lt;ref&gt;Harrison (1989), p. 84&lt;/ref&gt; They also held chains to suspend something. Connor suggests due to their location, a lamp is a believable use for the chains in their beaks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Connor109&quot;/&gt;

==See also==
*[[History of Roman and Byzantine domes]]

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

== Sources ==
* {{cite book | title=Late Antiquity: Empire and Successors, AD 425-600 | first1=Averil |last1=Cameron | first2=Bryan |last2=Ward-Perkins | first3=Michael |last3=Whitby | publisher=Cambridge University Press | year=2000 | isbn=978-0-521-32591-2 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Qf8mrHjfZRoC}}
* {{cite conference | first=Matthew P. | last=Canepa | title=The Late Antique Kosmos of Power: International Ornament and Royal Identity in the Sixth and Seventh Centuries. | conference=21st International Congress of Byzantine Studies | location=London | year=2006 |url=http://www.wra1th.plus.com/byzcong/paper/I/I.3_Canepa.pdf}}
* {{cite book | last = Connor | first = Carolyn L. |title = Women of Byzantium | location = New Haven | publisher = Yale University Press | year = 2004 | isbn = 9780300099577}}
* {{cite web | last=Fiolitaki | first=Penelope | date=2008-04-01 | title = St. Polyeuktos | publisher=Encyclopedia of the Hellenic World: Constantinople | url=http://constantinople.ehw.gr/Forms/fLemmaBodyExtended.aspx?lemmaID=11784 | accessdate=2009-06-07}}
* {{cite book | title=Solomon's Temple: Myth and History | last1=Hamblin | first1=William J. | last2=Seely | first2=David Rolph |publisher=Thames and Hudson | year=2007 | isbn=0-500-25133-9}}
* {{cite book | editor-first=Richard Martin | editor-last=Harrison | title=Excavations at Saraçhane in Istanbul | volume=I | publisher=Princeton University Press |year=1985 | isbn=978-0-691-03583-3}}
* {{cite book | first=Richard Martin | last=Harrison | title=A Temple for Byzantium: The Discovery and Excavation of Anicia Juliana's Palace Church in Istanbul. | location=London | publisher=Harvey Miller | year= 1989 |isbn=978-0-292-78109-2}}
* {{cite book | editor-first = Alexander| editor-last = Kazhdan | title = [[Oxford Dictionary of Byzantium]] | publisher = Oxford University Press | year = 1991 | isbn = 978-0-19-504652-6}}
* {{cite book | editor-last=Maas | editor-first=Michael | title=The Cambridge Companion to the Age of Justinian | publisher=Cambridge University Press | year=2005 | isbn=978-0-521-52071-3}}
* {{cite journal | first1=Cyril |last1=Mango |first2=Ihor |last2=Ševčenko |title=Remains of the Church of St. Polyeuktos at Constantinople | journal=[[Dumbarton Oaks Papers]] | volume=15 | year=1961 | pages=243–247 | doi=10.2307/1291183 | publisher=Dumbarton Oaks, Trustees for Harvard University | jstor=1291183}}
* {{cite book | title=A history of the later Roman Empire, AD 284-641: the transformation of the ancient world | first=Stephen | last= Mitchell | publisher=Wiley-Blackwell |year=2007 | isbn=978-1-4051-0857-7}}
* {{cite journal | first1=Robert | last1=Ousterhout | first2=Zeynep | last2=Ahunbay | first3=Metin | last3=Ahunbay | title=Study and restoration of the Zeyrek Camii in Istanbul: first report, 1997-98 | journal= [[Dumbarton Oaks Papers]] |volume=54 |year=2000 | pages=265–70 | url=http://www.doaks.org/publications/doaks_online_publications/DOP54/DP54ch15.pdf | doi=10.2307/1291844 | author4=Özügül | publisher=Dumbarton Oaks, Trustees for Harvard University | jstor=1291844}}
* {{cite book | title=The warrior saints in Byzantine art and tradition | first=Christopher |last=Walter | publisher=Ashgate Publishing, Ltd. | year=2003 | isbn=978-1-84014-694-3 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=BRju9VQdW3QC}}

== External links ==
* {{commons-inline|Church of St. Polyeuktos in Constantinople}}
* [http://www.nyu.edu/gsas/dept/fineart/html/Byzantine/index.htm?http&amp;&amp;&amp;www.nyu.edu/gsas/dept/fineart/html/Byzantine/26.htm Hag. Polyeuktos], layout plan of the building by Prof. Thomas Mathews, ''[http://www.nyu.edu/gsas/dept/fineart/html/Byzantine/index.htm?http&amp;&amp;&amp;www.nyu.edu/gsas/dept/fineart/html/Byzantine/home.htm The Byzantine Churches of Istanbul]'', Institute of Fine Arts, New York University

{{coord|41.014|N|28.953|E|display=title}}
{{Churches and Monasteries of Constantinople}}
{{good article}}

{{Authority control}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Polyeuctus, Church of St.}}
[[Category:527]]
[[Category:6th-century churches]]
[[Category:Byzantine sacred architecture]]
[[Category:Churches in Istanbul]]
[[Category:Former churches in Turkey]]
[[Category:Buildings designed to replicate Solomon's Temple]]
[[Category:Fatih]]
[[Category:6th century in the Byzantine Empire]]</text>
      <sha1>2urquo5tsnktjkdw788tgrcnnvrqqhu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
