<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Elizabeth of Bosnia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5693937</id>
    <revision>
      <id>742264091</id>
      <parentid>730864771</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-02T18:02:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anadessma</username>
        <id>1911284</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Marriage */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="37697">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2013}}
{{Infobox royalty
|consort=yes
| name            = Elizabeth of Bosnia
| succession      = [[Queen consort of Hungary]] and [[Croatia in the union with Hungary|Croatia]]
| succession1     = [[Queen consort of Poland]]
| image           =Mary &amp; Elizabeth of Hungary.jpg
| alt             = Middle-aged woman holding a young woman in her arms
| caption         = Elizabeth with her daughter [[Mary of Hungary|Mary]] in captivity, as imagined by [[Soma Orlai Petrich]]
| reign           = 20 June 1353&amp;nbsp;– 10 September 1382
| reign1          = 5 November 1370&amp;nbsp;– 10 September 1382
| spouse          = [[Louis I of Hungary|Louis I, King of Hungary and Poland]]
| issue           = [[Catherine of Hungary (1370–1378)|Catherine of Hungary]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mary, Queen of Hungary]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Jadwiga of Poland|Hedwig, Queen of Poland]]
| issue-link      = #Family tree
| issue-pipe      = Details
| house           = [[House of Kotromanić]]
| father          = [[Stephen II, Ban of Bosnia]]
| mother          = [[Elizabeth of Kuyavia]]
| birth_date      = {{circa|1339}} 
| birth_place     = 
| death_date      = January 1387
| death_place     = [[Novigrad Castle]], [[Novigrad, Zadar County|Novigrad]]&lt;br&gt;[[Croatia in the union with Hungary|Kingdom of Croatia]]
| place of burial = [[Székesfehérvár Basilica]], [[Hungary]]&lt;br&gt;(previously [[St Chrysogonus's Church]], [[Croatia]])
|}}

'''Elizabeth of Bosnia'''&lt;ref&gt;{{lang-bs|Elizabeta Kotromanić}}/Елизабета Котроманић; {{lang-hu|Kotromanics Erzsébet}}; {{lang-pl|Elżbieta Bośniaczka}}&lt;/ref&gt; ({{circa|1339}}&amp;nbsp;– January 1387) was [[queen consort]] and later [[regent]] of [[Kingdom of Hungary|Hungary]] and [[Croatia in the union with Hungary|Croatia]], as well as queen consort of [[Kingdom of Poland (1025–1385)|Poland]]. Daughter of [[Stephen II, Ban of Bosnia|Ban Stephen&amp;nbsp;II]] of [[Banate of Bosnia|Bosnia]], Elizabeth married [[Louis I of Hungary|King Louis&amp;nbsp;I of Hungary]] in 1353. In 1370, she gave birth to a long-anticipated heir, [[Catherine of Hungary (1370–1378)|Catherine]], and became Queen of Poland when Louis succeeded his uncle, [[Casimir III the Great|Casimir&amp;nbsp;III]]. The royal couple had two more daughters, [[Mary, Queen of Hungary|Mary]] and [[Jadwiga of Poland|Hedwig]], but Catherine died in 1378. Initially a powerless consort with no substantial influence, Elizabeth then started surrounding herself with noblemen loyal to her, led by her [[favourite]], [[Nicholas&amp;nbsp;I Garai]]. When Louis died in 1382, Mary ascended to the [[List of Hungarian monarchs|throne of Hungary]] with Elizabeth as regent. Unable to preserve the [[personal union]] of [[Union of Hungary and Poland|Hungary and Poland]], the [[queen dowager]] secured the [[Polish throne]] for her youngest daughter, Hedwig.

During her regency in Hungary, Elizabeth faced several rebellions led by [[John Horvat]] and [[John of Palisna]], who attempted to take advantage of Mary's insecure reign. In 1385, they invited [[Charles III of Naples|King Charles&amp;nbsp;III of Naples]] to depose Mary and assume the crown. Elizabeth responded by having Charles murdered two months after his [[coronation of the Hungarian monarch|coronation]], in 1386. She had the crown restored to her daughter and established herself as regent once more, only to be captured, imprisoned and ultimately strangled by her enemies.

==Descent and early years==
Born about 1339, Elizabeth was the daughter of [[Ban (title)|Ban]] [[Stephen II, Ban of Bosnia|Stephen&amp;nbsp;II of Bosnia]], the head of the [[House of Kotromanić]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 163&quot;/&gt; Her mother, [[Elizabeth of Kuyavia]], was a member of the [[House of Piast]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Kellogg, 9&quot;/&gt; and grandniece of [[Władysław I the Elbow-high|King Władysław I of Poland]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Rudzki, 47&quot;/&gt; The Hungarian queen dowager [[Elizabeth of Poland, Queen of Hungary|Elizabeth of Poland]] was first cousin once removed of Elizabeth's mother. After her daughter-in-law [[Margaret of Bohemia, Queen of Hungary|Margaret]] succumbed to the [[Black Death]] in 1349,&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 171&quot;/&gt; Queen Elizabeth expressed interest in her young kinswoman, having in mind a future match for her widowed and childless son, [[Louis I of Hungary|King Louis&amp;nbsp;I of Hungary]]. She insisted on immediately bringing the girl to her court in [[Visegrád]] for fostering. Despite her father's initial reluctance, Elizabeth was sent to the dowager's court.&lt;ref name=&quot;InstytutHistorii&quot;/&gt;

In 1350, [[Stephen Uroš IV Dušan of Serbia|Tsar Stephen Uroš&amp;nbsp;IV Dušan of Serbia]] attacked Bosnia in order to regain [[Zachlumia]]. The invasion was not successful, and the Tsar tried to negotiate peace, which would be sealed by [[arranged marriage|arranging]] Elizabeth's marriage to his son and [[heir apparent]], [[Stephen Uroš V of Serbia|Stephen Uroš&amp;nbsp;V]]. [[Mavro Orbini]], whose reliability in this regard &quot;is a subject of controversy&quot;, wrote that the Tsar expected Zachlumia to be ceded as Elizabeth's [[dowry]], which her father refused.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fine, 323&quot;/&gt; Later that year she was formally betrothed to the 24-year-old Louis,&lt;ref name=&quot;Várdy, 226&quot;/&gt; who hoped to counter Dušan's expansionist policy either with her father's help or &quot;as his eventual successor&quot;, according to historian [[Oscar Halecki]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 40&quot;/&gt;

==Marriage==
[[File:Ludvik1Uhry.jpg|thumb|Elizabeth and Louis kneeling in front of [[Catherine of Alexandria]], [[Chronicon Pictum]]]]
Elizabeth's marriage to Louis was celebrated in [[Buda]] on 20 June 1353.&lt;ref name=&quot;Michael, 303&quot;/&gt; The couple were related within the [[prohibited degree of kinship]], [[Casimir I of Kuyavia|Duke Casimir&amp;nbsp;I of Kuyavia]] being Elizabeth's maternal great-great-grandfather and Louis' maternal great-grandfather. A [[papal dispensation]] was thus necessary, but it was only sought four months after the wedding took place. The historian Iván Bertényi suggests that the ceremony may have been hastened by an [[unintended pregnancy]], as the couple had been in contact for years. If so, the pregnancy likely ended in a [[stillbirth]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bertényi, 89&quot;&gt;Bertényi, 89.&lt;/ref&gt; Elizabeth's mother had apparently died by the time she was married.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 88&quot;/&gt; Louis was dismayed when, upon his father-in-law's death later the same year, Elizabeth's young and ambitious cousin [[Tvrtko I of Bosnia|Tvrtko]] ascended the Bosnian throne.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 40&quot;/&gt; In 1357, Louis summoned the young Ban to [[Požega, Croatia|Požega]] and compelled him to surrender most of western Zachlumia as Elizabeth's dowry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 163&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fine, 369&quot;/&gt;

The new Queen of Hungary subjected herself entirely to her controlling mother-in-law, Elizabeth of Poland. The fact that the young queen's retinue consisted of the same individuals who had served the queen mother indicates that Elizabeth of Bosnia may not even have had her own court. Her mother-in-law's influence prevailed until 1370, when Louis [[Privilege of Buda|succeeded]] his maternal uncle, [[Casimir III the Great|Casimir&amp;nbsp;III]], as [[List of Polish monarchs|King of Poland]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 171&quot;/&gt; Elizabeth's maternal uncle, [[Władysław the White|Vladislaus the White]], had also been a candidate for the Polish throne.&lt;ref name=&quot;Várdy, 147&quot;/&gt; Following his [[coronation in Poland]], Louis brought Casimir's underage daughters, [[Anna of Poland, Countess of Celje|Anne]] and Hedwig, to be raised by Elizabeth.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jasienica, 6&quot;/&gt; Elizabeth, though [[List of Polish consorts|Queen of Poland]], was never crowned as such.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rożek, 49&quot;&gt;Rożek, 49.&lt;/ref&gt;

The problem of the succession marked Louis' reign. Elizabeth was long considered barren, and a succession crisis was expected after the childless king's death. Her brother-in-law [[Stephen, Duke of Slavonia|Stephen]] was [[heir presumptive]] until his death in 1354, when his son [[John, Duke of Slavonia|John]] replaced him. However, John also died in 1360.&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 169&quot;/&gt; A daughter was born to the King and Queen in 1365, but the child died the next year.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 49&quot;/&gt; For a few years, John's sister, [[Elizabeth of Slavonia|Elizabeth]], was treated as heir presumptive and a suitable marriage for her was being negotiated. Things suddenly took a different course after Elizabeth had three daughters in quick succession; [[Catherine of Hungary (1370–1378)|Catherine]] was born in July 1370, [[Mary, Queen of Hungary|Mary]] in 1371, and [[Jadwiga of Poland|Hedwig]] in 1373 or 1374.&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 169&quot;/&gt; Elizabeth is known to have written a book for the education of her daughters, a copy of which was sent to France in 1374. However, all copies have been lost.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jansen, 13&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Johnson, 203&quot;/&gt;

[[File:HAZU 77 17 lipnja 2008.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Woman handing a sarcophagus to a saint with her three daughters kneeling in front of her|Queen Elizabeth presenting a [[Chest of Saint Simeon|chest]] to St. Simeon, with her daughters praying]]
On 17 September 1374, Louis granted various concessions to the [[Polish nobility]] by the [[Privilege of Koszyce]], in exchange for their promise that a daughter of his would succeed him and that he, Elizabeth or his mother could indicate which one.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reddaway, 193&quot;/&gt; In Hungary, he focused on the [[centralization]] of power as means of ensuring that his daughters' rights would be respected.&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 174&quot;/&gt; Securing marriage to one of the princesses was a priority in European royal courts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 169&quot;/&gt; Mary was scarcely one year old when she was promised to [[Sigismund, Holy Roman Emperor|Sigismund of Luxembourg]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 170&quot;/&gt; In 1374, Catherine was betrothed to [[Louis I, Duke of Orléans|Louis of France]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 169&quot;/&gt; but died towards the end of 1378. The same year, Hedwig, promised to [[William, Duke of Austria|William of Austria]] in a ''[[sponsalia de futuro]]'', left her mother's court and moved to [[Vienna]], where she spent the next two years.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 69&quot;/&gt; The Polish lords swore to uphold Mary's rights in 1379, while Sigismund received this recognition three years later. Elizabeth was present, along with her husband and mother-in-law, at a meeting in [[Zólyom]] on 12 February 1380, whereby Hungarian lords confirmed Hedwig's Austrian match; this indicates that Louis may have intended to leave Hungary to Hedwig and William.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 73&quot;&gt;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 73.&lt;/ref&gt;

The King, weakened by illness, became progressively less active in the last years of his reign, devoting an increasing amount of time to prayer, as did his aging mother, who had returned from Poland in 1374. These circumstances allowed Elizabeth to assume a more prominent role at court. Her influence had grown steadily since she had given her husband heirs. It appeared probable that the crowns would pass to one of Elizabeth's underage daughters and by 1374, their rights were confirmed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 188&quot;/&gt; Behind the scenes, Elizabeth began ensuring that the succession would be as smooth as possible by encouraging a slow but decisive change in the personnel of the government. Warlike and illiterate barons were gradually replaced by a small group of noblemen who excelled in their professional skills but were not distinguished by birth or military ability. [[Palatine (Kingdom of Hungary)|Palatine]] [[Nicholas I Garai]] led the movement and enjoyed the full support of the Queen, and their power eventually became virtually unrestricted.&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 188&quot;/&gt;

==Widowhood and regency==
&lt;!---[[File:Elizabeth and Mary of Hungary at the tomb of Louis the Great.jpg|thumb|alt=Young woman crying at a tomb with her mother standing above her|Elizabeth and Mary mourning at the tomb of Louis I, by [[Sándor Liezen-Mayer]], 1864]]---&gt;
[[File:Louis's kingdoms and his vassal territories.png|thumb|right|alt=Map of Eastern and Southeast Europe|A map of the lands ruled by Louis]]
Louis died on 10 September 1382, with Elizabeth and their daughters at his bedside.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 75&quot;&gt;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 75.&lt;/ref&gt; Elizabeth, now [[queen dowager]], had Mary [[coronation of the Hungarian monarch|crowned &quot;King&quot; of Hungary]] only seven days later. Halecki believes that the reason behind Elizabeth's haste and Mary's masculine title was the dowager's desire to exclude Sigismund, her prospective son-in-law, from the government.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 97&quot;&gt;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 97.&lt;/ref&gt; Acted as [[regent]] on behalf of the eleven-year-old sovereign, Elizabeth made Garai her chief adviser. Her rule was not to be peaceful. The royal court was pleased with the arrangement, but Hungarian noblemen were unwilling to defer to a woman and objected to Mary's accession, maintaining that the lawful heir to the throne was [[Charles III of Naples|King Charles&amp;nbsp;III of Naples]], the only remaining male Angevin. Charles was, at that time, unable to claim Mary's throne because his own was threatened by [[Louis I, Duke of Anjou|Duke Louis&amp;nbsp;I of Anjou]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 195&quot;/&gt;

The first to rise against Elizabeth, in 1383, was [[John of Palisna]], Prior of [[Vrana (town)|Vrana]]. Historian [[John V. A. Fine]] says that the Prior &quot;seems to have been chiefly opposed&quot; to the centralizing policy which her husband had enforced. Her cousin Tvrtko also decided to take advantage of Louis' death and Elizabeth's unpopularity by trying to recover the lands he had lost to the King in 1357. Tvrtko and John formed an alliance against Elizabeth, but they were ultimately defeated by her army, with John being forced to flee to Bosnia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Van Antwerp Fine, 395&quot;/&gt;

===Polish succession===

Although Louis had designated Mary as his successor in both of his kingdoms, the Polish nobles, seeking an end to the [[personal union|personal]] [[Union of Hungary and Poland|union with Hungary]], were not willing to recognize Mary and her fiancé Sigismund as their sovereigns.&lt;ref name=&quot;Goodman, 208&quot;/&gt; They would have accepted Mary if she had moved to [[Kraków]] and reigned over both kingdoms from there rather than from Hungary, ruling according to their advice rather than that of the Hungarian nobles and marrying a prince of their choosing. Their intentions, however, were not to Elizabeth's taste. She too would have been required to move to Kraków, where a lack of men loyal to her would have rendered her unable to enforce her own will. Elizabeth was also aware of the difficulties her mother-in-law had faced during her regency in Poland, which had ended with the old queen fleeing her native kingdom in disgrace.&lt;ref name=&quot;Varga, 75&quot;/&gt;

An agreement was reached between Elizabeth's and Polish delegates in [[Sieradz]] on 26 February 1383.&lt;ref name=&quot;Przybyszewski, 7&quot;/&gt; The queen dowager thereby proposed her youngest daughter Hedwig as Louis' successor in Poland,&lt;ref name=&quot;Varga, 75&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 101&quot;/&gt; and absolved the Polish nobles from their 1382 oaths to Mary and Sigismund.&lt;ref name=&quot;Przybyszewski, 7&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 101&quot;/&gt; She agreed to send Hedwig to be crowned in Kraków but requested that, in view of her age, she spend three more years in Buda following the ceremony. The Poles, entangled in a [[Greater Poland Civil War|bloody civil war]], initially conceded to the requirement, but soon found it unacceptable for their monarch to reside abroad for so long. At the second meeting in Sieradz, held on 28 March, they contemplated offering the crown to Hedwig's distant relative, [[Siemowit IV, Duke of Masovia|Duke Siemowit&amp;nbsp;IV of Masovia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 101&quot;/&gt; They eventually opted against it, but at the third Sieradz meeting, on 16 June, Siemowit himself decided to lay claim to the crown. Elizabeth reacted by having an army of 12,000 men devastate Masovia in August, forcing him to drop his pretensions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Przybyszewski, 8&quot;/&gt; Meanwhile, she realized that she could not expect the nobles to accept her request and instead resolved to delay Hedwig's departure. Despite continuous Polish demands to expedite her arrival, Hedwig did not move to Kraków until the end of August 1384.&lt;ref name=&quot;Przybyszewski, 97&quot;/&gt; She was crowned on 16 October 1384.&lt;ref name=&quot;Goodman, 221&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 109&quot;/&gt; No regent was appointed, and the 10-year-old exercised her authority according to the advice of Kraków [[magnates of Poland and Lithuania|magnates]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Przybyszewski, 10&quot;/&gt; Elizabeth never saw her again.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 85&quot;/&gt;

In 1385, Elizabeth received an official delegation from [[Grand Duke of Lithuania|Grand Duke]] [[Jogaila]] of [[Grand Duchy of Lithuania|Lithuania]], who wished to marry Hedwig. In the [[Act of Kreva]], Jogaila promised to pay compensation to William of Austria on Elizabeth's behalf and requested that Elizabeth, as widow of King Louis and heiress of Poland herself as great-grandniece of King Władysław I (whose name Jogaila had purposely assumed on his baptism), legally adopt him as her son in order to give him a claim to the Polish crown in the event of Hedwig's death.&lt;ref name=&quot;mckitterick&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lietuvos&quot;/&gt; The marriage was celebrated in 1386.&lt;ref name=&quot;Goodman, 221&quot;/&gt;

===Mary's marriage===
Mary's fiancé Sigismund and his brother [[Wenceslaus IV of Bohemia|Wenceslaus]], King of Germany and Bohemia, were also opposed to Elizabeth and Garai. The queen dowager and the Palatine, on the other hand, were not enthusiastic about Sigismund reigning together with Mary. Both Sigismund and Charles schemed to invade Hungary; the former intended to marry Mary and become her co-ruler, while the latter intended to depose her. Elizabeth was determined to allow neither and, in 1384, started negotiating Mary's marriage to Louis of France, notwithstanding her daughter's engagement to Sigismund. Had this proposal been made after Catherine's death in 1378, the [[Western Schism]] would have represented a problem, with France recognising [[Antipope Clement VII|Clement&amp;nbsp;VII]] as pope and Hungary accepting [[Pope Urban VI|Urban&amp;nbsp;VI]]. However, Elizabeth was desperate to avoid an invasion in 1384 and unwilling to let the schism stand in the way of the negotiations with the French. Clement&amp;nbsp;VII issued a dispensation which annulled Mary's betrothal to Sigismund, and her [[proxy marriage]] to Louis was celebrated in April 1385, but it was not recognized by the Hungarian noblemen, who adhered to Urban VI.&lt;ref name=&quot;Goodman, 222&quot;/&gt;

Elizabeth's plan to have Mary married to Louis of France divided the court. The [[House of Lacković|Lackfis]], the master of the treasury [[Nicholas Zámbó]] and the judge royal [[Nicholas Szécsi]] openly opposed it and renounced their allegiance to the queen dowager in August, which resulted in her depriving them of all their offices and replacing them with Garai's partisans. The kingdom was on the verge of a civil war when Charles decided to invade, encouraged by [[John Horvat]] and his brother [[Paul Horvat (bishop)|Paul]], [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Zagreb|Bishop of Zagreb]]. Charles' imminent arrival forced Elizabeth to yield and abandon the idea of French marriage. While her envoys in Paris were preparing for Louis's journey, Elizabeth came to terms with her opponents and designated Szécsi as the new palatine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 196&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Elizabeth and Mary of Hungary at the tomb of Louis the Great.jpg|thumb|alt=Young woman crying at a tomb with her mother standing above her|Elizabeth and Mary mourning at Louis' tomb during Charles' coronation, painted by [[Sándor Liezen-Mayer]] in 1864]]
Four months after her proxy marriage to Louis, Sigismund entered Hungary and married Mary, but the reconciliation between the fractions turned out to be too late to forestall Charles' invasion. Sigismund fled to his brother's court in [[Prague]] in the autumn of 1385.&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 196&quot;/&gt;

===Deposition and restoration===
&lt;!---[[File:Molnár Elisabeth and Mary on the coronation of Cherles II of Hungary.jpg|thumb|left|alt=People gathered around a tomb while a bishop places crown on the head of a man in the background|Elizabeth and Mary at Louis' tomb during Charles' coronation, by [[József Molnár (painter)|József Molnár]], 1880's]]---&gt;

Charles's arrival was well-prepared. He was accompanied by his Hungarian supporters and Elizabeth was unable to raise an army against him or prevent him from convoking a [[Diet of Hungary|diet]], in which he obtained an overwhelming support. Mary was forced to abdicate, opening the path for Charles to be crowned on 31 December 1385.&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 196&quot;/&gt; Elizabeth and Mary were compelled to attend the ceremony&lt;ref name=&quot;Grierson, 236&quot;/&gt; and swear allegiance to him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 146&quot;/&gt;

Deprived of authority, Elizabeth feigned friendly feelings for Charles while his retinue was at the court, but after his supporters had returned to their homes, he was left defenseless.&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 198&quot;/&gt; She acted quickly and invited him to visit Mary in [[Buda Castle]]. Upon his arrival there on 7 February 1386, Elizabeth had Charles stabbed in her apartments and in her presence. He was taken to Visegrád, where he died on 24 February.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grierson, 236&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 198&quot;/&gt;

Having had the crown restored to her daughter, Elizabeth immediately proceeded to reward those who had helped her, giving a castle in [[Jelenec|Gimes]] to [[Blaise Forgách]], the [[master of the cupbearers]], who had mortally wounded Charles. In April, Sigismund was brought to Hungary by his brother Wenceslaus and the queens were pressured into accepting him as Mary's future co-ruler by the [[Treaty of Győr (1386)|Treaty of Győr]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 198&quot;/&gt; Having Charles murdered did not help Elizabeth as much as she hoped it would, however, as Charles's supporters immediately recognized his son [[Ladislaus of Naples|Ladislaus]] as heir&lt;ref name=&quot;Van Antwerp Fine, 397&quot;/&gt; and fled to [[Zagreb]]. Bishop Paul pawned church estates in order to collect money for an army against the queens.&lt;ref name=&quot;Šišić, 50&quot;&gt;Šišić, 50.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Death and aftermath==
[[File:The abduction of Elizabeth of Bosnia and Mary of Hungary.jpg|thumb|alt=Man defending a carriage containing two women from a group of armed men|Garai defending Elizabeth and Mary from the attackers, painted by [[Mihály Kovács (painter)|Mihály Kovács]] in c.&amp;nbsp;1895.]]

Elizabeth believed that her daughter's mere presence would help calm the opposition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 198&quot;/&gt; Accompanied by Garai and a modest following,&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 198&quot;/&gt; she and Mary set out for [[Đakovo]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Van Antwerp Fine, 397&quot;/&gt; However, Elizabeth had seriously misjudged the situation. On 25 July 1386, they were ambushed en route and attacked by John Horvat in [[Gorjani]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 198&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Van Antwerp Fine, 397&quot;/&gt; Their small entourage failed to fight off the attackers. Garai was killed by the rebels and his head was sent to Charles's widow [[Margaret of Durazzo|Margaret]], while the queens were imprisoned in the bishop of Zagreb's castle of [[Bosiljevo|Gomnec]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 198&quot;/&gt; Elizabeth took all blame for the rebellion and begged the attackers to spare her daughter's life.&lt;ref name=&quot;Duggan, 231&quot;/&gt;

Elizabeth and Mary were soon sent to [[Novigrad Castle]], with John of Palisna as their new jailer.&lt;ref name=&quot;Van Antwerp Fine, 397&quot;/&gt; Margaret insisted that Elizabeth be put to death.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gaži, 61&quot;&gt;Gaži, 61.&lt;/ref&gt; She was tried and, after the Christmas adjournment of the proceedings, found guilty of inciting Charles' murder.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 164&quot;/&gt; Sigismund marched into [[Slavonia]] in January 1387, with the intention to reach Novigrad and rescue the queens.&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 199&quot;/&gt; Towards the middle of January, when news of Sigismund's approach reached Novigrad, Elizabeth was strangled by guards before Mary's eyes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Van Antwerp Fine, 397&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 164&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 199&quot;/&gt;

Mary was released from the captivity by Sigismund's troops on 4 June.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 164&quot;/&gt; Having been secretly buried in [[St Chrysogonus's Church]] in [[Zadar]] on 9 February 1387, Elizabeth's body was exhumed on 16 January 1390, transferred by sea to [[Obrovac, Croatia|Obrovac]] and then carried overland to [[Székesfehérvár Basilica]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Petricioli, 196&quot;/&gt;

==Legacy==
[[File:Street of Elizabeth Kotromanic in Zadar.JPG|thumb|left|alt=A street sign|&quot;Street of Queen Elizabeth Kotromanić, donor of St. Simeon's casket&quot; in Zadar]]
Elizabeth was regarded by her contemporaries as an efficient but ruthless politician who used political intrigues to protect and defend her daughters' rights.&lt;ref name=&quot;Parsons, 16&quot;/&gt; She was a caring parent, but was neither politically talented nor competent to prepare Mary and Hedwig for their roles as monarchs. Elizabeth failed to set a good example for her daughters, and her unbalanced character and questionable methods in politics would serve more as a warning to the young sovereigns. Her procrastinations and inability to make clear decisions threatened Hedwig's status, while her endless problems with Croatian nobles and failure to improve relations with her native Bosnia made Mary's reign insecure and tumultuous.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 85&quot;/&gt;

Queen Elizabeth commissioned the creation of the [[Chest of Saint Simeon]] in 1381. The chest, located in [[Zadar]], is of great importance for the history of the city, as it depicts various historical events&amp;nbsp;– such as the death of her father&amp;nbsp;– and Elizabeth herself. According to legend, she stole the saint's finger and paid for the creation of the casket in order to atone for her sin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stewart, 210&quot;/&gt; The casket contains a scene which allegedly depicts the queen gone mad after stealing the relict.&lt;ref name=&quot;Filozofski fakultet u Zadru, 455&quot;/&gt;
{{clear}}

==Family tree==
The following family tree illustrates Elizabeth's kinship with her husband, as well as her and her daughters' relationships with their adversaries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 88&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 40&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Creighton, 69&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kosáry &amp; Várdy, 418&quot;/&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
{{familytree/start}}
{{familytree | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | |Cas| | | | | | | |Cas=[[Casimir I of Kuyavia]]}}
{{familytree | | | | | | | | | | | | | | |,|-|-|^|-|.| | | }}
{{familytree | | | | | |Mar| | | | | |Vla| | |Zie| | | | | |Zie=[[Ziemomysł of Kuyavia]]|Mar=[[Mary of Hungary, Queen of Naples|Mary of Hungary]]|Vla=[[Władysław I the Elbow-high|Vladislaus I of Poland]]}}
{{familytree | | | |,|-|-|^|-|-|.| | | |,|^|.| | | |!| | | | |}}
{{familytree | | |Joh| | | |Cha| | |!|Casm| |Cas| | | |Eli|v|Ste| |Cas=[[Casimir II of Kuyavia]]|Eli=[[Elizabeth of Serbia]]|Ste=[[Stephen I, Ban of Bosnia|Stephen I of Bosnia]]|Cha=[[Charles Martel of Anjou]]|Joh=[[John, Duke of Durazzo|John of Durazzo]]|Casm=[[Casimir III the Great|Casimir III of Poland]]}}
{{familytree | |,|-|^|-|.| | | |!| | | |!| | | |,|-|^|-|.| | | |,|-|^|-|.| |}}
{{familytree |Char| |Lou| |Cha|v|Elz| |Vla| |Els|v|Ste| |Vls| |Els=[[Elizabeth of Kuyavia]]|Ste=[[Stephen II, Ban of Bosnia|Stephen II of Bosnia]]|Elz=[[Elizabeth of Poland, Queen of Hungary|Elizabeth of Poland]]|Cas=[[Casimir III the Great|Casimir III of Poland]]|Vla=[[Władysław the White|Vladislaus of Kuyavia]]|Cha=[[Charles I of Hungary]]|Lou=[[Louis, Count of Gravina|Louis of Gravina]]|Vls=[[Vladislaus of Bosnia]]|Char=[[Charles, Duke of Durazzo|Charles of Durazzo]]}}
{{familytree | |!| | | |!| | | | | |!| | | | | | | | | | | |!| | | | | |!|}}
{{familytree |Mar|v|Cha| | | |Lou|-|-|-|-|v|-|-|-|-|Eli| | | |Tvr|Eli=Elizabeth of Bosnia|Lou=[[Louis I of Hungary]]|Cha=[[Charles III of Naples]]|Tvr=[[Tvrtko I of Bosnia]]|Mar=[[Margaret of Durazzo]]}}
{{familytree | | | |!| | | | | | | | | |,|-|-|-|+|-|-|-|.|}}
{{familytree | | |Lad| | | | | | | |Cat| |Mar| |Hed| | |Cat=[[Catherine of Hungary (1370-1378)|Catherine of Hungary]]|Mar=[[Mary of Hungary]]|Hed=[[Jadwiga of Poland|Hedwig of Poland]]|Sig=[[Sigismund, Holy Roman Emperor|Sigismund of Luxembourg]]|Jog=[[Jogaila|Jogaila of Lithuania]]|Lad=[[Ladislaus of Naples]]}}
{{familytree/end}}&lt;/center&gt;

==Notes==

{{reflist|colwidth=20em|refs=

&lt;ref name=&quot;Bertényi, 89&quot;&gt;Bertényi, 89.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Creighton, 69&quot;&gt;Creighton, 69.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Duggan, 231&quot;&gt;Duggan, 231.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 163&quot;&gt;Engel, 163.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 169&quot;&gt;Engel, 169.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 174&quot;&gt;Engel, 174.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 170&quot;&gt;Engel, 170.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 171&quot;&gt;Engel, 171.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 188&quot;&gt;Engel, 188.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 195&quot;&gt;Engel, 195.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 196&quot;&gt;Engel, 196-197.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 198&quot;&gt;Engel, 198.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel, 199&quot;&gt;Engel, 199.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Filozofski fakultet u Zadru, 455&quot;&gt;Filozofski fakultet u Zadru, 455.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Fine, 323&quot;&gt;Van Antwerp Fine, 323.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Fine, 369&quot;&gt;Van Antwerp Fine, 369.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Goodman, 208&quot;&gt;Goodman &amp; Gillespie, 208.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Goodman, 221&quot;&gt;Goodman &amp; Gillespie, 221.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Goodman, 222&quot;&gt;Goodman &amp; Gillespie, 222–223.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Grierson, 236&quot;&gt;Grierson &amp; Travaini, 236.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 164&quot;&gt;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 164.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 40&quot;&gt;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 40.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 49&quot;&gt;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 49.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 69&quot;&gt;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 69.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 73&quot;&gt;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 73.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 85&quot;&gt;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 85.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 88&quot;&gt;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 88.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 101&quot;&gt;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 101.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 109&quot;&gt;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 109.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 146&quot;&gt;Gromada &amp; Halecki, 146.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;InstytutHistorii&quot;&gt;Instytut Historii (Polska Akademia Nauk)&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Jansen, 13&quot;&gt;Jansen, 13.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Jasienica, 6&quot;&gt;Jasienica, 6.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Johnson, 203&quot;&gt;Johnson &amp; Wogan-Browne, 203.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Kosáry &amp; Várdy, 418&quot;&gt;Kosáry &amp; Várdy, 418.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Kellogg, 9&quot;&gt;Kellogg, 9.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Lietuvos&quot;&gt;Lithuanian historical studies, 10-11.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;mckitterick&quot;&gt;McKitterick, 709–712.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Michael, 303&quot;&gt;Michael, 303.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Parsons, 16&quot;&gt;Parsons, 16.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Przybyszewski, 7&quot;&gt;Przybyszewski, 7.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Przybyszewski, 8&quot;&gt;Przybyszewski, 8.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Przybyszewski, 10&quot;&gt;Przybyszewski, 10.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Przybyszewski, 97&quot;&gt;Przybyszewski, 97.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Petricioli, 196&quot;&gt;Petricioli, 196.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Reddaway, 193&quot;&gt;Reddaway, 193.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Rudzki, 47&quot;&gt;Rudzki, 47.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Stewart, 210&quot;&gt;Stewart, 210.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Van Antwerp Fine, 395&quot;&gt;Van Antwerp Fine, 395.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Van Antwerp Fine, 397&quot;&gt;Van Antwerp Fine, 396–397.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Várdy, 147&quot;&gt;Várdy, Grosschmid, Domonkos, 147.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Várdy, 226&quot;&gt;Várdy, Grosschmid, Domonkos, 226.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Varga, 75&quot;&gt;Varga, 41.&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

==References==
{{Refbegin|2}}
* {{Cite book|last=Bertényi|first=Iván|title=Nagy Lajos király|publisher=Kossuth Könyvkiadó|year=1989|isbn=963-09-3388-8}}
* {{Cite book|last=Creighton|first=Mandell|title=A History of the Papacy During the Period of the Reformation|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2011|isbn=1-108-04106-X}}
* {{Cite book|last=Duggan |first=Anne J. |title=Queens and Queenship in Medieval Europe: Proceedings of a Conference Held at King's College London, April 1995 |publisher=Boydell Press |year=2002 |isbn=0-85115-881-1 }}
* {{Cite book|last=Engel|first=Pal|editor-last=Ayton|editor-first=Andrew|title=The realm of St. Stephen: a history of medieval Hungary, 895–1526 Volume 19 of International Library of Historical Studies |publisher=Penn State Press |year=1999 |isbn=0-271-01758-9 |url= }}
* {{Cite book|last=|first=|title=Radovi: Razdio filoloških znanosti| volume=9 |publisher=Filozofski fakultet u Zadru|year=1976 |isbn=}}
* {{Cite book|last=Gaži |first=Stephen |title=A History of Croatia |publisher=Philosophical Library |year=1973 |isbn= }}
* {{Cite book|last1=Goodman|first1=Anthony|last2=Gillespie|first2=James|first= |title=Richard II: The Art of Kingship |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=2003 |isbn=0-19-926220-9 |url= }}
* {{Cite book|last1=Grierson|first1=Philip|last2=Travaini|first2=Lucia|title=Medieval European coinage: with a catalogue of the coins in the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge, Volume 14 |publisher=Cambridge University Press  |year=1998|isbn=0-521-58231-8|url=}}
* {{Cite book|last1=Gromada|first1=Tadeusz|last2=Halecki|first2=Oskar|first= |title=Jadwiga of Anjou and the rise of East Central Europe |publisher=Social Science Monographs |year=1991|isbn=0-88033-206-9|url=|authorlink2=Oskar Halecki}}
* {{Cite book|last=Instytut Historii (Polska Akademia Nauk) |title=Acta Poloniae historica, Issues 89–90 |publisher=Zakład Narodowy im. Ossolińskich |year=2004 |isbn= }}
* {{Cite book|last=Jansen|first=Sharon L. |title=Anne of France : lessons for my daughter&amp;nbsp;– Library of medieval women |publisher=DS Brewer |year=2004 |isbn=1-84384-016-2 |url= }}
* {{Cite book|last=Jasienica|first=Paweł|title=Jagiellonian Poland|publisher=American Institute of Polish Culture|year=1978|isbn= 978-1-881284-01-7|url= |authorlink1=Paweł Jasienica}}
* {{Cite book|last1=Johnson|first1=Ian Richard|last2=Wogan-Browne|first2=Jocelyn |title=The idea of the vernacular: an anthology of Middle English literary theory, 1280–1520 Library of medieval women |publisher=Penn State Press |year=1999 |isbn=0-271-01758-9 |url= }}
* {{Cite book|last=Kellogg |first=Charlotte |title=Jadwiga, Queen of Poland |publisher=Anderson House |year=1936 |isbn=}}
* {{Cite book|author=Lietuvos Istorijos institutas (Lietuvos Mokslų akademija) |title=Lithuanian historical studies, Volume 1 |publisher=The Institute |year=1996 |isbn= |url=}}
* {{Cite book|editor-last=Jones|editor-first=Michael|last=McKitterick|first=Rosamond |title=The New Cambridge Medieval History: c. 1300–c. 1415 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=2000 |isbn=0-521-36290-3 }}
* {{Cite book|first1=Domokos G.|last1=Kosáry|first2=Steven Béla|last2=Várdy|title=History of the Hungarian Nation|publisher=Danubian Press|year=1969|isbn=}}
* {{Cite book|last=Maurice|first=Michael|title=The Annals of Jan Długosz: An English Abridgement, Part 1480|publisher=IM Publications |year=1997 |isbn=1-901019-00-4}}
* {{Cite book|last=Parsons|first=John Carmi|title=Medieval Queenship|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|year=1997|isbn=0-312-17298-2}}
* {{Cite book|last=Petricioli |first=Ivo |title=Srednjovjekovnim graditeljima u spomen |publisher=Književni krug |year=1996 |language=Croatian |isbn= }}
* {{Cite book|last=Przybyszewski|first=Bolesław|title=Saint Jadwiga, Queen of Poland 1374–1399|publisher=Veritas Foundation Publication Centre|year=1997|language=|isbn=0-948202-69-6}}
* {{Cite book|last=Reddaway|first=William Fiddian|title=The Cambridge history of Poland|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=1950|language=|isbn= }}
* {{Cite book|last=Rożek|first=Michał|title=Polskie koronacje i korony|publisher=Krajowa Agencja Wydawnicza|year=1987|language=Polish|isbn=83-03-01913-9}}
* {{Cite book|last=Rudzki|first=Edward|title=Polskie królowe|publisher=Instytut Prasy i Wydawnictw &quot;Novum&quot;|year=1990|language=Polish|isbn=}}
* {{Cite book|last=Stewart |first=James |title=Croatia |publisher=New Holland Publishers |year=2006 |isbn=1-86011-319-2 }}
* {{Cite book|last=Šišić |first=Ferdo |title=Vojvoda Hrvoje Vukc̆ić Hrvatinić i njegovo doba (1350–1416) |publisher=Matice hrvatske | location=Zagreb | year=1902 |isbn=|language=Croatian}}
* {{Cite book|last=Van Antwerp Fine |first=John |title=The Late Medieval Balkans: A Critical Survey from the Late Twelfth Century to the Ottoman Conquest |publisher=University of Michigan Press |year=1994 |isbn=0-472-08260-4 }}
* {{Cite book|last1=Várdy|first1=Steven Béla|last2=Grosschmid|first2=Géza|last3=Domonkos|first3=Leslie S.|title=Louis the Great: King of Hungary and Poland|publisher=East European Monographs|year=1986|isbn=0-88033-087-2}}
* {{Cite book|last=Varga|first=Domonkos |title=Hungary in greatness and decline: the 14th and 15th centuries|publisher=Hungarian Cultural Foundation|year=1982|isbn=0-914648-11-X }}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
* {{commons-inline|Category:Elizabeth of Bosnia|Elizabeth of Bosnia}}
{{S-start}}
{{S-hou|[[House of Kotromanić]]||1340|January|1387|}}
{{S-roy}}
|-
{{S-vac|last=[[Margaret of Luxembourg]]}}
{{S-ttl | title = [[Queen consort of Hungary]] | years=1353&amp;nbsp;– 1382}}
{{S-vac|next=[[Margaret of Durazzo]]}}
|-
{{S-bef|before=[[Hedwig of Sagan]]}}
{{S-ttl | title = [[Queen consort of Poland]] | years=1370&amp;nbsp;– 1382}}
{{S-vac|next=[[Anne of Cilli]]}}
{{End}}
{{House of Kotromanić}}
{{Hungarian consorts}}

{{Good article}}

{{Authority control}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Elizabeth Of Bosnia}}
[[Category:1340 births]]
[[Category:1387 deaths]]
[[Category:14th-century female rulers]]
[[Category:14th-century viceregal rulers]]
[[Category:Deaths by strangulation]]
[[Category:Kotromanić dynasty]]
[[Category:House of Anjou-Hungary]]
[[Category:Hungarian queens consort]]
[[Category:Polish queens consort]]
[[Category:Women of medieval Poland]]
[[Category:Women of medieval Hungary]]
[[Category:Murdered royalty]]
[[Category:People of Byzantine descent]]</text>
      <sha1>6zfbrw0lrgkbdxlhabmdv165h159kmc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
