<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.28.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2600" case="first-letter">Topic</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Franklin's lost expedition</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>15746136</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744875368</id>
      <parentid>744863069</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-17T23:52:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Natty10000</username>
        <id>673769</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid vandalism revision 744863069 by [[Special:Contributions/2607:FEA8:D20:23E:D0F0:8F55:814B:42D2|2607:FEA8:D20:23E:D0F0:8F55:814B:42D2]] ([[User talk:2607:FEA8:D20:23E:D0F0:8F55:814B:42D2|talk]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="86645">{{Use British English|date=May 2012}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2012}}
[[File:The Arctic Council  planning a search for  Sir John Franklin by Stephen Pearce.jpg|thumb|200px|upright=1.4|''The Arctic Council planning a search for Sir John Franklin'' by [[Stephen Pearce]],  1851. Left to right are: [[George Back]], [[William Edward Parry]], Edward Bird, [[James Clark Ross]], [[Francis Beaufort]] (seated), John Barrow, Jnr, [[Edward Sabine]], [[William Alexander Baillie Hamilton]], [[John Richardson (naturalist)|John Richardson]] and [[Frederick William Beechey]]]]
[[File:Franklin's-Lost-Expedition.png|thumb|150px|Map of the probable routes taken by {{HMS|Erebus|1826|6|}} and {{HMS|Terror|1813|6}} during Franklin's lost expedition. Disko Bay is about {{convert|3200|km|mi}} from the mouth of the [[Mackenzie River]].]]
[[File:Sir John Barrow, 1st Bt by John Jackson.jpg|thumb|150px|upright|[[Sir John Barrow, 1st Baronet|Sir John Barrow]] promoted Arctic voyages of discovery during his long tenure as [[Second Secretary to the Admiralty]].]]
[[File:John Franklin.jpg|thumb|150px|upright|Sir [[John Franklin]] was Barrow's reluctant choice to lead the expedition.]]
[[File:LadyJaneFranklin.jpg|thumb|150px|upright|Portrait of [[Jane Griffin]] (later Lady Franklin), 24, in 1815. She married John Franklin in 1828, a year before he was knighted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopaedia |title=Franklin, Jane, Lady (1792–1875) |encyclopaedia=[[Dictionary of Australian Biography]] |publisher=Angus and Robertson |year=1949 |via=[[Project Gutenberg Australia]] |url=http://gutenberg.net.au/ebooks15/1500721h/0-dict-biogF.html#franklin1 |accessdate=2 March 2008 |first=Percival |last=Serle}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[File:Captaincrozier.jpg|thumb|150px|upright|Captain [[Francis Crozier|F. R. M. Crozier]], executive officer for the expedition, commanded {{HMS|Terror|1813|6}}.]]

'''Franklin's lost expedition''' was a British voyage of [[Arctic exploration]] led by Captain Sir [[John Franklin]] that departed England in 1845 aboard two ships, {{HMS|Erebus|1826|6}} and {{HMS|Terror|1813|6}}. A Royal Navy officer and experienced explorer, Franklin had served on three previous Arctic expeditions, the latter two as commanding officer. His fourth and last, undertaken when he was 59, was meant to traverse the last unnavigated section of the [[Northwest Passage]]. After a few early fatalities, the two ships became icebound in [[Victoria Strait]] near [[King William Island]] in the Canadian Arctic. The entire expedition, 129 men including Franklin, was lost.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Neatby |first1=Leslie H. |last2=Mercer |first2=Keith |last-author-amp=yes |title=Sir John Franklin |url=http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.ca/en/article/sir-john-franklin/ |work=The Canadian Encyclopedia |publisher=Historica Canada |date=&lt;!--undated--&gt; |accessdate=September 18, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Pressed by Franklin's wife, [[Jane Franklin|Jane, Lady Franklin]], and others, the [[Admiralty]] launched a search for the missing expedition in 1848. Prompted in part by Franklin's fame and the Admiralty's offer of a finder's reward, many subsequent expeditions joined the hunt, which at one point in 1850 involved eleven British and two American ships. Several of these ships converged off the east coast of [[Beechey Island]], where the first relics of the expedition were found, including the graves of three crewmen. In 1854, explorer [[John Rae (explorer)|John Rae]], while surveying near the Canadian Arctic coast southeast of King William Island, [[Rae–Richardson Arctic Expedition|acquired relics]] of and stories about the Franklin party from the [[Inuit]]. A search led by [[Francis Leopold McClintock]] in 1859 discovered a note left on King William Island with details about the expedition's fate. Searches continued through much of the 19th&amp;nbsp;century. [[2014 in archaeology|In 2014]], a Canadian search team located {{HMS|Erebus|1826|6}} west of [[O'Reilly Island]], in the eastern portion of [[Queen Maud Gulf]], in the waters of the Arctic archipelago. Finally, [[2016 in archaeology|two years later]], the {{HMS|Terror|1813|6}} wreck was found south of [[King William Island]] in pristine condition by the Arctic Research Foundation.

In 1981, a team of scientists led by Owen Beattie, a professor of anthropology at the University of Alberta, began a series of scientific studies of the graves, bodies, and other physical evidence left by Franklin's men on Beechey Island and King William Island. They concluded that the men whose graves had been found on Beechey Island most likely died of [[pneumonia]] and perhaps [[tuberculosis]] and that [[lead poisoning]] may have worsened their health, owing to badly [[solder]]ed cans held in the ships' food stores. However, it was later suggested that the source of this lead may not have been [[canning|tinned food]], but the distilled water systems fitted to the expedition’s ships.&lt;ref name=&quot;Battersby&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Battersby |first=William |url=http://www.hakluyt.com/PDF/Battersby_Franklin.pdf |title=Identification of the Probable Source of the Lead Poisoning Observed in Members of the Franklin Expedition |journal=[[Journal of the Hakluyt Society]] |year=2008 |access-date=25 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cut marks on human bones found on King William Island were seen as signs of [[cannibalism]]. The combined evidence of all studies suggested that [[hypothermia]], starvation, lead poisoning and disease including [[scurvy]], along with general exposure to a hostile environment whilst lacking adequate clothing and nutrition, killed everyone on the expedition in the years following its last sighting by Europeans in 1845.

The Victorian media portrayed Franklin as a hero despite the expedition's failure and the reports of cannibalism. Songs were written about him, and statues of him in his home town, in London, and in Tasmania credit him with discovery of the Northwest Passage which was actually found by John Rae. Franklin's lost expedition has been the subject of many artistic works, including songs, verse, short stories, and novels, as well as television documentaries.

==Background==
The search by Europeans for a western shortcut by sea from Europe to Asia began with the voyages of [[Christopher Columbus]] in 1492 and continued through the mid-19th century with a long series of exploratory expeditions originating mainly in England. These voyages, when to any degree successful, added to the sum of European geographic knowledge about the Western Hemisphere, particularly North America, and as that knowledge grew larger, attention gradually turned toward the Arctic. Voyagers of the 16th and 17th centuries who made geographic discoveries about North America included [[Martin Frobisher]], [[John Davis (English explorer)|John Davis]], [[Henry Hudson]], and [[William Baffin]]. In 1670, the incorporation of the [[Hudson's Bay Company]] led to further exploration of the Canadian coasts and interior and of the Arctic seas. In the 18th century, explorers included [[James Knight (explorer)|James Knight]], [[Christopher Middleton (navigator)|Christopher Middleton]], [[Samuel Hearne]], [[James Cook]], [[Alexander Mackenzie (explorer)|Alexander MacKenzie]], and [[George Vancouver]]. By 1800, their discoveries showed conclusively that no [[Northwest Passage]] navigable by ships lay in the temperate latitudes between the Pacific and the Atlantic Oceans.{{sfn|Savours|1999|pp=1–38}}

In 1804, Sir [[Sir John Barrow, 1st Baronet|John Barrow]] became Second Secretary of the [[Admiralty]], a post he held until 1845, and began a push by the Royal Navy to complete the Northwest Passage over the top of Canada and to navigate toward the North Pole. Over the next four decades, explorers including [[John Ross (Arctic explorer)|John Ross]], [[David Buchan]], [[William Edward Parry]], [[Frederick William Beechey]], [[James Clark Ross]], [[George Back]], [[Peter Warren Dease]], and Thomas Simpson made productive trips to the Canadian Arctic. Among these explorers was John Franklin, second-in-command of an expedition towards the North Pole in the ships ''Dorothea'' and ''Trent'' in 1818 and the leader of overland expeditions to and along the Arctic coast of Canada in 1819–22 and 1825–27.{{sfn|Savours|1999|pp=39–166}} By 1845, the combined discoveries of all of these expeditions had reduced the relevant unknown parts of the Canadian Arctic to a quadrilateral area of about {{convert|181300|km2|sqmi|0|abbr=on}}.{{sfn|Savours|1999|p=169}} It was into this unknown area that Franklin was to sail, heading west through [[Lancaster Sound]] and then west and south as ice, land, and other obstacles might allow, to complete the Northwest Passage. The distance to be navigated was roughly {{convert|1670|km|mi|-1}}.{{sfn|Cyriax|1939|pp=18–23}}

==Preparations==

===Command===
Barrow, who was 82 and nearing the end of his career, deliberated about who should command the expedition to complete the Northwest Passage and perhaps also find what Barrow believed to be an ice-free [[Open Polar Sea]] around the North Pole. Parry, his first choice, was tired of the Arctic and politely declined.{{sfn|Sandler|2006|pp=65–74}} His second choice, James Clark Ross, also declined because he had promised his new wife he was done with the Arctic.{{sfn|Sandler|2006|pp=65–74}} Barrow's third choice, [[James Fitzjames]], was rejected by the Admiralty on account of his youth.{{sfn|Sandler|2006|pp=65–74}} Barrow considered George Back but thought he was too argumentative.{{sfn|Sandler|2006|pp=65–74}} [[Francis Crozier]], another possibility, was of humble birth and Irish, which counted against him.{{sfn|Sandler|2006|pp=65–74}} Reluctantly, Barrow settled on the 59-year-old Franklin.{{sfn|Sandler|2006|pp=65–74}} The expedition was to consist of two ships, {{HMS|Erebus|1826|6|}} and {{HMS|Terror|1813|6}}, each of which had seen Antarctic service with James Clark Ross. Fitzjames was given command of ''Erebus'', and Crozier, who had commanded ''Terror'' during the Antarctica expedition with Ross in 1841–44, was appointed the executive officer and commander of ''Terror''. Franklin received his expedition command on 7 February 1845, and his official instructions on 5 May 1845.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Gibson |first=William, F.R.G.S. |title=Sir John Franklin's Last Voyage: A brief history of the Franklin expedition and the outline of the researches which established the facts of its tragic outcome |journal=The Beaver |page=48 |date=June 1937}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ships, provisions and crew===
''Erebus'' at 378 tons ([[Builder's Old Measurement|bm]]) and ''Terror'' at 331 tons (bm) were sturdily built and were outfitted with recent inventions.{{sfn|Sandler|2006|p=70}} Steam engines were fitted in ''Erebus'' and ''Terror'' to drive a single screw in each vessel; these engines were former locomotives from the London &amp; Croydon Railway. They enabled the ships to make {{convert|7.4|km/h|kn|0|lk=out|abbr=on}} on their own power.{{sfn|Savours|1999|p=180}} Other advanced technology included bows reinforced with heavy beams and plates of iron, an internal steam heating device for the comfort of the crew, screw propellers and iron rudders that could be withdrawn into iron wells to protect them from damage, ships' libraries of more than 1,000&amp;nbsp;books, and three&amp;nbsp;years' worth of conventionally preserved or tinned preserved food supplies.{{sfn|Sandler|2006|pp=71–73}} The latter was supplied from a provisioner, [[Stephen Goldner]], who was awarded the contract on 1 April 1845, a mere seven weeks before Franklin set sail.{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|pp=25, 158}} Goldner worked frantically on the large and hasty order of 8,000&amp;nbsp;tins. The speed required affected [[quality control]] of a proportion of the tins manufactured, which were later found to have lead soldering that was &quot;thick and sloppily done, and dripped like melted candle wax down the inside surface&quot;.{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|p=113}}

Most of the crew were Englishmen, many of them from the North Country, with a small number of Irishmen and Scotsmen. Aside from Franklin, Crozier, and Lieutenant Graham Gore, the only other officers who were Arctic veterans were an assistant surgeon and the two ice-masters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Potter |first=Russell A. (ed.) |authorlink=Russell Potter |title=Interview with Michael Smith, author of ''Captain Francis Crozier: Last Man Standing?'' |work=The Arctic Book Review, Vol. 8, Nos. 1 and 2 |date=Fall 2006 |url=http://www.ric.edu/faculty/rpotter/abr/Smith_Interview.htm |accessdate=14 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Australian connections===
Apart from Sir John Franklin himself, who was a former [[Governor of Tasmania|Lieutenant-Governor of Van Diemen's Land]], the crew included two people with close family connections to explorers of [[Australia]] who also died tragically.  Cmdr Henry Le Vesconte was the first cousin of [[William John Wills]], the co-leader of the 1861 [[Burke and Wills expedition]], the first to cross the Australian mainland from south to north; both Burke and Wills perished on the return journey.&lt;ref&gt;[http://tww.id.au/family-history-wills/get/pam.html Wills Family History]. Retrieved 6 June 2016&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.burkeandwills.net.au/Despatches/Wills/Wills_Letter_12.htm BurkeandWills.net]. Retrieved 6 June 2016&lt;/ref&gt;  William Gibson, a steward on HMS ''Terror'', was the elder brother of [[Alfred Gibson]], who disappeared on an 1874 expedition led by [[Ernest Giles]] to cross the deserts of [[Western Australia]] from east to west, and was honoured in the naming of the [[Gibson Desert]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.arcticwebsite.com/Franklin1845roster.html Arctic Website]. Retrieved 6 June 2016&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;William Battersby, [https://books.google.com.au/books?id=z1EdXmlVMF4C&amp;pg=PA188&amp;lpg=PA188&amp;dq=%22william+gibson%22+franklin+expedition&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=IK-PTq-bMP&amp;sig=_UAUmiYvlTvxKUXSdUCVmiS8DYs&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiv5dD1i5LNAhXLjpQKHa8QBew4ChDoAQghMAE#v=onepage&amp;q=%22william%20gibson%22%20franklin%20expedition&amp;f=false ''James Fitzjames: The Mystery Man of the Franklin Expedition''], p. 188. Retrieved 6 June 2016&lt;/ref&gt; From Giles' journal entry of 21 April 1873:
&lt;blockquote&gt;I remarked to Gibson as we rode along that this was the anniversary of Burke's and Wills's return to their depot at Coopers' Creek and then recited to him, as he did not appear to know anything whatever about it, the hardships they endured, their desperate struggles for existence and death there; and casually remarked that Mr Wills had a brother [sic] who also lost his life in the field of discovery, as he went out with Sir John Franklin in 1845. Gibson then remarked, &quot;Oh, I had a brother who died with Franklin at the North Pole and my father had a great deal of trouble getting his pay from Government&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Karma Abraham, &quot;Looking for Gibson&quot;, ''Sydney Morning Herald'', 11 September 1999, Good Weekend, p. 61&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Loss==
[[File:The memorial to the Franklin Expedition in the Chapel of the Naval College at Greenwich.jpg|thumb|150px|The memorial to the Franklin Expedition in the Chapel of the Naval College at Greenwich, containing the body returned here in 1869 (later identified as assistant surgeon Harry Goodsir&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Reardon |first=Sara |title=Skeleton May Help Solve Mystery of Doomed Franklin Expedition |date=12 July 2011 |url=http://news.sciencemag.org/2011/07/skeleton-may-help-solve-mystery-doomed-franklin-expedition |journal=Science |publisher=American Association for the Advancement of Science |accessdate=19 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;)]] The expedition set sail from [[Greenhithe]], England, on the morning of 19 May 1845, with a crew of 24&amp;nbsp;officers and 110&amp;nbsp;men. The ships stopped briefly in Stromness Harbour in the  [[Orkney]] Islands in northern Scotland, and from there they sailed to [[Greenland]] with HMS ''Rattler'' and a transport ship, ''Barretto Junior''.{{sfn|Cookman|2000|p=74}}

At the Whalefish Islands in [[Disko Bay]], on the west coast of Greenland, 10&amp;nbsp;oxen carried by the transport ship were slaughtered for fresh meat; supplies were transferred to ''Erebus'' and ''Terror'', and crew members wrote their last letters home. Letters written on board told how Franklin banned swearing and drunkenness.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Owen |first=Roderick |title=The fate of Franklin |publisher=[[Hutchinson (publisher)|Hutchinson]] |year=1978 |location=London |page=236 |isbn=978-0-09-131190-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Before the expedition's final departure, five&amp;nbsp;men were discharged and sent home on ''Rattler'' and ''Barretto Junior'', reducing the ships' final crew size to 129. The expedition was last seen by Europeans in late July 1845, when Captain Dannett of the whaler ''Prince of Wales'' and Captain Robert Martin of the whaler ''Enterprise'' encountered ''Terror'' and ''Erebus'' in [[Baffin Bay]], waiting for good conditions to cross to Lancaster Sound.{{sfn|Cyriax|1939|pp=66–68}}

Over the next 150&amp;nbsp;years, other expeditions, explorers, and scientists would piece together what happened next. Franklin's men wintered in 1845–46 on [[Beechey Island]], where three crew members died and were buried. ''Terror'' and ''Erebus'' became trapped in ice off [[King William Island]] in September 1846 and never sailed again. According to a note dated 25 April 1848, and left on the island by Fitzjames and Crozier, Franklin had died on 11 June 1847; the crew had wintered on King William Island in 1846–47 and 1847–48, and the remaining crew had planned to begin walking on 26 April 1848 toward the [[Back River]] on the Canadian mainland. Nine officers and fifteen men had already died; the rest would die along the way, most on the island and another 30 or 40 on the northern coast of the mainland, hundreds of miles from the nearest outpost of Western civilization.{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|pp=19–50}}

==Early searches==
After two&amp;nbsp;years had passed with no word from Franklin, public concern grew and [[Jane Franklin|Lady Franklin]]—as well as members of [[Parliament of the United Kingdom|Parliament]] and British newspapers—urged the Admiralty to send a search party. In response, the Admiralty developed a three-pronged plan put into effect in the spring of 1848 that sent an overland rescue party, led by Sir [[John Richardson (naturalist)|John Richardson]] and [[John Rae (explorer)|John Rae]], down the [[MacKenzie River]] to the Canadian Arctic coast. Two expeditions by sea were also launched, one entering the Canadian Arctic [[archipelago]] through Lancaster Sound, and the other entering from the Pacific side.{{sfn|Savours|1999|pp=186–89}} In addition, the Admiralty offered a reward of £20,000 (£{{formatnum:{{inflation|UK|20000|1848|r=-2}}}} as of {{CURRENTYEAR}}) &quot;to any Party or Parties, of any country, who shall render assistance to the crews of the Discovery Ships under the command of Sir John Franklin&quot;.{{sfn|Sandler|2006|p=80}} After the three-pronged effort failed, British national concern and interest in the Arctic increased until &quot;finding Franklin became nothing less than a crusade.&quot;{{sfn|Sandler|2006|pp=87–88}} Ballads such as &quot;[[Lady Franklin's Lament]]&quot;, commemorating Lady Franklin's search for her lost husband, became popular.{{sfn|Sandler|2006|p=266}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Potter |first=Russell A |title=Songs and Ballads About Sir John Franklin |url=http://www.ric.edu/faculty/rpotter/ballad.html |date=&lt;!--undated--&gt; |accessdate=26 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:A chart illustrative of the cruise of the American Arctic expedition in search of sir John Franklin in the years 1850 &amp; 51 fitted out by Henry Gunnell - UvA-BC OTM HB-KZL 101.14.13.jpg|thumb|150px|Map of searches in 1850–51]]

Many joined the search. In 1850, 11 British and [[First Grinnell Expedition|two American ships]] cruised the Canadian Arctic, including [[Breadalbane (ship)|''Breadalbane'']], and her sister ship {{HMS|Phoenix}}.{{sfn|Sandler|2006|p=102}} Several converged off the east coast of Beechey Island, where the first relics of the expedition were found, including remnants of a winter camp from 1845–46 and the graves of [[John Torrington]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Geiger |first=John |title='Iceman' Torrington Was Last of His Line |work=The Edmonton Sun |date=9 December 1984}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[John Hartnell]], and [[William Braine]]. No messages from the Franklin expedition were found at this site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Geiger |first=John |title=Was Murder Uncovered? |work=The Edmonton Sun |date=3 October 1984}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Picard |first=Carol |title=Iceman Wasn't 'Iced' – Autopsy on Seaman Reveals No Evidence of Foul Play |work=The Edmonton Sun |date=10 October 1984}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the spring of 1851, passengers and crew aboard several ships observed a huge iceberg off [[Newfoundland (island)|Newfoundland]] which bore two vessels, one upright and one on its beam ends.{{sfn|Gould|1928|pp=52–81}} The ships were not examined closely. It was suggested that the ships could have been ''Erebus'' and ''Terror'', though it is more likely that they were abandoned [[whaling ship]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.umanitoba.ca/libraries/units/archives/digital/abb/1852k.html |title=Arctic Blue Books – British Parliamentary Papers Abstract, 1852k. |publisher=Great Britain House of Commons |accessdate=10 September 2014 |date=1852 |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Sir Edward Belcher by Stephen Pearce.jpg|thumb|150px|upright|[[Edward Belcher]]]]

In 1852, [[Edward Belcher]] was given command of the government [[Arctic]] expedition in search of Sir [[John Franklin]]. This was unsuccessful; Belcher's inability to render himself popular with his subordinates was peculiarly unfortunate in an Arctic voyage, and he was not wholly suited to command vessels among ice. Four of the five ships ({{HMS|Resolute|1850|6}}, ''Pioneer'', {{HMS|Assistance|1850|2}} and ''Intrepid''){{sfn|Mowat|1973|p=285}} were abandoned in [[pack ice]], for which Belcher was court-martialed but acquitted. One of those ships, HMS ''Resolute'', was later recovered intact by an American whaler. Timbers from the ship were later used to manufacture three desks, one of which, the [[Resolute desk]], was presented by Queen Victoria to the [[President of the United States|U.S. President]] [[Rutherford B. Hayes]]; it has often been chosen by presidents for use in the [[Oval Office]] in the [[White House]].

==Overland searches==
{{Main article|Rae–Richardson Arctic Expedition|McClintock Arctic Expedition}}
[[Image:John Rae (explorer).jpg|thumb|150px|left|[[John Rae (explorer)|John Rae]] acquired the first Franklin expedition relics from the Inuit and reported on starvation and cannibalism among the dying crewmen.]]
[[Image:cfhall harpers.jpg|thumb|150px|left|upright|[[Charles Francis Hall]]]]
[[File:Relief on the gravestone of Lieutenant John Irving, R.N., Dean Cemetery Edinburgh.jpg|thumb|150px|upright|left|Gravestone of Lt. John Irving whose body was found and returned to Edinburgh for re-interment in 1881]]
[[Image:Franklin raerels 800.jpg|thumb|150px|right|upright|Relics of Franklin's 1845 expedition, from the ''[[Illustrated London News]]'', 1854]]
[[File:Franklin exp.jpg|thumb|150px|right|upright|Relics of Franklin's lost expedition found by McClintock]]
[[Image:Franklinexpeditionnote.jpg|thumb|150px|right|upright|The note found by McClintock in May 1859 in a cairn south of [[Back Bay]], [[King William Island]], detailing the fate of the Franklin expedition]]
[[File:Reward for finding Franklin Expedition.jpg|thumb|150px|upright|Poster offering a reward for help in finding the expedition]]

{{Location map
| Canada Nunavut
| caption = Location in Nunavut
| label = Adelaide Peninsula
| lat_deg = 68
| lat_min = 06
| lat_dir = N
| lon_deg = 097
| lon_min = 48
| lon_dir = W}}

In 1854, John Rae, while surveying the [[Boothia Peninsula]] for the [[Hudson's Bay Company]] (HBC), discovered further evidence of the lost men's fate. Rae met an [[Inuit|Inuk]] near [[Kugaaruk, Nunavut|Pelly Bay]] (now Kugaaruk, Nunavut) on 21 April 1854, who told him of a party of 35 to 40&amp;nbsp;white men who had died of starvation near the mouth of the Back River. Other Inuit confirmed this story, which included reports of cannibalism among the dying sailors. The Inuit showed Rae many objects that were identified as having belonged to Franklin and his men. In particular, Rae brought from the Pelly Bay Inuit several silver forks and spoons later identified as belonging to Fitzjames, Crozier, Franklin, and Robert Osmer Sargent, a [[shipmate]] aboard ''Erebus''. Rae's report was sent to the Admiralty, which in October 1854 urged the HBC to send an expedition down the Back River to search for other signs of Franklin and his men.{{sfn|Klutschak|Barr|1989|pp=xv–xvi}}{{sfn|Savours|1999|pp=270–277}}

Next were Chief Factor James Anderson and HBC employee James Stewart, who travelled north by canoe to the mouth of the Back River. In July 1855, a band of Inuit told them of a group of ''qallunaat'' ([[Inuktitut]] for &quot;whites&quot;) who had starved to death along the coast.{{sfn|Klutschak|Barr|1989|pp=xv–xvi}} In August, Anderson and Stewart found a piece of wood inscribed with &quot;Erebus&quot; and another that said &quot;Mr. Stanley&quot; (surgeon aboard ''Erebus'') on [[Montreal Island (Nunavut)|Montreal Island]] in [[Chantrey Inlet]], where the Back River meets the sea.{{sfn|Klutschak|Barr|1989|pp=xv–xvi}}

Despite the findings of Rae and Anderson, the Admiralty did not plan another search of its own. Britain officially labelled the crew deceased in service on 31 March 1854.{{sfn|Cookman|2000|p=2}} Lady Franklin, failing to convince the government to fund another search, personally commissioned [[McClintock Arctic Expedition|one more expedition]] under [[Francis Leopold McClintock]]. The expedition ship, the steam [[schooner]] ''Fox'', bought via public subscription, sailed from Aberdeen on 2 July 1857.

In April 1859, sledge parties set out from ''Fox'' to search on [[King William Island]]. On 5 May, the party led by Royal Navy Lieutenant William Hobson found a document in a [[cairn]] left by Crozier and Fitzjames.{{sfn|Cookman|2000|pp=8–9}} It contained two messages. The first, dated 28 May 1847, said that ''Erebus'' and ''Terror'' had wintered in the ice off the northwest coast of King William Island and had wintered earlier at Beechey Island after circumnavigating [[Cornwallis Island (Nunavut)|Cornwallis Island]]. &quot;Sir John Franklin commanding the Expedition. ''All well'' &quot;, the message said.{{sfn|Savours|1999|p=292}} The second message, written in the margins of that same sheet of paper, was much more ominous. Dated 25 April 1848, it reported that ''Erebus'' and ''Terror'' had been trapped in the ice for a year and a half and that the crew had abandoned the ships on 22 April. Twenty-four&amp;nbsp;officers and crew had died, including Franklin on 11 June 1847, just two weeks after the date of the first note. Crozier was commanding the expedition, and the 105&amp;nbsp;survivors planned to start out the next day, heading south towards the Back River.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/arctic/note-transcript.html |title=NOVA Arctic Passage – The Note in the Cairn (transcript) |accessdate=31 January 2008 |work=PBS |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150331205033/http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/arctic/note-transcript.html |archivedate=31 March 2015 |dead-url=no |date=&lt;!--undated--&gt; |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; This note contains significant errors; most notably the date of the expedition's winter camp at Beechey Island is incorrectly given as 1846–47 rather than 1845–46.{{sfn|Woodman|1995|p=5}}

The McClintock expedition also found a human skeleton on the southern coast of King William Island. Still clothed, it was searched, and some papers were found, including a seaman's certificate for Chief Petty Officer Henry Peglar (b. 1808), Captain of the Foretop, HMS ''Terror''. However, since the uniform was that of a ship's steward, it is more likely that the body was that of Thomas Armitage, gun-room steward on HMS ''Terror'' and a shipmate of Peglar, whose papers he carried.{{sfn|Savours|1999|pp=295–296}} At another site on the western extreme of the island, Hobson discovered a lifeboat containing two skeletons and relics from the Franklin expedition. In the boat was a large amount of abandoned equipment, including boots, silk handkerchiefs, scented soap, sponges, slippers, hair combs, and many books, among them a copy of ''[[The Vicar of Wakefield]]''. McClintock also took testimony from the Inuit about the expedition's disastrous end.{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|pp=34–40}}

Two expeditions between 1860 and 1869 by [[Charles Francis Hall]], who lived among the Inuit near [[Frobisher Bay]] on Baffin Island and later at [[Repulse Bay, Nunavut|Repulse Bay]] on the Canadian mainland, found camps, graves, and relics on the southern coast of King William Island, but none of the Franklin expedition survivors he believed would be found among the Inuit. Though he concluded that all of the Franklin crew were dead, he believed that the official expedition records would yet be found under a stone cairn.{{sfn|Schwatka|1965|pp=12–15}} With the assistance of his guides Ebierbing and [[Tookoolito]], Hall gathered hundreds of pages of Inuit testimony. Among these materials are accounts of visits to Franklin's ships, and an encounter with a party of white men on the southern coast of King William Island near Washington Bay. In the 1990s, this testimony was extensively researched by David C. Woodman, and was the basis of two books, ''Unravelling the Franklin Mystery'' (1992) and ''Strangers Among Us'' (1995), in which he reconstructs the final months of the expedition.

The hope of finding these lost papers led Lieutenant [[Frederick Schwatka]] of the U.S. Army to organise an expedition to the island between 1878 and 1880. Traveling to Hudson Bay on the schooner ''Eothen'', Schwatka, assembling a team that included Inuit who had assisted Hall, continued north by foot and [[dog sled]], interviewing Inuit, visiting known or likely sites of Franklin expedition remains, and wintering on King William Island. Though Schwatka failed to find the hoped-for papers, in a speech at a dinner given in his honour by the American Geographical Society in 1880, he noted that his expedition had made &quot;the longest sledge journey ever made both in regard to time and distance&quot;{{sfn|Schwatka|1965|pp=115–116}} of 11 months and 4 days and {{convert|4360|km|mi}}, that it was the first Arctic expedition on which the whites relied entirely on the same diet as the Inuit, and that it established the loss of the Franklin records &quot;beyond all reasonable doubt&quot;.{{sfn|Schwatka|1965|pp=115–116}} The Schwatka expedition found no remnants of the Franklin expedition south of a place known as Starvation Cove on the [[Adelaide Peninsula]]. This was well north of Crozier's stated goal, the Back River, and several hundred miles away from the nearest Western outpost, on the [[Great Slave Lake]]. Woodman wrote of Inuit reports that between 1852 and 1858 Crozier and one other expedition member were seen in the [[Baker Lake, Nunavut|Baker Lake]] area, about {{convert|400|km|mi}} to the south, where in 1948 [[Farley Mowat]] found &quot;a very ancient cairn, not of normal Eskimo construction&quot; inside which were shreds of a hardwood box with [[dovetail joint]]s.{{sfn|Woodman|1992|p=317}}&lt;ref&gt;Woodman was unable to track down the origin of these Inuit reports, and the builder or origins of the cairn found by Mowat are unknown.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Contemporary search expeditions==
* 1848:
** East: [[James Clark Ross]], ({{HMS|Enterprise|1848|6}}, {{HMS|Investigator|1848|6}}) only to Somerset Island because of ice.
** Center: [[Rae–Richardson Arctic Expedition]]  Mackenzie River and along the coast.
** West: HMS ''Plover'', HMS ''Herald'' to Bering Strait; [[William Pullen]] reaches Mackenzie by whaleboat.
* 1850:
** West: [[Richard Collinson]] (HMS ''Enterprise''), [[Robert McClure]] (HMS ''Investigator'') to Bering Strait. McClure frozen in at Banks Island and ''Investigator'' abandoned after two winters, crew trek east to Belcher expedition ships, becoming first Europeans to cross the northwest passage. Collinson reaches Coronation Gulf, furthest east of any ship.
** East: [[Horatio Austin]] ({{HMS|Resolute|1850|6}}), [[Erasmus Ommanney]] ({{HMS|Assistance|1850|6}}), plus 2 steam tenders, ''Pioneer'' and ''Intrepid'' (cpt John Bertie Cator 1850). Ommanney finds Franklin's Beechey Island camp. Austin's four and the below ships gather around Beechey Island, are frozen in and in spring send out sledge expeditions in all directions. They leave the Arctic before winter in 1851.
** East: Charles Forsyth (''Prince Albert'') financed by Lady Franklin; sledge on Somerset Island to Fury Beach.
** East: [[William Penny]] (''Lady Franklin'' and ''Sophia'')
** East: [[John Ross (Arctic explorer)|John Ross]] (schooner ''Felix'')
** East: [[Edwin de Haven]] ({{USS|Rescue|1850|6}}, {{USS|Advance|1850|6}}) mounted the [[First Grinnell Expedition]].
* 1851: [[William Kennedy (explorer)|William Kennedy]] (''Prince Albert'' again) finds [[Bellot Strait]] proving that Somerset Island is an island.
* 1852:
** [[Edward Augustus Inglefield]] in northern Baffin Bay.
** [[Edward Belcher]] in five ships: HMS ''Assistance'' (Belcher), HMS ''Resolute'' ([[Henry Kellett]]), ''Pioneer'' ([[Sherard Osborn]]), ''Intrepid'' ([[Francis Leopold McClintock]]) and depot ship {{HMS|North Star|1824|6}} (William Pullen); much sledge exploration; rescues crew of HMS ''Investigator''; all frozen in and abandoned except for ''North Star''. Joined by supply ships ''[[Breadalbane (ship)|Bredalbane]]'', which would be crushed by ice, and {{HMS|Phoenix|1832|6}}, which with ''North Star'' took off crews of the other ships, including that of McClure's HMS ''Investigator'', in 1854.
** [[Elisha Kane]] led the [[Second Grinnell Expedition]]
** Boat expedition up the Wellington Channel under the command of R. M'Cormick, R.N., in HMB ''Forlorn Hope''
* 1854: [[John Rae (explorer)|John Rae]] learns where Franklin lost his ship.
* 1855: Anderson and Stewart descend the [[Back River]] and find relics in [[Chantry Inlet]].
* 1857: McClintock finds relics at King William Island, including a ship's boat on runners containing two corpses.
* 1869: [[Charles Francis Hall]] at King William Island
* 1875: [[Allen Young]] blocked at Peel Sound
* 1878: [[Frederick Schwatka]] at King William Island

==Scientific expeditions==

===King William Island excavations (1981–82)===
In June 1981, [[Owen Beattie]], a professor of anthropology at the [[University of Alberta]], began the 1845–48 Franklin Expedition Forensic Anthropology Project (FEFAP) when he and his team of researchers and field assistants travelled from [[Edmonton]] to King William Island, traversing the island's western coast as Franklin's men did 132&amp;nbsp;years before. FEFAP hoped to find artifacts and skeletal remains in order to use modern [[Forensic science|forensics]] to establish identities and causes of death among the lost 129.{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|pp=51–52}}

Although the trek found archaeological artifacts related to 19th-century Europeans and undisturbed [[Disarticulation|disarticulated]] human remains, Beattie was disappointed that more remains were not found.{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|p=58}} Examining the bones of Franklin crewmen, he noted areas of pitting and scaling often found in cases of Vitamin C deficiency, the cause of [[scurvy]].{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|p=56}} After returning to Edmonton, he compared notes from the survey with James Savelle, an Arctic archaeologist, and noticed skeletal patterns suggesting [[cannibalism]].{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|pp=58–62}} Seeking information about the Franklin crew's health and diet, he sent bone samples to the Alberta Soil and Feed Testing Laboratory for [[trace element]] analysis and assembled another team to visit King William Island. The analysis would find an unexpected level of 226&amp;nbsp;[[parts per million]] (ppm) of lead in the crewman's bones, which was 10&amp;nbsp;times higher than the [[Scientific control|control]] samples, taken from Inuit skeletons from the same geographic area, of 26–36&amp;nbsp;ppm.{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|p=83}}

In June 1982, a team made up of Beattie; Walt Kowall, a graduate student in anthropology at the University of Alberta; Arne Carlson, an archaeology and geography student from Simon Fraser University in British Columbia; and Arsien Tungilik, an Inuk student and field assistant, were flown to the west coast of King William Island, where they retraced some of the steps of McClintock in 1859 and Schwatka in 1878–79.{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|p=63}} Discoveries during this expedition included the remains of between six and fourteen men in the vicinity of McClintock's &quot;boat place&quot; and artifacts including a complete boot sole fitted with makeshift cleats for better traction.{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|pp=77–82}}

===Beechey Island excavations and exhumations (1984–86)===
After returning to Edmonton in 1982 and learning of the lead-level findings from the 1981 expedition, Beattie struggled to find a cause. Possibilities included the lead [[solder]] used to seal the expedition's food tins, other food containers lined with lead foil, food colouring, tobacco products, [[pewter]] tableware, and lead-wicked candles. He came to suspect that the problems of lead poisoning compounded by the effects of scurvy could have been lethal for the Franklin crew. However, because skeletal lead might reflect lifetime exposure rather than exposure limited to the voyage, Beattie's theory could be tested only by forensic examination of preserved soft tissue as opposed to bone. Beattie decided to examine the graves of the buried crewmen on Beechey Island.{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|pp=83–85}}

[[File:BeecheyIsland Graves.jpg|thumb|150px|left|Graves of the crewmen buried on [[Beechey Island]] (2004)]]

After obtaining legal permission,{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|pp=86–87}} Beattie's team visited Beechey Island in August 1984 to perform autopsies on the three crewmen buried there.{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|p=85}} They started with the first crew member to die, Leading Stoker John Torrington. After completing Torrington's autopsy and exhuming and briefly examining the body of [[John Hartnell]], the team, pressed for time and threatened by the weather, returned to Edmonton with tissue and bone samples.{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|pp=111–120}} Trace element analysis of Torrington's bones and hair indicated that the crewman &quot;would have suffered severe mental and physical problems caused by lead poisoning&quot;.{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|p=123}} Although the autopsy indicated that pneumonia had been the ultimate cause of the crewman's death, lead poisoning was cited as a contributing factor.{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|pp=122–123}}

During the expedition, the team visited a place about {{convert|1|km|mi|1|abbr=on}} north of the grave site to examine fragments of hundreds of food tins discarded by Franklin's men. Beattie noted that the seams were poorly soldered with lead, which had likely come in direct contact with the food.{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|p=158}}&lt;ref name=&quot;LLTissues1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Kowall |first1=W.A. |last2=Krahn |first2=P.M. |last3=Beattie |first3=O. B. |last-author-amp=yes |title=Lead Levels in Human Tissues from the Franklin Forensic Project |journal=International Journal Environmental Analytical Chemistry |volume=35 |issue=2 |page=121 |year=1989 |publisher=Gordon and Breach Science Publishers |doi=10.1080/03067318908028385}}&lt;/ref&gt; The release of findings from the 1984 expedition and the photo of Torrington, a 138-year-old corpse well preserved by [[permafrost]] in the [[tundra]], led to wide media coverage and renewed interest in the lost Franklin expedition.

Subsequent research has suggested that another potential source for the lead may have been the ships' fresh-water systems rather than the tinned food. K.T.H. Farrer argued that &quot;it is impossible to see how one could ingest from the canned food the amount of lead, 3.3&amp;nbsp;mg per day over eight months, required to raise the PbB to the level 80&amp;nbsp;μg/dL at which symptoms of lead poisoning begin to appear in adults and the suggestion that bone lead in adults could be 'swamped' by lead ingested from food over a period of a few months, or even three years, seems scarcely tenable.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=K. T. H. |last=Farrer |title=Lead and the Last Franklin Expedition |journal=Journal of Archaeological Science |volume=20 |issue=4 |year=1993 |pages=399–409 |doi=10.1006/jasc.1993.1024}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, tinned food was in widespread use within the Royal Navy at that time and its use did not lead to any significant increase in lead poisoning elsewhere. However, and uniquely for this expedition only, the ships were fitted with converted railway [[Steam locomotive|locomotive]] engines for auxiliary propulsion which required an estimated one tonne of fresh water per hour when steaming. It is highly probable that it was for this reason that the ships were fitted with a unique [[Desalination|water distillation]] system which, given the materials in use at the time, would have produced large quantities of water with a very high lead content. William Battersby has argued that this is a much more likely source for the high levels of lead observed in the remains of expedition members than the tinned food.&lt;ref name=&quot;Battersby&quot;/&gt;

A further survey of the graves was undertaken in 1986. A camera crew filmed the procedure, shown in ''[[Nova (TV series)|Nova]]'''s television documentary, ''Buried in Ice'' in 1988.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video |first=Owen |last=Beattie |title=Buried in Ice |medium=television |publisher=WGHB and NOVA |location=Beechey Island |date=1988}}&lt;/ref&gt; Under difficult field conditions, Derek Notman, a radiologist and medical doctor from the [[University of Minnesota]], and radiology technician Larry Anderson took many [[X-ray]]s of the crewmen prior to autopsy. Barbara Schweger, an [[Arctic clothing]] specialist, and Roger Amy, a pathologist, assisted in the investigation.{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|pp=130–145}}

Beattie and his team had noticed that someone else had attempted to exhume Hartnell. In the effort, a pickaxe had damaged the wooden lid of his coffin, and the coffin plaque was missing.{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|p=116}} Research in Edmonton later showed that Sir Edward Belcher, commander of one of the Franklin rescue expeditions, had ordered the exhumation of Hartnell in October 1852, but was thwarted by the permafrost. A month later, [[Edward Augustus Inglefield|Edward A. Inglefield]], commander of another rescue expedition, succeeded with the exhumation and removed the coffin plaque.{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|pp=116–118}}

Unlike Hartnell's grave, the grave of Private William Braine was largely intact.{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|pp=146–47}} When he was exhumed, the survey team saw signs that his burial had been hasty. His arms, body, and head had not been positioned carefully in the coffin, and one of his undershirts had been put on backwards.{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|p=150}} The coffin seemed too small for him; its lid had pressed down on his nose. A large copper plaque with his name and other personal data punched into it adorned his coffin lid.{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|p=148}}

===NgLj-2 excavations (1992)===
In 1992, a team of archaeologists and forensic anthropologists identified a site, which they referenced as &quot;NgLj-2&quot;, on the western shores of King William Island. The site matches the physical description of Leopold McClintock's &quot;boat place&quot;. Excavations there uncovered nearly 400 bones and bone fragments, and physical artefacts ranging from pieces of clay pipes to buttons and brass fittings. Examination of these bones by Anne Keenleyside, the expedition's [[forensic]] scientist, showed elevated levels of lead and many cut-marks &quot;consistent with de-fleshing&quot;. On the basis of this expedition, it has become generally accepted that at least some groups of Franklin's men resorted to cannibalism in their final distress.&lt;ref name=&quot;Keenleyside&quot; /&gt;  On 18 June 2015, a study accepted for publication in the ''[[International Journal of Osteoarchaeology]]'' concluded that in addition to the de-fleshing of bones, 35 &quot;bones had signs of breakage and 'pot polishing,' which occurs when the ends of bones heated in boiling water rub against the cooking pot they are placed in&quot;, which &quot;typically occurs in the end stage of cannibalism, when starving people extract the marrow to eke out the last bit of calories and nutrition they can.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Ghose |first=Tia |title=Cracked Bones Reveal Cannibalism by Doomed Arctic Explorers |url=http://news.discovery.com/history/archaeology/cracked-bones-reveal-cannibalism-by-doomed-arctic-explorers-150722.htm |date=22 July 2015 |publisher=Discovery Communications |accessdate=20 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Wreck searches (1992–93)===
In 1992, Franklin author David C. Woodman, with the help of magnetometer expert Brad Nelson, organised &quot;Project Ootjoolik&quot; to search for the wreck reported by Inuit testimony to lie off the waters of Adelaide Peninsula. Enlisting both a National Research Council and a Canadian Forces patrol aircraft, each fitted with a sensitive magnetometer, a large search area to the west of Grant Point was surveyed from an elevation of {{convert|200|ft|m}}. Over 60 strong magnetic targets were identified, of which five were deemed to have characteristics most congruent to those expected from Franklin's ships.{{Citation needed|date=September 2016}}

In 1993, Dr. Joe McInnis and Woodman organised an attempt to identify the priority targets from the year before. A chartered aircraft landed on the ice at three of the locations, a hole was drilled through the ice, and a small sector-scan sonar was used to image the sea bottom. Unfortunately, due to ice conditions and uncertain navigation, it was not possible to exactly confirm the locations of the holes, and nothing was found although hitherto-unknown depths were found at the locations that were consistent with Inuit testimony of the wreck.{{Citation needed|date=September 2016}}

===King William Island (1994–95)===
In 1994 Woodman organised and led a land search of the area from [[Richard Collinson Inlet]] to (modern) Victory Point in search of the buried &quot;vaults&quot; spoken of in the testimony of the contemporary Inuit hunter Supunger. A 10-person team spent 10 days in the search, sponsored by the [[Royal Canadian Geographical Society]], and filmed by the [[Canadian Broadcasting Corporation|CBC]] ''Focus North''. No trace of the vaults was found.{{Citation needed|date=September 2016}}

In 1995, an expedition was jointly organised by Woodman, George Hobson, and American adventurer Steven Trafton – with each party planning a separate search. Trafton's group travelled to the Clarence Island to investigate Inuit stories of a &quot;white man's cairn&quot; there but found nothing. Dr. Hobson's party, accompanied by archaeologist Margaret Bertulli, investigated the &quot;summer camp&quot; found a few miles to the south of Cape Felix, where some minor Franklin relics were found. Woodman, with two companions, travelled south from Wall Bay to Victory Point and investigated all likely campsites along this coast, finding only some rusted cans at a previously unknown campsite near Cape Maria Louisa.{{Citation needed|date=September 2016}}

===Wreck searches (1997–2013)===
In 1997, a &quot;Franklin 150&quot; expedition was mounted by the Canadian film company Eco-Nova to use sonar to investigate more of the priority magnetic targets found in 1992. Senior archaeologist was Robert Grenier, assisted by Margaret Bertulli, and Woodman again acted as expedition historian and search coordinator. Operations were conducted from the [[CCGS Sir Wilfrid Laurier|Canadian Coast Guard icebreaker ''Laurier'']]. Approximately {{convert|40|km2|mi2}} were surveyed, without result, near Kirkwall Island. When detached parties found Franklin relics, primarily copper sheeting and small items, on the beaches of islets to the north of O'Reilly Island the search was diverted to that area, but poor weather prevented significant survey work before the expedition ended. A documentary, &quot;Oceans of Mystery: Search for the Lost Fleet&quot;, was produced by Eco-Nova about this expedition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.oceansdiscovery.com/about-us/impressum/oceans-of-mystery-documentary.html |title=Oceans Of Mystery Documentary |work=Oceans Discovery |accessdate=10 September 2014 |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |date=&lt;!--undated--&gt; |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140910200101/http://www.oceansdiscovery.com/about-us/impressum/oceans-of-mystery-documentary.html |archive-date=2014-09-10 |deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2000, [[James Delgado]] of the [[Vancouver Maritime Museum]] organised a re-enactment of the historic St. Roch passage westward through the Northwest Passage using the [[RCMP vessel Nadon|RCMP vessel ''Nadon'']] supported by the [[CCGS Simon Fraser|Canadian Buoy Tender ''Simon Fraser'']]. Knowing that ice would delay the transit in the area of King William Island, he offered the use of the Nadon as a search vessel to his friends Hobson and Woodman, and using the Nadon's Kongsberg/Simrad SM2000 forward-looking sonar, the survey of the northern search area around Kirkwall Island was continued without result.{{citation needed|date = September 2014}}

Three expeditions were mounted by Woodman to continue the magnetometer mapping of the proposed wreck sites, a privately sponsored expedition in 2001, and the Irish-Canadian Franklin Search Expeditions of 2002 and 2004. These made use of sled-drawn magnetometers working on the sea ice and completed the unfinished survey of the northern (Kirkwall Island) search area (2001), and the entire southern O'Reilly Island area (2002 and 2004). All high-priority magnetic targets were identified by sonar through the ice as geological in origin. In 2002 and 2004, small Franklin artefacts and characteristic explorer tent sites were found on a small islet northeast of O'Reilly Island during shore searches.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Moore |first=Charles |url=http://www.ric.edu/faculty/rpotter/woodman/2004_Field_Report_short.htm |title=Irish-Canadian Franklin Search Expedition, 2004 |publisher=Rhode Island College |accessdate=10 September 2014 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150605015105/http://www.ric.edu/faculty/rpotter/woodman/2004_Field_Report_short.htm |archivedate=5 June 2015 |dead-url=no |date=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--this paragraph is out of date; what, if anything, was done/found/concluded?--&gt;
In August 2008, a new search was announced, to be led by Robert Grenier, a senior archaeologist with [[Parks Canada]]. This search hoped to take advantage of the improved ice conditions, using [[side-scan sonar]] from a boat in open water. Grenier also hoped to draw from newly published Inuit testimony collected by oral historian [[Dorothy Harley Eber]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Robert |last=Grenier |title=Full Proposals for IPY 2007–2008 Activities |date=1 May 2009 |url=http://classic.ipy.org/development/eoi/proposal-details.php?id=330 |publisher=International Polar Year |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110429214941/http://classic.ipy.org/development/eoi/proposal-details.php?id=330 |archivedate=29 April 2011 |dead-url=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some of Eber's informants have placed the location of one of Franklin's ships in the vicinity of the [[Royal Geographical Society Island]], an area not searched by previous expeditions. The search was to also include local Inuit historian Louie Kamookak, who has found other significant remains of the expedition and would represent the indigenous culture.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Gilles |first=Rob |title=Canada to Search for Arctic Explorer's Ships |agency=Associated Press |date=16 August 2008 |url=http://apnews.myway.com/article/20080816/D92J5FK00.html |publisher=IAC Search &amp; Media |accessdate=17 August 2008 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080826031138/http://apnews.myway.com/article/20080816/D92J5FK00.html |archivedate=26 August 2008 |dead-url=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 25 July 2010, {{HMS|Investigator|1848|6}}, which had become icebound and was subsequently abandoned while searching for Franklin's expedition in 1853, was found in shallow water in [[Mercy Bay]] along the northern coast of [[Banks Island]] in Canada's western Arctic. The Parks Canada team reported that it was in good shape, upright in about 11 metres (36&amp;nbsp;feet) of water.&lt;ref name=&quot;ncoll073010&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Collins |first=Nick |title=Sir John Franklin Search Ship Found |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/northamerica/canada/7917134/Sir-John-Franklin-search-ship-found.html |accessdate=1 August 2010 |newspaper=Telegraph |date=30 July 2010 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150110152955/http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/northamerica/canada/7917134/Sir-John-Franklin-search-ship-found.html |archivedate=10 January 2015 |dead-url=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2013, a new search was announced by Parks Canada.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |url=http://www.newswire.ca/en/story/1208845/on-the-hunt-for-a-missing-piece-of-canadian-history-parks-canada-continues-search-for-lost-franklin-ships |date=9 August 2013 |title=On the Hunt for a Missing Piece of Canadian History: Parks Canada Continues Search for Lost Franklin Ships |publisher=CNW Group |accessdate=19 May 2014 |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Victoria Strait Expedition (2014)===
[[File:Franklin's Lost Expedition - Sonar Image of First Ship Found - Sept 2014.jpg|thumb|150px|right|Side-scan sonar images of the first ship found from the Franklin Expedition, HMS ''Erebus'']]
On 1 September 2014, a larger search by a Canadian team under the banner of the &quot;Victoria Strait Expedition&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pc.gc.ca/apps/cp-nr/release_e.asp?bgid=1799&amp;andor1=bg |title=Victoria Strait Expedition |publisher=[[Parks Canada]] |date=1 May 2015 |accessdate=20 September 2015 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20151004010237/http://www.pc.gc.ca/eng/culture/franklin/recherche-search/exp2014.aspx |archivedate=4 October 2015 |deadurl=no |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; found two items on [[Hat Island (Victoria Strait)|Hat Island]] in the Queen Maud Gulf near Nunavut's King William Island&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Franklin Expedition Ship Pieces Believed Discovered in Arctic |url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/franklin-expedition-ship-pieces-believed-discovered-in-arctic-1.2759925 |publisher=[[CBC News]] |date=8 September 2014 |accessdate=9 September 2014 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141006065319/http://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/franklin-expedition-ship-pieces-believed-discovered-in-arctic-1.2759925 |archivedate=6 October 2014 |dead-url=no |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; — a wooden object, possibly a plug for a deck [[Hawsehole|hawse]], the iron pipe through which the ship's chain cable would descend into the chain locker below; and part of a boat-launching davit bearing the stamps of two Royal Navy broad arrows.{{Citation needed|date=September 2016}}

On 9 September 2014, the expedition announced that on 7 September it had located one of Franklin's two ships.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=AAP |last2=Berney |first2=Leila |last-author-amp=yes |title=1800s British Expedition Shipwreck Found in the Arctic |url=http://www.australiangeographic.com.au/news/2014/09/1800s-british-expedition-shipwreck-found-in-the-arctic |accessdate=18 November 2014 |journal=Australian Geographic |date=12 September 2014 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150908013215/http://www.australiangeographic.com.au/news/2014/09/1800s-british-expedition-shipwreck-found-in-the-arctic |archivedate=8 September 2015 |dead-url=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=CBC_Found&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/lost-franklin-expedition-ship-found-in-the-arctic-1.2760311 |title=Lost Franklin Expedition Ship Found in the Arctic |publisher=[[CBC News]] |date=2014-09-09 |accessdate=9 September 2014 |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dailymotion.com/video/x25m7ya_british-ship-lost-in-arctic-170-years-ago-found_news |title=British Ship Lost in Arctic 170 Years Ago Found - Video Dailymotion |work=Dailymotion |accessdate=13 September 2014 |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |date=&lt;!--undated--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ship is preserved in very good condition, with side-scan sonar picking up even the deck planking.&lt;ref name=CBC_Found /&gt; The wreck lies at the bottom of the eastern portion of Queen Maud Gulf, west of O'Reilly Island. On 1 October at the [[House of Commons of Canada|House of Commons]], Prime Minister [[Stephen Harper]] confirmed that the wreck is indeed HMS ''Erebus''.&lt;ref name=globe&gt;{{cite news |title=Finding of Franklin Ship Fuels Harper's New Nationalism |first=Steven |last=Chase |newspaper=[[The Globe and Mail]] |location=Ottawa |date=9 September 2014 |url=http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/politics/finding-of-franklin-ship-fuels-harpers-new-nationalism/article20508270/ |accessdate=10 September 2014 |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://indiancountrytodaymedianetwork.com/2014/09/10/inuit-were-right-shipwreck-find-confirms-168-year-old-oral-history-156837 |title=The Inuit Were Right: Shipwreck Find Confirms 168-Year-Old Oral History |publisher=[[Indian Country Today Media Network|Indian Country Today]] |date=10 September 2014 |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=cbc-2014oct01&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/franklin-expedition-ship-found-in-arctic-id-d-as-hms-erebus-1.2784268 |title=Franklin Expedition Ship Found in Arctic ID'd as HMS ''Erebus'' |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |website=[[CBC News]] |date=1 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Arctic Research Foundation Expedition (2016)===

On 12 September 2016, it was announced that the [[Arctic Research Foundation]] expedition had found the wreck of {{HMS|Terror|1813|6}} south of [[King William Island]] in Terror Bay, which is at at {{coord|68|54|13|N|98|56|18|W|scale:1000000}}, and in &quot;pristine&quot; condition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/sep/12/hms-terror-wreck-found-arctic-nearly-170-years-northwest-passage-attempt |title=The Guardian:Ship found in Arctic 168 years after doomed Northwest Passage attempt |publisher=theguardian.com |date=2016-09-12 |accessdate=2016-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is many miles south of the last known location of ''Terror''.{{Citation needed|date=September 2016}}

===Scientific conclusions===
The FEFAP field surveys, excavations and exhumations spanned more than 10&amp;nbsp;years. The results of this study from King William Island and Beechey Island artefacts and human remains showed that the Beechey Island crew had most likely died of [[pneumonia]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Amy |first1=Roger |last2=Bhatnagar |first2=Rakesh |last3=Damkjar |first3=Eric |last4=Beattie |first4=Owen |last-author-amp=yes |title=The Last Franklin Expedition: Report of a Postmortem Examination of a Crew Member |journal=[[Canadian Medical Association Journal]] |volume=135 |issue=2 |pages=115–117 |date=15 July 1986 |pmid=3521821 |pmc=1491204}}&lt;/ref&gt; and perhaps [[tuberculosis]], which was suggested by the evidence of [[Pott's disease]] discovered in Braine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Notman |first=Derek N.H. |last2=Anderson |first2=Lawrence |last3=Beattie |first3=Owen B. |last4=Amy |first4=Roger |last-author-amp=yes |title=Arctic Paleoradiology: Portable Radiographic Examination of Two Frozen Sailors from the Franklin Expedition (1845–48) |journal=American Journal of Roentgenology (AJR) |volume=149 |pages=347–350 |year=1987 |publisher=[[American Roentgen Ray Society]] |url=http://www.ajronline.org/doi/pdf/10.2214/ajr.149.2.347 |format=PDF |accessdate=14 February 2008 |issn=0361-803X |doi=10.2214/ajr.149.2.347 |pmid=3300222}}&lt;/ref&gt; Toxicological reports pointed to [[lead poisoning]] as a likely contributing factor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Kowall |first1=Walter |last2=Beattie |first2=Owen B. |last3=Baadsgaard |first3=Halfdan |last-author-amp=yes |title=Did Solder Kill Franklin's Men? |journal=Nature |volume=343 |issue=6256 |pages=319–320 |date=25 January 1990 |doi=10.1038/343319b0 |bibcode=1990Natur.343..319K}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Kowall |first1=W.A. |last2=Krahn |first2=P.M. |last3=Beattie |first3=O. B. |last-author-amp=yes |title=Lead Levels in Human Tissues from the Franklin Forensic Project |journal=International Journal Environmental Analytical Chemistry |volume=35 |issue=2 |pages=119–126 |date=29 June 1988 |publisher=[[Gordon and Breach]] Science Publishers |doi=10.1080/03067318908028385}}&lt;/ref&gt; Blade cut marks found on bones from some of the crew were seen as signs of cannibalism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Keenleyside&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Keenleyside |first=Anne |last2=Bertulli |first2=Margaret |last3=Fricke |first3=Henry C. |last-author-amp=yes |title=The Final Days of the Franklin Expedition: New Skeletal Evidence |journal=Arctic |volume=50 |issue=1 |pages=36–46 |year=1997 |publisher=[[The Arctic Institute of North America]] |url=http://pubs.aina.ucalgary.ca/arctic/Arctic50-1-36.pdf |format=PDF |accessdate=30 April 2010 |issn=0004-0843 |doi=10.14430/arctic1089}}&lt;/ref&gt; Evidence suggested that a combination of cold, starvation and disease including scurvy, pneumonia and tuberculosis, all made worse by lead poisoning, killed everyone in the Franklin party.{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|pp=161–63}}

==Other factors==
Franklin's chosen passage down the west side of King William Island took ''Erebus'' and ''Terror'' into &quot;a ploughing train of ice ... [that] does not always clear during the short summers&quot;,{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|p=42}} whereas the route along the island's east coast regularly clears in summer{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|p=42}} and was later used by [[Roald Amundsen]] in his successful navigation of the Northwest Passage. The Franklin expedition, locked in ice for two winters in [[Victoria Strait]], was naval, not well-equipped or trained for land travel. Some of the crew members heading south from ''Erebus'' and ''Terror'' hauled many items not needed for Arctic survival. McClintock noted a large quantity of heavy goods in the lifeboat at the &quot;boat place&quot; and thought them &quot;a mere accumulation of dead weight, of little use, and very likely to break down the strength of the sledge-crews&quot;.{{sfn|Beattie|Geiger|1987|pp=39–40}} In addition, cultural factors might have prevented the crew from seeking help as quickly as possible from the Inuit or adopting their survival techniques.{{Citation needed|date=September 2016}}

==Timeline==
* 1845, 19 May: Franklin expedition sails from England
* 1845, July: Expedition docks in [[Greenland]], sends home five men and a batch of letters
* 1845, 28 July: Last sighting of expedition by Europeans (a whaling ship in [[Baffin Bay]])
* 1845–46: Expedition winters on [[Beechey Island]]. Three crewmen die of [[tuberculosis]] and are buried.
* 1846: {{HMS|Erebus|1826|6}} and {{HMS|Terror|1813|6}} leave Beechey Island and sail down [[Peel Sound]] towards [[King William Island]]
* 1846, 12 September: Ships trapped in the ice off King William Island
* 1846–47: Expedition winters on King William Island
* 1847, 28 May: Date of first note, says &quot;All well&quot;
* 1847, 11 June: Franklin dies
* 1847–48: Expedition again winters off King William Island, after the ice fails to thaw in 1847
* 1848, 22 April: ''Erebus'' and ''Terror'' abandoned after one year and seven months trapped in the ice
* 1848, 25 April: Date of second note, saying 24&amp;nbsp;men have died and the survivors plan to start marching south on 26 April to the [[Back River]]
* 1850 (?): Inuit board an abandoned ship, which is icebound off King William Island
* 1850 (?): Inuit see 40&amp;nbsp;men walking south on King William Island
* 1851 (?): Inuit hunters see four men still trying to head south, last verified sighting of survivors (as reported to [[Charles Francis Hall|Charles Hall]])
* 1852–58 (?): Inuit may have seen Crozier and one other survivor much further south in the Baker Lake area
* 1854: John Rae interviews local Inuit, who give him items from the expedition and tell him the men starved to death, after resorting to cannibalism
* 1859: McClintock finds the abandoned boat and the messages on an admiralty form in a [[cairn]] on King William Island
* 2014, September: [[Ryan Harris (underwater archaeologist)|Ryan Harris]] announced the finding of an underwater wreck. Further investigation determined that it is HMS ''Erebus'' and the news was confirmed 1 October in the [[House of Commons of Canada|Canadian House of Commons]].&lt;ref name=cbc-2014oct01 /&gt;
* 2016: Announcement &lt;ref&gt;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/sep/12/hms-terror-wreck-found-arctic-nearly-170-years-northwest-passage-attempt&lt;/ref&gt; of finding the wreck of {{HMS|Terror|1813|6}}&lt;ref name=&quot;GuardianSep16&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Watson |first=Paul |title=&quot;Ship found in Arctic 168 years after doomed Northwest Passage attempt&quot; |url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/sep/12/hms-terror-wreck-found-arctic-nearly-170-years-northwest-passage-attempt |newspaper=The Guardian |access-date=12 September 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; on Sept 12.  Confirmed by Parks Canada on Sept 26&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/north/hms-terror-confirmed-1.3779127&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==

===Historical===
The most meaningful outcome of the Franklin expedition was the mapping of several thousand miles of hitherto unsurveyed coastline by expeditions searching for Franklin's lost ships and crew. As Richard Cyriax noted, &quot;the loss of the expedition probably added much more [geographical] knowledge than its successful return would have done&quot;.{{sfn|Cyriax|1939|p=198}} At the same time, it largely quelled the Admiralty's appetite for Arctic exploration. There was a gap of many years before the [[British Arctic Expedition|Nares expedition]] and when Nares declared there was &quot;no thoroughfare&quot; to the North Pole, his words marked the end of the Royal Navy's historical involvement in Arctic exploration, the end of an era in which such exploits were widely seen by the British public as worthy expenditures of human effort and monetary resources. As a writer for ''[[Athenaeum (British magazine)|The Athenaeum]]'' put it, &quot;We think that we can fairly make out the account between the cost and results of these Arctic Expeditions, and ask whether it is worth while to risk so much for that which is so difficult of attainment, and when attained, is so worthless.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal=[[Athenaeum (British magazine)|The Athenaeum]] |date=1 October 1859 |title=unknown |page=315 |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; The navigation of the Northwest Passage in 1903–05 by [[Roald Amundsen]] with the ''[[Gjøa]]'' expedition effectively ended the centuries-long quest for the Northwest Passage.

===Cultural legacy===
[[File:Franklin statue.jpg|thumb|right|150px|upright|Statue of John Franklin in his home town of [[Spilsby]], [[Lincolnshire]], England.]]
[[File:Francis Crozier monument in Banbridge, County Down, Ireland.JPG|thumb|upright|Statue of Francis Crozier in his home town of [[Banbridge]], County Down.]]
For years after the loss of the Franklin Party, the Victorian media portrayed Franklin as a hero who led his men in the quest for the Northwest Passage. A statue of Franklin in his home town bears the inscription &quot;Sir John Franklin – Discoverer of the North West Passage&quot;, and statues of Franklin outside the [[Athenaeum Club, London|Athenaeum]] in London and in [[Tasmania]] bear similar inscriptions. Although the expedition's fate, including the possibility of cannibalism, was widely reported and debated, Franklin's standing with the Victorian public was undiminished. The expedition has been the subject of numerous works of non-fiction, including two books by [[Ken McGoogan]], ''[[Fatal Passage]]'' and ''[[Lady Franklin's Revenge]]''.

The mystery surrounding Franklin's last expedition was the subject of a 2006 episode of the [[NOVA (TV series)|NOVA]] television series ''[[Arctic Passage]]''; a 2007 television documentary, &quot;Franklin's Lost Expedition&quot;, on ''Discovery HD Theatre''; as well as a 2008 Canadian documentary, ''[[Passage (2008 film)|Passage]]''. In an episode of the 2009 ITV1 travel documentary series ''[[Billy Connolly: Journey to the Edge of the World]]'', presenter Connolly and his crew visited Beechey Island, filmed the gravesite, and gave details of the Franklin expedition.

In memory of the lost expedition, one of Canada's [[Northwest Territories]] subdivisions was known as the [[District of Franklin]]. Including the high Arctic islands; this jurisdiction was abolished when the area was set off into the newly created Nunavut Territory on 1 April 1999.

On 29 October 2009, a special service of thanksgiving was held in the chapel at the [[Old Royal Naval College]] in Greenwich, to accompany the rededication of the national monument to Franklin there. The service also included the solemn re-interment of the remains of Lieutenant Henry Thomas Dundas Le Vesconte, the only remains ever repatriated to England, entombed within the monument in 1873.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Lewis-Jones |first=Huw |url=http://www.ric.edu/faculty/rpotter/temp/HLJ_Franklin_Monument.pdf |title=Nelsons of Discovery: Notes on the Franklin Monument in Greenwich |format=PDF |accessdate=19 May 2011 |date=&lt;!--undated--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following day, a group of polar authors went to London's [[Kensal Green Cemetery]] to pay their respects to the Arctic explorers buried there.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Russell |last=Potter |url=http://visionsnorth.blogspot.com/2010/07/thoughts-on-mcclure-and-hms.html |title=Online Blog at McClure's Memorial in London |publisher=Russell Potter (blog) |via=Visionsnorth.blogspot.com |date=30 July 2010 |accessdate=19 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many other veterans of the searches for Franklin are buried there too, including Admiral Sir [[Horatio Thomas Austin]], Admiral Sir George Back, Admiral Sir Edward Augustus Inglefield, Admiral [[Bedford Clapperton Trevelyan Pim]], and Admiral Sir John Ross. Franklin's wife [[Jane Griffin]], Lady Franklin, is also interred at Kensal Green in the vault, and commemorated on a marble cross dedicated to her niece Sophia Cracroft.

====Portrayal in fiction and the arts====
From the 1850s through to the present day, Franklin's last expedition inspired numerous literary works. Among the first was a play, ''[[The Frozen Deep]]'', written by [[Wilkie Collins]] with assistance and production by [[Charles Dickens]]. The play was performed for private audiences at [[Tavistock House]] early in 1857, as well as at the [[Royal Gallery of Illustration]] (including a command performance for [[Victoria of the United Kingdom|Queen Victoria]]), and for the public at the Manchester Trade Union Hall. News of Franklin's death in 1859 inspired elegies, including one by [[Algernon Charles Swinburne]].

[[File:'The English at the Noth Pole' by Riou and Montaut 002.jpg|thumb|150px|left|Illustration by [[Édouard Riou]] for the title page of [[Jules Verne]]'s ''Voyages et aventures du capitaine Hatteras'' (''[[Journeys and Adventures of Captain Hatteras]]'')]]

Fictional treatments of the final Franklin expedition begin with [[Jules Verne]]'s ''[[Journeys and Adventures of Captain Hatteras]]'', (1866), in which the novel's hero seeks to retrace Franklin's footsteps and discovers that the [[North Pole]] is dominated by an enormous volcano. [[Mark Twain]] briefly satirized the fate of the expedition and its subsequent searches in the beginning of the story &quot;Some Learned Fables for Good Old Boys and Girls&quot; (1875).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.readbookonline.net/readOnLine/1545/ Full text]&lt;/ref&gt; The German novelist [[Sten Nadolny]]'s ''[[The Discovery of Slowness]]'' (1983; English translation 1987) takes on the entirety of Franklin's life, touching only briefly on his last expedition. Other recent novelistic treatments of Franklin include [[Mordecai Richler]]'s ''[[Solomon Gursky Was Here]]'' (1989), [[William T. Vollmann]]'s ''[[The Rifles (novel)|The Rifles]]'' (1994), John Wilson's ''North With Franklin: The Journals of James Fitzjames'' (1999); and [[Dan Simmons]]'s ''[[The Terror (novel)|The Terror]]'' (2007) - the latter of which is being developed as an [[AMC (TV channel)|AMC]] television series, announced in February 2013. The expedition has also been the subject of a horror role-playing game supplement, ''The Walker in the Wastes''. Most recently, [[Clive Cussler]]'s 2008 novel ''[[Arctic Drift]]'' incorporates the ordeal of the Franklin expedition as a central element in the story, and [[Richard Flanagan]]'s ''[[Wanting (novel)|Wanting]]'' (2009) deals with Franklin's deeds in both Tasmania and the Arctic. 2013’s novel ''The White Passage'' rounds out the list with a vaguely science-fiction take on the concepts of time-travel and the consequences of an alternate fate of the lost expedition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Alvarado |first=Kassandra |title=The White Passage |year=2013 |publisher=Smashwords |isbn=9781301113293 |url=http://www.barnesandnoble.com/w/the-white-passage-kassandra-alvarado/1115446649?ean=2940044544420 |accessdate=13 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 12 January 2012, [[BBC Radio 4]] broadcast a radio play entitled &quot;Erebus&quot; based on the Franklin expedition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b0196td4 |title=Erebus |work=BBC |accessdate=10 September 2014 |date=12 January 2012 |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Franklin's last expedition also inspired a great deal of music, beginning with the ballad &quot;[[Lady Franklin's Lament]]&quot; (also known as &quot;Lord Franklin&quot;), which originated in the 1850s and has been recorded by dozens of artists, among them [[Martin Carthy]], [[Pentangle (band)|Pentangle]], [[Sinéad O'Connor]], the [[Pearlfishers]], and John Walsh. Other Franklin-inspired songs include [[Fairport Convention]]'s &quot;I'm Already There&quot;, and [[James Taylor]]'s &quot;Frozen Man&quot; (based on Beattie's photographs of John Torrington).

The influence of the Franklin expedition on [[Canadian literature]] has been especially significant. Among the best-known contemporary Franklin ballads is &quot;[[Northwest Passage (song)|Northwest Passage]]&quot; by the late Ontario folksinger [[Stan Rogers]] (1981), which has been referred to as the unofficial Canadian national anthem.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopaedia |last=Gudgeon |first=Chris |title=Rogers, Stan |encyclopaedia=The Canadian Encyclopedia |publisher=Historica Foundation of Canada |year=2008 |url=http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/index.cfm?PgNm=TCE&amp;Params=A1ARTA0006907 |accessdate=2 March 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The distinguished Canadian novelist [[Margaret Atwood]] has also spoken of Franklin's expedition as a sort of national myth of Canada, remarking that &quot;In every culture many stories are told, (but) only some are told and retold, and these stories bear examining ... in Canadian literature, one such story is the Franklin expedition.&quot;{{sfn|Atwood|1995|p=11}} Other recent treatments by Canadian poets include a verse play, ''Terror and Erebus'', by [[Gwendolyn MacEwen]] that was broadcast on [[Canadian Broadcasting Corporation]] (CBC) radio in the 1960s, as well as [[David Solway]]'s verse cycle, ''Franklin's Passage'' (2003). [[Dominique Fortier]]'s 2008 French language novel, ''Du bon usage des étoiles'', creatively considers the Franklin expedition from a variety of perspectives and genres&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.editionsalto.com/depots/Fiche-Usage.pdf Fiche] (pdf, 3 p., french) for teachers)&lt;/ref&gt; and was both shortlisted and a finalist for several literary awards in Canada ([[2009 Governor General's Awards#French|2009 Governor General's Awards]]).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.editionsalto.com/fiche.php?no_livre=582 www.editionsalto.com].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sheila Fischman]]'s English translation of the novel, ''On the Proper Use of Stars'', was also shortlisted for the [[2010 Governor General's Awards#French|2010 Governor General's Awards]] for French to English Translation.

[[File:Manproposesgoddisposes.jpg|thumb|''[[Man Proposes, God Disposes]]'' by [[Edwin Henry Landseer]], 1864]]
In the visual arts, the loss of Franklin's expedition inspired a number of paintings in both the United States and Britain. In 1861, [[Frederic Edwin Church]] unveiled his great canvas ''[[The Icebergs]]''; later that year, prior to taking it to England for exhibition, he added an image of a broken ship's mast in silent tribute to Franklin. In 1864, [[Edwin Henry Landseer|Sir Edwin Landseer]]'s ''[[Man Proposes, God Disposes]]'' caused a stir at the annual Royal Academy exhibition; its depiction of two polar bears, one chewing on a tattered ship's ensign, the other gnawing on a human ribcage, was seen at the time as in poor taste, but has remained one of the most powerful imaginings of the expedition's final fate. The expedition also inspired numerous popular engravings and illustrations, along with many panoramas, [[diorama]]s, and [[magic lantern]] shows.{{sfn|Potter|2007}}

==References==

===Notes===
{{Reflist|20em}}

===Works cited===
{{refbegin|30em}}
* {{cite book |last=Atwood |first=Margaret |authorlink=Margaret Atwood |year=1995 |chapter=Concerning Franklin and His Gallant Crew |title=Strange Things: The Malevolent North in Canadian Literature |location=Oxford |publisher=[[Clarendon Press]] |isbn=0-19-811976-3 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last1=Beattie |first1=Owen |last2=Geiger |first2=John |authorlink1=Owen Beattie |authorlink2=John Geiger |last-author-amp=yes |year=1987 |title=Frozen in Time: Unlocking the Secrets of the Franklin Expedition |location=Saskatoon |publisher=Western Producer Prairie Books |isbn=0-88833-303-X |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Cookman |first=Scott |year=2000 |title=Iceblink: The Tragic Fate of Sir John Franklin's Lost Polar Expedition |location=New York |publisher=[[John Wiley &amp; Sons]] |isbn=0-471-37790-2 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Cyriax |first=Richard |year=1939 |title=Sir John Franklin's Last Arctic Expedition; a Chapter in the History of the Royal Navy |location=London |publisher=[[Methuen &amp; Co]] |oclc=9183074 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=eGbmWr2AFQMC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;ots=yOY4xAFRSm&amp;dq=Oddities%20--%20A%20Book%20of%20Unexplained%20Facts&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=Oddities a Book of Unexplained Facts |year=1928 |last=Gould |first=Rupert |authorlink=Rupert Thomas Gould |location=London |publisher=P. Allan &amp; Co. |accessdate=19 May 2011 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last1=Klutschak |first1=Heinrich |last2=Barr |first2=William |last-author-amp=yes |year=1989 |title=Overland to Starvation Cove |location=Toronto |publisher=[[University of Toronto Press]] |isbn=0-8020-5762-4 |ref=harv}}
*  {{cite book |title=Ordeal by Ice; the Search for the Northwest Passage |last=Mowat |first=Farley |year=1973 |publisher=McClelland and Stewart Ltd |location=Toronto |chapter=The Fate of Franklin |oclc=1391959 |page=285 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book |authorlink=Russell Potter |last=Potter |first=Russell |year=2007 |title=Arctic Spectacles: The Frozen North in Visual Culture |location=Seattle |publisher=[[University of Washington Press]] ISBN 978-0-295-98680-7 |ref={{sfnRef|Potter|2007}}}}
* {{cite book |last=Sandler |first=Martin |year=2006 |title=Resolute: The Epic Search for the Northwest Passage and John Franklin, and the Discovery of the Queen's Ghost Ship |location=New York |publisher=[[Sterling Publishing Co.]] |isbn=978-1-4027-4085-5 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Savours |first=Ann |year=1999 |title=The Search for the North West Passage |location=New York |publisher=[[St. Martin's Press]] |isbn=0-312-22372-2 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Schwatka |first=Frederick |authorlink=Frederick Schwatka |year=1965 |title=The Long Arctic Search; the Narrative of Lieutenant Frederick Schwatka, U.S.A., 1878–1880, Seeking the Records of the Lost Franklin Expedition |editor=[[Edouard A. Stackpole]] |location=New Bedford, Massachusetts |publisher=Reynolds-DeWalt |oclc=1012693 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Woodman |first=David C. |year=1995 |title=Strangers Among Us |location=Montreal |publisher=[[McGill-Queen's University Press]] |isbn=0-7735-1348-5 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Woodman |first=David C. |year=1992 |title=Unravelling the Franklin Mystery: Inuit Testimony |location=Montreal |publisher=McGill-Queen's University Press |isbn=0-7735-0936-4 |ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

===Further reading===
{{refbegin|30em}}
* {{cite journal |title=Franklin Saga Deaths: A Mystery Solved? |date=1990 |magazine=[[National Geographic Magazine]] |volume=178 |number=3 |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt;}}
* {{cite book |last=Beardsley |first=Martin |year=2002 |title=Deadly Winter: The Life of Sir John Franklin |location=London |publisher=Chatham Publishing |isbn=1-86176-187-2 }}
* {{cite book |authorlink=Pierre Berton |last=Berton |first=Pierre |year=1988 |title=The Arctic Grail: The Quest for the Northwest Passage and The North Pole, 1818–1909 |location=Toronto |publisher=[[McClelland &amp; Stewart]] |isbn=0-7710-1266-7}}
* {{cite book |last=Brandt |first=Anthony |year=2010 |title=The Man Who Ate His Boots: The Tragic History of the Search for the Northwest Passage |isbn=978-0-307-26392-6}}
* {{cite book |authorlink=John Brown (geographer) |first=John, F.R.G.S. |last=Brown |year=1860 |title=The North-West Passage and the Plans for the Search for Sir John Franklin: A Review with maps, &amp;c., Second Edition with a Sequel Including the Voyage of the Fox |location=London |publisher=[[Edward Stanford]]}}
* {{cite book |last=Coleman |first=E. C. |year=2006 |title=History of the Royal Navy and Polar Exploration: From Franklin to Scott: Vol. 2 |publisher=[[Tempus Publishing]] |isbn=978-0-7524-4207-5}}
* {{cite book |last=Davis-Fisch |first=Heather |year=2012 |title=Loss and Cultural Remains in Performance: The Ghosts of the Franklin Expedition |location=Toronto |publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]] |isbn=0-23034-032-6}}
* {{cite book |last=Edinger |first=Ray |year=2015 |title=Love and Ice: The Tragic Obsessions of Dr. Elisha Kent Kane, Arctic Explorer |location=Savannah |publisher=Frederic C. Beil |isbn=978-1-929490-42-4}}
* {{cite book |authorlink=Francis Leopold McClintock |last=M'Clintock |first=Francis L. |year=1860 |title=The Voyage of the Fox in the Arctic Seas: A Narrative of the Discovery of the Fate of Sir John Franklin and His Companions |location=Boston |publisher=[[Ticknor and Fields]]}}
* {{cite book |authorlink=Andrew Lambert |last=Lambert |first=Andrew |year=2010 |title=Franklin: Tragic Hero of Polar Exploration |location=London |publisher=[[Faber and Faber]] |isbn=978-0-571-23161-4}}
* {{cite book |last=Mirsky |first=Jeannette |year=1970 |title=To the Arctic!: The Story of Northern Exploration from Earliest Times |isbn=0-226-53179-1}}
* {{cite book |authorlink=Ken McGoogan |last=McGoogan |first=Ken |year=2002 |title=Fatal Passage: The True Story of John Rae, the Arctic Hero Time Forgot |location=New York |publisher=[[Carroll &amp; Graf Publishers]] |isbn=0-7867-0993-6}}
* {{cite book |last=McGoogan |first=Ken |year=2005 |title=Lady Franklin's Revenge: A True Story of Ambition, Obsession and the Remaking of Arctic History |location=Toronto |publisher=[[HarperCollins]] |isbn=978-0-00-200671-2}}
* {{cite book |last=Murphy |first=David |year=2004 |title=The Arctic Fox: Francis Leopold McClintock |location=Toronto |publisher=[[Dundurn Press]] |isbn=1-55002-523-6}}
* {{cite book |last1=Poulsom |first1=Neville W. |last2=Myers |first2=J. A. L. |last-author-amp=yes |year=2000 |title=British Polar Exploration and Research; a Historical and Medallic Record with Biographies 1818–1999 |location=London |publisher=Savannah |isbn=978-1-902366-05-0}}
* {{cite book |last=Simmons |first=Dan |authorlink=Dan Simmons |year=2007 |title=The Terror |location=Armonk, New York |publisher=[[Little, Brown and Company]] |isbn=0-316-01744-2}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|John Franklin's lost expedition}}
* [http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/arctic/ Arctic Passage], NOVA's companion website for ''[[Arctic Passage]]''
* [http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/author/5108 Books by John Franklin] Gutenberg Project &lt;!-- Accessed 10/31/2012 --&gt;
* [http://www.ric.edu/faculty/rpotter/woodman/mainpage.html Expedition reports for Woodman-involved efforts], Russell Potter
* [http://www.ric.edu/rpotter/SJFranklin.html Fate of Franklin], Russell Potter &lt;!-- Accessed 10/31/2012 --&gt;
* [http://www.biographi.ca/EN/ShowBio.asp?BioId=37516 Franklin biography], ''[[Dictionary of Canadian Biography]] Online'' &lt;!-- Accessed 10/31/2012 --&gt;
* [http://collections.rmg.co.uk/collections.html#!csearch;searchTerm=john_franklin Franklin collection], Royal Museums Greenwich &lt;!-- Accessed 10/31/2012 --&gt;
* [https://secure.flickr.com/photos/nationalmaritimemuseum/tags/franklinexpedition/ Franklin Expedition], National Maritime Museum images on Flickr
* [http://blogs.abc.net.au/tasmania/2012/07/the-life-and-times-of-sir-john-franklin.html Life and Times of Sir John Franklin] (audio file from 936 ABC Hobart) &lt;!-- Accessed 10/31/2012 --&gt;
* {{cite web|url=http://www.llanellich.org.uk/files/36-llanellis-lost-arctic-explorer|title=Llanelli’s Lost Arctic Explorer|publisher=Llanelli Community Heritage|accessdate=2015-05-17}}
* {{cite web|url=http://www.cbc.ca/news2/canada/features/franklin/|title=Searching for Franklin|publisher=Canadian Broadcasting Corporation|accessdate=2015-05-17}}
* {{Skeptoid | id=4482 | number=482 | title=Sir Franklin's Cannibals}}
{{Royal Navy Arctic exploration}}
{{Polar exploration|state=collapsed}}

{{Good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Franklins Northwest Passage Expedition}}
[[Category:1840s]]
[[Category:1845 in Canada]]
[[Category:1845 in the British Empire]]
[[Category:Arctic expeditions]]
[[Category:Expeditions from the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Exploration of the Arctic]]
[[Category:Geography of Canada]]
[[Category:History of Nunavut]]
[[Category:History of the Northwest Territories]]
[[Category:Incidents of cannibalism]]
[[Category:Maritime history of Canada]]
[[Category:19th century in the Arctic]]</text>
      <sha1>kb6nhee4xsr60s0lnw0mthqsv7kp0sl</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
