<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>French cuisine</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>11002</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750610121</id>
      <parentid>750606818</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-20T20:40:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sapphorain</username>
        <id>12923157</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 750606818 by [[Special:Contributions/68.196.122.169|68.196.122.169]] ([[User talk:68.196.122.169|talk]])If at least it were funny...</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="72024">{{About||the 2015 film|French Cuisine (film)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2011}}

[[File:Jacques Lameloise, escabèche d'écrevisses sur gaspacho d'asperge et cresson.jpg|thumb|A [[nouvelle cuisine]] presentation]]
[[File:Cuisine Trois étoiles.jpg|thumb|French [[haute cuisine]] presentation]]
[[File:French taste of wines.JPG|thumb|[[French wine]]s are usually made to accompany French cuisine]]

'''French cuisine''' consists of the [[cooking]] traditions and practices from [[France]].

In the 14th century [[Guillaume Tirel]], a [[Court (royal)|court]] [[chef]] known as &quot;Taillevent&quot;, wrote ''[[Le Viandier]]'', one of the earliest [[recipe]] collections of [[France in the Middle Ages|medieval France]]. During that time, French cuisine was heavily influenced by [[Italian cuisine]]. In the 17th century, chefs [[François Pierre La Varenne]] and [[Marie-Antoine Carême]] spearheaded movements that shifted French cooking away from its foreign influences and developed France's own indigenous style. [[French cheese|Cheese]] and [[French wine|wine]] are a major part of the cuisine. They play different roles regionally and nationally, with many variations and ''[[appellation d'origine contrôlée]]'' (AOC) (regulated appellation) laws.

French cuisine was codified in the 20th century by [[Auguste Escoffier]] to become the modern [[haute cuisine]]; Escoffier, however, left out much of the local culinary character to be found in the [[regions of France]] and was considered difficult to execute by home cooks. Gastro-tourism and the ''[[Guide Michelin]]'' helped to acquaint people with the rich [[bourgeois]] and peasant cuisine of the French countryside starting in the 20th century. [[Gascony|Gascon]] cuisine has also had great influence over the cuisine in the southwest of France. Many dishes that were once regional have proliferated in variations across the country.

Knowledge of French cooking has contributed significantly to Western cuisines. Its criteria are used widely in Western cookery school boards and [[culinary art|culinary education]]. In November 2010, French gastronomy was added by the [[UNESCO]] to its lists of the world's [[UNESCO Intangible Cultural Heritage Lists|&quot;intangible cultural heritage&quot;]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dallasnews.com/sharedcontent/dws/news/world/stories/DN-culture_17int.ART.State.Edition1.b21e71.html Bon appétit: Your meal is certified by the UN] Dallas Morning News&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=UNESCO |url=http://www.unesco.org/new/en/media-services/single-view/news/celebrations_healing_techniques_crafts_and_culinary_arts_added_to_the_representative_list_of_the_intangible_cultural_heritage/ |title=Celebrations, healing techniques, crafts and culinary arts added to the Representative List of the Intangible Cultural Heritage |publisher=UNESCO |date=2010-11-16 |accessdate=2012-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==

===Middle Ages===
[[File:Les Très Riches Heures du duc de Berry Janvier.jpg|thumb|left|[[John, Duke of Berry]] enjoying a grand meal. The Duke is sitting with a [[Cardinal (Catholicism)|cardinal]] at the high table, under a luxurious [[baldachin|baldaquin]], in front of the fireplace, tended to by several servants, including a [[meat carving|carver]]. On the table to the left of the Duke is a golden [[salt cellar]], or ''nef'', in the shape of a ship; illustration from ''[[Très Riches Heures du Duc de Berry]]'', circa 1410.]]

In French [[medieval cuisine]], banquets were common among the [[aristocracy]]. Multiple courses would be prepared, but served in a style called ''service en confusion'', or all at once. Food was generally eaten by hand, meats being sliced off in large pieces held between the thumb and two fingers. The sauces were highly seasoned and thick, and heavily flavored mustards were used. Pies were a common banquet item, with the crust serving primarily as a container, rather than as food itself, and it was not until the very end of the [[Late Middle Ages]] that the [[shortcrust pastry|shortcrust]] pie was developed. Meals often ended with an ''issue de table'', which later changed into the modern dessert, and typically consisted of ''[[dragée]]s'' (in the Middle Ages, meaning spiced lumps of hardened sugar or honey), aged cheese and spiced wine, such as [[hypocras]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheaton&quot;&gt;{{Cite book  | last = Wheaton | first = Barbara Ketcham | title = Savoring the Past: The French Kitchen and Table from 1300 to 1789 | publisher=First Touchstone | year = 1996 | location = New York | isbn = 978-0-684-81857-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|1–7}}

The ingredients of the time varied greatly according to the seasons and the church calendar, and many items were preserved with salt, spices, honey, and other preservatives. Late spring, summer, and autumn afforded abundance, while winter meals were more sparse. Livestock were slaughtered at the beginning of winter. Beef was often salted, while pork was salted and smoked. Bacon and sausages would be smoked in the chimney, while the tongue and hams were [[brine]]d and dried.  Cucumbers were brined as well, while greens would be packed in jars with salt. Fruits, nuts and root vegetables would be boiled in honey for preservation. Whale, dolphin and porpoise were considered fish, so during [[Lent]], the salted meats of these sea mammals were eaten.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheaton&quot; /&gt;{{rp|9–12}}

Artificial freshwater ponds (often called ''stews'') held [[carp]], [[pike (fish)|pike]], [[tench]], [[bream]], [[Eel (food)|eel]], and other fish. Poultry was kept in special yards, with pigeon and [[Squab (food)|squab]] being reserved for the elite. Game was highly prized, but very rare, and included [[venison]], [[wild boar]], hare, rabbit, and birds. Kitchen gardens provided herbs, including some, such as [[tansy]], [[rue]], [[Mentha pulegium|pennyroyal]], and [[hyssop]], which are rarely used today. Spices were treasured and very expensive at that time – they included pepper, cinnamon, cloves, nutmeg, and [[mace (spice)|mace]]. Some spices used then, but no longer today in French cuisine are [[cubeb]]s, long pepper (both from vines similar to black pepper), [[grains of paradise]], and [[galangal|galengale]]. Sweet-sour flavors were commonly added to dishes with vinegars and ''[[verjus]]'' combined with sugar (for the affluent) or honey. A common form of food preparation was to finely cook, pound and strain mixtures into fine pastes and mushes, something believed to be beneficial to make use of nutrients.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheaton&quot; /&gt;{{rp|13–15}}

Visual display was prized. Brilliant colors were obtained by the addition of, for example, juices from spinach and the green part of [[leek]]s. Yellow came from [[saffron]] or egg yolk, while red came from [[sunflower]], and purple came from ''[[Crozophora tinctoria]]'' or ''[[Heliotropium europaeum]]''. Gold and [[Metal leaf|silver leaf]] were placed on food surfaces and brushed with egg whites. Elaborate and showy dishes were the result, such as ''tourte parmerienne'' which was a pastry dish made to look like a castle with chicken-drumstick turrets coated with [[gold leaf]]. One of the grandest showpieces of the time was roast [[swan]] or [[peafowl|peacock]] sewn back into its skin with feathers intact, the feet and beak being [[gilded]]. Since both birds are stringy, and taste unpleasant, the skin and feathers could be kept and filled with the cooked, minced and seasoned flesh of tastier birds, like goose or chicken.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheaton&quot; /&gt;{{rp|15–16}}

The most well known French chef of the Middle Ages was [[Guillaume Tirel]], also known as Taillevent. Taillevent worked in numerous royal kitchens during the 14th century. His first position was as a kitchen boy in 1326. He was chef to [[Philip VI of France|Philip VI]], then the [[Dauphin of France|Dauphin]] who was son of [[John II of France|John II]]. The Dauphin became King [[Charles V of France]] in 1364, with Taillevent as his chief cook. His career spanned sixty-six years, and upon his death he was buried in grand style between his two wives. His tombstone represents him in armor, holding a shield with three cooking pots, ''marmites'', on it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheaton&quot; /&gt;{{rp|18–21}}

===Ancien Régime===

Under the ''[[ancien régime]]'', Paris was the central hub of culture and economic activity, and as such, the most highly skilled culinary craftsmen were to be found there. Markets in Paris such as ''[[Les Halles]]'', ''la Mégisserie'', those found along ''[[Rue Mouffetard]]'', and similar smaller versions in other cities were very important to the distribution of food. Those that gave French produce its characteristic identity were regulated by the [[guild]] system, which developed in the [[Middle Ages]]. In Paris, the guilds were regulated by city government as well as by the French crown. A guild restricted those in a given branch of the culinary industry to operate only within that field.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheaton&quot; /&gt;{{rp|71–72}}

There were two basic groups of guilds – first, those that supplied the raw materials; butchers, fishmongers, grain merchants, and gardeners. The second group were those that supplied prepared foods; bakers, [[pastry chef|pastry cook]]s, saucemakers, poulterers, and [[caterer]]s. There were also guilds that offered both raw materials and prepared food, such as the ''[[charcuterie|charcutiers]]'' and ''rôtisseurs'' (purveyors of roasted meat dishes). They would supply cooked meat pies and dishes as well as raw meat and poultry. This caused issues with butchers and poulterers, who sold the same raw materials.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheaton&quot; /&gt;{{rp|72–73}}  The guilds served as a training ground for those within the industry. The degrees of assistant-cook, full-fledged cook and master chef were conferred. Those who reached the level of master chef were of considerable rank in their individual industry, and enjoyed a high level of income as well as economic and job security. At times, those in the royal kitchens did fall under the [[guild]] hierarchy, but it was necessary to find them a parallel appointment based on their skills after leaving the service of the royal kitchens. This was not uncommon as the Paris cooks' guild regulations allowed for this movement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheaton&quot; /&gt;{{rp|73}}

During the 16th and 17th centuries, French cuisine assimilated many new food items from the [[New World]]. Although they were slow to be adopted, records of banquets show [[Catherine de' Medici]] (1519–1589?) serving sixty-six turkeys at one dinner.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheaton&quot; /&gt;{{rp|81}}  The dish called [[cassoulet]] has its roots in the New World discovery of [[haricot bean]]s, which are central to the dish's creation, but had not existed outside of the New World until its exploration by [[Christopher Columbus]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheaton&quot; /&gt;{{rp|85}}

[[Haute cuisine]] ({{IPA-fr|ot kɥizin|pron}}, &quot;high cuisine&quot;) has foundations during the 17th century with a chef named [[François Pierre La Varenne|La Varenne]]. As author of works such as ''Le Cuisinier françois'', he is credited with publishing the first true French cookbook. His book includes the earliest known reference to [[roux]] using pork fat. The book contained two sections, one for meat days, and one for [[fasting]]. His recipes marked a change from the style of cookery known in the Middle Ages, to new techniques aimed at creating somewhat lighter dishes, and more modest presentations of pies as individual pastries and turnovers. La Varenne also published a book on pastry in 1667 entitled ''Le Parfait confitvrier'' (republished as ''Le Confiturier françois'') which similarly updated and codified the emerging haute cuisine standards for desserts and pastries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheaton&quot; /&gt;{{rp|114–120}}

Chef [[François Massialot]] wrote ''Le Cuisinier roïal et bourgeois'' in 1691, during the reign of [[Louis XIV]]. The book contains menus served to the royal courts in 1690. Massialot worked mostly as a freelance cook, and was not employed by any particular household. Massialot and many other royal cooks received special privileges by association with the French royalty. They were not subject to the regulation of the guilds; therefore, they could cater weddings and banquets without restriction. His book is the first to list recipes alphabetically, perhaps a forerunner of the first culinary dictionary. It is in this book that a [[marinade]] is first seen in print, with one type for poultry and feathered game, while a second is for fish and shellfish. No quantities are listed in the recipes, which suggests that Massialot was writing for trained cooks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheaton&quot; /&gt;{{rp|149–154}}

The successive updates of ''Le Cuisinier roïal et bourgeois'' include important refinements such as adding a glass of wine to [[stock (food)|fish stock]]. Definitions were also added to the 1703 edition. The 1712 edition, retitled ''Le Nouveau cuisinier royal et bourgeois'', was increased to two volumes, and was written in a more elaborate style with extensive explanations of technique. Additional smaller preparations are included in this edition as well, leading to lighter preparations, and adding a third course to the meal. [[Ragout]], a stew still central to French cookery, makes its first appearance as a single dish in this edition as well; prior to that, it was listed as a garnish.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheaton&quot; /&gt;{{rp|155}}

===Late 18th century –  early 19th century===
{{copy edit|date=November 2016}}
[[File:Louis XV by Maurice-Quentin de La Tour.jpg|thumb|The wife of Louis XV of France, Queen Marie Leszczyńska influenced French cuisine]]
[[File:M-A-Careme.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Marie-Antoine Carême]]]]
Shortly before the French Revolution recipes like ''les bouchées la Reine'' gained importance. This was essentially royal kitchen run by the royal service mouth. As the name suggests it is a chicken-based recipe served on vol-au-vent performed under the influence of Queen [[Marie Leszczyńska]], the wife of [[Louis XV]]. This recipe is still popular today, as are other recipes from Queen Marie Leszczyńska like ''le consommé la Reine'' and ''le filet d'aloyau braisé à la royale''. Queen Marie is also the source of appearance of the lenses in the diet. 

The [[French Revolution]] was integral to the expansion of French cuisine, because it effectively abolished guilds. This meant any one chef could now produce and sell any culinary item he wished. [[Marie-Antoine Carême]] was born in 1784, five years before the onset of the [[French Revolution|Revolution]]. He spent his younger years working at a ''[[Pastry|pâtisserie]]'' until being discovered by [[Charles Maurice de Talleyrand-Périgord]], who would later cook for the French emperor [[Napoleon Bonaparte]]. Prior to his employment with Talleyrand, Carême had become known for his ''pièces montées'', which were extravagant constructions of pastry and sugar architecture.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mennell&quot;&gt;{{Cite book | last = Mennell | first = Stephen | title = All Manners of Food: eating and taste in England and France from the Middle Ages to the present, 2nd ed. | publisher=University of Illinois Press | year = 1996 | location = Chicago | isbn = 978-0-252-06490-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|144–145}}

More important to Carême's career was his contribution to the refinement of French cuisine. The basis for his style of cooking came from his sauces, which he named [[mother sauce]]s. Often referred to as [[fond]], meaning &quot;foundations&quot;, these base sauces, ''[[espagnole]]'', ''[[velouté]]'', and ''[[béchamel]]'', are still known today. Each of these sauces would be made in large quantities in his kitchen, as they were then capable of forming the basis of multiple derivatives. Carême had over one hundred sauces in his repertoire. In his writings, soufflés appear for the first time. Although many of his preparations today seem extravagant, he simplified and codified an even more complex cuisine that had existed beforehand. Central to his codification of the cuisine were ''Le Maître d'hôtel français'' (1822), ''Le Cuisinier parisien'' (1828) and ''L'Art de la cuisine française au dix-neuvième siècle'' (1833–5).&lt;ref name=&quot;Mennell&quot; /&gt;{{rp|144–148}}

===Late 19th century – early 20th century===
[[File:Auguste Escoffier 01.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Georges Auguste Escoffier]]]]
[[Georges Auguste Escoffier]] is commonly acknowledged as the central figure to the modernization of [[haute cuisine]] and organizing what would become the national cuisine of France. His influence began with the rise of some of the great hotels in Europe and America during the 1880s – 1890s. The [[Savoy Hotel]] managed by [[César Ritz]] was an early hotel in which Escoffier worked, but much of his influence came during his management of the kitchens in the Carlton from 1898 until 1921. He created a system of &quot;parties&quot; called the [[brigade system]], which separated the professional kitchen into five separate stations.

These five stations included the &quot;[[garde manger]]&quot; that prepared cold dishes; the &quot;entremettier&quot; prepared starches and vegetables, the &quot;rôtisseur&quot; prepared roasts, grilled and fried dishes; the &quot;[[saucier]]&quot; prepared sauces and soups; and the &quot;pâtissier&quot; prepared all pastry and desserts items. This system meant that instead of one person preparing a dish on one's own, now multiple cooks would prepare the different components for the dish. An example used is &quot;oeufs au plat Meyerbeer&quot;, the prior system would take up to fifteen minutes to prepare the dish, while in the new system, the eggs would be prepared by the entremettier, kidney grilled by the rôtisseur, truffle sauce made by the saucier and thus the dish could be prepared in a shorter time and served quickly in the popular restaurants.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mennell&quot; /&gt;{{rp|157–159}}

Escoffier also simplified and organized the modern menu and structure of the meal. He published a series of articles in professional journals which outlined the sequence, and then he finally published his ''Livre des menus'' in 1912. This type of service embraced the [[service à la russe]] (serving meals in separate courses on individual plates), which Félix Urbain Dubois had made popular in the 1860s. Escoffier's largest contribution was the publication of ''[[Le Guide Culinaire]]'' in 1903, which established the fundamentals of French cookery. The book was a collaboration with Philéas Gilbert, E. Fetu, A. Suzanne, B. Reboul, Ch. Dietrich, A. Caillat and others. The significance of this is to illustrate the universal acceptance by multiple high-profile chefs to this new style of cooking.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mennell&quot; /&gt;{{rp|159–160}}

''Le Guide Culinaire'' deemphasized the use of heavy sauces and leaned toward lighter [[White stock|fumet]]s, which are the essence of flavor taken from fish, meat and vegetables. This style of cooking looked to create garnishes and sauces whose function is to add to the flavor of the dish, rather than mask flavors like the heavy sauces and ornate garnishes of the past. Escoffier took inspiration for his work from personal recipes in addition to recipes from Carême, Dubois and ideas from Taillevent's ''Viander'', which had a modern version published in 1897. A second source for recipes came from existing peasant dishes that were translated into the refined techniques of haute cuisine.

Expensive ingredients would replace the common ingredients, making the dishes much less humble. The third source of recipes was Escoffier himself, who invented many new dishes, such as [[pêche Melba]] and [[crêpes Suzette]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Mennell&quot; /&gt;{{rp|160–162}}  Escoffier updated ''Le Guide Culinaire'' four times during his lifetime, noting in the foreword to the book's first edition that even with its 5,000 recipes, the book should not be considered an &quot;exhaustive&quot; text, and that even if it were at the point when he wrote the book, &quot;it would no longer be so tomorrow, because progress marches on each day.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last = Escoffier | first = Georges Auguste | title = Escoffier: The Complete Guide to the Art of Modern Cookery | publisher=John Wiley and Sons | year = 2002 | location = New York | pages = Foreword | isbn = 978-0-471-29016-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mid-20th century – late 20th century===
[[File:Paul Bocuse.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Paul Bocuse]]]]
The 1960s brought about innovative thought to the French cuisine, especially because of the contribution of Portuguese immigrants who had come to the country fleeing the forced drafting to the Colonial Wars Portugal was fighting in Africa. Many new dishes were introduced, as well as techniques. This period is also marked by the appearance of the &quot;Nouvelle Cuisine.&quot;

The term [[nouvelle cuisine]] has been used many times in the history of French cuisine which emphasized the freshness, lightness and clarity of flavor and inspired by new movements in world cuisine. In the 1740s, [[Menon (cookbook author)|Menon]] first used the term, but the cooking of [[Vincent La Chapelle]] and François Marin was also considered modern. In the 1960s, [[Henri Gault]] and [[Christian Millau]] revived it to describe the cooking of [[Paul Bocuse]], [[Jean Troisgros|Jean]] and [[Pierre Troisgros]], [[Michel Guérard]], Roger Vergé and [[Raymond Oliver]].&lt;ref&gt;''Joyeuse encyclopédie anecdotique de la gastronomie'', [[Michel Ferracci-Porri]] and Maryline Paoli, Preface by Chistian Millau, Ed. Normant 2012, France ISBN 978-2-915685-55-8&lt;/ref&gt; These chefs were working toward rebelling against the &quot;orthodoxy&quot; of [[Escoffier]]'s cuisine. Some of the chefs were students of [[Fernand Point]] at the ''[[La Pyramide|Pyramide]]'' in [[Vienne]], and had left to open their own restaurants. Gault and Millau &quot;discovered the formula&quot; contained in ten characteristics of this new style of cooking.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mennell&quot; /&gt;{{rp|163–164}}

The first characteristic was a rejection of excessive complication in cooking. Second, the cooking times for most fish, seafood, game birds, veal, green vegetables and pâtés was greatly reduced in an attempt to preserve the natural flavors. Steaming was an important trend from this characteristic. The third characteristic was that the cuisine was made with the freshest possible ingredients. Fourth, large menus were abandoned in favor of shorter menus. Fifth, strong marinades for meat and game ceased to be used. Sixth, they stopped using heavy sauces such as [[espagnole]] and béchamel thickened with flour based &quot;roux&quot;, in favor of seasoning their dishes with fresh herbs, quality butter, lemon juice, and vinegar. Seventh, they used regional dishes for inspiration instead of haute cuisine dishes. Eighth, new techniques were embraced and modern equipment was often used; Bocuse even used microwave ovens. Ninth, the chefs paid close attention to the dietary needs of their guests through their dishes. Tenth and finally, the chefs were extremely inventive and created new combinations and pairings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mennell&quot; /&gt;{{rp|163–164}}

Some have speculated that a contributor to nouvelle cuisine was World War II when animal protein was in short supply during the German occupation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last = Hewitt | first = Nicholas | title = The Cambridge Companion to Modern French Culture | publisher=The Cambridge University Press | year = 2003 | location = Cambridge | pages = 109–110 | isbn = 978-0-521-79465-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the mid-1980s food writers stated that the style of cuisine had reached exhaustion and many chefs began returning to the haute cuisine style of cooking, although much of the lighter presentations and new techniques remained.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mennell&quot; /&gt;{{rp|163–164}}

==National cuisine==
{{Main article|List of French dishes}}
There are many dishes that are considered part of French national cuisine today.

A meal often consists of three courses, ''hors d'œuvre'' or ''entrée'' (introductory course, sometimes soup), ''plat principal'' (main course), ''fromage'' (cheese course) or ''dessert'', sometimes with a salad offered before the cheese or dessert.

;Hors d'œuvre

&lt;gallery perrow=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
File:Terrine de saumon au basilic.JPG|''Basil salmon [[Terrine (food)|terrine]]''
File:Lobster bisque.jpg|''[[Bisque (food)|Bisque]]'' is a smooth and creamy French ''[[potage]]''
File:Foie gras en cocotte.jpg|''[[Foie gras]]'' with mustard seeds and green onions in duck ''[[Au jus|jus]]''
File:Croque monsieur.jpg|''[[Croque monsieur]]''
&lt;/gallery&gt;

;Plat principal

&lt;Gallery perrow=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
File:Pot au feu2.jpg|''[[Pot au feu]]'' is a ''[[cuisine classique]]'' dish
File:Flickr - cyclonebill - Bøf med pommes frites (1).jpg|''[[Steak frites]]'' is a simple and popular dish
File:Baguette_mie.jpg|''[[Baguette]]'' often accompanies the meal
File:200501 - 6 fromages.JPG|Some [[List of French cheeses|French cheeses]]
&lt;/Gallery&gt;

;Pâtisserie

&lt;Gallery perrow=&quot;6&quot;&gt;
File:Lille Meert2.JPG|Typical French ''[[pâtisserie]]''
File:Mille-feuille 20100916.jpg|''[[Mille-feuille]]''
File:Arc-en-ciel comestible.jpg|''[[Macaron]]
File:Eclairs at Fauchon in Paris.jpg|''[[Eclair]]
&lt;/Gallery&gt;

;Dessert

&lt;Gallery perrow=&quot;7&quot;&gt;
File:Creme Brulee.jpeg|''[[Crème brûlée]]''
File:Chocolate mousse.jpg|''[[Chocolate mousse|Mousse au chocolat]]''
File:Crêpe Suzette au Citron.jpg|''[[Crêpe]]
File:Café Liégeois.jpg|''[[Café liégeois]]

&lt;/Gallery&gt;

==Regional cuisine==
[[File:Départements+régions (France).svg|thumb|250px|The 22 [[regions of France|regions]] and 96 [[departments of France|departments]] of [[metropolitan France]] include [[Corsica]] (''Corse'', lower right). Paris area is expanded (inset at left).]]

French regional cuisine is characterized by its extreme diversity and style. Traditionally, each region of France has its own distinctive cuisine.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.french-country-decor-guide.com/french-country-cooking.html &quot;French Country Cooking.&quot;] [http://www.french-country-decor-guide.com French-country-decor-guide.com]. Accessed July 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Paris and Île-de-France===
Paris and Île-de-France are central regions where almost anything from the country is available, as all train lines meet in the city. Over 9,000 restaurants exist in Paris and almost any cuisine can be obtained here. High-quality [[Michelin Guide]]-rated restaurants proliferate here.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot;&gt;{{Cite book | last = Dominé | first = André  | title = Culinaria France | publisher=Könemann Verlagsgesellschaft mbh | location = Cologne | isbn = 978-3-8331-1129-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Champagne, Lorraine, and Alsace===
Game and ham are popular in [[Champagne, France|Champagne]], as well as the special sparkling wine simply known as ''[[Champagne]]''. Fine fruit preserves are known from [[Lorraine (region)|Lorraine]] as well as the [[quiche]] Lorraine. [[Alsace]] is influenced by the Alemannic food culture; as such, [[beer in France|beer]]s made in the area are similar to the style of bordering Germany. Dishes like [[choucroute]] (the French word for sauerkraut) are also popular.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|55}} Many &quot;Eaux de Vie&quot; (alcoholic distillation) also called schnaps is from this region, due to a wide variety of local fruits (cherry, raspberry, pear, grapes) and especially prunes (mirabelle, plum).[9]:259,295
{{Clear}}
&lt;Gallery&gt;
File:Champagne flute and bottle.jpg|''[[Champagne stemware|Flute]]'' of ''[[Champagne]]'' wine
File:Tarte flambée alsacienne 514471722.jpg|Alsatian ''[[flammekueche]]''
File:Andouillette.jpg|''[[Andouillette]]''
File:Quiches 2.jpg|''[[Quiche]]
&lt;/Gallery&gt;

[[File:Jean François Tourcaty, Carte Gastronomique de la France, 1809 Cornell CUL PJM 1033 01.jpg|thumbnail|&quot;Carte Gastronomique de la France&quot; belong to the outset of the &quot;Cours Gastronomique&quot; by Charles Louis Cadet de Gassicourt (1809).]]

===Nord Pas-de-Calais, Picardy, Normandy, and Brittany===
The coastline supplies many [[crustacean]]s, [[European seabass|sea bass]], [[monkfish]] and [[Herring (food)|herring]]. [[Normandy]] has top quality seafood, such as [[scallop]]s and [[Sole (fish)|sole]], while [[Brittany]] has a supply of lobster, crayfish and mussels. Normandy is home to a large population of apple trees; apples are often used in dishes, as well as [[cider]] and [[calvados (spirit)|Calvados]]. The northern areas of this region, especially [[Nord (French department)|Nord]], grow ample amounts of wheat, sugar beets and [[chicory]]. Thick stews are found often in these northern areas as well. The produce of these northern regions is also considered some of the best in the country, including cauliflower and artichokes. Buckwheat grows widely in Brittany as well and is used in the region's ''[[galette]]s'', called ''jalet'', which is where this dish originated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|93}}

&lt;Gallery&gt;
File:Crème Chantilly.jpg|''[[Crème Chantilly#Crème Chantilly|Crème Chantilly]]'' was created at the [[Château de Chantilly]]
File:Camembert.JPG|''[[Camembert]]'', cheese specialty from [[Normandy]]
File:GaletteCidre.JPG|''[[Crêpe]]'' and ''[[Cider#France|Cider]]'', speciality from [[Brittany]]
File:Belon_oysters_at_Belon_river,_France.jpg|''Belon'' oysters
&lt;/Gallery&gt;

===Loire Valley and central France===
High-quality fruits come from [[Loire Valley|the Loire Valley]] and central France, including cherries grown for the liqueur ''[[Guignolet]]'' and the 'Belle Angevine' pears. The strawberries and melons are also of high quality. Fish are seen in the cuisine, often served with a [[beurre blanc]] sauce, as well as wild game, lamb, calves, [[Charolais cattle]], ''Géline'' fowl, and high-quality goat cheeses. Young vegetables are used often in the cuisine, as are the specialty mushrooms of the region, ''champignons de Paris''. Vinegars from [[Orléans]] are a specialty ingredient used as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|129, 132}}

===Burgundy and Franche-Comté===
[[Burgundy (region)|Burgundy]] and [[Franche-Comté]] are known for their wines. [[pike (fish)|Pike]], [[perch]], river crabs, snails, game, [[redcurrant]]s, [[blackcurrant]]s are from both [[Burgundy (region)|Burgundy]] and [[Franche-Comté]]. Amongst savorous specialties accounted in the ''[[Cuisine franc-comtoise]]'' from the [[Franche-Comté]] region are [[Croûte aux morilles]], [[Poulet à la Comtoise]], [[trout]], smoked meat and cheese such as [[Mont d'Or (cheese)|Mont d'Or]], [[Comté (cheese)]] and [[Morbier (cheese)]] which are at the palate best eaten hot or cold, the exquisite [[Coq au vin jaune]] and especial dessert [[gâteau de ménage]]. [[Charolais cattle|Charolais]] beef, [[Bresse (chicken)|poultry]] from [[Bresse]], [[sea snail]], honey cake, [[Chaource]] and [[Époisses de Bourgogne|Epoisses cheese]] are specialties of the local cuisine of Burgundy. [[Dijon mustard]] is also a specialty of Burgundy cuisine. ''[[Crème de Cassis]]'' is a popular liquor made from the blackcurrants. Oil are used in the cooking here, types include nut oils and [[rapeseed]] oil.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|153,156,166,185}}

&lt;Gallery perrow=&quot;4&quot;&gt;

File:Coq morilles.jpg|''[[Coq au vin jaune]]''
File:Poulet de Bresse.jpg|''[[Poulet à la Comtoise]]''
File:Mont d'or chaud.jpg|''[[Mont d'Or chaud]]
File:Escargotbordeaux.jpg|''[[Escargot]]s, with special tongs and fork''
File:Coq au vin rouge.jpg|''[[Coq au vin]]''
File:Boeuf bourguignon servie avec des pâtes.jpg|''[[Bœuf bourguignon]]''
File:Beaujolais salad.jpg|''[[Beaujolais (wine)|Beaujolais]]'' wine
File:Dijon mustard on a spoon - 20051218.jpg|''[[Dijon Mustard|Moutarde de Dijon]]''
File:Vin Jaune.jpg|[[Comté (cheese)|Comté]] cheese &amp; [[Vin jaune]]
File:Bleu de Bresse cheese.jpg|''[[Bleu de Bresse]]
File:Gateau de menage.jpg|''[[Gâteau de ménage]]
&lt;/Gallery&gt;

===Lyon-Rhône-Alpes===
{{See also|Lyonnaise cuisine}}

[[Image:tartiflette and Fried Ham.jpg|thumb|260px|A cooked tartiflette and grilled ham]]
[[Image:Salade lyonnaise.JPG|thumb|260px|Salade lyonnaise]]

Fruit and young vegetables are popular in the cuisine from the [[Rhône valley]]. Poultry from [[Bresse]], guinea fowls from Drôme and fish from the Dombes lakes and mountain in [[Rhône-Alpes]] streams are key to the cuisine as well. [[Lyon]] and [[Savoy]] supply high quality sausages while the [[Alpine region|Alpine]] regions supply their specialty cheeses like [[Beaufort (cheese)|Beaufort]], [[Abondance (cheese)|Abondance]], [[Reblochon]], [[Tomme]] and [[Vacherin]]. ''Mères lyonnaises'' are a particular type of restaurateur relegated to this region that are the regions bistro. Celebrated chefs from this region include [[Fernand Point]], [[Paul Bocuse]], the Troisgros brothers and Alain Chapel. The [[Chartreuse Mountains]] are in this region, and the liquor [[Chartreuse (liquor)|Chartreuse]] is produced by the [[Grande Chartreuse]] monks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|197,230}}

===Poitou-Charentes and Limousin===
Oysters come from the Oléron-Marennes basin, while mussels come from the Bay of Aiguillon. High-quality produce comes from the region's hinterland, especially goat cheese. This region and in the [[Vendée]] is grazing ground for ''Parthenaise'' cattle, while poultry is raised in [[Challans]]. The region of [[Poitou-Charentes]] purportedly produces the best butter and cream in France. [[Cognac (drink)|Cognac]] is also made in the region along the [[Charente River]]. [[Limousin (region)|Limousin]] is home to the high-quality [[Limousin (cattle)|Limousin cattle]], as well as high quality sheep. The woodlands offer game and high-quality mushrooms. The southern area around [[Brive]] draws its cooking influence from [[Périgord]] and [[Auvergne (region)|Auvergne]] to produce a robust cuisine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|237}}

===Bordeaux, Périgord, Gascony, and Basque country===
{{Main article|Basque cuisine}}
[[Bordeaux]] is known for its wine, with certain areas offering specialty grapes for wine-making. Fishing is popular in the region for the cuisine, sea fishing in the [[Bay of Biscay]], trapping in the [[Garonne]] and stream fishing in the [[Pyrenees]]. The Pyrenees also support top quality lamb, such as the ''&quot;Agneau de Pauillac&quot;'', as well as high quality sheep cheeses. Beef cattle in the region include the ''[[Blonde d'Aquitaine]]'', ''Boeuf de Chalosse'', ''Boeuf Gras de Bazas'', and ''Garonnaise''. High quality free-range chicken, turkey, pigeon, [[capon]], goose and duck prevail in the region as well.  [[Gascony]] and [[Périgord]] cuisines includes high quality ''patés'', ''[[Terrine (food)|terrine]]s'', ''[[confit]]s'' and ''magrets''. This is one of the regions notable for its production of [[foie gras]] or fattened goose or duck liver. The cuisine of the region is often heavy and farm based.  [[Armagnac (drink)|Armagnac]] is also from this region, as are high quality prunes from [[Agen]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|259,295}}

France has several regions where people consume rat like Bordeaux.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schwabe1979&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Calvin W. Schwabe|title=Unmentionable Cuisine|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=SiBntk9jGmoC&amp;pg=PA204#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|year=1979|publisher=University of Virginia Press|isbn=978-0-8139-1162-5|pages=204–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;Gallery&gt;
File:Confitdecanard.jpg|''[[Confit de canard]]''
File:Foie gras with sauternes.jpg|A ''[[Terrine (food)|terrine]]'' of ''[[foie gras]]'' with a bottle of ''[[Sauternes (wine)|Sauternes]]''
File:Truffe coupée.jpg|Black Périgord ''[[Truffle]]''
File:Tourin.jpg|''[[Tourin]]'', a garlic soup from [[Dordogne]]
&lt;/Gallery&gt;

===Toulouse, Quercy, and Aveyron===
[[Gers]], a department of France, is within this region and has high quality poultry, while [[La Montagne Noire]] and [[Lacaune]] area offers high quality hams and dry sausages. White corn is planted heavily in the area both for use in fattening the ducks and geese for foie gras and for the production of ''millas'', a cornmeal porridge.  [[Haricot bean]]s are also grown in this area, which are central to the dish [[cassoulet]]. The finest sausage in France is commonly acknowledged to be the ''saucisse de Toulouse'', which also finds its way into their version of ''cassoulet'' of [[Toulouse]]. The [[Cahors]] area produces a high quality specialty &quot;black wine&quot; as well as high-quality [[truffle]]s and mushrooms.

This region also produces milk-fed lamb. Unpasteurized [[domestic sheep|ewe]]'s milk is used to produce the [[Roquefort]] in [[Aveyron]], while  in [[Laguiole]] is producing unpasteurized cow's milk cheese. The [[Salers]] cattle produce quality milk for cheese, as well as beef and veal products. The volcanic soils create flinty cheeses and superb lentils. Mineral waters are produced in high volume in this region as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|313}} Cabécou cheese is from Rocamadour, a medieval settlement erected directly on a cliff, in the rich countryside of Causses du Quercy.  This area is one of the region’s oldest milk producers; it has chalky soil, marked by history and human activity, and is favourable for the raising of goats.

&lt;Gallery&gt;
File:Bol d'aligot.jpg|''[[Aligot]]''
File:Roquefort cheese.jpg|''[[Roquefort]]'' cheese
File:Bowl of cassoulet.JPG|''[[Cassoulet]]''
&lt;/Gallery&gt;

===Roussillon, Languedoc, and Cévennes===
Restaurants are popular in the area known as ''[[Le Midi]]''. Oysters come from the Etang de Thau, to be served in the restaurants of Bouzigues, Meze, and [[Sète]]. Mussels are commonly seen here in addition to fish specialties of Sète, ''Bourride'', ''Tielles'' and ''Rouille de seiche''. In the [[Languedoc]]  ''jambon cru'', sometimes known as ''jambon de montagne'' is produced. High quality ''[[Roquefort]]'' comes from the ''brebis'' (sheep) on the [[Larzac]] plateau. The [[Cévennes|Les Cévennes]] area offers mushrooms, chestnuts, berries, honey, lamb, game, sausages, ''pâtés'' and goat cheeses.  [[Catalan people|Catalan]] influence can be seen in the cuisine here with dishes like brandade made from a purée of dried [[Cod (food)|cod]] wrapped in [[Chard|mangold]] leaves. Snails are plentiful and are prepared in a specific ''Catalan'' style known as a ''cargolade''. [[Wild boar]] can be found in the more mountainous regions of the ''Midi''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|349,360}}

===Provence-Alpes-Côte d'Azur===
{{See also|Provencal cuisine}}

The [[Provence]] and [[Côte d'Azur]] region is rich in quality citrus, vegetables, fruits, and herbs; the region is one of the largest suppliers of all these ingredients in France. The region also produces the largest amount of olives, and creates superb olive oil. [[Lavender]] is used in many dishes found in ''Haute Provence''. Other important herbs in the cuisine include [[thyme]], [[Common sage|sage]], [[rosemary]], [[basil]], [[Satureja|savory]], [[fennel]], [[marjoram]], [[tarragon]], [[oregano]], and [[bay leaf]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nice-cooking.com/la-cuisine-nicoise/|title=Nice Cooking|publisher=La Cuisine Niçoise|accessdate=2015-12-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Honey is a prized ingredient in the region. Seafood proliferates throughout the coastal area and is heavily represented in the cuisine. Goat cheeses, air-dried sausages, lamb, beef, and chicken are popular here. Garlic* and anchovies are used in many of the region's sauces, as in ''Poulet Provençal'', which uses white wine, tomatoes, herbs, and sometimes anchovies, and [[Pastis]] is found everywhere that alcohol is served. The cuisine uses a large amount of vegetables for lighter preparations. Truffles are commonly seen in Provence during the winter. [[Thirteen desserts]] in Provence are the traditional Christmas dessert,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.provenceweb.fr/e/mag/terroir/traditions/ukindex.htm |title=Christmas traditions |publisher=Provenceweb.fr |accessdate=2012-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; e.g. [[quince cheese]], biscuits, almonds, [[nougat]], apple, and [[fougasse (bread)|fougasse]].

Rice is grown in the [[Camargue]], which is the northernmost rice growing area in Europe, with [[Camargue red rice]] being a specialty.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|387,403,404,410,416}} Anibal Camous, a Marseillais who lived to be 104, maintained that it was by eating garlic daily that he kept his “youth” and brilliance. When his eighty-year-old son died, the father mourned : “ I always told him he wouldn’t live long, poor boy. He ate too little garlic !” (''cited by chef Philippe Gion'')

&lt;Gallery perrow=&quot;4&quot;&gt;
File:Flickr - cyclonebill - Salade_niçoise (2).jpg|''[[Salade niçoise]]''
File:AOC Vacqueyras rosé + lavande.jpg|[[Vacqueyras AOC|Vacqueyras]] wine
File:Flickr - cyclonebill - Bouillabaisse med rouille.jpg|''[[Bouillabaisse]]''
File:Pan-bagnat 1.jpg|''[[Pan bagnat]]''
File:Ratatouille-Dish.jpg|''[[Ratatouille]]''
File:Bourride de fruits de mer.JPG|''[[:fr:Bourride|Bourride de fruits de mer]]''
File:Salade mesclun et chèvre chaud sur toasts.jpg|''[[Mesclun|Salade Mesclun]]''
File:Pieds et paquets 2.jpg|''[[Pieds paquets]]''
&lt;/Gallery&gt;

===Corsica===
{{See also|Cuisine of Corsica}}
Goats and sheep proliferate on the island of [[Corsica]], and lamb are used to prepare dishes such as &quot;stufato&quot;, [[ragout]]s and roasts. Cheeses are also produced, with &quot;[[brocciu]]&quot; being the most popular. [[Chestnut]]s, growing in the Castagniccia forest, are used to produce flour, which is used in turn to make bread, cakes and [[polenta]]. The forest provides acorns used to feed the pigs and [[boar]]s that provide much of the protein for the island's cuisine. Fresh fish and seafood are common. The island's pork is used to make fine hams, sausage and other unique items including ''[[capicola|coppa]]'' (dried rib cut), ''lonzu'' (dried pork fillet), ''figatella'', ''salumu'' (a dried sausage) ''salcietta'', ''Panzetta'', bacon, ''figatellu'' (smoked and dried liverwurst) and ''prisuttu'' (farmer's ham).  [[Clementine]]s (which hold an AOC designation), lemons, nectarines and figs are grown there. Candied [[citron]] is used in [[nougat]]s, while and the aforementioned brocciu and chestnuts are also used in desserts. Corsica offers a variety of wines and fruit liqueurs, including [[Cap Corse]], [[Patrimonio]], ''Cédratine'', ''Bonapartine'', ''liqueur de myrte'', ''vins de fruit'', ''Rappu'', and ''[[eau-de-vie]] de châtaigne''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|435,441,442}}

===French Guiana===
{{See also|French Guianese Cuisine|Awara broth}}
[[File:Photo du Bouillon d'Awara.jpeg|thumb|[[Awara broth]]]]
[[File:Dizé milé avec crème impériale et glace coco.JPG|thumb|Dize mile with coconut ice cream and  a imperial cream]]
'''French Guianese Cuisine''' is a blend of the different cultures that have settled in [[French Guiana]]. Creole and Chinese restaurants are common in major cities such as [[Cayenne]], [[Kourou]] and [[Saint-Laurent-du-Maroni]]. Many indigenous animal species such as [[caiman]] and [[tapir]] are used in spiced stews.

==Specialties by season==
French cuisine varies according to the season. In summer, salads and fruit dishes are popular because they are refreshing and produce is inexpensive and abundant. Greengrocers prefer to sell their fruit and vegetables at lower prices if needed, rather than see them rot in the heat. At the end of summer, mushrooms become plentiful and appear in stews throughout France. The hunting season begins in September and runs through February. Game of all kinds is eaten, often in elaborate dishes that celebrate the success of the hunt. Shellfish are at their peak when winter turns to spring, and oysters appear in restaurants in large quantities.

With the advent of deep-freeze and the air-conditioned ''[[hypermarché]]'', these seasonal variations are less marked than hitherto, but they are still observed, in some cases due to legal restrictions. [[Crayfish (food)|Crayfish]], for example, have a short season and it is illegal to catch them out of season.&lt;ref&gt;Imported crayfish are unrestricted, and many arrive from Pakistan.&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, they do not freeze well.

==Foods and ingredients==
{{Unreferenced section|date=August 2010}}

French regional cuisines use locally grown vegetables, such as ''pomme de terre'' (potato), ''blé'' ([[wheat]]), ''[[Haricot bean|haricots verts]]'' (a type of French green bean), ''carotte'' (carrot), ''poireau'' ([[leek]]), ''navet'' ([[turnip]]), ''aubergine'' ([[eggplant]]), ''courgette'' ([[zucchini]]), and ''échalotte'' ([[shallot]]).

French regional cuisines use locally grown fungi, such as ''truffe'' ([[Tuber (genus)|truffle]]), ''champignon de Paris'' ([[button mushroom]]), ''chanterelle ou girolle'' ([[chanterelle]]), ''pleurote (en huître)'' ([[oyster mushroom]]s), and ''cèpes'' ([[porcini]]).

Common fruits include oranges, tomatoes, [[tangerine]]s, [[peach]]es, [[apricot]]s, [[apple]]s, [[pear]]s, [[plum]]s, [[Cherry|cherries]], [[Strawberry|strawberries]], [[Raspberry|raspberries]], [[redcurrant]]s, [[Blackberry|blackberries]], [[grape]]s, [[grapefruit]], and [[blackcurrant]]s.

Varieties of meat consumed include ''poulet'' ([[Chicken (food)|chicken]]), ''pigeon'' ([[Squab (food)|squab]]), ''canard'' ([[Duck (food)|duck]]), ''oie'' ([[goose]], the source of [[foie gras]]), ''bœuf'' ([[beef]]), ''veau'' ([[veal]]), ''porc'' ([[pork]]), ''agneau'' ([[Lamb (food)|lamb]]), ''mouton'' ([[mutton]]), ''caille'' ([[quails in cookery|quail]]), ''cheval'' ([[horse meat|horse]]), ''grenouille'' ([[frog legs|frog]]), and ''[[escargot]]'' (snails). Commonly consumed fish and seafood include [[Cod (food)|cod]], [[canned sardines]], [[sardine (food)|fresh sardines]], canned [[tuna]], fresh tuna, [[Salmon (food)|salmon]], [[trout]], [[mussel]]s, [[Herring (food)|herring]], [[oyster]]s, [[Shrimp (food)|shrimp]] and [[calamari]].

Eggs are fine quality and often eaten as: [[omelette]]s, hard-boiled with [[mayonnaise]], [[Scrambled eggs|scrambled]] plain, scrambled ''[[haute cuisine]]'' preparation, œuf à la coque.

Herbs and seasonings vary by region, and include ''[[fleur de sel]]'', ''[[herbes de Provence]]'', [[tarragon]], [[rosemary]], [[marjoram]], [[lavender]], [[thyme]], [[fennel]], and [[Common sage|sage]].

Fresh fruit and vegetables, as well as fish and meat, can be purchased either from supermarkets or specialty shops. Street markets are held on certain days in most localities; some towns have a more permanent covered market enclosing food shops, especially meat and fish retailers. These have better shelter than the periodic street markets.

&lt;Gallery perrow=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
File:Herbesdeprovence.jpg|''[[Herbes de provence]]''
File:Charetveau.jpg|''[[Charolais cattle]]''
File:Champignons Agaricus.jpg|''[[Champignon de Paris]]''
File:HaricotsVerts2.JPG|''[[Haricot bean|Haricots verts]]''
File:France-AOC Piment d'Espelette-2005-08-05.jpg|''[[Espelette pepper|Piments d'Espelette]]''
File:Fleur de sel2.jpg|''[[Fleur de sel]] de [[Guérande]]''
File:Wine grapes03.jpg|''[[Grape|Grappe de raisin]]''
File:Bressehühner-1.jpg|''[[Poulet de Bresse]]''
File:Wheat close-up.JPG|''Blé ([[Wheat]])''
&lt;/Gallery&gt;

==Structure of meals==

===Breakfast===
[[File:Cafe con leche y cruasán.jpg|thumb|right|[[Coffee|Café]] with a [[croissant]] for breakfast]]

''Le petit déjeuner'' (breakfast) is traditionally a quick meal consisting of ''tartines'' (slices) of French bread with butter and honey or jam, sometimes [[brioche]], along with café au lait (also called &quot;café crème&quot;), or black coffee, or tea,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Larousse Gastronomique|year=2009|publisher=Clarkson Potter|location=New York|isbn=978-0-307-46491-0|page=780}}&lt;/ref&gt; more rarely hot chicory. Children often drink [[hot chocolate]] in bowls or cups along with their breakfasts. ''[[Croissants]]'', ''[[pain aux raisins]]'' or ''[[pain au chocolat]]'' (also named ''chocolatine'' in the south of France) are mostly included as a weekend treat. Breakfast of some kind is always served in cafés opening early in the day.

There are also savoury dishes for breakfast.
For example, &quot;le petit déjeuner gaulois&quot; or &quot;petit déjeuner fermier&quot; with the famous long narrow bread slices with soft white cheese topped or boiled ham, called &quot;'''mouillettes'''&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.larousse.fr/dictionnaires/francais/mouillette/52900&lt;/ref&gt; which you dip in a soft-boiled egg and some fruit juice and hot drink.
Another variation called &quot;le petit déjeuner chasseur&quot;, meant to be very hearty, is served with pâté and other charcuterie products. A more classy version, called &quot;le petit déjeuner du voyageur&quot; where delicatessens serve gizzard, bacon, salmon, omelet, or croque-monsieur, with or without soft-boiled egg and always with the traditional coffee/tea/chocolate along fruits or fruit juice. When the egg is cooked sunny-side over the croque-monsieur, it is called a croque-madame.
In Germinal and other novels, Émile Zola also reported the '''briquet''' : two long bread slices stuffed with butter, cheese and or ham. It can be eaten as a standing/walking breakfast, or meant as a &quot;second&quot; one before lunch.
In the movie &quot;[[Bienvenue chez les Ch'tis]]&quot;, Philippe Abrams ([[Kad Merad]]) and Antoine Bailleul ([[Dany Boon]]) share together countless breakfasts consisting of ''tartines de Maroilles'' (a rather strong cheese) along with their hot chicory.

===Lunch===
''Le déjeuner'' (lunch) is a two-hour mid-day meal or an one-hour lunch break. In some smaller towns and in the south of France, the two-hour lunch may still be customary. Sunday lunches are often longer and are taken with the family.&lt;ref name=&quot;Steele&quot;/&gt;  Restaurants normally open for lunch at noon and close at 2:30&amp;nbsp;pm. Some restaurants close on Monday during lunch hours.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fodors&quot;&gt;{{Cite book | last = Fodor's | title = See It. France. 2nd ed. | publisher=Fodor's Travel Publications | year = 2006 | location = New York | isbn = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In large [[List of communes in France with over 20,000 inhabitants (1999 census)|cities]], a majority of working people and [[List of colleges and universities in France|students]] eat their lunch at a corporate or school cafeteria, which normally serve complete meals as described above; it is not usual for students to bring their own lunch food. For companies that do not operate a cafeteria, it is common for [[white-collar worker]]s to be given lunch vouchers as part of their employee benefits. These can be used in most restaurants, supermarkets and ''[[traiteur (culinary profession)|traiteurs]]''; however, workers having lunch in this way typically do not eat all three dishes of a traditional lunch due to price and time constraints. In smaller cities and towns, some working people leave their workplaces to return home for lunch. Also, an alternative, especially among [[blue-collar worker]]s, eating sandwiches followed with a dessert; both dishes can be found ready-made at bakeries and supermarkets for budget prices.

===Dinner===
''Le dîner'' (dinner) often consists of three [[full course dinner|courses]], ''[[hors d'œuvre]]'' or ''[[entrée]]'' (appetizers or introductory course, sometimes soup), ''plat principal'' (main course), and a cheese course or dessert, sometimes with a salad offered before the cheese or dessert. Yogurt may replace the cheese course, while a simple dessert would be fresh fruit. The meal is often accompanied by bread, [[French wine|wine]] and [[mineral water]]. Most of the time the bread would be a baguette which is very common in France and is made almost every day. Main meat courses are often served with vegetables, along with potatoes, rice or pasta.&lt;ref name=&quot;Steele&quot;&gt;{{Cite book | last = Steele | first = Ross | title = The French Way, 2nd ed. | publisher=McGraw-Hill | year = 2001  | location = New York | isbn = }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|82}} Restaurants often open at 7:30&amp;nbsp;pm for dinner, and stop taking orders between the hours of 10:00&amp;nbsp;pm and 11:00&amp;nbsp;pm. Some restaurants close for dinner on Sundays.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fodors&quot; /&gt;{{rp|342}}

==Beverages and drinks==
In French cuisine, beverages that precede a meal are called [[apéritif]]s (literally: ''that opens the appetite''), and can be served with [[amuse-bouche]]s (literally: ''mouth amuser''). Those that end it are called [[digestif]]s.

;Apéritifs

The apéritif varies from region to region: [[Pastis]] is popular in the south of France, [[Crémant d'Alsace]] in the eastern region. [[Champagne]] can also be served. [[Kir (cocktail)|Kir]], also called « ''Blanc-cassis'' », is a common and popular apéritif-cocktail made with a measure of [[crème de cassis]] (blackcurrant liqueur) topped up with [[white wine]]. The word ''Kir Royal'' is used when white wine is replaced with a ''Champagne'' wine. A simple glass of red wine, such as [[Beaujolais nouveau]], can also be presented as an apéritif, accompanied by [[amuse-bouche]]s. Some apéritifs can be [[fortified wine]]s with added herbs, such as [[cinchona]], [[gentian]] and [[vermouth]]. Trade names that sell well include [[Suze (drink)|Suze]] (the classic gentiane), [[Byrrh]], [[Dubonnet]], [[Noilly Prat]].

;Digestifs

Digestifs are traditionally stronger, and include [[Cognac (brandy)|Cognac]], [[Armagnac (brandy)|Armagnac]], [[Calvados (brandy)|Calvados]] and fruit alcohols.

==French cuisine of Christmas==
Mainly in France serving turkey with chestnuts for Christmas. We also serve for this time the smoked salmon, oysters, caviar and ''foie gras''. To this we must add snails and white pudding. Also, the Yule log is a very French tradition during Christmas. Chocolate and cakes also occupy a prominent place for Christmas in France.This cuisine is normally accompanied by Champagne, typically french drink. Tradition says that thirteen desserts complete the Christmas meal in reference to the twelve apostles and Christ. These desserts gather the most fruit and confectionery France.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cheznoscousins.com/2014/12/30/10-traditions-noel-francaises/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.joyeux-noel.com/noeldanslemonde.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ambafrance-at.org/Noel-le-Nouvel-An-et-la-Fete-des-Rois&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://referat.clopotel.ro/Les_fetes_de_Noel_en_France-14079.html&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Bûche de Noël chocolat framboise maison.jpg|thumb|Yule log, a french Christmas tradition.]]

==Food establishments==
[[File:Cooks 050918 154402.jpg|thumb|Cooks at work]]

===History===
The modern restaurant has its origins in French culture. Prior to the late 18th century, diners who wished to &quot;dine out&quot; would visit their local [[guild]] member's kitchen and have their meal prepared for them. However, guild members were limited to producing whatever their guild registry delegated them to.&lt;ref name=&quot;Spang&quot;&gt;{{Cite book | last = Spang | first = Rebecca L. | title = The Invention of the Restaurant, 2nd Ed. | publisher=Harvard University Press | year = 2001 | location =  | isbn = 978-0-674-00685-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|8–10}} These guild members offered food in their own homes to steady clientele that appeared day-to-day but at set times. The guest would be offered the meal [[table d'hôte]], which is a meal offered at a set price with very little choice of dishes, sometimes none at all.&lt;ref name=&quot;Spang&quot; /&gt;{{rp|30–31}}

The first steps toward the modern restaurant were locations that offered ''restorative'' [[bouillon]]s, or ''restaurants'' – these words being the origin of the name &quot;restaurant&quot;. This step took place during the 1760s–1770s. These locations were open at all times of the day, featuring ornate tableware and reasonable prices. These locations were meant more as meal replacements for those who had &quot;lost their appetites and suffered from jaded palates and weak chests.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Spang&quot; /&gt;{{rp|34–35}}

In 1782 Antoine Beauvilliers, [[pastry chef]] to the future [[Louis XVIII]], opened one of the most popular restaurants of the time – the ''Grande Taverne de Londres'' – in the arcades of the [[Palais-Royal]]. Other restaurants were opened by chefs of the time who were leaving the failing monarchy of France, in the period leading up to the French Revolution. It was these restaurants that expanded upon the limited menus of decades prior, and led to the full restaurants that were completely legalized with the advent of the French Revolution and abolition of the guilds. This and the substantial discretionary income of the [[French Directory]]'s ''[[nouveau riche]]'' helped keep these new restaurants in business.&lt;ref name=&quot;Spang&quot; /&gt;{{rp|140–144}}

[[File:Train bleu 05.jpg|thumb|Restaurant ''Le Train Bleu'', in Paris]]
[[File:Bouchon leTablier.jpg|thumb|A [[bouchon]], ''Le tablier'' (the apron), in Vieux Lyon]]
[[File:Café de Flore.jpg|thumb|''Café de Flore'', in Paris]]

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+Categories
!English
!French
!Description
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|colspan=2|[[Restaurant]]
|More than 5,000 in Paris alone, with varying levels of prices and menus. Open at certain times of the day, and normally closed one day of the week. Patrons select items from a printed [[menu]]. Some offer regional menus, while others offer a modern styled menu. Waiters and waitresses are trained and knowledgeable professionals. By law, a prix-fixe menu must be offered, although high-class restaurants may try to conceal the fact. Few French restaurants cater to vegetarians. The ''[[Guide Michelin]]'' rates many of the better restaurants in this category.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|30}}
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|colspan=2|[[Bistro|Bistro(t)]]
|Often smaller than a restaurant and many times using chalk board or verbal menus. Wait staff may well be untrained. Many feature a regional cuisine. Notable dishes include [[coq au vin]], [[pot-au-feu]], [[confit de canard]], calves' liver and [[entrecôte]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|30}}
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|colspan=2|Bistrot à Vin
|Similar to ''[[cabaret]]s'' or ''[[tavern]]es'' of the past in France. Some offer inexpensive alcoholic drinks, while others take pride in offering a full range of vintage [[Appellation (wine)|AOC]] wines. The foods in some are simple, including sausages, ham and cheese, while others offer dishes similar to what can be found in a bistro.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|30}}
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|colspan=2|[[Bouchon]]
|Found in [[Lyon]], they produce traditional Lyonnaise cuisine, such as sausages, duck pâté or roast pork. The dishes can be quite fatty, and heavily oriented around meat. There are about twenty officially certified traditional bouchons, but a larger number of establishments describing themselves using the term.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last = Boudou | first = Evelyne |author2=Jean-Marc Boudou | title = Les bonnes recettes des bouchons lyonnais | publisher=Libris | year = 2003 | location = Seyssinet | isbn = 978-2-84799-002-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|Brewery
|[[Brasserie]]
|These establishments were created in the 1870s by refugees from [[Alsace-Lorraine]]. These establishments serve beer, but most serve wines from Alsace such as [[Riesling]], [[Sylvaner]], and [[Gewürztraminer]]. The most popular dishes are [[choucroute]] and [[seafood]] dishes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|30}} In general, a brasserie is open all day every day, offering the same menu.&lt;ref&gt;Ribaut, Jean-Claude (8 February 2007). ''[[Le Monde]]''.  &quot;Les brasseries ont toujours l'avantage d'offrir un service continu tout au long de la journée, d'accueillir les clients après le spectacle et d'être ouvertes sept jours sur sept, quand les restaurants ferment deux jours et demi par semaine.&quot;&lt;br&gt;&quot;Brasseries have the advantage of offering uninterrupted service all day, seven days a week, and of being open for the after-theatre crowd, whereas restaurants are closed two and a half days of the week.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|colspan=2|[[Coffeehouse|Café]]
|Primarily locations for coffee and alcoholic drinks. Tables and chairs are usually set outside, and prices marked up somewhat ''en terrasse''. The limited foods sometimes offered include [[croque-monsieur]], salads, ''[[moules-frites]]'' ([[mussel]]s and ''[[pommes frites]]'') when in season.  ''Cafés'' often open early in the morning and shut down around nine at night.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|30}}
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|colspan=2|[[Tea house|Salon de Thé]]
|These locations are more similar to cafés in the rest of the world. These tearooms often offer a selection of cakes and do not offer alcoholic drinks. Many offer simple snacks, salads, and sandwiches. Teas, hot chocolate, and chocolat à l'ancienne (a popular chocolate drink) offered as well. These locations often open just prior to noon for lunch and then close late afternoon.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|30}}
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|colspan=2|[[Bar (establishment)|Bar]]
|Based on the American style, many were built at the beginning of the 20th century (particularly around World War I, when young American expatriates were quite common in France, particularly Paris). These locations serve cocktails, whiskey, [[pastis]] and other alcoholic drinks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|30}}
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|colspan=2|Estaminet
|Typical of the [[Nord-Pas-de-Calais]] region, these small bars/restaurants used to be a central place for farmers, mine or textile workers to meet and socialize, sometimes the bars would be in a grocery store.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.leershistorique.com/page2_6estaminets.html Les estaminets]&lt;/ref&gt; Customers could order basic regional dishes, play boules, or use the bar as a meeting place for clubs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Wytteman| first=JP (ed.)|date=1988|title=Le Nord de la préhistoire à nos jours|trans-title=|language=fr|publisher=Bordessoules|isbn= |access-date=}} p. 260.&lt;/ref&gt; These estaminets almost disappeared, but are now considered a part of Nord-Pas-de-Calais history, and therefore preserved and promoted.
|}

===Restaurant staff===
Larger restaurants and hotels in France employ extensive staff and are commonly referred to as either the ''kitchen brigade'' for the kitchen staff or ''dining room brigade'' system for the dining room staff. This system was created by [[Georges Auguste Escoffier]].  This structured team system delegates responsibilities to different individuals that specialize in certain tasks. The following is a list of positions held both in the kitchen and dining rooms brigades in France:&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|32}}

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+Staff
!Section
!French
!English
!Duty
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|rowspan=27|Kitchen brigade
|{{lang|fr|[[Chef de cuisine]]}}
|Head chef
|Responsible for overall management of kitchen. They supervise staff, create menus and new recipes with the assistance of the restaurant manager, make purchases of raw food items, trains apprentices and maintains a sanitary and hygienic environment for the preparation of food.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|32}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|Sous-chef de cuisine}}
|Deputy Head chef
|Receives orders directly from the ''chef de cuisine'' for the management of the kitchen and often represents the ''chef de cuisine'' when he or she is not present.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|32}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|Chef de partie}}
|Senior chef
|Responsible for managing a given station in the kitchen where they specialize in preparing particular dishes. Those that work in a lesser station are referred to as a ''demi-chef''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|32}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|Cuisinier}}
|Cook
|This position is an independent one where they usually prepare specific dishes in a station. They may be referred to as a ''cuisinier de partie''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|32}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|Commis}}
|Junior cook
|Also works in a specific station, but reports directly to the ''chef de partie'' and takes care of the tools for the station.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|32}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|Apprenti(e)}}
|Apprentice
|Many times they are students gaining theoretical and practical training in school and work experience in the kitchen. They perform preparatory or cleaning work.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|30}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|Plongeur}}
|Dishwasher
|Cleans dishes and utensils and may be entrusted with basic preparatory job.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|32}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|Marmiton}}
|Pot and pan washer
|In larger restaurants takes care of all the pots and pans instead of the ''plongeur''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|33}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|[[Saucier]]}}
|Saucemaker/Sauté cook
|Prepares [[sauce]]s, warm ''[[hors d'œuvres]]'', completes meat dishes and in smaller restaurants may work on fish dishes and prepares sautéed items. This is one of the most respected positions in the kitchen brigade.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|32}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|Rôtisseur}}
|Roast cook
|Manages a team of cooks that roasts, broils and deep fries dishes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|32}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|Grillardin}}
|Grill cook
|In larger kitchens this person prepares the grilled foods instead of the ''rôtisseur''.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIA&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=The Culinary Institute of America|author-link=The Culinary Institute of America|title=The Professional Chef|edition=8th|location=[[Hoboken, New Jersey]]|publisher=[[John Wiley &amp; Sons]]|date=2006|isbn=978-0-7645-5734-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|8}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|Friturier}}
|Fry cook
|In larger kitchens this person prepares fried foods instead of the ''rôtisseur''.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIA&quot;/&gt;
|-
|{{lang|fr|Poissonnier}}
|Fish cook
|Prepares fish and seafood dishes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|33}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|Entremetier}}
|Entrée preparer
|Prepares soups and other dishes not involving meat or fish, including vegetable dishes and egg dishes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|32}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|Potager}}
|Soup cook
|In larger kitchens this person reports to the ''entremetier'' and prepares the soups.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIA&quot;/&gt;
|-
|{{lang|fr|Legumier}}
|Vegetable cook
|In larger kitchen this person also reports to the ''entremetier'' and prepares the vegetable dishes.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIA&quot;/&gt;
|-
|{{lang|fr|[[Garde manger]]}}
|Pantry supervisor
|responsible for preparation of cold ''[[hors d'œuvres]]'', prepares salads, organizes large buffet displays and prepares [[charcuterie]] items.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|30}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|Tournant}}
|Spare hand/ roundsperson
|Moves throughout kitchen assisting other positions in kitchen
|-
|{{lang|fr|[[Pâtissier]]}}
|Pastry cook
|Prepares desserts and other meal end sweets and for location without a ''boulanger'' also prepares breads and other baked items. They may also prepare pasta for the restaurant.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|33}}
|-
|colspan=2|{{lang|fr|Confiseur}}
|Prepares candies and ''[[petit four]]s'' in larger restaurants instead of the ''pâtissier''.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIA&quot;/&gt;
|-
|colspan=2|{{lang|fr|Glacier}}
|Prepares frozen and cold desserts in larger restaurants instead of the ''pâtissier''.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIA&quot;/&gt;
|-
|colspan=2|{{lang|fr|Décorateur}}
|Prepares show pieces and specialty cakes in larger restaurants instead of the ''pâtissier''.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIA&quot;/&gt;{{rp|8–9}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|[[Boulanger]]}}
|Baker
|Prepares bread, cakes and breakfast pastries in larger restaurants instead of the ''pâtissier''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|33}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|Boucher}}
|Butcher
|butchers meats, poultry and sometimes fish. May also be in charge of breading meat and fish items.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIA&quot;/&gt;
|-
|{{lang|fr|Aboyeur}}
|Announcer/ expediter
|Takes orders from dining room and distributes them to the various stations. This position may also be performed by the ''sous-chef de partie''.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIA&quot;/&gt;
|-
|colspan=2|{{lang|fr|Communard}}
|Prepares the meal served to the restaurant staff.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIA&quot;/&gt;
|-
|colspan=2|{{lang|fr|Garçon de cuisine}}
|Performs preparatory and auxiliary work for support in larger restaurants.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|33}}
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|rowspan=20|Dining room brigade
|{{lang|fr|Directeur de la restauration}}
|General manager
|Oversees economic and administrative duties for all food related business in large hotels or similar facilities including multiple restaurants, bars, catering and other events.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|33}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|Directeur de restaurant}}
|[[Restaurant manager]]
|Responsible for the operation of the restaurant dining room which includes managing staff, hiring and firing staff, training of staff and economic duties of the such matters. In larger establishments there may be an assistant to this position who would replace this person in their absence.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|33}}
|-
|colspan=2|{{lang|fr|[[Maître d'hôtel]]}}
|Welcomes guests, and seats them at tables. They also supervise the service staff. It is this person that commonly deals with complaints and verifies patron bills.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|33}}
|-
|colspan=2|{{lang|fr|Chef de salle}}
|Commonly in charge of service for the full dining room in larger establishments; this position can be combined into the ''maître d'hotel'' position.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIA&quot;/&gt;
|-
|colspan=2|{{lang|fr|Chef de rang}}
|The dining room is separated into sections called ''rangs''. Each ''rang'' is supervised by this person to coordinate service with the kitchen.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|33}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|Demi-chef de rang}}
|rowspan=2|Back server
|rowspan=2|Clears plates between courses if there is no ''commis débarrasseur'', fills water glasses and assists the ''chef de rang''.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIA&quot;/&gt;
|-
|{{lang|fr|commis de rang}}
|-
|colspan=2|{{lang|fr|Commis débarrasseur}}
|Clears plates between courses and the table at the end of the meal.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|33}}
|-
|colspan=2|{{lang|fr|Commis de suite}}
|In larger establishments, this person brings the different courses from the kitchen to the table.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|33}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|Chef d'étage}}
|Captain
|Explains the menu to the guest and answers any questions. This person often performs the tableside food preparations. This position may be combined with the ''chef de rang'' in smaller establishment.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIA&quot;/&gt;
|-
|{{lang|fr|Chef de vin}}
|rowspan=2|Wine server
|rowspan=2|Manages wine cellar by purchasing and organizing as well as preparing the wine list. This person also advises the guest on wine choices and serves it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|33}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|[[Sommelier]]}}
|-
|colspan=2|{{lang|fr|chef sommelier}}
|rowspan=2|In larger establishments, this person will manage a team of sommeliers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|33}}
|-
|colspan=2|{{lang|fr|chef caviste}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|Serveur de restaurant}}
|Server
|This position found in smaller establishments performs the multiple duties of various positions in the larger restaurants in the service of food and drink to the guest.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|33}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|Responsable de bar}}
|rowspan=2|Bar manager
|rowspan=2|Manages the bar in a restaurant which includes ordering and creating drink menus; they also oversee the hiring, training and firing of barmen. Also manages multiple bars in a hotel or other similar establishment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|33}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|Chef de bar}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|Barman}}
|Bartender
|Serves alcoholic drinks to guests.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|33}}
|-
|colspan=2|{{lang|fr|Dame du vestiaire}}
|Coat room attendant who receives and returns guests coats and hats.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|33}}
|-
|{{lang|fr|Voituriers}}
|Valet
|Parks guests' cars and retrieves them upon the guests exiting the restaurant.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domine&quot; /&gt;{{rp|33}}
|}

==See also==
{{portal|France|Food}}
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* ''[[Larousse Gastronomique]]''
* ''[[Le Répertoire de la Cuisine]]''
* [[French paradox]]
* [[List of French dishes]]
* [[List of French cheeses]]
* [[List of French desserts]]
* [[List of French restaurants]]
* [[List of French soups and stews]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* Patrick Rambourg, ''Histoire de la cuisine et de la gastronomie françaises'', Paris, Ed. Perrin (coll. tempus n° 359), 2010, 381 pages. ISBN 978-2-262-03318-7
* Bryan Newman, &quot;[http://behind-the-french-menu.blogspot.com Behind the French Menu]&quot;,

==External links==
{{cookbook|Cuisine of France}}
{{Commons category|Cuisine of France}}
{{Wikivoyage|Cuisine of France}}
*[http://www.english.rfi.fr/france/20110923-france-stages-first-ever-gastronomy-day France stages first-ever Gastronomy Day] Radio France Internationale in English

{{France topics}}
{{cuisine}}
{{European topic|| cuisine}}
{{Mediterranean cuisine}}

{{Good article}}

{{Authority control}}

===French cuisine===

The initial language of this article was French.

{{DEFAULTSORT:French Cuisine}}
[[Category:French cuisine|*]]
[[Category:French chefs]]</text>
      <sha1>l1t3oam5zvmllv6xyvu6deoocrf3fx1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
