<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Grand Western Canal</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>620186</id>
    <revision>
      <id>723155986</id>
      <parentid>723155959</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-06-01T10:34:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Smalljim</username>
        <id>100426</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added [[Category:Industrial archaeological sites in Somerset]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="31347">{{Grand Western Canal plan}}
The '''Grand Western Canal''' ran between [[Taunton]] in [[Somerset]] and [[Tiverton, Devon|Tiverton]] in [[Devon]] in the United Kingdom. The [[canal]] had its origins in various plans, going back to 1796, to link the [[Bristol Channel]] and the [[English Channel]] by a canal, bypassing [[Lands End]]. An additional purpose of the canal was the supply of [[limestone]] and [[coal]] to [[lime kiln]]s along with the removal of the resulting [[quicklime]], which was used as a fertiliser and for building houses. This intended canal-link was never completed as planned, as the coming of the railways removed the need for its existence.&lt;ref name=hadfield-9&gt;[[Charles Hadfield (historian)|Hadfield, Charles]] (1955). &quot;Chapter IX: The Schemes to Join the English and Bristol Channels&quot;. In: ''The Canals of Southern England''. London: Phoenix House Ltd.&lt;/ref&gt;

Construction was in two phases. A level section from Tiverton to Lowdwells on the Devon/Somerset border, opened in 1814, and was capable of carrying broad-beam barges, carrying up to 40&amp;nbsp;tons. The Somerset section, suitable for tub-boats, which were about 20&amp;nbsp;feet (6.1&amp;nbsp;m) long and capable of carrying eight tons, opened in 1839. It included an [[Canal inclined plane|inclined plane]] and seven [[boat lift]]s, the earliest lifts to see commercial service in the UK. The lifts predated the [[Anderton Boat Lift]] by nearly 40 years.

The 11 miles of Devon section remains open, despite various threats to its future, and is now a designated [[country park]] and local nature reserve, and allows navigation. The Somerset section was closed in 1867, and is gradually disappearing from the landscape, although sections are now used as a footpath. It maintains a historical interest and has been subject to some archaeological excavations.

==History==
[[Image:Grand western canal.jpg|alt=Stagnant water between banks covered in vegetation. Part of a house can be seen to the right.|thumb|left|The current end of navigation on the Grand Western Canal at Lowdwells Lock]]
The Grand Western Canal was conceived as one of several competing schemes to alleviate the hazards and delays of coastal sailing ships making a passage around [[Land's End]] to get between the [[Bristol Channel]] and the [[English Channel]].&lt;ref name=hadfield-9/&gt; A canal from the mouth of the [[River Exe]] to [[Exeter]] had been opened in 1566; and eight miles of the [[River Tone]] had been made navigable in 1638. Navigation of the River Tone had been extended to [[Taunton]] in 1717, by the construction of locks on the upper section.&lt;ref name=harris&gt;Helen Harris (1996) ''The Grand Western Canal'', Devon Books, ISBN 0-86114-901-7&lt;/ref&gt;

Against this background, in 1768 a committee of men commissioned [[James Brindley]] to survey a route, in the form of a canal, between Taunton and Exeter; and the survey was duly carried out by [[Robert Whitworth]] in 1769.&lt;ref name=hadfield-9/&gt; This was to have been called the '''Exeter to Uphill Canal'''; as it involved a route from [[Topsham, Devon|Topsham]] or [[Exeter]] to [[Taunton]], then the use of the [[River Tone]] and a second canal from [[Burrow Bridge]], via [[Bridgwater]], [[Glastonbury]], [[Wells, Somerset|Wells]] and [[Axbridge]], to [[Uphill]].&lt;ref name=hadfield-9/&gt; Nothing further came of the plan until the 1790s, when various canal engineers were consulted, and in 1794 [[John Rennie (engineer)|John Rennie]] was asked by a different committee, the '''Grand Western Canal Committee''', to make another survey, which was adopted, and formed the basis for a planned [[Act of Parliament]]. Opposition from the City of Exeter, who feared it would compete with the [[Exeter Canal]] for transportation of [[coal]], was eventually softened; and the Act was passed on 24 March 1796.&lt;ref name=hadfield-9/&gt;&lt;ref name=harris/&gt;

The Act authorised a canal from Taunton to Topsham with branches to [[Tiverton, Devon|Tiverton]] and [[Cullompton]]. Water supply would be derived from proposed reservoirs, one on the River Tone and two on the [[River Culm]], and from any other available sources within 2000&amp;nbsp;yd (1.8&amp;nbsp;km) of the line of the canal. The canal company was also authorised to improve the River Tone near Taunton, and to raise £220,000, plus an additional £110,000 if required. Navigation onwards from Taunton was via the River Tone and the [[River Parrett]]. Construction did not start immediately.&lt;ref name=harris/&gt;

===Construction===
{{Grand Western Canal map}}
[[Image:Gradnwesterncanalhalberton.jpg|alt=Water with trees on the left and a tow path to the right|thumb|left|Grand Western Canal at [[Halberton]], Seen from Manley Bridge, looking towards [[Tiverton, Devon|Tiverton]].]]
Finally in 1810, work started under the direction of John Thomas. Surprisingly, the decision was taken to start in the middle, with a {{convert|2.5|mi|km|0}} section of the main line and the {{convert|9|mi|km|0}} branch to Tiverton. The logic for this was that there was a large potential trade in limestone between quarries at Canonsleigh and Tiverton, and this would generate income. The summit level was cut {{convert|16|ft|m|0}} lower than the original plans, so that no locks would be required, but this greatly increased the amount of earthworks required. A further Act was obtained in 1811 to sanction this, and to re-route the canal near [[Halberton]],&lt;ref name=harris/&gt; where Rock Bridge was constructed to carry the road over the canal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Rock Bridge at Halberton | work=Images of England | url=http://www.imagesofengland.org.uk/details/default.aspx?id=95389 | accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; The same engineers that built the canal also built a substantial country house,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Rock House and adjacent range of outbuildings | work=Images of England | url=http://www.imagesofengland.org.uk/details/default.aspx?id=95391 | accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; turnpike house&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Turnpike Cottage | work=Images of England | url=http://www.imagesofengland.org.uk/details/default.aspx?id=95392 | accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; and cottages&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Cottage 100 metres east of Rock - House | work=Images of England | url=http://www.imagesofengland.org.uk/details/default.aspx?id=95390 | accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; at the site. Several other bridges, including Batten's Bridge,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Batten's Bridge | work=Images of England | url=http://www.imagesofengland.org.uk/details/default.aspx?id=95330 | accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Crownhills Bridge,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Crownhills Bridge | work=Images of England | url=http://www.imagesofengland.org.uk/details/default.aspx?id=95340 | accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Greenway Bridge&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Greenway Bridge | work=Images of England | url=http://www.imagesofengland.org.uk/details/default.aspx?id=95380 | accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Sellick Bridge&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Sellick Bridge | work=Images of England | url=http://www.imagesofengland.org.uk/details/default.aspx?id=95362 | accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; were also constructed at Halberton to carry minor roads over the canal.

[[Image:Gradnwesterncanalsampfordpeverell.jpg|alt=Water in front of trees, a house and a church.|thumb|left|The canal at Sampford Peverell where it cuts right through the village. The house in front of the church is the old vicarage which the company had to replace]]
With costs much higher than anticipated, work ceased in June 1811. After much deliberation, it was decided to continue construction, and to obtain a third Act of Parliament to authorise increased charges for carriage of goods. By 1812, progress was being made, but was hampered by the need for rock cuttings at [[Holcombe Rogus]]. Leakage also meant that some sections needed to be lined with [[Puddling (engineering)|puddle clay]]. Lime kilns were constructed to provide the materials, which can still be seen beside the canal,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Waytown Limekilns | work=Images of England | url=http://www.imagesofengland.org.uk/details/default.aspx?id=352085 | accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; close to the Waytown Tunnel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Waytown Tunnel | work=Images of England | url=http://www.imagesofengland.org.uk/details/default.aspx?id=95949 | accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fenacre Bridge&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Fenacre Bridge at Burlescombe | work=Images of England | url=http://www.imagesofengland.org.uk/details/default.aspx?id=352088 | accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Fossend Bridge&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Fossend Canal Bridge at Burlescombe | work=Images of England | url=http://www.imagesofengland.org.uk/details/default.aspx?id=95882 | accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; were constructed at [[Burlescombe]], where culverts were also needed to manage the streams.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Twin Culverts at Burlescombe | work=Images of England | url=http://www.imagesofengland.org.uk/details/default.aspx?id=352087 | accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; At a total cost of £244,505, the canal was opened on 25 August 1814, when the first boat travelled from Lowdwells to Tiverton, laden with coal.&lt;ref name=harris/&gt;

At [[Sampford Peverell]] two rectories were built in 1836, at the expense of the Grand Western Canal Company, in compensation for cutting through the grounds and demolishing the south wing of the Old Rectory.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Sampford Peverell The Old Rectory | work=Images of England | url=http://www.imagesofengland.org.uk/details/default.aspx?id=95997 | accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Sampford Peverell The Rectory | work=Images of England | url=http://www.imagesofengland.org.uk/details/default.aspx?id=95997 | accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two road bridges were also needed in the village.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Sampford Peverell Bridge | work=Images of England | url=http://www.imagesofengland.org.uk/details/default.aspx?id=96005 | accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Buckland Bridge | work=Images of England | url=http://www.imagesofengland.org.uk/details/default.aspx?id=96006 | accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Second Phase===
[[Image:Gradnwesterncanallimekilns.jpg|alt=A footpath to the left, water in the centre of the picture and on the right a stone wall with arch shaped openings.|thumb|left|A bank of limekilns at Waytown, [[Holcombe Rogus]].]]
[[File:Grand Western Canal Aqueduct at Nynehead.JPG|thumb|left|This fine ashlar arch carried the canal over the drive to [[Nynehead Court]].]]
Traffic on the opened section was much lower than anticipated, and the prospects of building the rest of the canal dwindled, as profits were minimal. However, in 1829 [[James Green (engineer)|James Green]] turned his attention to the link to Taunton. He had been the architect of the [[Bude Canal]], which was built for [[Tub boat|tub-boats]] and used inclined planes to change levels, and proposed a similar solution here. The [[Bridgwater and Taunton Canal]] had opened in 1827, making navigation from Taunton to [[Bridgwater]] easier than on the River Tone. In a report of 1830, Green proposed using vertical lifts instead of inclined planes, and estimated the cost of the canal at £65,000.&lt;ref name=harris/&gt;

Work started in 1831, and progressed quickly, including the construction of a bridge at [[Bradford on Tone]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Bridge over Grand Western Canal at Trefusis Farm, Bradford on Tone | work=Images of England | url=http://www.imagesofengland.org.uk/details/default.aspx?id=270944 | accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Harpford Bridge at [[Langford Budville]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Harpford Bridge over remains of Grand Western Canal, Langford Budville | work=Images of England | url=http://www.imagesofengland.org.uk/details/default.aspx?id=270979 | accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; where a new warehouse was also built.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Warehouse about 25 a west of Harpford Bridge, Langford Budville | work=Images of England | url=http://www.imagesofengland.org.uk/details/default.aspx?id=270980 | accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to the boat lift in [[Nynehead]]&lt;ref name=&quot;nyneheadliftremians&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nyneheadlift&quot;/&gt; two aqueducts were required within the village.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Aqueduct, formerly carrying Grand Western Canal over driveway to Nynehead Court | work=Images of England | url=http://www.imagesofengland.org.uk/details/default.aspx?id=270995 | accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Aqueduct formerly carrying the Grand Western Canal over the River Tone, now disused | work=Images of England | url=http://www.imagesofengland.org.uk/details/default.aspx?id=270996 | accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The route in Taunton was altered to connect to the Bridgwater and Taunton Canal directly, rather than using a short stretch of the River Tone. Seven lifts and one inclined plane were to be built, and it was these features that caused the subsequent delay in the completion of the canal. Teething problems with the design of the lifts gradually came to light, and although the cost of rectifying these was borne by Green, the canal could not be opened. There were also problems with the inclined plane. The canal was partially opened to [[Wellington, Somerset|Wellington]], in 1835; but in January 1836, Green was dismissed.&lt;ref name=harris/&gt;

===Completion===
The engineer W A Provis was asked to survey the works, and to report on the lifts and the causes of the failure of the plane. His clear report is an important source of information on the canal at the time of its construction. Some remedial work was instigated, following the report, including the provision of a steam engine to power the Wellisford incline. The {{convert|14|mi|km|1}} extension was fully opened on 28 June 1838, at a cost of about £80,000.&lt;ref name=harris/&gt;

==Boat lifts==
{{Main|Boat lift}}
[[File:Grand Western Lift.svg|alt=Diagrammatic representation of chambers with caisons being raised and lower on chains below a wheel.|thumb|right|Diagram showing the arrangement of the boat lifts]]
Green's use of boat lifts was innovative. The idea was not new, as he acknowledged in an article describing the lifts which he published in ''Transactions''&lt;ref&gt;Transactions of the Institution of Civil Engineers, Volume 2, 1838&lt;/ref&gt; in 1838, having been suggested in principle by a Dr James Anderson of Edinburgh in 1796. Robert Weldon had tried to build one on the [[Somerset Coal Canal|Somersetshire Coal Canal]] in 1798, which was replaced by an inclined plane after persistent failures. One was built at [[Ruabon]] on the [[Ellesmere Canal]] in 1796, but was replaced as it was not robust enough for regular use. [[James Fussell IV|James Fussell]] built one on the abortive [[Dorset and Somerset Canal]], but the works were abandoned before it was ever used regularly. The lift at [[Tardebigge Locks|Tardebigge]] on the [[Worcester and Birmingham Canal]] was replaced by [[Tardebigge Locks|locks]] in 1815 as it was &quot;too complex and delicate&quot;, according to Rennie. Finally, another lift at [[Camden Town]] on the [[Regent's Canal]] was replaced by locks in 1815 because it could not be made to work.&lt;ref name=harris/&gt;

===Principles===
With no working prototypes, Green set about building seven lifts. The principle was simple. Two caissons were suspended from three carrying wheels of {{convert|16|ft|m|0}} diameter, by wrought iron chains. The caisson at the bottom was jacked against the front wall of the lift to seal it, and a door or gate was opened to allow the boat to float in. The caisson at the top was jacked against the back wall in a similar manner. When both boats were in, the doors on the caissons and lift were closed, and the jacks released. Because a boat displaces its own weight in water, the system should be balanced, and a small amount of energy is required to start the boats moving. When the top caisson reaches the bottom, the jacks are applied, the doors are opened, and the boats can continue.&lt;ref name=harris/&gt;

In order to maintain the balance, a second chain was fixed to the bottom of the caisson, so that the total length of chain on each side of the lift remained the same. As a caisson descended, the chain coiled up at the bottom of the lift. The small amount of energy was created by ensuring that the ascending caisson was a little too low by the time the descending one reached the bottom. Thus it would hold a greater depth of water by the time it was ready to descend again. In practice, about {{convert|2|in|cm|0}} of water, weighing about a ton, was found to be sufficient.&lt;ref name=harris/&gt;

===Problems===
The difficulty was that Anderson had suggested that the water in the caisson chambers should be at a lower level than that in the canal. This had not been implemented, and so the lower caisson would not sink deep enough for either boat to be floated out. Attempts to fit gates and to let the water in the chamber drain to waste had proved ineffective. Ultimately, lock chambers were built at the foot of the each lift. These were filled with water from the upper level, so that the boat could float out, and it then descended the final {{convert|3|ft|m|1}} as it would in a conventional lock. Only the lift at Greenham used Anderson's principle, and included a proper drain to lower the level in the chambers.&lt;ref name=harris/&gt;

[[File:Grand Western plane.svg|alt=Diagrammatic representation of the working of an inclined plane with water lower on the left than on the right with a chain running up the slope between them.|thumb|right|Diagram showing the arrangement of the Wellisford inclined plane]]
With the inclined plane, the problems stemmed from a mis-calculation. Power was provided by a large tank, filled with water, which descended in a shaft, raising one boat on a trolley and allowing another to descend as it did so. When the tank reached the bottom of the shaft, the water discharged, and the second tank was used to reverse the process. Green had been the engineer on the [[Bude Canal]], where this design had been used successfully, but the size of the tanks at Wellisford were much too small. On the Bude Canal, a tank holding 15&amp;nbsp;tons of water was required to raise a boat weighing six tons. The Grand Western Canal used boats holding eight tons, but the tanks only held ten tons of water, whereas tests indicated that about 25&amp;nbsp;tons was needed. It was for this reason that the steam engine was obtained to supply the power.&lt;ref name=harris/&gt;

===Locations of the boat lifts===
[[File:Nynehead Boat Lift.JPG|thumb|Remains of Nynehead Boat Lift.]]
{{PoIgb start}}
{{PoIgb|Greenham Lift|50.972|-3.310|ST080200|42&amp;nbsp;ft (12.8&amp;nbsp;m)}}
{{PoIgb|Wellisford Plane|50.987|-3.282|ST100216|81&amp;nbsp;ft rise 440&amp;nbsp;ft long (24.7&amp;nbsp;m x 134&amp;nbsp;m)}}
{{PoIgb|Winsbeer Lift|50.991|-3.254|ST120220|18&amp;nbsp;ft (5.5&amp;nbsp;m)}}
{{PoIgb|Nynehead Lift|50.991|-3.226|ST140220|24&amp;nbsp;ft (7.3&amp;nbsp;m)}}
{{PoIgb|Trefusis Lift|51.001|-3.197|ST160230|38.5&amp;nbsp;ft (11.7&amp;nbsp;m)}}
{{PoIgb|Allerford Lift|51.018|-3.169|ST180250|19&amp;nbsp;ft (5.8&amp;nbsp;m)}}
{{PoIgb|Norton Fitzwarren Lift|51.019|-3.155|ST190250|12.5&amp;nbsp;ft (3.8&amp;nbsp;m)}}
{{PoIgb|Taunton Lift|51.022|-3.102|ST228253|23.5&amp;nbsp;ft (7.2&amp;nbsp;m)}}
{{PoIgb end}}
{{kml}}

==Operation==
[[Image:Gradnwesterncanaltiverton.jpg|alt=A narrow boat moored alongside grassy area. Houses can be seen in the background.|thumb|left|The terminus at [[Tiverton, Devon|Tiverton]]. A series of old limekilns built into the superstructure survive underneath the elevated canal terminus]]
The Somerset section of the canal was suitable for tub-boats, which were about {{convert|20|ft|m|1}} long and capable of carrying eight tons. The Devon section was suitable for larger broad-beam barges, carrying up to 40&amp;nbsp;tons. Income from tolls increased steadily from £971 in 1835, rising to £2754 in 1838 and £4926 in 1844. At this point, competition from the railways started. The [[Bristol and Exeter Railway]] reached Taunton in 1842 and Exeter in 1844. A branch to [[Tiverton, Devon|Tiverton]] was opened in 1848, and although the canal company received £1200 for loss of trade while an aqueduct was constructed over the line of the railway, deficits started to mount up almost immediately.&lt;ref name=harris/&gt;

In 1853, with income no longer meeting operational costs, the canal was leased to the Bristol and Exeter Railway. From 1854, the company started to pay a dividend to its shareholders of 0.2%. Just ten years later, an [[Act of Parliament]] was obtained to sell the canal to the railway company and to abandon the Somerset section of the canal. The transfer took place on 13 April 1865, and the tub-boat canal was closed in 1867. The lifts were dismantled, and most of the route sold back to the original landowners.&lt;ref name=harris/&gt;

===Decline===
Limestone traffic continued on the Tiverton section. Only two boats were working the canal by 1904, and the last commercial traffic was roadstone from Whipcott quarry to Tiverton, where there was a crushing plant. Around 7,000&amp;nbsp;tons per year were transported up to 1925. After this the only income was from the washing of [[sheep]], for which a charge was made for every 20 sheep, and the sale of [[Nymphaeaceae|water lilies]] which grew in the canal. In the 1930s, dams were built at both ends of a section near Halberton, where persistent leakage could not be cured.&lt;ref name=harris/&gt;

Having passed into the ownership of the [[Great Western Railway]] in 1888, the canal became the responsibility of the [[British Transport Commission]] when the railways were nationalised in 1948, and was formally closed in 1962. The responsibility for it passed to the [[British Waterways Board]] in 1964.&lt;ref name=harris/&gt;

==Restoration==
[[Image:Gradnwesterncanalbradford.jpg|alt=Stream running through channel overgrown with vegetation.|thumb|The remains of the old canal by Trefusis Farm, [[Bradford on Tone]]. One of the canal’s seven lifts was located near here.]]
With various plans for using the route of the canal for landfill and for a bypass, some local interest was aroused regarding its future. The Tiverton Canal Preservation Committee was formed in 1962. This committee was stirred to action by plans in 1966 to infill parts of the canal so that housing could be built over it. Tiverton Borough Council gave the committee the power to negotiate with the [[British Waterways Board]] in March 1967, but the Board were unwilling to offer financial assistance.&lt;ref name=harris/&gt;

Changes in legislation aided the cause. From 1968, county councils could set up [[country park]]s, under the [[Countryside Act 1968]], and the [[Transport Act 1968]] enabled the British Waterways Board to allow local authorities to maintain or purchase inland waterways. By 1969, BWB had stated that they were prepared to hand over the canal to Devon County Council, together with some money for maintenance. With some representatives within the council wavering, the preservation committee organised a walk along the entire canal on 18 October 1969. Around 400 walkers set off, with the local member of Parliament firing a starting gun, and by the time Tiverton was reached, the party totalled about 1200 people.&lt;ref name=harris/&gt;

===Handover===
[[Image:Gradnwesterncanalswansneck.jpg|alt=Cyclist on tow path to the left of canal under trees.|thumb|Cycling beside the canal at the &quot;Swan's Neck&quot; north west of [[Halberton]]]]
[[File:Grand Western Canal Aqueduct over the RiverTone.JPG|thumb|Remains of the aqueduct over the River Tone. The cast iron trough on the right carried the canal and the tow path was to the left]]
By April 1970, the British Waterways Board had agreed to give the canal to Devon County Council, with £30,000 for maintenance. The actual contract was signed on 5 May 1971 at Tiverton Town Hall, when General Sir [[Hugh Stockwell]] of the BWB also handed over a cheque for £38,750 to Colonel Eric Palmer, chairman of Devon County Council. The transfer of the canal was effective from 24 June 1971.&lt;ref name=harris/&gt;

The new owners set to work immediately. The dry section was excavated and lined with a [[Butyl rubber|butyl]] [[Pond liner|liner]] to prevent leakage. The canal was reopened in 1971.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Russell |first=Ronald |title=Lost Canals of England and Wales |year=1971 |publisher=[[David &amp; Charles]] |location=Newton Abbot, Devon |isbn=0-7153-5417-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Navigation was restricted to unpowered boats, with the exception of a maintenance boat that was used for cutting weed, while the final section from Fossend to Lowdwells, which would have been part of the original main line to [[Exeter]], is designated as a [[nature reserve]], and so all navigation and angling is discouraged.&lt;ref name=harris/&gt; The canal is now a designated [[country park]], and a horse-drawn tourist narrowboat runs from Tiverton. Since 2003 powered boats have been allowed on the Canal, subject to Licence from Devon County Council. The Canal is also a very popular Coarse Fishing spot  and angling rights on the Canal are leased to the Tiverton and District Angling Club. In addition to holding a valid Environment Agency Rod Licence, a permit must be purchased in advance.

The Somerset section is largely dry and is gradually disappearing into the landscape, as a result of roads improvements and ploughing, but a footpath has been established along much of its route, and archaeological excavations of the lift at [[Nynehead]], the only one where there are still substantial remains,&lt;ref name=&quot;nyneheadliftremians&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=Remains of vertical lift on former Grand Western Canal. | work=Images of England | url=http://www.imagesofengland.org.uk/details/default.aspx?id=270999 | accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nyneheadlift&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nynehead.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=27&amp;Itemid=87 |title=The Boat Lift on The Grand Western at Nynehead |accessdate=2009-12-03 |format= |work=Nynehead Village Web Site }}&lt;/ref&gt; were carried out between 1998 and 2003 by the [[Somerset Industrial Archaeological Society]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rchs.org.uk/trial/6-1%20Boat%20lifts%20GWC.pdf|title=The Boat Lifts of the Grand Western Canal, Denis Dodd, Railway and Canal Historical Society|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== 2012 breach and repair ==
Exceptionally heavy rainfall in November 2012 caused a major break in the Grand Western Canal's banks, near [[Halberton]], necessitating nearby homes to be evacuated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Great Western Canal runs DRY after one side collapses in torrential rain |url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2235946/Great-Western-Canal-runs-DRY-embankment-collapses-torrential-rain-fierce-winds.html|accessdate=31 August 2013|newspaper=Daily Mail|date=20 November 2012|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Grand Western Canal breach captured at Halberton, Devon|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-20450182|accessdate=24 November 2012|newspaper=BBC News|date=22 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two temporary dams were installed which allowed the rest of the canal to remain open&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| title =Grand Western Canal repairs costing £3m begin| url =http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-devon-23223338| date = 8 July 2013| accessdate = 31 August 2013| work=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt; and meant the horse drawn barge at Tiverton was able to run throughout the summer of 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title =Tourists think Tiverton's Grand Western Canal has no water in it, says businessman| url =http://www.thisisdevon.co.uk/Tourists-think-Tiverton-s-Grand-Western-Canal/story-19453330-detail/story.html#axzz2dZKuj4RL| date = 2 July 2013 | accessdate = 31 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Around 400 fish were returned to the canal from a flooded field but many fish including pike, eels, perch, bream, tench and roach were lost. About 25 people from the Environment Agency and Tiverton Angling Club assisted with saving the fish.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| title =Breached Grand Western Canal to be restocked with fish| url =http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-devon-20732450| date = 16 December 2012| accessdate = 31 August 2013| work=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Environment Agency restocked the canal with 3,000 fish in January 2013 and by May the Environment Agency said they were flourishing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| title = Fish stock in breached Grand Western Canal now 'flourishing'| url =http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-devon-22463009| date =11 May 2013 | accessdate = 31 August 2013| work=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Devon County Council agreed to pay for repairs to the canal, in time for its 200th anniversary and on 7 July 2013, a 3 million pound project to repair the breach, began with an official turf cutting. The repairs included rebuilding the failed embankment and raising the level to reduce the risk of overtopping in the future, and further improvements to water management.The canal was lined with an impermeable material along the length of the embankment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title =Turf cutting marks start of Grand Western Canal repairs| url =http://www.tivertonian.co.uk/tivertonian-news/tivertonian-events/item/680-turf-cutting-marks-start-of-grand-western-canal-repairs.html| date = 9 July 2013| accessdate = 31 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition a water level monitoring and alarm system has been installed. This system has sensors in Tiverton and Burlescombe and alerts the canal rangers and Devon County Council if the levels become exceptionally high.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title = Water levels managed 'better than ever before'|date = 7 January 2014|last = Wevill|last2 = Richard|work = Culm Valley Gazette|pages = 14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Refilling of the breached section began on 4 March 2014 using a  [[sluice]] gate at Rock Bridge which gradually filled the empty section&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| title=Water pours back into repaired section of Tiverton canal |url=http://www.middevongazette.co.uk/Water-pours-repaired-section-Tiverton-canal/story-20752611-detail/story.html | accessdate = 4 March 2014|newspaper= Mid Devon Gazette|date = 4 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the canal was officially re-opened on 19 March 2014 by chairman of Devon County Council Councillor Bernard Hughes.  Six narrow boats, led by Chairmen of Halberton Parish Council, Councillor Ken Browse, were the first to travel on the new section.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| title= Narrow boats return for first journey on fixed canal |url=http://www.middevongazette.co.uk/Narrow-boats-return-journey-fixed-canal/story-20829229-detail/story.html | accessdate = 19 March 2014|newspaper= Mid Devon Gazette|date = 19 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|UK Waterways}}
*[[Waterways in the United Kingdom]]

==References==
{{reflist |colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons Category|Grand Western Canal}}
*[http://www.devon.gov.uk/grand_western_canal Grand Western Canal home page] (on Devon County Council website)
*[http://www.discovertiverton.co.uk/attraction_details.asp?attractionID=48 GWC Information]
{{Canals of Britain}}

{{good article}}

[[Category:Canals in Devon]]
[[Category:Canals in Somerset]]
[[Category:History of Somerset]]
[[Category:History of Devon]]
[[Category:Canals opened in 1814]]
[[Category:Canals opened in 1839]]
[[Category:1814 establishments in England]]
[[Category:Industrial archaeological sites in Devon]]
[[Category:Industrial archaeological sites in Somerset]]</text>
      <sha1>81r6sxtmt9i17g08xuiz53dmixs7jeo</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
