<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Grayrigg derailment</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9675955</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745337403</id>
      <parentid>740203129</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-20T15:17:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>RuthAS</username>
        <id>5365701</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Incident */ Add improved image of the Docker bridge WCML</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25602">{{EngvarB|date=August 2014}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2014}}
{{Infobox rail accident
| title      = Grayrigg derailment
| image      = VirginPendolinoDerailment.jpg
| caption    = &lt;small&gt;The scene of the accident&lt;/small&gt;
| date       = 23 February 2007
| time       = 20:15 [[GMT]]
| location   = [[Grayrigg]], Cumbria
| coordinates= {{coord|54.357|-2.660|region:GB_type:event|display=inline,title}}
| country    = England
| line       = [[West Coast Main Line]]
| operator   = [[Virgin Trains]]
| type       = 
| cause      = Defective points due to poor maintenance and inspection procedures.
| trains     = 1
| pax        = 105 + 4 crew&lt;ref name=Final&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.gov.uk/raib-reports/derailment-at-grayrigg |title=Derailment at Grayrigg 23 February 2007 |publisher=Rail Accident Investigation Branch |accessdate=7 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| deaths     = 1
| injuries   = 30 serious, 58 minor&lt;ref name=Final/&gt;
| footnotes  = [[List of rail accidents in the United Kingdom|List of UK rail accidents by year]]
}}

The '''Grayrigg derailment''' was a fatal [[Train wreck|railway accident]] that occurred at approximately 20:15 [[Greenwich Mean Time|GMT]] on 23 February 2007, just to the south of [[Grayrigg]], Cumbria, in the [[North West England]] region of the United Kingdom. The initial conclusion of the accident investigation is that the [[derailment]] was caused by a faulty set of [[Railroad switch|points]] (number 2B) on the Down Main running line, controlled from Lambrigg [[Lever frame#Ground frames|ground frame]]. The scheduled inspection on 18 February 2007 had not taken place and the faults had gone undetected.&lt;ref name=BBC6398057&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/6398057.stm|title=Rail crash report blames points|publisher=[[BBC News Online]] | date=26 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the accident killed far fewer people than some other accidents on the West Coast Main Line, it had a major negative impact on Network Rail's safety record.

== Incident ==
The 17:30 [[Virgin West Coast]] [[British Rail Class 390|''Pendolino'']] [[West Coast Main Line]] InterCity service from [[Euston railway station|London Euston]] to [[Glasgow Central railway station|Glasgow Central]] derailed at 20:15 by a faulty set of points almost immediately after crossing the Docker Viaduct (the rear half of the train would still have been crossing the bridge whilst the front derailed at the points).&lt;ref name=&quot;virgin&quot;&gt;{{cite press release| url=http://www.virgintrainsmediaroom.com/index.cfm?articleid=1004 | title=Serious incident in Cumbria&amp;nbsp;– Statement No. 3–24 February 2007 | publisher=Virgin Trains| date=24 February 2007| accessdate=24 February 2007|archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070927235205/http://www.virgintrainsmediaroom.com/index.cfm?articleid=1004 |archivedate = 27 September 2007|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; The train was reported to have been travelling at {{convert|95|mph|abbr=on|disp=flip}} when it was derailed.&lt;ref name=BBC6391633&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/6391633.stm|title=One dead in Cumbria train crash |publisher=[[BBC News Online]] | date=24 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The train consisted of unit 390033 '&lt;nowiki/&gt;''City of Glasgow''', which was constructed at [[Washwood Heath]], Birmingham in 2002, and nine carriages. It carried 105&amp;nbsp;passengers and four crew.&lt;ref name=Final/&gt;
[[File:Docker Viaduct 19.10.2016.jpg|thumb|right|Docker Viaduct carrying the [[West Coast Main Line]] just south of the site of the accident. The rear half of the train would have been crossing the bridge whilst the front derailed at the points immediately north of the bridge.]]
Passengers said that the [[Railroad car|carriages]] of the train began rocking and swaying violently before the train left the rails and careered down an embankment, with the first carriages jack-knifing and most of the train coming to rest in a field. The train was reported as being evacuated around midnight. Emergency crews scanned the train with [[Thermographic camera|thermal imagery equipment]] to make sure there was no one still inside. Up to 500 rescuers attended the scene, along with at least 12 ambulances, at least five [[fire apparatus|fire engines]], three [[Royal Air Force]] [[Westland Sea King|Sea King]] [[RAF Search and Rescue Force|search and rescue]] helicopters, the [[International Rescue Corps]], three civilian mountain rescue teams plus [[RAF Leeming]] [[Royal Air Force Mountain Rescue Service|Mountain Rescue Team]], and one [[Merseyside Police]] helicopter. The rescue operation was hindered by rain, darkness, and access problems caused by the narrow country lanes and muddy fields.&lt;ref name=BBC6398057 /&gt; Emergency vehicles experienced difficult conditions, needing to be towed by farm vehicles or tractors after becoming bogged down in mud.
The train's derailment caused severe damage to the [[Overhead line|Overhead Line Equipment]] and tripped the entire circuit between Brock (near [[Preston, Lancashire|Preston]]) and [[Tebay]] resulting in a number of other electric-powered services coming to a halt and all signalling equipment immediately turning to danger (red) in accordance with the system's [[fail safe]] design.

Live BBC television coverage at 08:15 the following morning showed that although the whole train had been derailed, the rear carriages were standing nearly vertically on the sleepers and ballast. Standard class, the front five carriages, were the worst affected, and the rear four first class carriages were in better condition. The leading carriage, a driving motor coach, had headed down the embankment, and turned end-for-end as it fell. It was lying on its side at the foot of the embankment. The second carriage had jack-knifed against the first, breaking the coupling, and so had not followed it down the bank. This second carriage came to rest some distance further along the track, at a steep angle with one end in the air. The middle part of the train toppled sideways down the embankment. All the partially [[friction stir welding|friction stir welded]] carriages remained structurally intact, with damage mainly confined to the [[crumple zone]]s at their ends. None of the windows broke, and lighting remained in all the carriages. Most injuries occurred in the front two carriages. The driver, who had stayed at the controls (but had little option to move once the accident had started and had no prior indication of derailment), was trapped for about an hour while specialist cutting equipment was used to free him from his cab.&lt;ref name=BBC2/&gt; The other three members of the crew were in the rear first class section of the train.

Survivors were initially received at Grayrigg Primary School, which had been opened as a Survivor Reception Centre. Hospitals in the area, including some over the Scottish border in [[Dumfries and Galloway]], were put on standby, but not all received patients. According to BBC News, five passengers were admitted to [[Royal Preston Hospital]] in a critical condition. Police later released a statement revealing that one passenger, 84-year-old Margaret Masson from [[Glasgow]], had died in hospital. Her funeral took place on 31 March 2007 at [[Craigton, Glasgow|Craigton]] crematorium in Glasgow.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newsandstar.co.uk/news/1.69817|title=Rail Victim's Funeral|publisher=News &amp; Star|date=31 March 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Diagram start --&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;thumb tright&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #f9f9f9; border: 1px solid #CCCCCC; margin:0.5em;&quot;&gt;
{| border=&quot;0&quot; cellpadding=&quot;10&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 85%; border: 1px solid #CCCCCC; margin: 0.3em;&quot;
|-
|{{Image label begin|image=Cumbriarailcrash.svg|width=300}}
{{Image label|x=-74.0|y=-367.0|scale=-1|text=[[Oxenholme Lake District railway station|Oxenholme]]}}
{{Image label|x=-17.0|y=-339.0|scale=-1|text=[[Kendal]]}}
{{Image label|x=-176.0|y=-214.0|scale=-1|text=[[Grayrigg]]}}
{{Image label|x=-263.0|y=-50.0|scale=-1|text=[[Tebay]]}}
{{Image label|x=-9.0|y=-404.0|scale=-1|text=[[West Coast Main Line]]}}
{{Image label|x=-189.0|y=-356.0|scale=-1|text=[[M6 motorway]]}}
{{Image label small|x=-124.0|y=-261.0|scale=-1|text=Site of accident}}

{{Image label end}}
|}
&lt;div style=&quot;border: none;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;thumbcaption&quot;&gt;The location of the accident&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!-- Diagram end --&gt;

== Aftermath ==
A family liaison centre was set up in [[Glasgow Central Station]] for worried relatives.

Within three hours of the derailment the site of the accident had been sealed off with a five-mile cordon. The line was expected to be closed for two weeks, with [[Virgin Trains]] saying that the line would not reopen to passenger services until 12 March 2007.&lt;ref name=BBC3/&gt; The recovery operation was slowed by problems in getting [[lifting gear|heavy lifting gear]] to the site which required temporary roads to be constructed.

[[Richard Branson|Sir Richard Branson]], [[Virgin Group]] chairman, visited the site of the derailment at 11:00 the following morning to comment on the incident. During his news conference at the site he said that he regarded the driver, named as Iain Black from [[Dumbarton]],&lt;ref name=BBC4&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/scotland/6480567.stm|title=Hero train driver tells of ordeal|date=22 March 2007|publisher=[[BBC News Online]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; as a hero, as he had attempted to stop the train and remained in his seat to ensure the safety of passengers.&lt;ref name=BBC2/&gt; Black left hospital in late March and stated that &quot;I've got to be in the cab to help the train and it never crossed my mind to leave.&quot;&lt;ref name=BBC4/&gt;

Branson also later thanked local residents for their help at the accident site, describing how he &quot;was very impressed to hear how those kind people rallied round, opening their hearts and opening their doors to strangers in distress&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thewestmorlandgazette.co.uk/news/kendaltrainderails/newsderailment/display.var.1230829.0.community_praised_for_heroic_response.php|title=Community praised for heroic response|publisher=Westmorland Gazette|date = 2 March 2007|accessdate = 15 April 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Local farmers assisted the emergency services by transporting equipment using [[quad bike]]s and [[four-wheel drive]] vehicles. Sergeant Jo Fawcett of the [[Cumbria Constabulary]] also offered thanks, saying that &quot;There are so many people who have given up their own time to contribute in some way to dealing with the aftermath of the derailment that it would be unfair to name them for fear of missing someone out.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/cumbria/6421909.stm|title=Praise for rail crash site locals|publisher=[[BBC News Online]]|date=6 April 2007|accessdate=15 April 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Branson also paid tribute to the [[British Rail Class 390|Pendolino]] train, comparing it to a &quot;tank&quot;. He also added &quot;If the train had been old stock then the number of injuries and the mortalities would have been horrendous&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/6392935.stm|title= It is a very sad day&amp;nbsp;– Branson|publisher=BBC News|date = 24 February 2007|accessdate = 26 September 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Several sources also gave their praise due to the fact that the carriages generally stayed intact during the accident.

As a result of the suspicion that faulty points were the cause of the Grayrigg Derailment, [[Network Rail]] checked over 700 sets of similar points across the country as a &quot;precautionary measure&quot;&lt;ref name=BBC3&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/6393867.stm | title=Crash sparks national rail checks | publisher=[[BBC News Online]] | date=24 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; saying later that &quot;nothing of concern&quot; had been found.&lt;ref name=OtherPointsOK&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/6394451.stm | title=Network safe, rail bosses insist | publisher=[[BBC News Online]] | date=25 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The operation to remove the train from the site began on the evening of 1 March 2007 with the first carriages moved from the embankment. This allowed passengers' property to be retrieved and gave investigators access to the train interior, which previously had not been possible because it would have been unsafe.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/cumbria/6410631.stm|title=First carriages moved from wreck|publisher=[[BBC News Online]]|date=2 March 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The last of the carriages were removed on 4 March 2007 and the [[A685 road]] was reopened.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thisisthelakedistrict.co.uk/display.var.1235443.0.last_rails_cars_and_crane_shipped_out.php|title =Last rails cars and crane 'shipped out'|publisher=Westmorland Gazette|date=5 March 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The points which caused the derailment, and points 2A on the opposite line, were removed from the track following the derailment and the line is now welded continuously for {{convert|2.2|mi}} including the line over the Docker viaduct.

The derailment also brought down the [[overhead line equipment]] which had to be replaced. Modern double-line catenary from a single stand was used for this, which reduces the risk of carriages bending if a derailment occurs, for example becoming wedged between the overhead line stanchions as seen in the [[Southall rail crash|Southall crash]]. 

In 2013 the [[British Transport Police]] (BTP) [[wikt:posthumously|posthumously]] awarded a Chief Constables Commendation to a member of its staff, Jon Ratcliffe, who was at the time of the disaster Media and Marketing Manager for BTP's North Western Area. He received the commendation for his good handling of media enquires in the aftermath of the crash. Jon Ratcliffe died in 2008 following a sudden illness.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.btp.police.uk/latest_news/local_news_north_western/posthumous_commendation.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;

== Cause ==
Lambrigg ground frame, {{convert|660|yd|m}} south-west of the accident site, controls two crossovers, each one comprising two sets of [[railroad switch|points]] allowing trains to cross from one running line to the other in emergencies or during track maintenance work. These points are used only occasionally, operated locally after a release is obtained from [[Carlisle, Cumbria|Carlisle]] power [[signal box]]. They are normally locked in the main line &quot;running&quot; position. Early statements by Chief Superintendent Martyn Ripley of [[British Transport Police]] suggested that investigations would focus on these points.

Investigations were launched by the [[Rail Accident Investigation Branch]] and [[HM Railway Inspectorate|Her Majesty's Railway Inspectorate]].&lt;ref name=BBC2&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/6392197.stm|title=Crash inquiry to focus on points|publisher=[[BBC News Online]] | date=24 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[National Union of Rail, Maritime and Transport Workers|RMT]] rail union leader [[Bob Crow]] said on BBC News that a points failure was responsible for the incident. Experts compared the cause to that of the [[Potters Bar rail crash]] in 2002.&lt;ref name=BBC3/&gt;

On 26 February, an interim report published by the [[Rail Accident Investigation Branch]] outlined the current progress of the investigation.&lt;ref name=raib&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.raib.gov.uk/cms_resources/070226_I012007_Grayrigg.pdf|title=RAIB interim report into a derailment at Grayrigg, Cumbria 23 February 2007|publisher=Rail Accident Investigation Branch}} Note: passenger numbers subsequently revised from 111 to 105 in final report.&lt;/ref&gt; The report contained a single conclusion, that the immediate cause of the accident was the condition of the stretcher bar arrangement at points 2B at Lambrigg crossover, which resulted in the loss of [[rail gauge|gauge separation]] of the point switch blades. The stretcher bars (components that hold the moving blades of the points the correct distance apart) had been found to be disconnected or missing. Of the three bars, one was not in position, another had nuts and bolts missing, and two were fractured. The points in question were facing the direction of travel of the train.

Following the RAIB report, [[Network Rail]] released a statement in which its Chief Executive, [[John Armitt]], described how the organisation was &quot;devastated to conclude that the condition of the set of points at [[Grayrigg]] caused this terrible accident&quot;. He apologised &quot;to all the people affected by the failure of the infrastructure&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.networkrail.co.uk/aspx/4008.aspx|title=Network Rail responds to initial RAIB report|publisher=[[Network Rail]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The RAIB report noted that the [[Network Rail New Measurement Train]] ran over the site on 21 February. This train uses [[laser]]s and other instruments to make measurements of the [[track geometry]] and other features such as overhead line height and stagger, and the track gauge, twist and cant. It is not used to inspect points, but it does make a video record of the track which can be reviewed later. Responding to the suggestion that the train's video might have been used to detect the points damage and thereby prevent the accident, a Network Rail spokesman said:

&lt;blockquote&gt;The [inspection] train runs at speeds of up to 125&amp;nbsp;mph, or 95&amp;nbsp;mph on this stretch. There would be no point somebody watching it at that speed as they wouldn't be able to pick up any faults. It has to be run in super-slow motion to spot faults. The train runs for up to 18&amp;nbsp;hours a day, seven days a week. It would probably take someone most of the month to watch one day's worth of data. It's not what it's there for. It's a backwards reference tool.&lt;ref name=&quot;mirror&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Network Rail admitted it failed to carry out a scheduled visual track inspection in the area on the Sunday before the derailment.{{Citation needed|date=September 2016}}

[[Bob Crow]] of [[National Union of Rail, Maritime and Transport Workers|the RMT union]] said:

&lt;blockquote&gt;This is shutting the stable door after the horse has well and truly bolted. We argued this train should not replace visual inspections. Inspectors who walk the track are the eyes and ears of the railway. They don't just check the safety of the track, they look at the area surrounding it, check for signs of potential trouble such as gaps in the fence where vandals could get in.&lt;ref name=&quot;mirror&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.mirror.co.uk/news/topstories/tm_headline=rail-chiefs-never-watched-broken-rail-vid%26method=full%26objectid=18684956%26siteid=89520-name_page.html| title=Rail Chiefs Never Watched Broken Rail Vid| publisher=Mirror.co.uk| date=28 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

As part of the investigation by the [[British Transport Police]], three Network Rail employees were arrested and bailed, one in July 2007 and two in November 2007&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/7097284.stm|title=Two men arrested over train crash |publisher=[[BBC News Online]]|date=15 November 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; All three were due to answer bail in March 2008 but this was extended until the end of June pending further inquiries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/7314174.stm|title=Three rail workers' bail extended  |publisher=[[BBC News Online]]|date=26 March 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 9 February 2009, the British Transport Police confirmed that none of the three Network Rail employees arrested in connection with the derailment will be charged following advice from the [[Crown Prosecution Service]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/cumbria/7879827.stm|title=No charges over fatal rail crash|publisher=[[BBC News Online]]|date=9 February 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Subsequent service disruption ==
Immediately after the accident, all services were suspended and the [[First ScotRail]] Sleeper train, the [[Caledonian Sleeper]], was curtailed and passengers transferred to overnight coaches.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/scotland/6392055.stm|title=Crash leads to travel disruption|publisher=[[BBC News Online]]|date=24 February 2007|accessdate=19 March 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The line closure that followed the initial service suspension saw most Virgin services terminate at [[Preston railway station|Preston]] or [[Lancaster railway station|Lancaster]] from the south, with buses to [[Carlisle railway station|Carlisle]] and all stations along the route. The only exception was an early-morning and late-evening through service from Carlisle to London and return. This was diesel-hauled via Blackburn and Settle. There were also several non-stop trains from [[Preston, Lancashire|Preston]] to [[London Euston]]. Local services all terminated short but many were able to make their journeys as their destinations were off branches. The [[Caledonian Sleeper]] was diverted via the [[East Coast Main Line]], along with freight services, although some were diesel-hauled via Blackburn and Settle.

Trains began running on the line again on 12 March subject to a speed restriction of {{convert|80|km/h|abbr=on}} at the crash site. The first train was the 05:10 [[Manchester Piccadilly station|Manchester]] to [[Glasgow Central station|Glasgow]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.sky.com/skynews/article/0,,30000-1255245,00.html|title=Trains Back on Crash Line|publisher=[[Sky News]]|accessdate=11 March 2007}} {{dead link| date=June 2010 | bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Prior incidents ==
The Grayrigg derailment was not the first [[List of rail accidents in the United Kingdom|British railway accident]] to feature a train or locomotive named ''City of Glasgow'' on the West Coast Mainline. In the [[Harrow and Wealdstone railway accident]] on 8 October 1952, the locomotive of the sleeper train from [[Perth, Scotland|Perth]] to [[Euston Station|London Euston]], whose crew was responsible for the incident, was [[LMS Princess Coronation Class|Class 8P]] No. 46242 ''City of Glasgow''.

In the area near the accident, south of [[Tebay]] in Cumbria, on 15 February 2004 another fatal incident had occurred, the [[Tebay rail accident]], when four rail workers were killed by a runaway track maintenance trailer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/4816206.stm | title=Pair jailed for Tebay rail deaths | publisher=[[BBC News Online]] | date=17 March 2006 | accessdate=24 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also close by was a collision on the Lambrigg Crossing on 18 May 1947.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://home.clara.net/gw0hqd/bumps/180547/180547.htm | title=Ministry of Transport Accident Report Between Grayrigg and Oxenholme, L.M.S.R., May 18, 1947 | publisher=[[Railway Gazette]] | accessdate=24 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Prosecution ==
On 13 January 2012, the [[Office of Rail Regulation]] announced that [[Network Rail]] were to be prosecuted under Section 3(1) of the [[Health and Safety at Work Act 1974]] for &quot;the company's failure to provide and implement suitable and sufficient standards, procedures, guidance, training, tools and resources for the inspection and maintenance of fixed stretcher bar points&quot;. At the first hearing at [[Lancaster, Lancashire|Lancaster]] [[Magistrates' Court (England and Wales)|Magistrates' Court]] on 28 February 2012, Network Rail indicated an intention to plead guilty to the charges.&lt;ref name=BBC16544694&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-cumbria-16544694 |title=Network Rail to be prosecuted over Grayrigg crash |publisher=BBC News Online |accessdate=13 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 4 April 2012, Network Rail were fined a total of £4,118,037 including costs following the court case.&lt;ref name=BBC17609369&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-cumbria-17609369 |title=Grayrigg crash: Network Rail fined £4m over death |publisher=BBC News Online |accessdate=4 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Critical commentary appeared in the media concerning the [[Knight Bachelor|knighthood]] awarded to [[John Armitt]] in the [[2012 New Year Honours]] for services to engineering and construction. Armitt had been Chief Executive of Network Rail at the time of the Grayrigg derailment, and the family of a victim of the accident criticised the award, which coincidentally was conferred on the same day that Network Rail were prosecuted for the accident.&lt;ref name=bbc-knighthood&gt;{{cite news|title=Grayrigg crash victim's son 'disgusted' by knighthood|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-cumbria-17223196|accessdate=2 March 2012|newspaper=BBC News|date=1 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After a two-week hearing one of the issues [[Coroner]] Ian Smith announced that he would be issuing a rule 43 report.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-cumbria-15593840|date=4 November 2011|publisher=BBC News|accessdate=10 July 2013|location=Cumbria|title=Grayrigg train crash: Faulty points caused woman's death}}&lt;/ref&gt; The intention of the report is to raise concerns with authorities to prevent similar incidents occurring again.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.irwinmitchell.com/newsandmedia/2011/november/lessons-must-be-learned-from-grayrigg-train-crash-inquest|last=Dixon|first=Rob|date=8 November 2011|publisher=Irwin Mitchell|accessdate=10 July 2013|location=Sheffield|title='Lessons Must Be Learned' From Grayrigg Train Crash Inquest}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{wikinews|Virgin Train crashes in England}}
* [[List of rail accidents in the United Kingdom]]
* [[List of rail accidents (2000–2009)]]

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}
{{2007 railway accidents}}
{{good article}}

[[Category:Railway accidents in Cumbria]]
[[Category:2007 in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Railway accidents in 2007]]
[[Category:History of Cumbria]]
[[Category:21st century in Cumbria]]
[[Category:Derailments in the United Kingdom]]</text>
      <sha1>2q6dqpgjmypfhttmvwv94itmq7ej14q</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
