<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Interstate 215 (Utah)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1677616</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749118019</id>
      <parentid>748661582</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-12T14:45:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Route description */clean up; http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and other Google services using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24533">{{Infobox road
|state=UT
|type=Interstate
|route=215
|alternate_name=
|section=127
|map=I-215 (UT) map.svg
|length_mi=28.946
|length_round=3
|length_ref=&lt;ref name=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=Interstate 215 Reference | publisher=[[Utah Department of Transportation]] | url=http://www.dot.utah.gov/main/uconowner.gf?n=7262615752008692|format=PDF |year = 2008 | accessdate = December 30, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|established=1963
|beltway_city=[[Salt Lake City]]
|direction_a=[[Counterclockwise|CCW]]
|terminus_a={{jct|state=UT|I|80}} in [[Millcreek, Utah|Millcreek]]
|junction={{jct|state=UT|SR|152}} in [[Cottonwood Heights, Utah|Cottonwood Heights]]&lt;br&gt;{{jct|state=UT|I|15}} in [[Murray, Utah|Murray]]&lt;br&gt;{{jct|state=UT|UT|201}} in [[West Valley City, Utah|West Valley City]]&lt;br&gt;{{jct|state=UT|I|80}} in Salt Lake City&lt;br&gt;{{jct|state=UT|UT|67}} in [[North Salt Lake, Utah|North Salt Lake]]
|direction_b=[[Clockwise|CW]]
|terminus_b={{jct|state=UT|I|15}} in North Salt Lake
|previous_type=UT
|previous_route=212
|next_type=UT
|next_route=218
}}
'''Interstate 215''' ('''I-215'''), also known locally as the ''belt route'' or ''two-fifteen'',&lt;ref name=&quot;ksl name&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ksl.com/?nid=148&amp;sid=3720987|title=Morning accident has some questioning if semi truck ban is needed|last=Boal|first=Jed|author2=Giauque, Marc|date=July 9, 2008|publisher=[[KSL-TV|KSL.com]]|accessdate=August 10, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; is an auxiliary interstate in the [[U.S. state]] of [[Utah]] that forms a 270-degree loop around Salt Lake City and many of its suburbs. The route begins at the mouth of [[Parley's Canyon]] at the junction of [[I-80 (UT)|I-80]] and heads south through the edge of the [[Salt Lake City metropolitan area]]'s eastern suburbs of [[Millcreek, Utah|Millcreek]], [[Holladay, Utah|Holladay]], and [[Cottonwood Heights, Utah|Cottonwood Heights]]. It continues west through [[Murray, Utah|Murray]] before turning north again, passing through the city's first-ring western suburbs of [[Taylorsville, Utah|Taylorsville]] and [[West Valley City, Utah|West Valley City]]. It then enters [[North Salt Lake, Utah|North Salt Lake]] and [[Davis County, Utah|Davis County]] for a short distance before reaching [[I-15 (UT)|I-15]].

The interstate was proposed in the mid-1950s, along with I-15 and I-80 through Salt Lake City. At the time, only the western portion of the belt route was assigned as I-215. The eastern portion of the belt route was designated ''Interstate 415''. However, the I-415 designation was scrapped to provide a single route number for the entire route in 1969, with the I-215 designation covering the complete belt route. The freeway was constructed in segments, beginning with a section completed in 1963 from Redwood Road in North Salt Lake to 2100 North near the [[Salt Lake City International Airport|airport]]. Originally planned to be complete in the mid-1970s, challenges from citizens' groups over environmental impact statements led to the completion of the last section of I-215 in 1989 between 6200 South and 4500 South in Holladay.

==Route description==
[[File:2015-09-29 11 22 09 View east along Interstate 80 about 127 miles east of the Nevada state line at the junction with Interstate 215 in Salt Lake City, Utah.jpg|thumb|left|The southeastern terminus of I-215 at I-80]]
I-215 begins at an interchange at the mouth of [[Parley's Canyon]] in [[Millcreek, Utah|Millcreek]] near the southeast corner of [[Salt Lake City]] that connects [[I-80 (UT)|I-80]], Foothill Drive ([[Utah State Route 186|State Route 186]], or SR-186) and Parleys Way. At this point, I-215 splits into three legs, connecting I-80 toward Salt Lake City, Foothill Drive and Parleys Way, and I-80 through Parley's Canyon. From here, the freeway travels southeast along the [[Salt Lake Valley]]'s east bench with three lanes in each direction. The route enters a residential area of [[East Millcreek, Utah|East Millcreek]] and turns south. Then, the first exit appears, an incomplete [[diamond interchange]] with 3300 South ([[SR-171 (UT)|SR-171]]) that lacks an off-ramp from northbound I-215. Past this interchange, an on-ramp connects 3800&amp;nbsp;South to northbound I-215. A block further south is a partial interchange lacking an off-ramp from northbound I-215 onto 3900&amp;nbsp;South. Entering [[Holladay, Utah|Holladay]], I-215 is heading south but soon turns southwest. An off-ramp here allows northbound motorists to connect to Wasatch Boulevard. However, this exit is signed as 3900&amp;nbsp;South and 3300&amp;nbsp;South because of the incomplete interchanges on both roads. Past an interchange at 4500 South ([[SR-266 (UT)|SR-266]]) that serves southbound I-215, the road turns south again and begins descending toward [[Knudsen's Corner, Utah|Knudsen's Corner]] and [[Cottonwood Heights, Utah|Cottonwood Heights]]. At this point, the southbound lanes are lower than the parallel northbound lanes. The belt route flattens out upon reaching an interchange at 6200 South at Knudsen's Corner.&lt;ref name=&quot;gmaps&quot;&gt;{{google maps |url=https://maps.google.com/maps?q=salt+lake+city,+ut&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;oe=utf-8&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;ll=40.736332,-111.86554&amp;spn=0.215398,0.703125&amp;z=11 |title=Interstate 215 Overview |accessdate=August 10, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:I-215past21stNorth.jpg|thumb|right|250px|I-215 northbound approaching Legacy Parkway]]
As the freeway enters Cottonwood Heights, it turns west and becomes a sunken freeway. Then it reaches an interchange at Highland Drive, signed as 2000 East ([[SR-152 (UT)|SR-152]]). This interchange features a grade-separated ramp from northbound 2000 East to eastbound I-215. Past this junction, another interchange at Union Park Avenue appears. Another grade-separated ramp from Union Park Avenue is present. The freeway enters Murray as an interchange serving westbound motorists connects to 280&amp;nbsp;East and State Street ([[U.S. Route 89 in Utah|U.S. Route 89]], or US-89). Eastbound travelers connect to State Street further west at a separate exit. The road turns northwest for a short time to approach a junction at [[I-15 (UT)|I-15]] (often called the South Interchange, in ). Approaching the interchange, the route gains two lanes and reverts to a ground-level freeway. The freeway crosses I-15 and loses one lane as it enters [[Taylorsville, Utah|Taylorsville]] and curves to the northwest, crossing the [[Jordan River (Utah)|Jordan River]] in the process. Right before a [[partial cloverleaf interchange]] at Redwood Road ([[SR-68 (UT)|SR-68]]) the route turns west one final time before turning north after the interchange. The freeway continues north and has another partial cloverleaf interchange at 4700 South (SR-266). The route enters [[West Valley City, Utah|West Valley City]] and encounters 3500 South (SR-171), where its eastbound lanes have a grade-separated ramp to northbound I-215. The road turns northeast and enters an industrial area of western Salt Lake City. After reaching a [[cloverleaf interchange]] at [[SR-201 (UT)|SR-201]], the route turns north again. Beyond a [[single-point urban interchange]] at California Avenue, the freeway continues north.&lt;ref name=&quot;gmaps&quot;/&gt;

[[File:2015-11-03 11 13 03 View east from an airplane along the southern portion of Interstate 215 as it crosses the cities of Taylorsville, Murray and Midvale, Utah and interchanges with Interstate 15.jpg|thumb|left|View east along the southern portion of I-215]]
A partial [[stack interchange]] involving I-80, Redwood Road, and the access road to [[Salt Lake City International Airport]] is next. The freeway loses one lane in each direction as the interstate passes the airport to the east. Two diamond interchanges at 700&amp;nbsp;North and 2100&amp;nbsp;North occur as the freeway approaches [[Davis County, Utah|Davis County]]. Past 2100&amp;nbsp;North, the freeway enters rural [[Salt Lake County, Utah|Salt Lake County]], and the road curves to the northwest. An interchange at [[Legacy Parkway]] gives northbound I-215 motorists and southbound Legacy Parkway motorists their respective connections. The road turns east and loses one lane in each direction. There is a [[diamond interchange]] at SR-68 before the highway merges into northbound I-15 in [[North Salt Lake, Utah|North Salt Lake]].&lt;ref name=&quot;gmaps&quot;/&gt;

==History==
[[Image:Snow in June.jpg|right|thumb|250px|Looking southward at the southern terminus of [[SR-186 (UT)|SR-186]] toward the counter-clockwise end of I-215 at the mouth of [[Parley's Canyon]]]]
[[File:I-215 dates.svg|250px|right|thumb|A diagram showing the year each section of I-215 opened]]
A belt route around Salt Lake City was first proposed in 1955, with the Utah Highway Department (the predecessor to the present-day [[Utah Department of Transportation]]) holding hearings concerning construction beginning in early 1958.&lt;ref name=&quot;80article&quot;&gt;{{Citation
  | last = Peterson
  | first = Corey
  | title = I-215 Belt Route – 30 years from conception to completion?
  | newspaper = [[Deseret News]]
  | date = July 23, 1980
  | pages = 2H
  | url = https://news.google.com/newspapers/p/deseret_news?id=nromAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=IoMDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5139,2532151&amp;dq=belt+route&amp;hl=en
  | accessdate = November 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The southeast quadrant of the route was originally placed from a junction at proposed I-15 in Murray northeasterly through Murray and Holladay, eventually reaching the east bench at 3900 South. From there, it would have run north toward the mouth of Parley's Canyon at proposed I-80 (at the time [[US-40 (UT)|US-40]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;9jun60&quot;&gt;{{Citation
  | title = Compromise Plan On Belt Route Gets Area Support At Surprise Unveiling
  | newspaper = [[Deseret News]]
  | date = June 9, 1960
  | pages = 1B
  | url = https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=MlMoAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=gUgDAAAAIBAJ&amp;dq=belt%20route&amp;pg=7076%2C1997194
  | accessdate = November 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Almost immediately, this plan was met with opposition among local residents in the area. The proposed route would have bisected the primarily residential Holladay suburb, as well as the southern portion of Murray. After more than two years of hearings and widespread opposition from residents, the Highway Department released their proposed routing in June 1960, which placed the southeast quadrant where it runs today. While quelling criticism from some,&lt;ref name=&quot;9jun60&quot;/&gt; others remained in opposition, saying the route was still too intrusive along residential areas.&lt;ref name=&quot;28jun60&quot;&gt;{{Citation
  | last = Ellis
  | first = Dexter
  | title = Hot Protests Greet 'Belt' Plan At Olympus High School Meet
  | newspaper = [[Deseret News]]
  | date = June 28, 1960
  | pages = 1B
  | url = https://news.google.com/newspapers/p/deseret_news?id=QFMoAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=gUgDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5126,6084553&amp;dq=belt+route&amp;hl=en
  | accessdate = November 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The western quadrant was also admonished for being placed to close to other major arterials.&lt;ref name=&quot;20jan59&quot;&gt;{{Citation
  | title = Proposed Belt Route Draws Farm Queries
  | newspaper = [[Deseret News]]
  | date = January 20, 1959
  | pages = A5
  | url = https://news.google.com/newspapers/p/deseret_news?id=nromAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=IoMDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5139,2532151&amp;dq=belt+route&amp;hl=en
  | accessdate = November 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In November 1963, a small, two-lane portion of the northwest quadrant of the belt route opened from Redwood Road ([[SR-68 (UT)|SR-68]]) in Davis County west and south to 2100 North, north of the [[Salt Lake City International Airport]].&lt;ref name=&quot;20nov63&quot;&gt;{{Citation
  | title = Ribbon Cutting Opens Section of Belt Route
  | newspaper = [[Deseret News]]
  | date = November 20, 1963
  | pages = 1B
  | url = https://news.google.com/newspapers/p/deseret_news?id=I5cqAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=D1gEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=3726,4130227&amp;dq=belt+route+2200+north&amp;hl=en
  | accessdate = November 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite map
  |publisher = United States Department of Agriculture
  |title=Historic Aerials website
  |url = http://www.historicaerials.com/aerials.php?scale=5.90178383123315E-06&amp;lat=40.8338835677001&amp;lon=-111.935744585967&amp;year=1965
  |edition = 1965
  |accessdate = January 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; This portion of road was extended east to I-15 in North Salt Lake and upgraded to freeway standards by 1969.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=National Bridge Inventory |publisher=Nationalbridges.com |date=2009 |url=http://nationalbridges.com/nbi_record.php?StateCode=49&amp;struct=++++++++0C+512 |accessdate=January 24, 2011 }}{{dead link|date=June 2016|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Construction of the southeast quadrant from I-80 (at the time replacing US-40) at Parley's Canyon to 4600 South in Holladay began in mid-1965. This involved realigning Wasatch Boulevard to parallel the route and truncating that road at 3300 South. Prior to this, Wasatch Boulevard connected to US-40. The section from I-80 to 3300 South opened by January 1967,&lt;ref name=&quot;udotmap67&quot;&gt;{{Cite map
  |publisher = [[Utah Department of Transportation]]
  |title = Salt Lake Area Interstate System
  |edition = 1967}}
&lt;/ref&gt; with the portion of roadway from 3300 South to 4500 South opening in November 1969.&lt;ref name=&quot;80article&quot;/&gt;

By 1973, construction was progressing on the western quadrant between I-15 in Murray and [[SR-201 (UT)|SR-201]] (at the time US-40A/US-50A). Land acquisition was also taking place for the rest of the southeastern quadrant between 300 East in Murray and 4600 South in Holladay. However, a citizens' group named Cottonwood Inc. halted right-of-way acquirements due to the lack of an environmental impact statement (EIS). Also controversial was a proposed cloverleaf interchange at 2000 East.&lt;ref name=&quot;1jun73&quot;&gt;{{Citation
  | last = Wirsing
  | first = Whit
  | title = Residents oppose belt route plan
  | newspaper = [[Deseret News]]
  | date = June 1, 1973
  | pages = B1
  | url = https://news.google.com/newspapers/p/deseret_news?id=ZkkOAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=Kn8DAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4052,98567&amp;dq=belt+route&amp;hl=en
  | accessdate = November 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; By mid-1975, an EIS was released with four main alternatives: a no-build alternative which would leave a gap in the southeast quadrant, building the road along the modern-day path (at about 6400 South), moving the southern portion southwest through Fort Union and Midvale to 7200 South, or extending the eastern portion further south to Sandy and then west along 9000 South.&lt;ref name=&quot;18jul1975&quot;&gt;{{Citation
  | last = Dean
  | first = Suzanne
  | title = Here's summary on belt route impact issues
  | newspaper = [[Deseret News]]
  | date = July 18, 1975
  | pages = B1
  | url = https://news.google.com/newspapers/p/deseret_news?id=HaQqAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=k1sEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=7189,4455670&amp;dq=belt+route&amp;hl=en
  | accessdate = November 6, 2010}} {{Dead link|date=April 2012|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cottonwood Inc. filed a lawsuit challenging the EIS. Meanwhile, I-215 from SR-201 in the western quadrant to 280 East in Murray opened in November 1976.&lt;ref name=&quot;80article&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Interstate 215 - Utah.jpg|right|thumb|250px|Westbound on I-215 toward the Union Park Avenue interchange]]
After 1976, gaps in the belt route were present from 2100 North near the airport to SR-201 and from State Street in Murray to 4600 South in Holladay. The first step in completing the gap was taken in June 1979, when construction of the interstate from State Street to 700 East began.&lt;ref name=&quot;4jun1979&quot;&gt;{{Citation
  | title = Work begins on segment of belt route
  | newspaper = [[Deseret News]]
  | date = June 4, 1979
  | pages = 12A
  | url = https://news.google.com/newspapers/p/deseret_news?id=34cqAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=Z1sEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=3894,730854&amp;dq=belt+route&amp;hl=en
  | accessdate = November 6, 2010}} {{Dead link|date=April 2012|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was followed by the Cottonwood Inc. lawsuit being awarded in favor of UDOT in November 1979. In July 1985, the route from 280 East to Union Park Avenue was completed. At the time, this portion of road was the most expensive in the state in terms of cost per mile, due to the road being depressed below surrounding neighborhoods.&lt;ref name=&quot;29apr85&quot;&gt;{{Citation
  | title = Behind schedule but finished by July
  | newspaper = [[Deseret News]]
  | date = April 29, 1985
  | pages = B1
  | url = https://news.google.com/newspapers/p/deseret_news?id=tRkPAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=HIQDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=3932,6808410&amp;dq=belt+route+11th+east&amp;hl=en
  | accessdate = November 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The next section to open was from 2100 North south to I-80 in 1987.&lt;ref name=&quot;30jul87&quot;&gt;{{Citation
  | title = I-80 on-ramp near airport open to traffic
  | newspaper = [[Deseret News]]
  | date = July 30, 1987
  | pages = G25
  | url = https://news.google.com/newspapers/p/deseret_news?id=e5opAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=RoQDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4010,6304715&amp;dq=Interstate+215+complete&amp;hl=en
  | accessdate = November 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was followed by a section between Union Park Avenue and 2000 East, opened in November 1987, which was also built as a sunken freeway.&lt;ref name=&quot;6nov87&quot;&gt;{{Citation
  | last = Spangler
  | first = Jerry
  | title = I-215 now stretches a little further
  | newspaper = [[Deseret News]]
  | date = November 6, 1987
  | pages = B1
  | url = https://news.google.com/newspapers/p/deseret_news?id=kORNAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=GoQDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=1477,3128332&amp;dq=belt+route+completed&amp;hl=en
  | accessdate = November 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The western quadrant of the freeway was completed in October 1988, closing the gap between SR-201 and I-80 (however, the California Avenue interchange wasn't opened until mid-1989).&lt;ref name=&quot;30sep88&quot;&gt;{{Citation
  | last = Riley Roche
  | first = Lisa
  | title = Delay in opening I-215 interchange questioned
  | newspaper = [[Deseret News]]
  | date = September 30, 1988
  | pages = B2
  | url = https://news.google.com/newspapers/p/deseret_news?id=UjwjAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=CIQDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4551,6252548&amp;dq=belt+route+1988&amp;hl=en
  | accessdate = November 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In August 1989, the road from 2000 East to 6200 South was finished, and the belt route was completed with the opening of freeway between 4500 South and 6200 South in October 1989.&lt;ref name=&quot;18oct89&quot;&gt;{{Citation
  | last = Thompson
  | first = Jan
  | title = I-215 belt route's finished – finally
  | newspaper = [[Deseret News]]
  | date = October 18, 1989
  | pages = B1
  | url = https://news.google.com/newspapers/p/deseret_news?id=xZUpAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=4oMDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4117,784014&amp;dq=belt+route+complete&amp;hl=en
  | accessdate = November 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since 1989, the only major modifications that have occurred on the belt route have consisted of the rebuilding of the southern I-15 interchange in 2001, widening from six to eight lanes from 4700 South in Taylorsville to I-15 in Murray in 2004, and the addition of an interchange at [[Legacy Parkway]] in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
  | title = Wasatch Front Regional Council 2030 Transportation Plan
  | url = http://www.wfrc.org/cms/publications/Adopted_2007-2030_RTP/Chapter%208%20-%20Recommended%20Improvements.pdf
  | accessdate = November 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;14sep08&quot;&gt;{{Citation
  | last = Dougherty
  | first = Joseph
  | title = 'The Legacy Parkway is done' — and it's open to commuters
  | newspaper = [[Deseret News]]
  | date = September 14, 2008
  | url = http://www.deseretnews.com/article/700258693/The-Legacy-Parkway-is-done--and-its-open-to-commuters.html?pg=1
  | accessdate = November 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 3300 South and 4500 South overpasses were rebuilt as well, in 2008 and 2007 respectively.&lt;ref name=&quot;18aug08&quot;&gt;{{Citation
  | last = Raymond
  | first = Arthur
  | title = I-80 reopens ahead of schedule
  | newspaper = [[Deseret News]]
  | date = August 18, 2008
  | url = http://www.deseretnews.com/article/700251696/I-80-reopens-ahead-of-schedule.html
  | accessdate = November 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;28sep07&quot;&gt;{{Citation
  | last = Warburton
  | first = Nicole
  | title = 'The Legacy Parkway is done' — and it's open to commuters
  | newspaper = [[Deseret News]]
  | date = September 28, 2007
  | url = http://www.deseretnews.com/article/695213885/A-bridge-too-far-Not-this-one.html
  | accessdate = November 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As part of the original proposal of a belt route through Salt Lake City, the southeastern quadrant received the designation of I-415. To maintain continuity in the belt route, the 415 number was replaced in favor of the I-215 designation covering the entire route in 1969.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dot.utah.gov/main/uconowner.gf?n=200609191605231|title=SR-215 History|date=October 14, 1968|publisher=[[Utah Department of Transportation|State Road Commission of Utah]]|accessdate=July 29, 2008|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Exit list==
{{jcttop|exit|length_ref=&lt;ref name=&quot;reference&quot;/&gt;}}
{{UTint|exit
|county=Salt Lake
|cspan=21
|location=Salt Lake City
|type=incomplete
|mile=0.00
|road={{jct|state=UT|I|80|dir1=West|location1=[[Reno, Nevada|Reno]]}}
|notes=CCW exit, CW entrance and eastern terminus; I-80 east exit 128
}}
{{UTint|exit
|location=Millcreek Township
|lspan=4
|type=incomplete
|exit=1
|mile=1.061
|road={{jct|state=UT|SR|186|dir1=west|name1=Foothill Drive|road=Parleys Way west}}
|notes=CCW exit, CW entrance; I-80 exit 129
}}
{{UTint|exit
|type=incomplete
|exit=2
|mile=1.466
|road={{jct|state=UT|I|80|dir1=East|city1=Park City|location2=[[Cheyenne, Wyoming|Cheyenne]]}}
|notes=No CW exit; I-80 west exit 130
}}
{{UTint|exit
|type=incomplete
|exit=3
|mile=1.701
|road={{jct|state=UT|UT|171|name1=3300&amp;nbsp;South|road=Wasatch Boulevard}}
|notes=No CCW exit
}}
{{UTint|exit
|exit=4
|mile=2.615
|road=3900&amp;nbsp;South, 3300&amp;nbsp;South (Wasatch Boulevard)
|notes=
}}
{{UTint|exit
|location=Holladay
|type=incomplete
|exit=5
|mile=3.491
|road={{jct|state=UT|UT|266|name1=4500&amp;nbsp;South}}
|notes=CW exit and entrance
}}
{{UTint|exit
|location1=Holladay
|location2=Cottonwood Heights
|lspan=2
|exit=6
|mile=6.080
|road={{jct|state=UT|UT|190|name1=6200&amp;nbsp;South|road=3000&amp;nbsp;East|location1=Ski areas}}
}}
{{UTint|exit
|exit=8
|mile=7.481
|road={{jct|state=UT|UT|152|name1=2000&amp;nbsp;East}}
}}
{{UTint|exit
|location=Cottonwood Heights
|exit=9
|mile=9.076
|road=Union Park Avenue
}}
{{UTint|exit
|location=Murray
|lspan=3
|type=incomplete
|exit=10
|mile=10.205
|road=280&amp;nbsp;East
|notes=CW exit and entrance
}}
{{UTint|exit
|type=incomplete
|exit=11
|mile=10.646
|road={{jct|state=UT|US|89|name1=[[State Street (Salt Lake County)|State Street]]}}
|notes=CCW exit and entrance
}}
{{UTint|exit
|exit=12
|mile=11.256
|road={{jct|state=UT|I|15|location1=[[Las Vegas, Nevada|Las Vegas]]|city2=Salt Lake City}}
|notes=I-15 exit 298
}}
{{UTint|exit
|location=Taylorsville
|lspan=2
|exit=13
|mile=13.288
|road={{jct|state=UT|UT|68|name1=Redwood Road}}
}}
{{UTint|exit
|exit=15
|mile=15.258
|road={{jct|state=UT|UT|266|name1=4700&amp;nbsp;South|city1=Taylorsville}}
}}
{{UTint|exit
|location=West Valley City
|exit=18
|mile=17.351
|mile2=17.571
|road={{jct|state=UT|UT|171|name1=3500&amp;nbsp;South|location1=[[Maverik Center]]|city2=West Valley City}}
|notes=Signed as exits 18A, 18B CW
}}
{{UTint|exit
|location=Salt Lake City
|lspan=6
|exit=20
|mile=19.232
|mile2=19.625
|road={{jct|state=UT|UT|201|city1=Magna}}
|notes=SR 201 exits 15A-B.
}}
{{UTint|exit
|exit=21
|mile=20.396
|road=California Avenue
}}
{{UTint|exit
|exit=22
|mile=21.764
|road={{jct|state=UT|I|80|road=Redwood Road ([[Utah State Route 68|SR-68]])|location1=[[Cheyenne, Wyoming|Cheyenne]]|location2=[[Reno, Nevada|Reno]]|location3=[[Salt Lake City International Airport|Airport]]}}
|notes=Signed as exits 22A (westbound I-80) and 22B (eastbound I-80) CCW; I-80 exit 117
}}
{{UTint|exit
|exit=23
|mile=23.365
|road=700&amp;nbsp;North
}}
{{UTint|exit
|exit=25
|mile=25.341
|road=2100&amp;nbsp;North
}}
{{UTint|exit
|type=incomplete
|exit=26
|mile=26.701
|road={{jct|state=UT|UT|67|name1=[[Legacy Parkway]]}}
|notes=CW entrance, CCW exit
}}
{{UTint|exit
|county=Davis
|cspan=2
|location=North Salt Lake
|lspan=2
|exit=27
|mile=27.115
|road={{jct|state=UT|UT|68|name1=Redwood Road}}
}}
{{UTint|exit
|type=incomplete
|mile=28.946
|road={{jct|state=UT|I|15}}
|notes=CW exit, CCW entrance and northern terminus; I-15 south exit 313
}}
{{Jctbtm|col=7|key=CCW&amp;nbsp;– counterclockwise ; CW&amp;nbsp;– clockwise|keys=incomplete}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}
{{Commons category}}
{{Attached KML|display=inline,title}}
{{3di|15}}
{{Good article}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=January 2014}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Interstate 15-2 (Utah)}}
[[Category:Auxiliary Interstate Highways|15-2 Utah]]
[[Category:Interstate Highways in Utah|15-2]]
[[Category:Interstate 15|215 Utah]]
[[Category:Transportation in Salt Lake County, Utah]]
[[Category:Transportation in Davis County, Utah]]</text>
      <sha1>mkix1gz96mu0k7i99dvjiw4eesmr0az</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
