<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.28.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2600" case="first-letter">Topic</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Malcolm II of Scotland</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>148037</id>
    <revision>
      <id>737043305</id>
      <parentid>737040740</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-31T11:54:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2A01:CB04:53:1E00:CCC5:89B8:37D4:212C</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23761">{{redirects|Malcolm II|other people named Malcolm II}}
{{Infobox royalty
| name = Malcolm II
| image = Malcolm II of Scotland.jpg
| image_size = 200
| caption = Fanciful 17th century depiction of the king (his actual appearance is unknown)
| succession = [[List of Scottish monarchs|King of Scots]]
| reign = 1005&amp;ndash;1034
| predecessor = [[Kenneth III of Scotland|Kenneth III]]
| successor = [[Duncan I of Scotland|Duncan I]]
| issue = [[Bethóc]]&lt;br /&gt; Donada&lt;br /&gt; Olith
| house = [[House of Alpin|Alpin]]
| father = [[Kenneth II of Scotland|Kenneth II]]
| birth_date = c. 954
| death_date = {{death date|1034|11|25|df=y}}
| death_place = [[Glamis]]
| place of burial = [[Iona]]
}}
'''Malcolm''' ([[Scottish Gaelic language|Gaelic]]: ''Máel Coluim''; born c. 954 - died 25 November 1034),&lt;ref&gt;Skene, ''Chronicles'', pp. 99–100.&lt;/ref&gt; was [[King of the Scots]] from 1005 until his death.&lt;ref&gt;Malcolm's birth date is not known, but must have been around 980 if the [[Flateyjarbók]] is right in dating the marriage of his daughter and [[Sigurd Hlodvisson]] to the lifetime of [[Olaf Tryggvason]]; ''Early Sources'', p. 528, quoting ''Olaf Tryggvason's Saga''.&lt;/ref&gt; He was a son of [[Kenneth II of Scotland|King Kenneth II]]; the [[Prophecy of Berchán]] says that his mother was a woman of [[Leinster]] and refers to him as '''''Forranach''''', &quot;the destroyer&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Early Sources'', pp. 574&amp;ndash;575.&lt;/ref&gt;

To the [[Irish annals]] which recorded his death, Malcolm was ''ard [[rí]] Alban'', [[High King]] of Scotland. In the same way that [[Brian Bóruma]], [[High King of Ireland]], was not the only king in [[Ireland]], Malcolm was one of several kings within the geographical boundaries of modern [[Scotland]]: his fellow kings included the [[king of Strathclyde]], who ruled much of the south-west, various [[Norse-Gael]] kings on the western coast and the [[Hebrides]] and, nearest and most dangerous rivals, the kings or [[Mormaers of Moray]]. To the south, in the [[Kingdom of England]], the Earls of [[Bernicia]] and [[Northumbria]], whose predecessors as [[kings of Northumbria]] had once ruled most of southern Scotland, still controlled large parts of the southeast.&lt;ref&gt;Higham, pp. 226&amp;ndash;227, notes that the kings of the English had neither lands nor mints north of the [[River Tees|Tees]].&lt;/ref&gt;

== Early years ==
Malcolm II was born to [[Kenneth II of Scotland]]. He was grandson of [[Malcolm I of Scotland]]. In 997, the killer of [[Causantín mac Cuilén|Constantine]] is credited as being Kenneth, son of Malcolm. Since there is no known and relevant Kenneth alive at that time (King Kenneth having died in 995), it is considered an error for either [[Kenneth III of Scotland|Kenneth III]], who succeeded Constantine, or, possibly, Malcolm himself, the son of Kenneth II.&lt;ref&gt;''Early Sources'', pp. 517&amp;ndash;518. John of Fordun has Malcolm as the killer; Duncan, p. 46, credits [[Cináed mac Duib|Kenneth MacDuff]] with the death of Constantine.&lt;/ref&gt; Whether Malcolm killed Constantine or not, there is no doubt that in 1005 he killed Constantine's successor Kenneth III in battle at [[Monzievaird]] in [[Strathearn]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Chronicon Scotorum]], s.a. 1005; ''Early Sources'', pp. 521&amp;ndash;524; Fordun, IV, xxxviii. Berchán places Cináed's death by the Earn.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[John of Fordun]] writes that Malcolm defeated a [[Norway|Norwegian]] army &quot;in almost the first days after his coronation&quot;, but this is not reported elsewhere. Fordun says that the [[Diocese of Aberdeen|Bishopric of Mortlach]] (later moved to [[Aberdeen]]) was founded in thanks for this victory over the Norwegians.&lt;ref&gt;''Early Sources'', p. 525, note 1; Fordun, IV, xxxix&amp;ndash;xl.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Children ==
Malcolm demonstrated a rare ability to survive among early Scottish kings by reigning for twenty-nine years. He was a clever and ambitious man. Brehon tradition provided that the successor to Malcolm was to be selected by him from among the descendants of [[Áed mac Cináeda|King Aedh]], with the consent of Malcolm’s ministers and of the church. Ostensibly in an attempt to end the devastating feuds in the north of Scotland, but obviously influenced by the Norman feudal model, Malcolm ignored tradition and determined to retain the succession within his own line. But since Malcolm had no son of his own, he undertook to negotiate a series of dynastic marriages of his three daughters to men who might otherwise be his rivals, while securing the loyalty of the principal chiefs, their relatives. First he married his daughter [[Bethóc|Bethoc]] to [[Crínán of Dunkeld|Crinan]], Thane of The Isles, head of the house of Atholl and secular Abbot of Dunkeld; then his youngest daughter, Olith, to [[Sigurd the Stout|Sigurd, Earl of Orkney]]. His middle daughter, Donada, was married to [[Findláech of Moray|Finlay, Earl of Moray]], Thane of Ross and Cromarty and a descendant of [[Loarn mac Eirc|Loarn of Dalriada]]. This was risky business under the rules of succession of the Gael, but he thereby secured his rear and, taking advantage of the renewal of Viking attacks on England, marched south to fight the English. He defeated the Angles at [[Battle of Carham|Carham]] in 1018 and installed his grandson, Duncan, son of the Abbot of Dunkeld and his choice as Tanist, in Carlisle as King of Cumbria that same year.&lt;ref&gt;1. BETHOC [Beatrix Beatrice Betoch] &quot;Genealogy of King William the Lyon&quot; dated 1175 names &quot;Betoch filii Malcolmi&quot; as parent of &quot;Malcolmi filii Dunecani&quot;. The Chronicle of the Scots and Picts dated 1177 names &quot;Cran Abbatis de Dunkelden et Bethok filia Malcolm mac Kynnet&quot; as parents of King Duncan. source Beatrice who married Crynyne Abthane of Dul and Steward of the Isles

2. DONADA [Dovada Duada Doada Donalda] R alph Holinshed's 1577 Chronicle of Scotland names &quot;Doada&quot; as second daughter of Malcolm II King of Scotland and adds that she married &quot;Sinell the thane of Glammis, by whom she had issue one Makbeth&quot;.

3. OLITH [Alice Olith Anlite] Orkneyinga Saga records that “Earl Sigurd” married “the daughter of Malcolm King of Scots”. Snorre records the marriage of &quot;Sigurd the Thick&quot; and &quot;a daughter of the Scottish king Malcolm&quot;. Ulster journal of archaeology, Volume 6  By Ulster Archaeological Society names her as (Alice) wife of Sygurt and daughter of Malcolm II. The American historical magazine, Volume 2 By Publishing Society of New York, Americana Society pg 529 names her Olith or Alice.
&lt;/ref&gt;

== Bernicia ==
The first reliable report of Malcolm II's reign is of an invasion of [[Bernicia]] in 1006, perhaps the customary ''crech ríg'' (literally royal prey, a raid by a new king made to demonstrate prowess in war), which involved a [[siege]] of [[Durham, England|Durham]]. This appears to have resulted in a heavy defeat by the Northumbrians, led by [[Uhtred of Bamburgh]], later [[Earl of Bernicia]], which is reported by the [[Annals of Ulster]].&lt;ref&gt;Duncan, pp. 27&amp;ndash;28; Smyth, pp. 236&amp;ndash;237; Annals of Ulster, s.a. 1006.&lt;/ref&gt;

A second war in Bernicia, probably in 1018, was more successful. The [[Battle of Carham]], by the [[River Tweed]], was a victory for the Scots led by Malcolm II and the men of Strathclyde led by their king, [[Owen the Bald]]. By this time Earl Uchtred may have been dead, and [[Eiríkr Hákonarson]] was appointed Earl of Northumbria by his brother-in-law [[Cnut the Great]], although his authority seems to have been limited to the south, the former kingdom of [[Deira (kingdom)|Deira]], and he took no action against the Scots so far as is known.&lt;ref&gt;Duncan, pp. 28&amp;ndash;29 suggests that Earl Uchtred may not have died until 1018. Fletcher accepts that he died in Spring 1016 and the Eadwulf Cudel was Earl of Bernicia when Carham was fought in 1018; Higham, pp. 225&amp;ndash;230, agrees. Smyth, pp. 236&amp;ndash;237 reserves judgement as to the date of the battle, 1016 or 1018, and whether Uchtred was still living when it was fought. See also Stenton, pp. 418&amp;ndash;419.&lt;/ref&gt; The work ''[[De obsessione Dunelmi]]'' (''The siege of Durham'', associated with [[Symeon of Durham]]) claims that Uchtred's brother [[Eadwulf Cudel]] surrendered [[Lothian]] to Malcolm II, presumably in the aftermath of the defeat at Carham. This is likely to have been the lands between [[Dunbar]] and the Tweed as other parts of Lothian had been under Scots control before this time. It has been suggested that Cnut received tribute from the Scots for Lothian, but as he had likely received none from the Bernician Earls this is not very probable.&lt;ref&gt;''Early Sources'', p. 544, note 6; Higham, pp. 226&amp;ndash;227.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Cnut ==&lt;!-- Linked to [[Cnut the Great]] --&gt;
Cnut, reports the ''[[Anglo-Saxon Chronicle]]'', led an army into Scotland on his return from [[pilgrimage]] to [[Rome]]. The ''Chronicle'' dates this to 1031, but there are reasons to suppose that it should be dated to 1027.&lt;ref&gt;ASC, Ms D, E and F; Duncan, pp. 29&amp;ndash;30.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Duchy of Burgundy|Burgundian]] chronicler [[Rodulfus Glaber]] recounts the expedition soon afterwards, describing Malcolm as &quot;powerful in resources and arms … very Christian in faith and deed.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Early Sources'', pp. 545&amp;ndash;546.&lt;/ref&gt; Ralph claims that peace was made between Malcolm and Cnut through the intervention of [[Richard II, Duke of Normandy|Richard]], [[Duke of Normandy]], brother of Cnut's wife [[Emma of Normandy|Emma]]. Richard died in about 1027 and Rodulfus wrote close in time to the events.&lt;ref&gt;Ralph was writing in 1030 or 1031; Duncan, p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt;

It has been suggested that the root of the quarrel between Cnut and Malcolm lies in Cnut's pilgrimage to Rome, and the coronation of [[Holy Roman Emperor]] [[Conrad II, Holy Roman Emperor|Conrad II]], where Cnut and [[Rudolph III of Burgundy|Rudolph III]], [[King of Burgundy]] had the place of honour. If Malcolm were present, and the repeated mentions of his piety in the annals make it quite possible that he made a pilgrimage to Rome, as did [[Mac Bethad mac Findláich]] (&quot;Macbeth&quot;) in later times, then the coronation would have allowed Malcolm to publicly snub Cnut's claims to overlordship.&lt;ref&gt;Duncan, pp. 31&amp;ndash;32; the alternative, he notes, that Cnut was concerned about support for [[Olaf II of Norway|Olaf Haraldsson]], &quot;is no better evidenced.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Cnut obtained rather less than previous English kings, a promise of peace and friendship rather than the promise of aid on land and sea that [[Edgar of England|Edgar]] and others had obtained. The sources say that Malcolm was accompanied by one or two other kings, certainly Mac Bethad, and perhaps [[Echmarcach mac Ragnaill]], [[King of Mann and the Isles]], and of [[Galloway]].&lt;ref&gt;Duncan, pp. 29&amp;ndash;30. ''St. Olaf's Saga'', c. 131 says &quot;two kings came south from Fife in Scotland&quot; to meet Cnut, suggesting only Malcolm and Mac Bethad, and that Cnut returned their lands and gave them gifts. That Echmarcach was king of Galloway is perhaps doubtful; the Annals of Ulster record the death of [[Suibne mac Cináeda]], ''rí Gall-Gáedel'' (&quot;King of Galloway&quot;) by Tigernach, in 1034.&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Anglo-Saxon Chronicle'' remarks of the submission &quot;but he [Malcolm] adhered to that for only a little while&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;ASC, Ms. D, s.a. 1031.&lt;/ref&gt; Cnut was soon occupied in [[Norway]] against Olaf Haraldsson and appears to have had no further involvement with Scotland.

== Orkney and Moray ==
Olith a daughter of Malcolm, married [[Sigurd Hlodvisson]], [[Earl of Orkney]].&lt;ref&gt;''Early Sources'', p. 528; ''Orkneyinga Saga'', c. 12.&lt;/ref&gt; Their son [[Thorfinn Sigurdsson]] was said to be five years old when Sigurd was killed on 23 April 1014 in the [[Battle of Clontarf]]. The ''[[Orkneyinga Saga]]'' says that Thorfinn was raised at Malcolm's court and was given the [[Mormaerdom of Caithness]] by his grandfather. Thorfinn, says the ''[[Heimskringla]]'', was the ally of the king of Scots, and counted on Malcolm's support to resist the &quot;tyranny&quot; of Norwegian King Olaf Haraldsson.&lt;ref&gt;''Orkneyinga Saga'', cc. 13&amp;ndash;20 &amp; 32; ''St. Olaf's Saga'', c. 96.&lt;/ref&gt; The chronology of Thorfinn's life is problematic, and he may have had a share in the Earldom of Orkney while still a child, if he was indeed only five in 1014.&lt;ref&gt;Duncan, p.42; reconciling the various dates of Thorfinn's life appears impossible on the face of it. Either he was born well before 1009 and must have died long before 1065, or the accounts in the ''Orkneyinga Saga'' are deeply flawed.&lt;/ref&gt; Whatever the exact chronology, before Malcolm's death a client of the king of Scots was in control of Caithness and Orkney, although, as with all such relationships, it is unlikely to have lasted beyond his death.

If Malcolm exercised control over Moray, which is far from being generally accepted, then the annals record a number of events pointing to a struggle for power in the north. In 1020, Mac Bethad's father [[Findláech mac Ruaidrí]] was killed by the sons of his brother Máel Brigte.&lt;ref&gt;[[Annals of Tigernach]], s.a. 1020; Annals of Ulster, s.a. 1020, but the killers are not named. The Annals of Ulster and the [[Book of Leinster]] call Findláech &quot;king of Scotland&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; It seems that [[Máel Coluim of Moray|Máel Coluim mac Máil Brigti]] took control of Moray, for his death is reported in 1029.&lt;ref&gt;Annals of Ulster and Annals of Tigernach, s.a. 1029. Malcolm's death is not said to have been by violence and he too is called king rather than mormaer.&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the accounts of the Irish annals, English and Scandinavian writers appear to see Mac Bethad as the rightful king of Moray: this is clear from their descriptions of the meeting with Cnut in 1027, before the death of Malcolm mac Máil Brigti. Malcolm was followed as king or earl by his brother [[Gille Coemgáin of Moray|Gillecomgan]], husband of [[Gruoch]], a granddaughter of King Kenneth III. It has been supposed that Mac Bethad was responsible for the killing of Gille Coemgáin in 1032, but if Mac Bethad had a cause for feud in the killing of his father in 1020, Malcolm too had reason to see Gille Coemgáin dead. Not only had Gillecomgan's ancestors killed many of Malcolm's kin, but Gillecomgan and his son [[Lulach]] might be rivals for the throne. Malcolm had no living sons, and the threat to his plans for the succession was obvious. As a result, the following year Gruoch's brother or nephew, who might have eventually become king, was killed by Malcolm.&lt;ref&gt;Duncan, pp. 29&amp;ndash;30, 32&amp;ndash;33 and compare Hudson, ''Prophecy of Berchán'', pp. 222&amp;ndash;223. ''Early Sources'', p.571; Annals of Ulster, s.a. 1032 &amp; 1033; [[Annals of Loch Cé]], s.a. 1029 &amp; 1033. The identity of the ''M. m. Boite'' killed in 1033 is uncertain, being reading as &quot;the son of the son of Boite&quot; or as &quot;M. son of Boite&quot;, Gruoch's brother or nephew respectively.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Strathclyde and the succession ==
It has traditionally been supposed that King Owen the Bald of [[Kingdom of Strathclyde|Strathclyde]] died at the Battle of Carham and that the kingdom passed into the hands of the Scots afterwards. This rests on some very weak evidence. It is far from certain that Owen died at Carham, and it is reasonably certain that there were kings of [[List of kings of Strathclyde|Strathclyde]] as late as the 1054, when [[Edward the Confessor]] sent [[Sigurd the Dane|Earl Siward]] to install &quot;[[Malcolm II of Strathclyde|Malcolm]] son of the king of the Cumbrians&quot;. The confusion is old, probably inspired by [[William of Malmesbury]] and embellished by John of Fordun, but there is no firm evidence that the kingdom of Strathclyde was a part of the kingdom of the Scots, rather than a loosely subjected kingdom, before the time of Malcolm II of Scotland's great-grandson [[Malcolm III of Scotland|Malcolm Canmore]].&lt;ref&gt;Duncan, pp. 29 and 37–41; Oram, ''David I'', pp. 19–21.&lt;/ref&gt;

By the 1030s Malcolm's sons, if he had any, were dead. The only evidence that he did have a son or sons is in Rodulfus Glaber's chronicle where Cnut is said to have stood as godfather to a son of Malcolm.&lt;ref&gt;''Early Sources'', p. 546; Duncan, pp. 30–31, understands Rodulfus Glaber as meaning that Duke Richard was godfather to a son of Cnut and Emma.&lt;/ref&gt; His grandson Thorfinn would have been unlikely to be accepted as king by the Scots, and he chose the sons of his other daughter, [[Bethóc]], who was married to [[Crínán of Dunkeld|Crínán]], [[lay abbot]] of [[Dunkeld]], and perhaps [[Mormaer of Atholl]]. It may be no more than coincidence, but in 1027 the Irish annals had reported the burning of Dunkeld, although no mention is made of the circumstances.&lt;ref&gt;Annals of Ulster and Annals of Loch Cé, s.a. 1027.&lt;/ref&gt; Malcolm's chosen heir, and the first ''tánaise ríg'' certainly known in Scotland, was [[Duncan I of Scotland|Duncan]].

It is possible that a third daughter of Malcolm married Findláech mac Ruaidrí and that Mac Bethad was thus his grandson, but this rests on relatively weak evidence.&lt;ref&gt;Hudson, pp. 224–225 discusses the question and the reliability of [[Andrew of Wyntoun]]'s chronicle, on which this rests.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Death and posterity ==
[[File:King Malcolms Gravestone at Glamis.jpg|thumb|19th-century engraving of &quot;King Malcolm's grave stone&quot; (Glamis no. 2) at [[Glamis]]]]
Malcolm died in 1034, [[Marianus Scotus]] giving the date as 25 November 1034. The king lists say that he died at [[Glamis]], variously describing him as a &quot;most glorious&quot; or &quot;most victorious&quot; king. The Annals of Tigernach report that &quot;Malcolm mac Cináeda, king of Scotland, the honour of all the west of Europe, died.&quot; The Prophecy of Berchán, perhaps the inspiration for John of Fordun and [[Andrew of Wyntoun]]'s accounts where Malcolm is killed fighting bandits, says that he died by violence, fighting &quot;the parricides&quot;, suggested to be the sons of Máel Brigte of Moray.&lt;ref&gt;''Early Sources'', pp. 572&amp;ndash;575; Duncan, pp. 33&amp;ndash;34.&lt;/ref&gt;

Perhaps the most notable feature of Malcolm's death is the account of Marianus, matched by the silence of the Irish annals, which tells us that Duncan I became king and ruled for five years and nine months. Given that his death in 1040 is described as being &quot;at an immature age&quot; in the Annals of Tigernach, he must have been a young man in 1034. The absence of any opposition suggests that Malcolm had dealt thoroughly with any likely opposition in his own lifetime.&lt;ref&gt;Duncan, pp. 32&amp;ndash;33.&lt;/ref&gt;

Tradition, dating from Fordun's time if not earlier, knew the [[Pictish stone]] now called &quot;Glamis 2&quot; as &quot;King Malcolm's grave stone&quot;. The stone is a Class II stone, apparently formed by re-using a [[Bronze Age]] standing stone. Its dating is uncertain, with dates from the 8th century onwards having been proposed. While an earlier date is favoured, an association with accounts of Malcolm's has been proposed on the basis of the iconography of the carvings.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |last=Laing |first=Lloyd |title=The date and context of the Glamis, Angus, carved Pictish stones |journal=Proceedings of the Society of Antiquaries of Scotland |year=2001 |volume=131 |pages=223&amp;ndash;239 |location=Edinburgh |url=http://ads.ahds.ac.uk/catalogue/adsdata/PSAS_2002/pdf/vol_131/131_223_239.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the question of Malcolm's putative pilgrimage, pilgrimages to Rome, or other long-distance journeys, were far from unusual. Thorfinn Sigurdsson, Cnut and Mac Bethad have already been mentioned. [[Rognvald Kali Kolsson]] is known to have gone crusading in the [[Mediterranean]] in the 12th century. Nearer in time, [[Dyfnwal III of Strathclyde|Dyfnwal of Strathclyde]] died on pilgrimage to Rome in 975 as did Máel Ruanaid uá Máele Doraid, King of the [[Cenél Conaill]], in 1025.

Not a great deal is known of Malcolm's activities beyond the wars and killings. The [[Book of Deer]] records that Malcolm &quot;gave a king's dues in Biffie and in Pett Meic-Gobraig, and two davochs&quot; to the monastery of [[Old Deer]].&lt;ref&gt;Gaelic Notes in the Book of Deer.&lt;/ref&gt; He was also probably not the founder of the Bishopric of Mortlach-Aberdeen. John of Fordun has a peculiar tale to tell, related to the supposed &quot;Laws of Malcolm MacKenneth&quot;, saying that Malcolm gave away all of Scotland, except for the Moot Hill at [[Scone, Perth and Kinross|Scone]], which is unlikely to have any basis in fact.&lt;ref&gt;Fordun, IV, xliii and Skene's notes; Duncan, p. 150; Barrow, ''Kingdom of the Scots'', p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Notes ==
{{reflist|2}}

== References ==
''For primary sources see also '' '''External links''' ''below.''
&lt;div style=&quot;font-size: 90%&quot;&gt;
* [[Alan Orr Anderson|Anderson, Alan Orr]], ''Early Sources of Scottish History A.D. 500&amp;ndash;1286'', volume 1. Reprinted with corrections. Paul Watkins, Stamford, 1990. ISBN 1-871615-03-8
* Anon., ''Orkneyinga Saga: The History of the Earls of Orkney'', tr. Hermann Pálsson and Paul Edwards. Penguin, London, 1978. ISBN 0-14-044383-5
* [[Geoffrey Barrow|Barrow, G.W.S.]], ''The Kingdom of the Scots.'' Edinburgh University Press, Edinburgh, 2003. ISBN 0-7486-1803-1
* Duncan, A.A.M., ''The Kingship of the Scots 842&amp;ndash;1292: Succession and Independence.'' Edinburgh University Press, Edinburgh, 2002. ISBN 0-7486-1626-8
* Fletcher, Richard, ''Bloodfeud: Murder and Revenge in Anglo-Saxon England.'' Penguin, London, 2002. ISBN 0-14-028692-6
* [[John of Fordun]], ''Chronicle of the Scottish Nation'', ed. [[William Forbes Skene]], tr. Felix J.H. Skene, 2 vols. Reprinted, Llanerch Press, Lampeter, 1993. ISBN 1-897853-05-X
* Higham, N.J., ''The Kingdom of Northumbria AD 350&amp;ndash;1100.'' Sutton, Stroud, 1993. ISBN 0-86299-730-5
* Hudson, Benjamin T., ''The Prophecy of Berchán: Irish and Scottish High-Kings of the Early Middle Ages.'' Greenwood, London, 1996.
* Smyth, Alfred P. ''Warlords and Holy Men: Scotland AD 80&amp;ndash;1000.'' Reprinted, Edinburgh: Edinburgh UP, 1998. ISBN 0-7486-0100-7
* [[Frank Stenton|Stenton, Sir Frank]], ''Anglo-Saxon England.'' 3rd edition, Oxford University Press, Oxford, 1971 ISBN 0-19-280139-2
* [[Snorri Sturluson|Sturluson, Snorri]], ''Heimskringla: History of the Kings of Norway'', tr. Lee M. Hollander. Reprinted University of Texas Press, Austin, 1992. ISBN 0-292-73061-6
&lt;/div&gt;

== External links ==
* [http://celt.ucc.ie/index.html CELT: Corpus of Electronic Texts] at [[University College Cork]] includes the ''Annals of Ulster'', ''Tigernach'', ''the Four Masters'' and ''Innisfallen'', the ''Chronicon Scotorum'', the ''Lebor Bretnach'' (which includes the ''Duan Albanach''), Genealogies, and various Saints' Lives. Most are translated into English, or translations are in progress.
* [http://www.worldwideschool.org/library/catalogs/bysubject-hst-european-Heimskringla.html Heimskringla] at [http://www.worldwideschool.org/ World Wide School]
* [http://www.northvegr.org/misc%20primary%20sources/icelandic%20sagas%20vol%203/titles.html &quot;icelandic sagas&quot;] at [http://www.northvegr.org/ Northvegr]
* [http://jebbo.home.texas.net/asc/e/e-L.html Anglo-Saxon Chronicle] an XML edition by Tony Jebson ([http://omacl.org/Anglo/ translation] at OMACL)
* [http://www.bbc.co.uk/scotland/history/articles/malcolm_ii/ Malcolm II, King of Alba 1005 – 1034]. Scotland's History. BBC.

{{S-start}}
{{s-hou | [[House of Alpin]] ||c. 980 ||25 November 1034}}
{{s-reg | }}
{{succession box |
  title=[[King of Scots]] |
  before=[[Kenneth III of Scotland|Kenneth III]]|
  after=[[Duncan I of Scotland|Duncan I]] |
  years=1005&amp;ndash;1034
}}
{{S-end}}

{{Pictish and Scottish Monarchs}}

{{good article}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2011}}

{{Authority control}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Malcolm 02 Of Scotland}}
[[Category:1034 deaths]]
[[Category:House of Alpin]]
[[Category:11th-century Scottish monarchs]]
[[Category:Burials at Iona Abbey]]
[[Category:Year of birth unknown]]
[[Category:954 births]]</text>
      <sha1>mnpprag1x2qjcmvlusm5k10ekbl86ej</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
