<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.28.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2600" case="first-letter">Topic</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>North Staffordshire Railway</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>564120</id>
    <revision>
      <id>723073286</id>
      <parentid>723064844</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-05-31T20:51:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Nthep</username>
        <id>1755837</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 723064844 by [[Special:Contributions/86.163.243.242|86.163.243.242]] ([[User talk:86.163.243.242|talk]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="49029">{{Use British English|date=January 2013}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2013}}
{{Infobox SG rail
| railroad_name     = North Staffordshire Railway
| logo_filename     = Logo 4.jpg
| logo_size         = 
| system_map        = 
| map_caption       =
| map_size          =
| marks             =
| image             = 
| image_size        =
| image_caption     =
| locale            = [[Staffordshire|North Staffordshire]]&lt;br/&gt;[[United Kingdom]]
| start_year        = 1845
| end_year          = 1923
| old_gauge=
| predecessor_line  =
| successor_line    = [[London, Midland and Scottish Railway]]
| length            =
| hq_city           = [[Stoke-on-Trent]]
| website           =
}}

{{North Staffordshire Railway RDT}}

The '''North Staffordshire Railway''' (NSR) was a [[Great Britain|British]] [[railway]] company formed in 1845 to promote a number of lines in the [[Stoke-on-Trent|Staffordshire Potteries]] and surrounding areas in [[Staffordshire]], [[Cheshire]], [[Derbyshire]] and [[Shropshire]].

The company was based in [[Stoke-on-Trent]] and was nicknamed '''The Knotty'''; its lines were built to the [[standard gauge]] of {{RailGauge|UKsg}}.  The main routes were constructed between 1846 and 1852 and ran from [[Macclesfield]] to [[Norton Bridge, Staffordshire|Norton Bridge]], just north of [[Stafford]], and from [[Crewe]] to Egginton Junction, west of [[Derby]].  Within these main connections with other railway companies, most notably the [[London and North Western Railway]] (LNWR), the company operated a network of smaller lines although the total route mileage of the company never exceeded {{convert|221|mi|km|1}}.  The majority of the passenger traffic was local although a number of LNWR services from [[Manchester]] to [[London]] were operated via Stoke.  Freight traffic was mostly coal and other minerals but the line also carried the vast majority of china and other pottery goods manufactured in England.

As the NSR was surrounded by other larger railway companies, there were in the 19th century several attempts emanating from other companies or proposals from NSR shareholders to amalgamate with one or more of the other companies that adjoined it.  None of these came to fruition and the NSR remained an independent company up to 1923 when it became part of the [[London, Midland and Scottish Railway|London, Midland and Scottish Railway Company]].

==Before the railway==
The area of north Staffordshire known today as the [[Stoke-on-Trent|City of Stoke-on-Trent]] was already a thriving industrial area before the arrival of the railways.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=17}}  The establishment of the pottery industry and the development of coal and ironstone mines in the 18th century had provided a need for materials, most noticeably clay, to be brought into the area. A corresponding need also arose for the resulting fragile goods i.e. pottery to be taken away from the area. This need had given rise in the mid to late 18th century of the construction of the [[Trent &amp; Mersey Canal]] (T&amp;M) and its various branches. Opened in 1777{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=18}} it was a spectacular success and paid dividends reaching 75% in 1822.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=18}}  By 1845 this had fallen to a still impressive 30%{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=18}} despite the onset of railway development in the North West of England. In 1836 the canal carried {{convert|184500|LT|t ST|0|lk=on}} of goods away and brought in {{convert|143610|LT|t ST|0}}.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=19}}

It was the Trent &amp; Mersey Canal company that built the first railway in north Staffordshire when in 1776{{sfnp|Jeuda|1999a|p=8}} it was granted powers to build a railway, or [[plateway]], from Caldon Low&lt;!-- The use of this spelling is known to be controversial. Different publications and organisations use different variations e.g. the Ordnance Survey use Caldon Low for the quarries but ''Cauldon Lowe'' for the hill behind the quarries. Cauldon Low is used by several businesses in the area. Christiansen and Miller use Caldon Low and as most of the references are to the quarry not the hill or the village of Cauldon, Caldon Low is used here. --&gt; limestone quarries to the canal basin at [[Froghall]] in the [[River Churnet#The Churnet Valley|Churnet Valley]].

==Formation of the company==
The [[Railway Mania]] of 1845 found the Potteries still without a railway, although the surrounding towns of Stafford, Crewe, Derby and Macclesfield were all connected to the fledgling railway system. The ''Staffordshire Potteries Railway'' promoted a route from [[Macclesfield]] to the [[Grand Junction Railway]] mainline at [[Norton Bridge, Staffordshire|Norton Bridge]] plus a spur to [[Crewe]].{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=24}}  At the same time the ''Churnet Valley Railway'' promoted a line from Macclesfield to [[Derby]] with a branch to [[Stoke-upon-Trent|Stoke]].{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=24}} After these two companies applied for the necessary powers to build the lines, Parliament suggested a pause of a year &quot;to afford time for consideration and for maturing some more complete scheme for the accommodation of that important district&quot;.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=25}}

The two companies decided to join forces to make a new approach to Parliament. They also incorporated in the scheme a proposal to join the [[Trent Valley Line|Trent Valley Railway]] into the Potteries. To do this they promoted the ''North Staffordshire or Churnet Valley and Trent Junction Railway''.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=25}}  This prospective company issued its prospectus on 30 April 1845 from offices at 1 Old Palace Yard, [[Westminster]], [[London]].{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=25}}  There was to be a share capital of £2,350,000 (£{{Formatprice|{{Inflation|UK|2350000|1845|{{inflation-year|UK}}|r=0}}}} in {{inflation-year|UK}}).{{Inflation-fn|UK}} in £20 shares (117,500 shares).{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=25}}

The prospectus outlined the NSR's plans for two main lines. The ''Pottery Line'' running from a junction with the [[Manchester and Birmingham Railway|Manchester &amp; Birmingham railway]] at [[Congleton]] to the Grand Junction Railway at [[Colwich, Staffordshire|Colwich]] was promoted, as 'giving the most ample accommodation to the towns of [[Tunstall, Staffordshire|Tunstall]], [[Burslem]], [[Newcastle-under-Lyme]], [[Hanley, Staffordshire|Hanley]], [[Stoke-upon-Trent|Stoke]], [[Fenton, Staffordshire|Fenton]], [[Longton, Staffordshire|Longton]] and [[Stone, Staffordshire|Stone]]'. The ''Churnet Line'' was to run from Macclesfield though [[Leek]], [[Cheadle, Staffordshire|Cheadle]] and [[Uttoxeter]] to join the [[Midland Railway]] line between [[Burton-upon-Trent]] and Derby forming a direct link between [[Manchester]] and Derby.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=25}}

The company was formally incorporated in April 1845 under the shorter name of the North Staffordshire Railway.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=26}}  As a way of eliminating opposition to the Company's Bills in Parliament, and to allow it to promote a line to [[Liverpool]], the company made an agreement to take over the Trent &amp; Mersey Canal Company. This was achieved by T&amp;M shares being swapped for [[preference share]]s in the NSR.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=26}}  These preference shares paid a guaranteed annual dividend of 5% once the entire railway was open.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=26}}  The total purchase cost of the T&amp;M to the NSR £1,170,000.{{sfnp|Jeuda|1999b|p=7}}

On 25 November 1845 the ''Derby and Crewe Railway'' was absorbed into the NSR Scheme. This was a line that was being supported by the [[Grand Junction Railway]] (GJR) running between Derby and [[Crewe]] via Uttoxeter and Stoke. It was to eliminate the opposition of the Grand Junction company to the other NSR proposals that the NSR agreed to absorb the ''Derby and Crewe''. However part of the deal was that the proposed line from [[Kidsgrove railway station|Harecastle]] to Liverpool was abandoned. Despite having arranged to purchase the T&amp;M canal for a considerable sum, to obtain support for the Liverpool extension the NSR agreed to the GJR demand. All that survived of the NSR Liverpool plan was the short branch to [[Sandbach]] from Harecastle.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=28}}

==Parliamentary approval and construction==
On 26 June 1846, the three NSR acts were passed with the total of £2,900,000{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=29}} in share capital being shared amongst the three lines, with seven years allowed for the completion of each line. The ''North Staffordshire Railway (Pottery Line) Act''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |date=26 June 1846 |title=North Staffordshire Railway (Pottery Line) Act 1846 |periodical=Acts of the Parliaments of the United Kingdom |volume=1846 |issue=''c.lxxxv'' |url=http://www.opsi.gov.uk/chron-tables/local/chron033 |accessdate=25 April 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  provided for the construction of the line from Macclesfield to Colwich with branches to [[Norton Bridge railway station|Norton Bridge]], Newcastle, Silverdale and Crewe. This act also vested the Trent &amp; Mersey Canal in the NSR. Allocated capital for this work was £1,500,000. The second act, the ''North Staffordshire Railway (Harecastle and Sandbach) Act''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |date=26 June 1846 |title=North Staffordshire Railway (Harecastle and Sandbach) Act 1846 |periodical=Acts of the Parliaments of the United Kingdom |volume=1846 |issue=''c.lxxxiv'' |url=http://www.opsi.gov.uk/chron-tables/local/chron033 |accessdate=25 April 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; provided for the construction of the line from [[Kidsgrove railway station|Harecastle]] to [[Sandbach]], allocated capital for these works was £200,000. Finally the ''North Staffordshire Railway (Churnet Valley Line) Act''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |date=26 June 1846 |title=North Staffordshire Railway (Churnet Valley) Act 1846 |periodical=Acts of the Parliaments of the United Kingdom |volume=1846 |issue=''c.lxxxvi'' |url=http://www.opsi.gov.uk/chron-tables/local/chron033 |accessdate=25 April 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; authorised the construction of the line from North Rode to Burton, a branch from [[Tutbury]] to Willington Junction near Derby, and the line between Uttoxeter and Stoke;  £1,200,000 of capital was allocated to this.

To start the construction work, there was an official 'cutting of the first sod' ceremony. This took place in September 1846{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=12}} The site chosen for the ceremony was a field in [[Etruria, Staffordshire|Etruria]]. A roped off enclosure for directors was created and the remainder of the field was reserved for invited guests. A mile long procession headed by [[John Lewis Ricardo]], [[Member of Parliament]] for [[Stoke-upon-Trent (UK Parliament constituency)|Stoke-on-Trent]] and chairman of the NSR Company, formed. On Ricardo's arrival, the crowds broke through the roped off area and Ricardo was pushed and shoved. During the actual cutting he buckled the silver spade and had difficulty removing the sod. Finally, his hat blew away.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=37}}

[[File:Cutting.jpeg|thumb|Cutting of the first sod at Etruria]]

Construction work went ahead under the supervision of the Consulting Engineer, [[George Parker Bidder]]. By February 1847 there were 1,318 men and 60 horses working between [[Macclesfield]] and Colwich and they had removed {{convert|80000|cuyd|m3}} of earth, driven {{convert|843|yd|m|0}} of tunnel heading and erected {{convert|12000|yd|m|0}} yards of fencing.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=40}}

On 2 July 1847 the ''North Staffordshire Railway Act''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |date=2 July 1847 |title=North Staffordshire Railway Act 1847 |periodical=Acts of the Parliaments of the United Kingdom |volume=1847 |issue=''c.cviii'' |url=http://www.opsi.gov.uk/chron-tables/local/chron036 |accessdate=25 April 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; was passed. The act was necessary was because of problems encountered with the construction of the Crewe branch. The opportunity was taken to authorise several other deviations and small branches. It also consolidated the previous acts and importantly, forced the NSR to ensure that all lines were completed by specifying that ordinary [[dividend]]s were not to exceed 5% until the Churnet Valley and Willington lines had been opened.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=42}}

Work continued apace and by 3 April 1848 the first freight trains were run.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=44}} Passenger services started on 17 April 1848 and the first passenger train left the temporary station at Wheildon Road, Stoke, hauled by locomotive No. 1 ''Dragon'', heading for a temporary station at Norton Bridge on the [[London and North Western Railway]] (LNWR).{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=12}}  The opening of the line gave the Potteries a railway link with Birmingham and London which made it an instant success with the public. Profits for the first two months were £1,668 'exceeding expectations'.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=45}}

The remaining lines under the original Acts were opened in stages but all were completed and open by the end of 1852 when the Stoke to Newcastle and Newcastle to Knutton sections opened.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=49}} A few months after the opening of the first line, the imposing permanent station in Winton Square, Stoke was opened on 9 October 1848. [[Stoke-on-Trent railway station|Stoke station]] then became the headquarters of the NSR.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=102}}

==Later lines==
Later branches constructed in the nineteenth century included lines from Stoke-on-Trent to [[Congleton]] via [[Smallthorne]] and [[Biddulph]]; Stoke-on-Trent to [[Leek, Staffordshire|Leek]]; Newcastle to [[Silverdale, Staffordshire|Silverdale]], [[Keele]] and [[Market Drayton]] (junction with the [[Great Western Railway]]); [[Alsager]] to [[Audley, Staffordshire|Audley]], Leycett and Keele, and [[Rocester]] to [[Ashbourne, Derbyshire|Ashbourne]].{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|pp=299–301}}

Also opened in the nineteenth century was the only NSR line to achieve any degree of fame, the [[Potteries Loop Line]] from [[Etruria railway station|Etruria]] via Hanley, Cobridge, Burslem, Tunstall, Pitts Hill, Newchapel and Goldenhill to [[Kidsgrove]] Liverpool Rd. Authorised in stages in 1864–5, it opened to traffic in 1873.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=299}}  Its fame came from several mentions and a description of a journey on a Burslem to Hanley train in [[Arnold Bennett|Arnold Bennett's]] ''[[The Old Wives' Tale]]''.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|pp=292–293}}

Twentieth century construction included a branch from Leek to Cauldon Lowe via Waterhouses{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=118}} from where the {{RailGauge|2ft6in}} narrow gauge [[Leek and Manifold Valley Light Railway]] (L&amp;MV) was constructed through the Hamps and Manifold river valleys to Hulme End near [[Hartington]]. Although the L&amp;MV was nominally independent the NSR both worked and operated the line.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=118}}

Finally in 1910, [[Trentham Park Branch Line|a very short line]] was built from Stoke-on-Trent to Trentham Park. It was authorised as part of an alternative line to Newcastle-under-Lyme but construction work beyond Trentham was quickly abandoned owing to rising costs.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=115}}  The same act of parliament also transferred the [[Cheadle Branch Line|Cheadle Railway]] to the NSR.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=114}} The Cheadle Railway was a small local company constructed with NSR's backing, built at great cost over a period of twelve years. It was a short line from [[Cresswell, Staffordshire|Cresswell]] to [[Cheadle, Staffordshire|Cheadle]], this line, only four miles long, included a very difficult tunnel. The line was opened from Cresswell to Totmonslow 7 November 1892 and to Cheadle, 1 January 1901.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=82}}

A full list of authorisation and opening dates for sections of the NSR is [[#NSR main lines and branch lines—opening dates|given below]].

==Macclesfield, Bollington and Marple Railway==
{{Main|Macclesfield, Bollington and Marple Railway}}

The Macclesfield, Bollington and Marple Railway (MB&amp;M) was a joint line which the NSR participated in.{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=49}}  A short line of just under {{convert|11|mi|km|0}}{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=303}} it was opened with the [[Manchester, Sheffield and Lincolnshire Railway]] (MS&amp;L) in 1869 to give the NSR to Manchester independently of the LNWR. As relationships between the NSR and the LNWR grew better the reason for the line lessened as the MB&amp;M route to Manchester was 5 miles longer than the LNWR route.{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=51}}&gt; Both passenger and freight traffic was handled by the MS&amp;L (or as it later became the [[Great Central Railway]]) with the buildings maintained by the NSR.{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=51}}

==Running powers with other companies==
As a company with only a small route mileage the NSR made extensive use of [[Arrangements between railroads#Trackage rights|running powers]] and in exchange granted running powers to other companies.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=209}}

The earliest agreements were reached with the LNWR. In 1849 an agreement was reached where LNWR traffic could work over the NSR system but in exchange a certain amount of the LNWR London trains had to be routed via Stoke.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=58}} These Manchester to London Euston restaurant car expresses were unique in often being hauled by NSR tank engines from Manchester to Stoke-on-Trent where the LNWR express engines took over for the run via Stone, Sandon, Colwich, and the main line to [[London Euston]]. The NSR received a payment for every through passenger on these trains and employed a small army of ticket inspectors to examine and clip (with its distinctive 'P' clip) every ticket during the Stoke-on-Trent station stop.{{sfnp|Walley|2003}} The agreement did give the NSR access to destinations such as [[Llandudno]], Manchester, Stafford, [[Wolverhampton]] and [[Buxton]]. NSR goods trains were able to run to places such as Liverpool and [[Rugby, Warwickshire|Rugby]].{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|pp=209–210}}  The LNWR also used running rights over the Uttoxeter–Ashbourne line to run through coaches from Buxton to London via Nuneaton.{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=34}} As well as the running power agreements with the LNWR there was a very short joint line of {{convert|32|chain|m|0}} at Middlewood and three jointly owned stations; Ashbourne, Colwich and Macclesfield Goods.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=303}}

Equally important in terms of traffic but not as extensive in terms of route were the running power agreements with the [[Midland Railway]] (MR). For the NSR passenger traffic into Derby and Burton was authorised and good traffic as far afield as [[Wellingborough]].{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=209}} The arrangements with these two companies allowed the NSR to run its longest passenger service, between Derby and Llandudno. These trains only ran {{convert|44.5|mi|km|1}} on NSR rails, with {{convert|6.5|mi|km|1}} over MR but with the majority, {{convert|67.5|mi|km|1}} over the LNWR.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=209}}

In 1867, an independent local company built the [[Stafford and Uttoxeter Railway]], later incorporated into the [[Great Northern Railway (Great Britain)|Great Northern Railway]] (GNR).  The GNR built its [[GNR Derbyshire and Staffordshire Extension]] from [[Nottingham]] and [[Derby Friargate railway station|Derby Friargate]] via [[Mickleover]] to [[Egginton Junction railway station|Egginton Junction]] with running powers over the NSR from Etwall, through [[Uttoxeter]], to Bromshall Junction. The GNR granted the NSR running rights to [[Nottingham]], [[Colwick]], [[Leicester]] and [[Peterborough]].{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=209}} Apart from excursion trains to Nottingham and goods trains to Colwick, the NSR did not take advantage of these powers.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=209}}

Although the NSR had joint ownership of the MB&amp;M with the MS&amp;L the NSR did not have running powers over the rest of the MS&amp;L and was content to let the MS&amp;L handle all traffic north of Middlewood.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=211}} Finally with both the NSR and the [[Great Western Railway]] (GWR) expanding into Shropshire running rights were agreed for NSR trains to run to Hodnet and Wellington and in return GWR goods trains could run to Stoke.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|pp=209–210}}

==Amalgamation proposals and financial strength==
There were several proposals made either to the NSR or by it, to merge or lease or sell the company to other railway companies. The first was in 1849 when the LNWR, using its financial strength, made suggestions about a merger. To avoid this the NSR had to agree to the running powers outlined above.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=58}} A further attempt in 1851 got as far as a parliamentary bill being submitted for amalgamation until the [[Select Committee (Westminster System)|select committee]] appointed to look at the bill reported against the idea.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=60}}  The LNWR made a further attempt in 1855 which failed because of concerted opposition by the MR, MS&amp;L and GWR.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=60}}  Less than twenty years later, in 1870, these four companies all combined to look at taking over the NSR following a decision by the NSR board to sell or lease the company. The four rival companies were unable to agree on who would take what share of the NSR and the proposal floundered.{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=62}}

In 1875 the MS&amp;L proposed an amalgamation which initially found favour with the NSR board and shareholders but eventually fell through when the MS&amp;L finances were investigated{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=62}} and it was found that the MS&amp;L was no stronger financially than the NSR. Only two years later some NSR shareholders proposed a merger with the MR,{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=62}} the board dismissed the proposal with the chairman reminding shareholders that &lt;blockquote&gt;
The NSR had a small mileage and had to collect traffic for the large companies which surrounded it. They made profits from good mileages while the NSR had to do a great deal for comparatively little return.{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=62}}
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The quote about little return was accurate. In 1877 the NSR dividend was only 2% compared with the dividend of 6% paid by the LNWR to its shareholders.{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=62}} A year later the dividend fell to its lowest ever point of only 1⅝%.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=97}}  However it recovered and after 1881 never fell below 3%.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=97}}  In 1891 the NSR paid a 5% dividend for the first time, a level not to be reached again until 1913.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=128}}

In 1913 the NSR ranked as the eighteenth largest company by route mileage with {{convert|216|mi|km|0}}.{{sfnp|Jenkinson|1988|p=86}} Passenger numbers stood at 7,200,000{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=159}} and goods traffic handled by the NSR consisted of {{convert|1750000|LT|MT|0}} of goods, nearly {{convert|4000000|LT|MT|0}} of coal and coke and over {{convert|2000000|LT|MT|0}} of other minerals.{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=76}}  Among the {{convert|1750000|LT|MT|0}} of goods was {{convert|150000|LT|MT|0}} of pottery, over five-sixths of the entire production in Britain.{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=76}}

==Grouping==
{{details|Railways Act 1921}}
Under the [[Railways Act 1921]], the NSR was one of the eight major companies designated to form the North Western, Midland and West Scottish Group.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|date=19 August 1921|title=Railways Act 1921|periodical=Acts of the United Kingdom Parliament |volume=1921 |issue=55 |pages=schedule 1|url=http://www.opsi.gov.uk/RevisedStatutes/Acts/ukpga/1921/cukpga_19210055_en_1|accessdate=28 April 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This group became the [[London, Midland and Scottish Railway]] (LMS).  The act came into force on 1 January 1923 but along with the [[Caledonian Railway]], the NSR amalgamation into the LMS was delayed until 1 July 1923 due to certain legal requirements not being completed by the due date.{{sfnp|Nock|1982|p=14}}

==Accidents and incidents==
*In January 1885, a [[London and North Western Railway]] express passenger train collided with a freight train near [[Stoke-on-Trent]]. One person was killed.{{sfnp|Hall|1990|p=52}}

==Other interests==
In common with most other British railway companies, the NSR decided early on that it was advantageous to carry out its own maintenance work in all departments and also to undertake much of its own new construction work. [[Stoke railway works]] were opened in 1849,{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=251}} capable of producing [[carriages]], [[wagons]] and other equipment.  Construction of [[locomotives]] followed later, commencing in 1864.{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=79}}

Ownership of the Trent &amp; Mersey canal made the NSR the biggest canal owning railway{{sfnp|Simmons|1997|p=353}} with {{convert|130|mi|km|0}} of waterways owned. The T&amp;M owned [[Rudyard Lake]] which the NSR made use of as a leisure complex, building a golf course, in 1905, on land adjoining the lake.{{sfnp|Jeuda|1999b|p=7}}  A further area of interest, again via ownership of the T&amp;M, was the lease on Caldon Low quarries.{{sfnp|Jeuda|1999b|p=7}}  Associated with the quarry was the {{RailGauge|3ft6in}} tramway that ran from the quarries to Froghall making the NSR the operator of lines of three different gauges.
[[File:Bucknall &amp; Northwood Station 1933424 71025ab9.jpg|thumb|right|275px|Bucknall &amp; Northwood Station in 1962]]

Although the NSR principally served the urban areas of the Potteries, it did promote the area for tourism, especially the [[River Churnet|Churnet Valley]] which local hoteliers had labelled as &quot;Staffordshire's little Switzerland&quot;.{{sfnp|Kelly|1896|p=53}}  The company issued a 150-page guide called ''Picturesque Staffordshire'' to support this promotion and dispel the widespread held idea that the county was dull and bleak{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=9}} In addition to the tourist traffic generated the NSR owned three hotels; the ''[[North Stafford Hotel|North Stafford]]'' in Stoke (opposite Stoke station), the ''Churnet Valley'' in Leek and the ''Hotel Rudyard'' at Rudyard.{{sfnp|Dow|1970|p=6}}

==Officers of the company==
&lt;ref&gt;This section is compiled from {{cite web |title=A Chronology of the North Staffordshire Railway |url= http://www.lnw1.demon.co.uk/chronology.htm  |publisher=The North Staffordshire Railway Study Group|accessdate=12 May 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
! Name
! Period of tenure
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;|'''Chairmen'''
|-
|[[John Lewis Ricardo]]
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1845–1855
|-
|Thomas Broderick
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1855
|-
|John Lewis Ricardo
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1855–1862
|-
|Thomas Broderick
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1862–1865
|-
|Charles Pearson
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1865–1874
|-
|Colin Minton Campbell
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1874–1883
|-
|[[Sir Thomas Salt, 1st Baronet|Sir Thomas Salt]]
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1883–1904
|-
|[[Tonman Mosley, 1st Baron Anslow|Tonman Mosley (later Lord Anslow)]]
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1904–1923
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;|'''General managers'''
|-
|Samuel Bidder
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1847–1853
|-
|James Forsyth
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1853–1863
|-
|Percy Morris
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1863–1876
|-
|Martin Smith
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1876–1882
|-
|William Phillipps
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1882–1919
|-
|Frederick Arthur Lowry Barnwell
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1919–1923
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;|'''Resident Engineers'''
|-
|Samuel Bidder
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1845–1848
|-
|James Forsyth
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1848–1865
|-
|James Johnson
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1865–1870
|-
|Thomas Dodds
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1870–1874
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;|'''Locomotive superintendents'''
|-
|Thomas Angus
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1874–1875
|-
|Charles Clare
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1875–1882
|-
|Luke Longbottom
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1882–1902
|-
|John Adams
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1902–1915
|-
|John Hookham
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1915–1923
|-
|}

==Motive power and rolling stock==

===Locomotives===
{{further|Locomotives of the North Staffordshire Railway}}
NSR motive power came from a mixture of sources. Before the establishment of Stoke works there was a complete reliance on outside contractors. The first locomotives were either purchased from contractors building the line{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=78}} or firms such as [[Sharp Brothers and Company]], [[B. Hick and Sons|B. Hick and Son]], [[Kitson, Thompson and Hewitson]], the [[Vulcan Foundry]] or [[Jones and Potts]].{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=309}}

Originally the resident engineers were responsible for the locomotive stock and the first four holders of this post were all primarily civil engineers.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=214}}  In 1863 the new general manager, Morris, commissioned an outside report on the NSR locomotive fleet which recommended the rebuilding of 50 engines.{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=78}}  By the time this report was produced a new engineer, Johnson, had been appointed.  He undertook the improvements but the results were unsatisfactory and Johnson left in 1870 after only five years in post.{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=79}} The only significant event of Johnson's tenure was the building of the first engines at Stoke works when three [[0-6-0T]] engines were built in 1868.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=309}}  Johnson's successor, Dodds, fared no better as his patented wedge motion, a type of [[valve gear]], was unsuccessful. Dodds was dismissed in 1875 and a new post of locomotive superintendent created with a locomotive engineer, Angus, in charge.{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=79}}  Although only in post for two years Angus replaced all the wedge motions with [[Stephenson valve gear]].{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=79}}

There followed a long period of locomotive construction internally with all locomotives between 1875 and 1900 coming from the company works.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|pp=311–313}}  The vast majority of these being [[Tank locomotive|tank engines]] although a small number of [[Tender (rail)|tender engines]] were constructed.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|pp=311–313}}  Most engines, whether tank or tender locomotives were built with either [[2-4-0]] or [[0-6-0]] wheel arrangements.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|pp=311–313}} An urgent need for heavier goods engines prompted the company to go to contractors and a small number of 0-6-0 designs were purchased from [[Nasmyth, Wilson and Company]].{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=225}}  In 1903 five [[0-6-2T]] engines were purchased from Vulcan Foundry{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=227}} and with the exception of two locomotives for shunting purchased from [[Kerr Stuart]] in 1919 these were the last engines not to be built by the company at Stoke.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=233}}

Apart from engine No 1 of 1848 being named ''Dragon'' only two other NSR engines were ever named, in 1882 Class C 2-4-0 No. 55 was named ''Colin Minton Campbell'' and Class C No. 54 ''John Bramley Moore'' after the chairman and deputy chairman of the company, respectively.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=222}}

The NSR also used a small number of [[railmotor]]s with three being purchased in 1905 from [[Beyer, Peacock and Company]].{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=83}}  They were used on routes such as the Stoke–Newcastle service but were not a success. The vehicles did survive until grouping but had been taken out of service for some time some years earlier.{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=83}} In addition to the NSR locomotives were the two engines of the Leek &amp; Manifold and the three engines that worked the Caldon Low quarries. The former were purchased from [[Kitson and Company]] and the latter from [[Brush Traction|Henry Hughes]] and [[W. G. Bagnall]].{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=315}}

At grouping 196 steam locomotives including the L&amp;MV and Caldon Low engines{{sfnp|Essery|Jenkinson|1981|pp=77–79}} were absorbed into the LMS along with the three railmotors and one battery electric locomotive. This last engine was built at Stoke in 1917 for shunting the copper works at [[Oakamoor]].{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=233}} Four engines under construction at Stoke in 1923 were completed and also added to the LMS stock.{{sfnp|Rowledge|1989|p=29}} Although many of the locomotives were not old, due to the LMS policy of standardisation all NSR engines had been withdrawn from service by 1939.{{sfnp|Essery|Jenkinson|1981|pp=77–79}}  The one exception was the battery electric shunting locomotive which remained in service until 1963.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=233}}

Two NSR locomotives are preserved. NSR No. 2, an 0-6-2T [[NSR New L Class|New L class]] (one of the four constructed in 1923) and the battery electric locomotive.  Both formed part of the [[List of rolling stock items in the UK National Collection|national collection]] at the [[National Railway Museum]]&lt;ref name=&quot;NRM&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=NRM Collections: Locomotives |url=http://www.nrm.org.uk/OurCollection/LocomotivesAndRollingStock.aspx |publisher=National Railway Museum |location= York |year=2009 |accessdate=13 May 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; but in 2016 ownership of the New L class locomotive was transferred to the [[Foxfield Railway]] where the locomotive is now on display.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.national-preservation.com/threads/nsr-new-l-no-2.692013/ |title=NSR New L No 2 |date=25 April 2016 |accessdate=28 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Locomotive depots====
The largest [[Motive power depot|locomotive depot]] was at Stoke, with 125 engines at grouping.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=236}}  The next largest was Alsager with an allocation of 15 engines. Other NSR depots existed at Macclesfield, Derby, Uttoxeter, Burton and Crewe.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=236}}  Stoke also had sub-sheds at [[Market Drayton]], [[Leekbrook]] and Ashbourne.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=236}}  NSR engines were also sub-shedded at other companies depots, with arrangements existing at the LNWR sheds at Stafford, Liverpool Edge Hill and Manchester Longsight and the GNR shed at Nottingham Colwick.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=236}}

====Locomotive liveries====
Up to 1882 locomotives were a bright green with black and white lining with a [[Stafford knot|Staffordshire knot]] emblem on the tank or tender sides.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=222}}  Longbottom introduced a new livery of a red brown with black, yellow and [[vermilion]] lining.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=222}}  Longbottom was succeeded by Adams who changed the livery once more to a crimson shade called Madder Lake{{efn|Although called Madder Lake, the [[pigment]] was not made from the [[Rubia|Madder]] plant but from [[Cochineal#Dye|Cochineal]]. {{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=227}} }}with yellow and vermilion lining. The knot emblem was replaced by the company coat of arms and the words ''North Stafford''.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=227}}

===Coaching stock===
The NSR coaching stock was, even until grouping, predominantly four and six wheeled vehicles.{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=88}} Four-wheeled carriages were the norm from the start and the last were constructed in the 1880s,{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=238}} although by then they had progressed from the unbraked coaches of the 1840s with the introduction of the [[Emergency brake (train)|communication cord]] in 1869{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=238}} and the [[Vacuum brake|simple vacuum brake]] in 1883.{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=87}} The first [[bogie]] coaches were introduced in 1906{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=242}} for use on the Derby–Llandudno service{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=88}} and these were followed by further examples until 1923. By 1919 all carriages, except 13 four-wheelers used on miners trains, had been fitted with steam heating{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=244}} and a number of vehicles had been fitted with through pipes to allow use in trains equipped with [[Vacuum brake#Limitations|Westinghouse brakes]].{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=244}} Most carriages were constructed at Stoke but some were purchased from companies such as the [[Metro Cammell|Metropolitan Carriage, Wagon and Finance Company]].{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=244}}

One area were the NSR was a pioneer was in the use of electrical lighting being the largest of only three British railway companies{{efn|The others were the [[London, Tilbury and Southend Railway|London, Tilbury &amp; Southend]] and the [[Great North of Scotland Railway|Great North of Scotland]]{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=241}} }} to switch from oil to electric lighting and not use any form of gas lighting.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=241}}  The first coach was fitted in 1897 and new stock constructed from 1899 had electric lighting as standard.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=241}}  Conversion of the remaining stock was slow and in 1910 there were still some oil lit carriages in service.{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=88}}

====Coaching liveries====
Coaching stock was originally claret{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=245}} but in 1875 was changed to Victoria Brown and white (except for branch line trains which carried an all over Victoria Brown livery) with gold and blue lining.  Victoria Brown was the same red brown colour as Longbottom had introduced for NSR locomotives.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=245}}  In 1882 waist panels were additionally painted white.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=245}}  This colour scheme lasted until 1896 when it was changed to an overall Victoria Lake (brown) colour with gold and blue lining.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=245}} Adams changed the livery to Madder Lake in 1903 to match the locomotives, the lining became yellow and red.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=245}}  A final minor change was to paint the waist panels of first class compartments cream to distinguish them.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=246}} A constant presence was the company coat of arms being displayed on the coach sides.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=245}}

===Goods stock===
Over its life the NSR built or bought many thousands of goods wagons.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|pp=246–247}}  Early wagons had [[Buffer (rail transport)|dumb buffers]] with [[Buffer (rail transport)|spring buffers]] being introduced from 1870.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|pp=246–247}}  Early wagons were not of high capacity e.g. typical open wagons were only of {{convert|4|LT|MT}} capacity.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|pp=246–247}} but capacities grew to {{convert|10|LT|MT}} on average by 1923.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|pp=246–247}}

The NSR handed over to the LMS 6,612 goods wagons of which over 5,000 were open wagons for the transport of coal and other minerals.{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=88}}  This number was dwarfed by the number of wagons owned by the pits, ironworks, other industrial operations and traders in the Stoke area.{{sfnp|Christiansen|1997|p=88}}  An unusual set of wagons to be seen were the bright yellow with red lettering vans owned by the [[Ringling Bros. and Barnum &amp; Bailey Circus|Barnum and Bailey]] circus who had their main English depot in Stoke.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=251}}

====Goods liveries====
Goods vehicles were painted red oxide with white lettering and a white Staffordshire knot.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=250}} The letters ''N.S.R'' with only two full stops were carried in small letters.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=250}}  From 1912 the letters were increased in size but changed to just ''N S'' with a central knot and no full stops.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=250}}

==The Knotty==
The NSR is one of the few railways to become the subject of a play. In 1966, [[Peter Cheeseman]], artistic director of The [[Victoria Theatre, Stoke]] wrote a musical documentary about the NSR called ''The Knotty''. Featured in the play were the voices of several NSR staff who had been interviewed especially for the play.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Memories of The Knotty|url=http://www.thisisstaffordshire.co.uk/nostalgia/Memoryarticle-459025-details/article.html |publisher= Staffordshire Evening Sentinel|date= 8 November 2008  |accessdate=28 April 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The script with introductory notes by Cheeseman was published in 1970.{{sfnp|Syssoyeva|Proudfit|2013|p=104}} Sound recordings of the production, ''The Knotty - a musical documentary'', was released on LP by Argo Transacord (ZTR 125) in 1970 and as a digital version in 2014 it was digitised by  Transacord Digital.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.discogs.com/Cast-Of-The-Victoria-Theatre-Stoke-On-Trent-The-Knotty-A-Musical-Documentary/release/6690925 |title=Cast Of The Victoria Theatre, Stoke-On-Trent – The Knotty (A Musical Documentary) |date=2016 |accessdate=2 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==NSR main lines and branch lines—opening dates==
Ricardo, North Staffordshire Railway chairman described the network as being like &quot;a small octopus&quot;;{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=58}} but not one NSR station was more than {{convert|30|mi|km}} from Stoke-on-Trent.{{sfnp|Dow|1970|p=105}} Dates of authorisation and opening are given in the following table.{{sfnp|Christiansen|Miller|1971|p=299}}

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Section of Line
! Date Construction
Authorised
! Passenger
Service Started
! Goods
Service Started
|-
| Stoke-on-Trent – Norton Bridge
| 26 June 1846
| 17 April 1848
| 3 April 1848
|-
| Stoke-on-Trent – Uttoxeter
| 26 June 1846
| 7 August 1848
| 7 August 1848
|-
| Uttoxeter – Burton-on-Trent
| 26 June 1846
| 11 September 1848
| 11 September 1848
|-
| Stoke-on-Trent – Crewe and Congleton
| 26 June 1846
| 9 October 1848
| 9 October 1848
|-
| Stone–Colwich
| 26 June 1846
| 1 May 1849
| 1 May 1849
|-
| Congleton–Macclesfield
| 26 June 1846
| 18 June 1849
| 18 June 1849
|-
| [[Churnet Valley Line]]
 
| 26 June 1846
| 13 July 1849
| 13 July 1849
|-
| Tutbury–Derby
| 26 June 1846
| 13 July 1849
| 13 July 1849
|-
| Harecastle–Sandbach
| 26 June 1846
| 3 July 1893
| 21 January 1852
|-
| Stoke-on-Trent – Newcastle-under-Lyme
| 26 June 1846
| 6 September 1852
| 6 September 1852
|-
| Newcastle-under-Lyme – Knutton
| 2 July 1847
| May 1863
| 6 September 1852
|-
| Knutton–Silverdale
| 13 August 1859
| May 1863
| 1850{{efn|Goods traffic between Knutton and Silverdale started in 1850, even though it was not authorised until nine years later. Ralph Sneyd owned collieries and ironworks in the Silverdale area. In 1849 Sneyd began construction of his own private goods line which was about {{convert|2|mi|km}} long – this was not authorised by parliament. When the NSR came to build its lines in this area they took a 999 year lease of Mr Sneyd's private line and incorporated it into its own network. Parliamentary authorisation for the line was granted retrospectively by Mr Sneyd's Railway Act 1861{{Cite news |title=Mr. Sneyd's Railway 1861 |periodical=Acts of the Parliaments of the United Kingdom |volume=1861 |issue=''c.lxxi'' |url=http://www.opsi.gov.uk/chron-tables/local/chron050 |accessdate=28 April 2009 }} }}
|-
| Silverdale – Market Drayton
| 29 July 1864
| 1 February 1870
| 1 February 1870
|-
| Etruria–Shelton
| 2 July 1847
| January 1862
| 1850
|-
| Shelton–Hanley
| 13 August 1859
| 13 July 1864
| 20 December 1861
|-
| Hanley–Burslem
| 5 July 1865
| 1 November 1873
| 1 November 1873
|-
| Burslem–Tunstall
| 5 July 1865
| 1 December 1873
| 1 December 1873
|-
| Tunstall–Goldenhill
| 5 July 1865
| 1 October 1874
| 1 October 1874
|-
| Goldenhill–Kidsgrove
| 5 July 1865
| 15 November 1875
| 15 November 1875
|-
| Rocester–Ashbourne
| 22 July 1848
| 31 May 1852
| 31 May 1852
|-
| Biddulph Valley Line
| 24 July 1854
| 1 June 1864
| 28 August 1860
|-
| [[Stoke–Leek line|Milton Junction - Leek Brook Junction]]
| 13 July 1863
| 1 November 1867
| 1 November 1867
|-
| Audley Line
| 29 July 1864
| 28 June 1880
| 24 July 1870
|-
| Cresswell–Tean
| 7 August 1888
| 7 November 1892
| 7 November 1892
|-
| Tean–Cheadle
| 7 August 1888
| 1 January 1901
| 1 January 1901
|-
| [[Leek and Manifold Valley Light Railway|Waterhouses - Hulme End (L&amp;MVLR)]]

| 6 March 1899
| 27 June 1904
| 29 June 1904
|-
| [[Waterhouses branch line|Leek Brook - Ipstones]]

| 6 March 1899
| 5 June 1905
| 5 June 1905
|-
| [[Waterhouses branch line|Ipstones - Waterhouses]]
| 6 March 1899
| 1 July 1905
| 1 July 1905
|-
| Trentham Park Branch
| 21 August 1907
| 1 April 1910
| 1 April 1910
|-
|}

==See also==
* [[Leek and Manifold Valley Light Railway]]

==Notes==

===Explanatory notes===
{{notelist}}

===References===
{{Reflist|30em}}

===Sources===
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |last1=Christiansen |first1=Rex |last2=Miller |first2=Robert William |title=The North Staffordshire Railway |year=1971 |publisher=David &amp; Charles |location=[[Newton Abbot]], [[Devon]] |isbn=0-7153-5121-4 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book |last1=Christiansen |first1=Rex |title=Portrait of the North Staffordshire Railway|year=1997|publisher=Ian Allan |location=[[Shepperton]], [[Surrey]] |isbn=0-7110-2546-0 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book |last1=Dow |first1=George |authorlink1=George Dow|title= North Staffordshire Album|year=1970|publisher=Ian Allan |location=[[Shepperton]], [[Surrey]]|isbn=0-7110-0128-6 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book |last1=Essery |first1=Bob |authorlink1=Bob Essery |last2=Jenkinson |first2=David |authorlink2= David Jenkinson |title=An Illustrated History of LMS Locomotives. Volume 1: General Review and Locomotive Liveries |year=1981 |publisher= Oxford Publishing |location=[[Oxford]] |isbn=0-86093-087-4|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Hall |first=Stanley |title=The Railway Detectives |year=1990 |publisher=Ian Allan |location=London |isbn=0 7110 1929 0 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book |last1=Jenkinson |first1=David |authorlink1=David Jenkinson|title=British railway carriages of the 20th century. Volume 1: The end of an era, 1901–1922|year=1988 |publisher=Guild Publishing |location=London |isbn=0-85059-912-1 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last1=Jeuda |first1=Basil |title=The Churnet Valley Railway |year=1999a |publisher=Lightmoor Press |location=[[Lydney]], [[Gloucestershire]]|isbn=978-1-899889-05-1 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book |last1=Jeuda |first1=Basil |title=The Knotty, an illustrated survey of the North Staffordshire Railway |year=1999b |publisher=Lightmoor Press |location=[[Lydney]], [[Gloucestershire]]|isbn=1-899889-01-9 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book  |title= Kelly's directory of Staffordshire |year=1896|publisher=[[Kelly's Directory|Kelly &amp; Co]] |location=London |ref={{harvid|Kelly|1896}}}}
* {{cite book |last1=Nock |first1=Oliver |authorlink1=O. S. Nock |title=A History of the LMS: The first years 1923–1930 |volume=1 |date= |year=1982 |publisher=George Allen &amp; Unwin |location=London |isbn=0-04-385087-1 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Rowledge|first=John W P|title=LMS Engines: names, numbers, types &amp; classes|year=1989|publisher=Redwood Burn|location=Trowbridge, Wiltshire|isbn=0-7153-9381-2|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |editor1-first=Jack |editor1-last=Simmons |editor2-first=Gordon|editor2-last=Biddle |title=The Oxford Companion to British railway history |year=1997|publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford|isbn=0-19-211697-5 |ref={{harvid|Simmons|1997}} }}
* {{cite book |editor1-last=Syssoyeva |editor1-first=Kathryn Mederos |editor2-last=Proudfit |editor2-first=Scott |title=A History of Collective Creation |year=2013 |publisher=Palgrove Macmillan |location=New York |isbn=978-1-137-33129-8 |ref={{harvid|Syssoyeva|Proudfit|2013}} }}
* {{cite web | title =North Staffordshire Railway Passenger Services 1910–1999 | last1=Walley| first1 =Noel | url =http://www.greatorme.org.uk/knottystudy.htm | date = May 2003| accessdate =27 April 2009|ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
*[http://www.nsrsg.org.uk/ The North Staffordshire Railway Study Group]
*[http://www.churnetvalleyrailway.co.uk Churnet Valley Railway]
*[http://www.greatorme.org.uk/knottyphotos.html North Staffordshire Railway Photographs]
*[http://www.search.exploringthepotteries.org.uk/engine/theme/default.asp?theme=308 Historic photographs of the NSR from Stoke-on-Trent Museums Service]

{{Big Four pre-nationalisation British railway companies}}
{{LMSconstituents}}
{{Stoke-on-Trent}}

{{good article}}

[[Category:North Staffordshire Railway]]
[[Category:Companies based in Stoke-on-Trent]]
[[Category:Railway companies established in 1845]]
[[Category:Railway lines opened in 1848]]
[[Category:Railway companies disestablished in 1923]]
[[Category:History of Staffordshire]]
[[Category:LMS constituents]]
[[Category:Pre-grouping British railway companies]]
[[Category:Rail transport in Staffordshire]]
[[Category:Rail transport in Stoke-on-Trent]]</text>
      <sha1>1flvv15t8ee7lu539ayterlubuk5hdo</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
