<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.28.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2600" case="first-letter">Topic</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Southeast Asia Treaty Organization</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>889148</id>
    <revision>
      <id>730330764</id>
      <parentid>729660232</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-07-18T09:47:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jodosma</username>
        <id>18240633</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>formatting [infobox]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23178">{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2013}}
{{good article}}
{{Infobox organization
|name         = Southeast Asia Treaty Organization
|image        = Flag of SEATO.svg
|image_border = 
|size         = &lt;!-- default 200 --&gt;
|alt          = SEATO flag
|caption      = SEATO's flag
|map          = Map of SEATO member countries - de.svg
|mcaption     = Map of SEATO members, shown in blue.
|abbreviation = SEATO
|motto        = 
|formation    = 8 September 1954
|extinction   = 30 June 1977
|type         = [[Intergovernmental organization|intergovernmental]] [[military alliance]]
|status       = &lt;!-- ad hoc, treaty, foundation, etc --&gt;
|purpose      = &lt;!-- focus as e.g. humanitarian, peacekeeping, etc --&gt;
|headquarters = [[Bangkok]], [[Thailand]]
|location     = 
|coords       = &lt;!-- Coordinates of location using a coordinates template --&gt;
|region_served = [[Southeast Asia]]
|membership   =  {{Collapsible list|title=8 nations|{{flag|Australia}}|{{flag|New Zealand}}|{{flag|Pakistan}} (including [[East Pakistan]], now [[Bangladesh]])|{{flag|Philippines|1936}}|{{flag|Thailand}}|{{flag|France}}|{{flag|United Kingdom}}|{{flag|United States}}}}&lt;br /&gt;'''States protected by SEATO'''{{Collapsible list|title=2 nations|{{flag|South Vietnam}}|{{flag|Kingdom of Laos}}}}
|language     = &lt;!-- official languages --&gt;
|leader_title = &lt;!-- position title for the leader of the org --&gt;
|leader_name  = &lt;!-- name of leader --&gt;
|main_organ   = &lt;!-- gral. assembly, board of directors, etc --&gt;
|parent_organization = &lt;!-- if one --&gt;
|affiliations = &lt;!-- if any --&gt;
|num_staff    = 
|num_volunteers =
|budget       = 
|website      = 
|remarks      =
}}

The '''Southeast Asia Treaty Organization''' ('''SEATO''') was an [[international organization]] for [[collective security|collective defense]] in [[Southeast Asia]] created by the '''Southeast Asia Collective Defense Treaty''', or '''Manila Pact''', signed in September 1954 in [[Manila]], [[Philippines]]. The formal institution of SEATO was established on 19 February 1955 at a meeting of treaty partners in [[Bangkok]], Thailand &lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Leifer|2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; The organization's headquarters were also in Bangkok. Eight members joined the organization.

Primarily created to block further [[communism|communist]] gains in Southeast Asia, SEATO is generally considered a failure because internal conflict and dispute hindered general use of the SEATO military; however, SEATO-funded cultural and educational programs left long-standing effects in Southeast Asia. SEATO was dissolved on 30 June 1977 after many members lost interest and withdrew.

The United States still considers the mutual defense aspects of its treaty active for Australia, France, New Zealand, Philippines, Thailand, and the United Kingdom.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.state.gov/s/l/treaty/collectivedefense/&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origins and structure==
[[File:CongressBuilding SEATO.jpg|thumb|right|250px|alt=A picture of a few SEATO nation leaders in Manila in 1966|The leaders of some of the SEATO nations in front of the [[Old Legislative Building (Manila)|Congress Building]] in [[Manila]], hosted by Philippine President [[Ferdinand Marcos]] on 24 October 1966]]
The Southeast Asia Collective Defense Treaty, or Manila Pact, was signed on 8 September 1954 in [[Manila]],&lt;ref name=Franklin1&gt;{{harvnb|Franklin|2006|p=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; as part of the American [[Truman Doctrine]] of creating anti-communist bilateral and collective defense treaties.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Jillson|2009|p=439}}&lt;/ref&gt; These treaties and agreements were intended to create alliances that would contain communist powers ([[China|Communist China]], in SEATO's case).&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Ooi|2004|pp=338–339}}&lt;/ref&gt; This policy was considered to have been largely developed by American diplomat and Soviet expert [[George F. Kennan]]. President [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]]'s Secretary of State [[John Foster Dulles]] (1953–1959) is considered to be the primary force behind the creation of SEATO, which expanded the concept of anti-communist collective defense to Southeast Asia,&lt;ref name=Franklin1/&gt; and then-Vice President Richard Nixon advocated an Asian equivalent of NATO upon returning from his late-1953 Asia trip.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Nixon Alone,&quot; by Ralph de Toledano, p. 173-74&lt;/ref&gt; The organization, headquartered in Bangkok, was created in 1955 at the first meeting of the Council of Ministers set up by the treaty, contrary to Dulles's preference to call the organization &quot;ManPac&quot;.

SEATO was intended to be a Southeast Asian version of the [[NATO|North Atlantic Treaty Organization]] (NATO),&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Boyer et al.|2007|p=836}}&lt;/ref&gt; in which the military forces of each member would be coordinated to provide for the collective defense of the members' country.  Organizationally, SEATO was headed by the Secretary General, whose office was created in 1957 at a meeting in [[Canberra]],&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Franklin|2006|p=184}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Page548&gt;{{harvnb|Page|2003|p=548}}&lt;/ref&gt; with a council of representatives from member nations and an international staff. Also present were committees for economics, security, and information.&lt;ref name=Page548/&gt; SEATO's first Secretary General was [[Pote Sarasin]], a Thai diplomat and politician who had served as Thailand's ambassador to the U.S. between 1952 and 1957,&lt;ref name=Franklin186&gt;{{harvnb|Franklin|2006|p=186}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Weiner|2008|p=351}}&lt;/ref&gt; and as Prime Minister of Thailand from September 1957 to 1 January 1958.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cabinet.thaigov.go.th/eng/pm_his.htm|title=History of Thai Prime Ministers|publisher=Royal Thai Government|accessdate=22 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Unlike the NATO alliance, SEATO had no joint commands with standing forces.&lt;ref name=EB60&gt;{{harvnb|Encyclopaedia Britannica (India)|2000|p=60}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, SEATO's response protocol in the event of communism presenting a &quot;common danger&quot; to the member nations was vague and ineffective, though membership in the SEATO alliance did provide a rationale for a large-scale U.S. military intervention in the region during the [[Vietnam War]] (1955–1975).&lt;ref name=Maga&gt;{{harvnb|Maga|2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Membership==
[[File:SEATO Conference in Manila.gif|thumb|left|300px|alt=Picture of the 1966 SEATO conference in Manila|1966 SEATO conference in Manila]]
Despite its name, SEATO mostly included countries located outside of the region but with an interest either in the region or the organization itself. They were [[Australia]], [[France]], [[New Zealand]], [[Pakistan]] (including [[East Pakistan]], now [[Bangladesh]]), the [[Philippines]], [[Thailand]], the [[United Kingdom]] and the [[United States]].&lt;ref name=EB60/&gt;

The Philippines and Thailand were the only [[Southeast Asia]]n countries that actually participated in the organization. Both shared close ties with the United States, particularly the [[Philippines]], and both faced incipient communist insurgencies against their own governments.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.state.gov&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Southeast Asia Treaty Organization (SEATO), 1954|url=http://history.state.gov/milestones/1953-1960/SEATO|publisher=Office of the Historian. U.S. Department of State|accessdate=3 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Thailand]] became a member upon the discovery of the newly founded &quot;Thai Autonomous Region&quot; (the [[Xishuangbanna Dai Autonomous Prefecture]]) in [[Yunnan]] (in South West China) - apparently feeling threatened by potential Chinese communist subversion on its land.&lt;ref&gt;US PSB, 1953 United States Psychological Studies Board (US PSB). (1953). US Psychological Strategy Based on Thailand, 14 September. Declassified Documents Reference System, 1994, 000556–000557, WH 120.&lt;/ref&gt; Other regional countries like [[Post-independence Burma, 1948–62|Burma]] and [[Indonesia]] were far more minded with domestic internal stability rather than concern of communist threat,&lt;ref name=&quot;history.state.gov&quot;/&gt; and thus rejected joining it.&lt;ref&gt;[http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article18430820 Nehru Has Alternative To SEATO]. (1954, 5 August). The Sydney Morning Herald (NSW : 1842 - 1954), p. 1. Retrieved 3 October 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Federation of Malaya|Malaya]] (including [[Singapore]]) also chose to not participate formally, though it was kept updated with key developments due to its close relationship with the United Kingdom.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.state.gov&quot;/&gt; The rest of [[Southeast Asia]]n countries: [[Vietnam]], [[Cambodia]] and [[Laos]] were prevented from taking part in any international military alliance as a result of the [[Geneva Agreements]] signed 20 July of the same year concluding the end of the [[First Indochina War]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Wikisource:The Final Declaration of The Geneva Conference: On Restoring Peace in Indochina, July 21, 1954]]&lt;/ref&gt; However, with the lingering threat coming from communist [[North Vietnam]] and the possibility of the [[domino effect|domino theory]] with [[Indochina]] turning into a communist frontier, SEATO got these countries under its protection - an act that would be considered to be one of the main justifications for the U.S. involvement in the [[Vietnam War]].&lt;ref name=Blaxland138&gt;{{harvnb|Blaxland|2006|p=138}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kingdom of Cambodia (1953–70)|Cambodia]], however rejected the protection in 1956.&lt;ref name=Grenville366&gt;{{harvnb|Grenville|2001|p=366}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The majority of SEATO members were not located in [[Southeast Asia]]. To Australia and New Zealand, SEATO was seen as a more satisfying organization than [[ANZUS]] – a collective defense organization with the U.S.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=W. Brands, Jr.|first=Henry|title=From ANZUS to SEATO: United States Strategic Policy towards Australia and New Zealand, 1952-1954|journal=The International History Review|date=May 1987|volume= 9|series=No. 2|pages=250–270|doi=10.1080/07075332.1987.9640442}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Great Britain and France joined partly due to having long maintained colonies in the region, and partly due to concerns over developments in [[Indochina]]. Pakistan, however, was simply interested in joining over the appeal of potential support for its long struggle against India.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.state.gov&quot;/&gt; Last but not least, the U.S. upon perceiving Southeast Asia to be a pivotal frontier for [[Cold War]] geopolitics saw the establishment of SEATO as essential to its [[Cold War]] [[Containment|containment policy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;history.state.gov&quot;/&gt;

All in all, the membership reflected a mid-1950s combination of anti-communist Western nations and such nations in Southeast Asia. The United Kingdom, France and the United States, the latter of which joined after the [[United States Senate|U.S. Senate]] ratified the treaty by an 82–1 vote,&lt;ref name=Hearden46&gt;{{harvnb|Hearden|1990|p=46}}&lt;/ref&gt; represented the strongest Western powers.&lt;ref name=Tarling604&gt;{{harvnb|Tarling|1992|p=604}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Canada]] also considered joining, but decided against it in order to concentrate on its [[NATO]] responsibilities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blaxland138&quot;/&gt;
{{Reflist|group=lower-alpha}}

===Secretaries-General===
Secretaries-General of SEATO:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Name !! Country !! From !! To
|-
| [[Pote Sarasin]] || {{Country|Thailand}} || 5 September 1957 || 22 September 1957
|-
| [[William Worth (diplomat)|William Worth]] (&lt;small&gt;acting&lt;/small&gt;) || {{Country|Australia}} || 22 September 1957 || 10 January 1958
|-
| Pote Sarasin || {{Country|Thailand}} || 10 January 1958 || 13 December 1963
|-
| William Worth (&lt;small&gt;acting&lt;/small&gt;) || {{Country|Australia}}|| 13 December 1963 || 19 February 1964
|-
| {{link-interwiki|vertical-align=sup|en=Konthi Suphamongkhon|lang=de}} || {{Country|Thailand}} || 19 February 1964 || 1 July 1965
|-
| [[Jesus M. Vargas]] || {{Country|Philippines}} || 1 July 1965 || 5 September 1972
|-
| {{link-interwiki|vertical-align=sup|en=Sunthorn Hongladarom|lang=de}} || {{Country|Thailand}} || 5 September 1972 || 30 June 1977
|}

==Military aspects==
[[File:Sabre Mk32s RAAF in Thailand early 1960s.jpg|thumb|250px|Australian No. 79 Squadron Sabres at Ubon Royal Thai Air Force Base in Thailand, deployed as part of Australia's commitment to SEATO|alt=A monoplane aircraft with three men and a fuel tanker truck. One of the men is wearing military uniform and the other two are clad only in shorts. The aircraft is mainly painted grey, but is marked with the Royal Australian Air Force roundel and stripes on its tail. The tail of another aircraft of similar appearance is visible in the background.]]

After its creation, SEATO quickly became insignificant militarily, as most of its member nations contributed very little to the alliance.&lt;ref name=Blaxland138/&gt; While SEATO military forces held joint military training, they were never employed because of internal disagreements. SEATO was unable to intervene in [[Laotian Civil War|conflicts in Laos]] because France and Britain rejected use of military action.&lt;ref name=Grenville366/&gt; As a result, the U.S. provided unilateral support for Laos after 1962.&lt;ref name=Grenville366/&gt; Though sought by the U.S., involvement of SEATO in the [[Vietnam War]] was denied because of lack of British and French cooperation.&lt;ref name=Hearden46/&gt;&lt;ref name=Grenville366/&gt;

Both the United States and Australia cited the alliance as justification for involvement in Vietnam.&lt;ref name=Blaxland138/&gt; American membership in SEATO provided the United States with a rationale for a large-scale U.S. military intervention in Southeast Asia.&lt;ref name=Maga/&gt; Other countries, such as Great Britain and key nations in Asia, accepted the rationale.&lt;ref name=Maga/&gt; In 1962, as part of its commitment to SEATO, the [[Royal Australian Air Force]] deployed [[CAC Sabre]]s of its [[No. 79 Squadron RAAF|No. 79 Squadron]] to [[Ubon Royal Thai Air Force Base]], Thailand. The Sabres began to play a role in the Vietnam War in 1965, when their air defence responsibilities expanded to include protection of [[United States Air Force|USAF]] aircraft using Ubon as a base for strikes against North Vietnam.&lt;ref name=Stephens36&gt;{{harvnb|Stephens|1995|p=36}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Independent Review Panel|title=Report to the Minister Assisting the Minister for Defence|date=9 July 2004|url=http://www.defence.gov.au/medals/Content/+060%20Reviews%20and%20Reports/Complete%20Ubon%20Report.pdf|accessdate=1 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cultural effects==
[[File:seatostamp.jpg|thumb|right|150px|alt=A picture of a U.S. postage stamp bearing the SEATO emblem|A [[Postage stamps and postal history of the United States|U.S. Postage Stamp]] for SEATO]]
In addition to joint military training, SEATO member states worked on improving mutual social and economic issues.&lt;ref name=Franklin183&gt;{{harvnb|Franklin|2006|p=183}}&lt;/ref&gt; Such activities were overseen by SEATO's Committee of Information, Culture, Education, and Labor Activities, and proved to be some of SEATO's greatest successes.&lt;ref name=Franklin183/&gt; In 1959, SEATO's first Secretary General, Pote Sarasin, created the [[Asian Institute of Technology|SEATO Graduate School of Engineering]] (currently the Asian Institute of Technology) in Thailand to train engineers.&lt;ref name=Franklin186/&gt; SEATO also sponsored the creation of the Teacher Development Center in Bangkok, as well as the Thai Military Technical Training School, which offered technical programs for supervisors and workmen.&lt;ref name=Franklin188&gt;{{harvnb|Franklin|2006|p=188}}&lt;/ref&gt; SEATO's Skilled Labor Project (SLP) created artisan training facilities, especially in Thailand, where ninety-one training workshops were established.&lt;ref name=Franklin188/&gt;

SEATO also provided research funding and grants in agriculture and medical fields.&lt;ref name=Franklin189&gt;{{harvnb|Franklin|2006|p=189}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1959, SEATO set up the Cholera Research Laboratory in Bangkok, later establishing a second Cholera Research Laboratory in [[Dhaka|Dhaka, Bangladesh]].&lt;ref name=Franklin189/&gt; The Dhaka laboratory soon became the world's leading [[cholera]] research facility and was later renamed the [[International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, Bangladesh]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Franklin|2006|pp=189–190}}&lt;/ref&gt; SEATO was also interested in literature, and a SEATO Literature Award was created and given to writers from member states.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ppat.dbp.gov.my/ppat2001/trislipa.htm|title=Literary Trends and Literary Promotions in Thailand|last=Boonkhachorn|first=Trislipa|accessdate=24 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism and dissolution==
Though Secretary of State Dulles considered SEATO an essential element in American foreign policy in Asia, historians have considered the Manila Pact a failure and the pact is rarely mentioned in history books.&lt;ref name=Franklin1/&gt; In ''The Geneva Conference of 1954 on Indochina'', [[James Cable|Sir James Cable]], a diplomat and naval strategist,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/obituaries/1359279/Sir-James-Cable.html|title=Sir James Cable|date=13 October 2001|work=www.telegraph.co.uk|publisher=Telegraph Media Group|accessdate=29 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; described SEATO as &quot;a fig leaf for the nakedness of American policy&quot;, citing the Manila Pact as a &quot;zoo of paper tigers&quot;.&lt;ref name=Franklin1/&gt;

Consequently, questions of dissolving the organization arose. Pakistan withdrew in 1972 after East Pakistan seceded and became Bangladesh in 26th March 1971.&lt;ref name=Page548/&gt; France withdrew financial support in 1975,&lt;ref name=EB60/&gt; and the SEATO council agreed to the phasing out of the organization.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Thai given mandate to dissolve SEATO |author= |url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=0lQ0AAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=YbkFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=3661%2C2633318 |newspaper=The Montreal Gazette |date=25 September 1975 |accessdate=8 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; After a final exercise on 20 February 1976, the organization was formally dissolved on 30 June 1977.&lt;ref name=EB60/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.almc.army.mil/ALU_INTERNAT/CountryNotes/PACOM/THAILAND.pdf |title=Thailand |author= |date= |work=Army Logistics University |publisher=[[United States Army]] |accessdate=6 July 2012 |quote=Despite the dissolution of the SEATO in 1977, the Manila Pact remains in force and, together with the Thanat-Rusk communiqué of 1962, constitutes the basis of U.S. security commitments to Thailand.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[ANZUS|Australia, New Zealand, United States Security Treaty]] (ANZUS)
* [[Association of Southeast Asian Nations]] (ASEAN)
* [[Central Treaty Organization]] (CENTO)
* [[NATO|North Atlantic Treaty Organization]]  (NATO)
* [[Organization of American States]] (OAS)

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
*{{cite book|ref=harv|title=Strategic Cousins: Australian and Canadian Expeditionary Forces and the British and American Empires|first=John C.|last=Blaxland|year=2006|publisher=McGill-Queen's University Press|isbn=978-0-7735-3035-5}}
*{{cite book|ref={{harvid|Boyer et al.|2007}}
|title=The Enduring Vision|edition=6th AP|first=Paul|last=Boyer|first2=Clifford|last2=Clark, Jr.|first3=Joseph|last3=Kett|first4=Neal|last4=Salisbury|first5=Harvard|last5=Sitkoff|first6=Nancy|last6=Woloch|publisher=Houghton Mifflin|year=2007|isbn=978-0-618-80163-3}}
*{{cite book|ref={{harvid|Encyclopaedia Britannica (India)|2000}}|year=2000|title=Students' Britannica India, Volume Five|author=Encyclopaedia Britannica (India)|publisher=Popular Prakashan|isbn=978-0-85229-760-5}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|first=John K.|last=Franklin|title=The Hollow Pact: Pacific Security and the Southeast Asia Treaty Organization|year=2006|publisher=ProQuest|isbn=978-0-542-91563-5}}
*{{cite book|ref={{harvid|Grenville|2001}}|title=The Major International Treaties of the Twentieth Century: A History and Guide with Texts|editor1-first=John|editor1-last=Grenville|editor2-first=Bernard|editor2-last=Wasserstein|isbn=978-0-415-14125-3|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|year=2001}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|title=Vietnam: Four American Perspectives|editor-first=Patrick J.|editor-last=Hearden|publisher=Purdue University Press|year=1990|isbn=978-1-55753-003-5}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Jillson|first=Cal|title=American Government: Political Development and Institutional Change|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|year=2009|isbn=978-0-415-99570-2}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Leifer|first=Michael|title=Michael Leifer: Selected Works on Southeast Asia|editor=Chin Kin Wah, Leo Suryadinata|year=2005|isbn=978-981-230-270-0}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|first=Timothy P.|last=Maga|year= 2010|publisher=Penguin|isbn=978-1-61564-040-9|title=The Complete Idiot's Guide to the Vietnam War, 2nd Edition}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|title=Southeast Asia: A Historical Encyclopedia, From Angkor Wat to East Timor, Volume 2|editor-first=Keat Gin|editor-last=Ooi|publisher=ABC-CLIO|year=2004|isbn=978-1-57607-770-2}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|title=Colonialism: An International Social, Cultural, and Political Encyclopedia|editor-first=Melvin E.|editor-last=Page|publisher=ABC-CLIO|year=2003|isbn=978-1-57607-335-3}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|title=Going Solo: The Royal Australian Air Force, 1946–1971|first=Alan|last=Stephens|publisher=Australian Govt. Pub. Service|year=1995|isbn=978-0-644-42803-3}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|title=The Cambridge History of Southeast Asia: Volume 2|first=Nicholas|last=Tarling|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=1992|isbn=978-0-521-35506-3}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|title=Legacy of Ashes: The History of the CIA|first=Tim|last=Weiner|publisher=Random House Digital|year=2008|isbn=978-0-307-38900-8}}

==Further reading==
* Buszynski, Leszek. ''SEATO: The Failure of an Alliance Strategy''. Singapore: Singapore University Press, 1983.
*{{cite book|last=Haas|first=Michael|title=The ''Asian Way to Peace: A Story of Regional Cooperation''|publisher=Praeger|year=1989|isbn=0-275-93216-8}}
*{{cite book|last=Dreisbach|first=Kai|title=USA und ASEAN. Amerikanische Aussenpolitik und regionale Kooperation in Südostasien vom Vietnamkrieg bis zur Asienkrise|publisher=Wissenschaftlicher Verlag|year=2004|isbn=3-88476-656-2|language=German}}

==External links==
* [http://avalon.law.yale.edu/20th_century/usmu003.asp Copy of the Southeast Asia Collective Defense Treaty (Manila Pact); 8 September 1954], from Yale Law School
* {{Internet Archive short film|id=gov.archives.arc.2569671|name=Big Picture: Southeast Asia Treaty Organization (SEATO) Nations}}

{{Cold War}}

[[Category:20th-century military alliances]]
[[Category:1977 disestablishments]]
[[Category:Anti-communist organizations]]
[[Category:Cold War treaties]]
[[Category:Former international organizations]]
[[Category:Military history of Southeast Asia]]
[[Category:History of the United States (1945–64)]]
[[Category:International military organizations]]
[[Category:Intergovernmental organizations established by treaty]]
[[Category:Military alliances involving Australia]]
[[Category:Military alliances involving France]]
[[Category:Military alliances involving New Zealand]]
[[Category:Military alliances involving Pakistan]]
[[Category:Military alliances involving the Philippines]]
[[Category:Military alliances involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Military alliances involving the United States]]
[[Category:Organizations established in 1954]]
[[Category:Organizations disestablished in 1977]]
[[Category:Organizations based in Bangkok]]</text>
      <sha1>1gqizk4zh3vrcjnmmde7niqh5yill1v</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
