<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.28.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2600" case="first-letter">Topic</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Usama ibn Munqidh</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>449671</id>
    <revision>
      <id>741158592</id>
      <parentid>727837359</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-25T19:24:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mannerheimo</username>
        <id>2160039</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>removed [[Category:Arab historians]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24948">{{Infobox person
| name        = Usama ibn Munqidh
| image       = 
| image_size  = 
| caption     = 
| birth_name  = 
| birth_date  = {{birth date|1095|07|04}}
| birth_place = [[Shaizar]]
| death_date  = {{death date and age|1188|11|17|1095|07|04}}
| death_place = [[Damascus]]
| death_cause = 
| resting_place = [[Mount Qasiyun]]
| resting_place_coordinates = 
| residence   = 
| nationality = 
| other_names = 
| known_for   = 
| education   = 
| employer    = 
| occupation  = Poet, courtier, soldier
| home_town   = 
| title       = 
| religion    = [[Islam]]
| spouse      = 
| partner     = 
| children    = Murhaf ibn Munqidh
| parents     = Murshid ibn Munqidh
| relatives   = Sultan ibn Munqidh
| website     = 
}}
'''Majd ad-Dīn Usāma ibn Murshid ibn ʿAlī ibn Munqidh al-Kināni al-Kalbi'''&lt;ref&gt;''Majd ad-Din'' is an [[laqab|honorific title]] meaning &quot;glory of the faith&quot;. His given name, ''Usama'', means &quot;lion&quot;. Murshid was his father, Ali his grandfather, and Munqidh his great-grandfather. The Munqidh family belonged to Kinanah from Kalb from the Qudhaa. Paul M. Cobb, ''Usama ibn Munqidh: Warrior-Poet in the Age of Crusades'' (Oxford: Oneworld, 2005), p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt; (also '''Usamah''', '''Ousama''', etc.; {{lang-ar|'''أسامة بن منقذ'''}}) (July 4, 1095 – November 17, 1188&lt;ref&gt;According to [[Ibn Khallikan]] he was born on 27 [[Jumada al-Thani]], 488 [[Hijri year|AH]] and died 23 [[Ramadan (calendar month)|Ramadan]] 584 AH. ''Ibn Khallikan's Biographical Dictionary'', trans. [[William MacGuckin, Baron de Slane]], vol. 1 (Paris: 1842), p. 179. The [[Gregorian calendar]] dates are from Cobb, ''Usama ibn Munqidh'', p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt;) was a [[Islamic Golden Age|medieval Muslim]] poet, author, ''[[furusiyya|faris]]'' (knight), and diplomat from the [[Banu Munqidh]] dynasty of [[Shaizar]] in northern [[Syria]]. His life coincided with the rise of several medieval Muslim dynasties, the arrival of the [[First Crusade]], and the establishment of the [[crusader states]].

He was the nephew and potential successor of the emir of Shaizar, but was exiled in 1131 and spent the rest of his life serving other leaders. He was a courtier to the [[Burid dynasty|Burids]], [[Zengid dynasty|Zengids]], and [[Ayyubid dynasty|Ayyubids]] in [[Damascus]], serving the [[Zengi]], [[Nur ad-Din Zengi|Nur ad-Din]], and [[Saladin]] over a period of almost fifty years. He also served the [[Fatimid]] court in [[Cairo]], as well as the [[Artuqids]] in [[Hisn Kayfa]]. He travelled extensively in Arab lands, visiting Egypt, Syria, Palestine and along the Tigris River, and went on pilgrimage to [[Mecca]]. He often meddled in the politics of the courts in which he served, and he was exiled from both Damascus and Cairo.

During and immediately after his life, he was most famous as a poet and ''[[adab (behavior)|adib]]'' (a &quot;man of letters&quot;). He wrote many poetry anthologies, such as the ''Kitab al-'Asa'' (&quot;Book of the Staff&quot;), ''Lubab al-Adab'' (&quot;Kernels of Refinement&quot;), and ''al-Manazil wa'l-Diyar'' (&quot;Dwellings and Abodes&quot;), and collections of his own original poetry. In modern times, he is remembered more for his ''[[Kitab al-I'tibar]]'' (&quot;Book of Learning by Example&quot; or &quot;Book of Contemplation&quot;), which contains lengthy descriptions of the [[crusade]]rs, whom he interacted with on many occasions, and some of whom he considered friends.

Most of his family was killed in an [[1157 Hama earthquake|earthquake at Shaizar]] in 1157. He died in Damascus in 1188, at the age of 93.

== Early life ==
[[File:Shayzar3.jpg||right|300px|thumb|The fortress of Shaizar.|alt=A photograph of a ruined castle on top of a hill. A river runs below it.]]
Usama was the son of Murshid, and the nephew of Nasr, [[emir]] of [[Shaizar]].

Shaizar was seen as a strategically important site and the gateway to enter and control inner Syria. The Arabs initially conquered Shaizar during the [[Muslim conquest of the Levant]] in 637. Due to its importance it exchanged hands numerous times between the Arabs and Byzantines, who regained it in 999. In 1025 the Banu Munqid tribe were given an allocation of land beside Shaizar by the ruler of Hama, Saleh al-Murdase. Over time they expanded their lands building fortifications and castles until Usamas grandfather Iz Al-Dawlah Al-Murhif Nasr retook it in 1180.&lt;ref&gt;Philip K Hitti: An Arab-Syrian Gentleman and Warrior in the Period of the Crusades: Memoirs of Usamah Ibn-Munqidh (Kitab Al-Itibar)&lt;/ref&gt;

When Nasr died in 1098, Usama's father, Majd Al-Deen Abi Salamah Murshed (1068- 1137) became the emir of Shaizar and the surrounding cities.&lt;ref&gt;Philip K Hitti: An Arab-Syrian Gentleman and Warrior in the Period of the Crusades: Memoirs of Usamah Ibn-Munqidh (Kitab Al-Itibar)&lt;/ref&gt; However he soon gave up his position to Usama's Uncle (Iz Al-Deen Abi Al-Asaker Sultan Mrdad), [[Sultan ibn Munqidh|Sultan]], since Murshid was more interested in studying religion, writing the Quraan and hunting than matters of politics.&lt;ref&gt;Cobb, ''Usama ibn Munqidh'', p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Philip K Hitti: An Arab-Syrian Gentleman and Warrior in the Period of the Crusades: Memoirs of Usamah Ibn-Munqidh (Kitab Al-Itibar)&lt;/ref&gt;

During Usamas life and when his uncle ruled Shaizr was attacked numerous times by Bani Klab in Aleppo, the Assassins sect, the Byzantines and the crusaders. It was struck with siege engines for 10 days in 1137 by the Byzantines and the crusaders attempted on many occasions to storm it. However, due to its natural fortifications along with castles and walls it never fell.&lt;ref&gt;Philip K Hitti: An Arab-Syrian Gentleman and Warrior in the Period of the Crusades: Memoirs of Usamah Ibn-Munqidh (Kitab Al-Itibar)&lt;/ref&gt;

As a child, Usama was the second of four boys and raised by his nurse, Lu'lu'a, who had also raised his father and would later raise Usama's own children.&lt;ref&gt;Cobb, ''Usama ibn Munqidh'', p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; He was encouraged by his father to [[Hafiz (Qur'an)|memorize the Qur'an]], and was also tutored by scholars such as Ibn Munira of [[Kafartab]] and Abu Abdullah al-Tulaytuli of [[Toledo, Spain|Toledo]]. He spent much of his youth [[medieval hunting|hunting]] with his family, partly as recreation and certainly as warrior (faris) training for battle as part of [[furusiyya]]. He also had much direct experience of battle, against the neighbouring crusader [[County of Tripoli]] and [[Principality of Antioch]], hostile Muslim neighbours in [[Hama]], [[Homs]], and elsewhere, and [[Hashshashin]] who had established a base near Shaizar.&lt;ref&gt;Cobb, ''Usama ibn Munqidh'', pp. 5–14.&lt;/ref&gt;

Sultan did not initially have any male heirs and it is possible that Usama expected to succeed him.&lt;ref&gt;''The Book of Contemplation: Islam and the Crusades'', trans. Paul M. Cobb (Penguin Classics, 2008), introduction, p. xxv.&lt;/ref&gt; He certainly singled him out among his brothers by teaching him, tutoring him in the ways of war and hunting. He even favoured him for personal missions and as a representative.&lt;ref&gt;Philip K Hitti: An Arab-Syrian Gentleman and Warrior in the Period of the Crusades: Memoirs of Usamah Ibn-Munqidh (Kitab Al-Itibar)&lt;/ref&gt; However, after Sultan had his own son, he no longer appreciated the presence of Usama and Murshid's other sons. According to Usama, Sultan was jealous after a particularly successful lion-hunt in 1131 when he entered the town with a large lion head in his arms as a hunting trophy. When his grandmother saw this she warned him about the effect this could have on his uncle.&lt;ref&gt;Usama Ibn Munqid: Kitab Al Itibar Page 126&lt;/ref&gt; However, despite this he still spoke well of his uncle on a few occasions in his autobiography and highlighted his noble actions.&lt;ref&gt;Usam Ibn Munqid: Kitab Al Itibar Page 71&lt;/ref&gt; Usama ultimately left Shaizar temporarily in 1129 and after his father died in 1137 his exile became permanent.&lt;ref&gt;Philip K Hitti: An Arab-Syrian Gentleman and Warrior in the Period of the Crusades: Memoirs of Usamah Ibn-Munqidh (Kitab Al-Itibar)&lt;/ref&gt;

His uncle died in 1154 and his son, Taj Al-Dawlah Naser Al-Deen Mohammad, inherited the castle. However he was the last of the line when an earthquake in 1157 struck the area killing scores.

== Damascus and Egypt ==

Usama went to Homs, where he was taken captive in a battle against [[Zengi]], the [[atabeg]] of [[Mosul]] and [[Aleppo]], who had just captured nearby Hama. After his capture he entered Zengi's service, and travelled throughout northern Syria, Iraq, and Armenia fighting against Zengi's enemies, including the [[Abbasid]] caliph outside [[Baghdad]] in 1132. In 1135 he returned to the south, to Hama, where one of Zengi's generals, al-Yaghisiyani, was appointed governor. He returned to Shaizar when his father died in May 1137, and again in April 1138 when [[Byzantine emperor]] [[John II Comnenus]] [[Siege of Shaizar|besieged the city]].&lt;ref&gt;Cobb, ''Usama ibn Munqidh'', pp. 20–24.&lt;/ref&gt;

The emperor's siege of Shaizar was unsuccessful, but Shaizar was heavily damaged. After the siege, Usama left Zengi's service and went to [[Damascus]], which was ruled by [[Mu'in ad-Din Unur]], the atabeg of the [[Burid dynasty]]. Zengi was determined to conquer Damascus, so Usama and Unur turned to the crusader [[Kingdom of Jerusalem]] for help. Usama was sent on a preliminary visit to Jerusalem in 1138, and in 1139 Zengi captured [[Baalbek]] in Damascene territory. In 1140 Unur sent Usama back to Jerusalem to conclude a treaty with the crusaders, and both he and Unur visited their new allies numerous times between 1140 and 1143. Afterwards, Usama was suspected of being involved in a plot against Unur, and he fled Damascus for [[Fatimid]] [[Cairo]] in November, 1144.&lt;ref&gt;Cobb, ''Usama ibn Munqidh'', pp. 26–31.&lt;/ref&gt;

In Cairo he became a wealthy courtier, but he was involved in plots and conspiracies there as well. The young [[az-Zafir]] became caliph in 1149, and Ibn as-Sallar became [[vizier]], with Usama as one of his advisors. As-Sallar sent Usama to negotiate an alliance against the crusaders with Zengi's son [[Nur ad-Din Zengi|Nur ad-Din]], but the negotiations failed. Usama took part in battles with the crusaders outside of [[Ashkelon|Ascalon]] on his way back to Egypt, and after he left, his brother 'Ali was killed at [[Gaza City|Gaza]].&lt;ref&gt;Cobb, ''Usama ibn Munqidh'', pp. 34–37.&lt;/ref&gt;

Back in Egypt, as-Sallar was assassinated in 1153 by his son Abbas, Abbas's son Nasr, and caliph az-Zafir, who, according to Usama, was Nasr's lover. Thirteenth-century historian [[Ibn al-Athir]] says that Usama was the instigator of this plot.&lt;ref&gt;''The Chronicle of Ibn al-Athir for the Crusading Period from al-Kamil i'l-Ta'rikh, Part 2: The Years 541–589/1146–1193: The Age of Nur al-Din and Saladin'', trans. D.S. Richards. Crusade Texts in Translation 15 (Aldershot: Ashgate, 2007), p. 62.&lt;/ref&gt; Usama may also have been behind the assassination of az-Zafir by Abbas, in 1154. Az-Zafir's relatives called upon a supporter, Ibn Ruzzik, who chased Abbas out of Cairo, and Usama followed him. He lost his possessions in Cairo, and on the way to Damascus his retinue was attacked by the crusaders and [[Bedouin]] nomads, but in June 1154 he safely reached Damascus, which had recently been captured by Nur ad-Din. Ibn Ruzzik tried to persuade him to come back, as the rest of his family was still in Cairo, but Usama was able to bring them to Damascus, through crusader territory, in 1156. The crusaders promised to transport them safely, but they were attacked and pillaged, and Usama lost his entire library.&lt;ref&gt;Cobb, ''Usama ibn Munqidh'', pp. 37–43.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Later years ==
[[File:Qasiyon Damascus.JPG|thumb|right|Alt=A photo a modern city with a mountain in the background. There is a road, cars, street lights, a sign, and other city infrastructure in the foreground.|Mount Qasiyun in Damascus, where Usama was buried.]]
In 1157, Shaizar was destroyed by an [[1157 Hama earthquake|earthquake]], killing almost all of Usama's relatives. They were there for the [[Khitan (circumcision)|circumcision]] of the son of his cousin Muhammad, who had recently succeeded Sultan as emir. The only survivor was Muhammad's wife. Usama had remained in Damascus, and after the destruction of his homeland he remained there in semi-retirement. He went on [[hajj|pilgrimage to Mecca]] in 1160, then went on campaign against the crusaders with Nur ad-Din in 1162, and was at the [[Battle of Harim]] in 1164. That year, Usama left Nur ad-Din's service and went north to the court of [[Kara Arslan]], the [[Artuqid]] emir of [[Hisn Kayfa]].&lt;ref&gt;Cobb, ''Usama ibn Munqidh'', pp. 44–48.&lt;/ref&gt;

Usama's life in Hisn Kayfa is very obscure, but he travelled throughout the region, and probably wrote many of his works there. In 1174 Usama was invited to Damascus to serve [[Saladin]], who had succeeded Nur ad-Din earlier that year and was a friend of Usama's son Murhaf. Usama lived in semi-retirement, as he did in Hisn Kayfa, and often met with Saladin to discuss literature and warfare. He may have also taught [[Islamic poetry|poetry]] and [[hadith]] in Damascus, and held poetry salons for Saladin and his chief men, including [[al-Qadi al-Fadl]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crusades-encyclopedia.com/alqadialfadil.html al-Qadi al-Fadil]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Imad ad-Din al-Isfahani]]. He died on November 17, 1188.&lt;ref&gt;Cobb, ''Usama ibn Munqidh'', pp. 63–64.&lt;/ref&gt; He was buried in Damascus on [[Mount Qasiyun]], although the tomb is now lost.&lt;ref&gt;''The Book of Contemplation'', trans. Cobb, introduction, pp. xxxii–xxxiii.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Family ==

Usama had three brothers, Muhammad, 'Ali, and Munqidh; his cousin, also named Muhammad, succeeded Usama's uncle Sultan as emir of Shaizar. He had a son, Murhaf, in 1126, and another son, Abu Bakr, who died as a child. He had a daughter, Umm Farwa, in Hisn Kayfa in 1166. He mentions other children, but their names, and the name of his wife or wives, are unknown.&lt;ref&gt;Cobb, ''Usama ibn Munqidh'', pp. 16–17, 51, and the family tree on p. xxiv.&lt;/ref&gt;

The picture he painted of his father was of a pious religious man who was not interested in the affairs of this world. He would spend most of his time reading the Quraan, fasting and hunting during the day and at night would copy the Quraan. He also recounted a few battles his father joined against the crusaders in his autobiography Kitab al Itibar.&lt;ref&gt;Usama Ibn Munqid: Kitab al Itibar Page 191,197&lt;/ref&gt;

== Religion ==

It is sometimes assumed that Usama was [[Shi'ite]], because he often writes about [['Ali]], his family cooperated with the Fatimids and other Shi'ite dynasties, and he himself served the Fatimids in Egypt. [[Philip K. Hitti]] thought he had a &quot;secret sympathy&quot; with the Shi'ites.&lt;ref&gt;''An Arab-Syrian Gentleman and Warrior in the Period of the Crusades; Memoirs of Usamah ibn-Munqidh'' (Kitab al i'tibar), trans [[Philip K. Hitti]] (New York, 1929), introduction, p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt; Paul M. Cobb does not think there is enough evidence one way or the other, but believes he was probably [[Sunni]] with &quot;acceptable Shi'ite tendencies.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Cobb, ''Usama ibn Munqidh'', p. 74.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Robert Graham Irwin|Robert Irwin]] thinks the Banu Munqidh were [[Twelver]] Shi'ites (unlike the Fatimids who were [[Sevener]]s), and that another clue to Usama's Shi'ism is his dislike of [[jihad]], which was not a Shi'ite doctrine.&lt;ref&gt;[[Robert Graham Irwin|Robert Irwin]], &quot;Usamah ibn Munqidh: An Arab-Syrian gentleman at the time of the crusades reconsidered.&quot; ''The Crusades and their Sources: Essays Presented to Bernard Hamilton'', eds. John France and W.G. Zajac (Aldershot: Ashgate, 1998), p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt; Usama also admired Christian monks and holy men, and was disturbed that Muslims were not as pious as Christians. He was very fond of [[Sufi]]s when he first learned about them late in his life in Damascus.&lt;ref&gt;Cobb, ''Usama ibn Munqidh'', p. 77.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Works ==

Around 1171 in Hisn Kayfa, Usama wrote the ''Kitab al-'Asa'' (&quot;Book of the Staff&quot;), a poetry anthology about famous walking sticks and other staffs, and ''al-Manazil wa'l-Diyar'' (&quot;Dwellings and Abodes&quot;). In Damascus in the early 1180s he wrote another anthology, the ''Lubab al-Adab'' (&quot;Kernels of Refinement&quot;), instructions on living a properly cultured life. He is most famous for the ''[[Kitab al-I'tibar]]'' (translated various ways, most recently as ''the Book of Contemplation''), which was written as a gift to Saladin around 1183. It is not exactly a &quot;memoir&quot;, as [[Philip Hitti]] translated the title, although it does include many autobiographical details that are incidental to the main point.&lt;ref&gt;''The Book of Contemplation'', trans. Cobb, introduction, pp. xxxiii–xxxv.&lt;/ref&gt; It was meant to be &quot;a book of examples ('''ibar'') from which to draw lessons.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Cobb, ''Usama ibn Munqidh'', p. 63.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1880, [[Hartwig Derenbourg]] was the first to discover the ''Kitab al-I'tibar'', which survived in only one manuscript, in the possession of the [[Escorial]] Monastery near [[Madrid]]. Derenbourg was also the first to produce an Arabic edition (1886), a biography of Usama (1889), and a French translation (1895). In 1930, Hitti produced an improved Arabic edition, and an English translation. Qasim as-Samarrai produced another Arabic edition in 1987.&lt;ref&gt;''The Book of Contemplation'', trans. Cobb, introduction, pp. xxxviii–xxxix.&lt;/ref&gt;

Usama wrote in &quot;Middle Arabic&quot;, a less formal style of [[classical Arabic]].&lt;ref&gt;''The Book of Contemplation'', trans. Cobb, introduction, p. xxxvii.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Reputation ==

Usama was known for meddling in the business of others, rather than commanding any power of his own. As the [[Encyclopaedia of Islam]] says, &quot;his career was a troubled one, and for this his own actions were surely responsible in large part.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;R. S. Humphreys, ''Munḳid̲h̲, Banū'', in Encyclopaedia of Islam, 2nd. ed., vol. VII (Leiden: Brill, 1960–2002), p. 579.&lt;/ref&gt;

To contemporary and later medieval Muslims, however, he was best remembered for his poetry and his poetry anthologies.&lt;ref&gt;Cobb, ''Usama ibn Munqidh'', p. 116.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ibn Khallikan]], author of a fourteenth-century biographical dictionary, calls him &quot;one of the most powerful, learned, and intrepid members of the [Munqidh] family&quot; and speaks at great length about his poetry.&lt;ref&gt;''Ibn Khallikan's Biographical Dictionary'', trans. MacGuckin, p. 179.&lt;/ref&gt;

He was also known for his military and hunting exploits. [[Ibn al-Athir]] described him as &quot;the ultimate of bravery&quot;, regarding his presence at the Battle of Harim.&lt;ref&gt;''The Chronicle of Ibn al-Athir'', trans. D.S. Richards, p. 134.&lt;/ref&gt;

For modern readers he is most famous for the ''Kitab al-I'tibar'' and his descriptions of life in Syria during the early crusades. The disjointed nature of the work has given him a reputation as a senile rambler, although it is actually written with an anthological structure, with humorous or moralistic tales that are not meant to proceed chronologically, as a true autobiography would.&lt;ref&gt;''The Book of Contemplation'', trans. Cobb, introduction, p. xxxi.&lt;/ref&gt; Since this style of literature, ''[[Adab (literature)|adab]]'' in Arabic, does not necessarily have to be factual, historians are quick to point out that Usama's historical material cannot always be trusted. Usama's anecdotes about the crusades are sometimes obvious jokes, exaggerating their &quot;[[other]]ness&quot; to entertain his Muslim audience.&lt;ref&gt;Cobb, ''Usama ibn Munqidh'', p. 69.&lt;/ref&gt; As [[Carole Hillenbrand]] wrote, it would be &quot;dangerously misleading to take the evidence of his book at its face value.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Carole Hillenbrand]], ''The Crusades: Islamic Perspectives'' (Routledge, 2000), p. 260.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Bibliography ==
{{Wikisourcelang|ar|%D9%85%D9%84%D9%81:%D9%83%D8%AA%D8%A7%D8%A8_%D8%A7%D9%84%D8%A7%D8%B9%D8%AA%D8%A8%D8%A7%D8%B1.pdf|Hartwig Derenbourg's Arabic edition of the Kitab al'Itibar}}

=== Editions and translations of Usama's works ===
* ''Ousama ibn Mounkidh, un emir Syrien au premier siècle des croisades (1095–1188)'', ed. [[Hartwig Derenbourg]]. Paris, 1889.
* ''An Arab-Syrian Gentleman and Warrior in the Period of the Crusades; Memoirs of Usāmah ibn-Munqidh'' (Kitab al i'tibar), trans [[Philip K. Hitti]]. New York, 1929.
* ''Memoirs Entitled Kitāb al-I'tibār'', ed. Philip K. Hitti (Arabic text). Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1930.
* ''Lubab al-Adab'', ed. A. M. Shakir. Cairo: Maktabat Luwis Sarkis, 1935.
* ''Diwan Usama ibn Munqidh'', ed. A. Badawi and H. Abd al-Majid. Cairo: Wizarat al-Ma'arif al-Umumiyya, 1953.
* ''Kitab al-Manazil wa'l-Diyar'', ed. M. Hijazi. Cairo: Al-Majlis al-A'la li-l-Shu'un al-Islamiyya, 1968.
* ''Kitab al-'Asa'', ed. Hassan Abbas. Alexandria: Al-Hay'at al-Misriyya al-'Amma li-l-Kitab, 1978.
* ''Al-Badi' fi-l-Badi''', ed. A. Muhanna. Beirut: Dar al-Kutub al-'Ilmiyya, 1987.
* ''Kitab al i'tibar'', ed. Qasim as-Samarra'i. Riyadh, 1987.
* &quot;Usama ibn Munqidh's ''Book of the Staff (Kitab al'Asa)'': autobiographical and historical excerpts,&quot; trans. Paul M. Cobb. ''Al-Masaq: Islam and the Medieval Mediterranean'' 17 (2005).
* &quot;Usama ibn Munqidh's ''Kernels of Refinement (Lubab al-Adab)'': autobiographical and historical excerpts,&quot; trans. Paul M. Cobb. ''Al-Masaq: Islam and the Medieval Mediterranean'' 18 (2006)
* ''The Book of Contemplation: Islam and the Crusades'', trans. Paul M. Cobb. Penguin Classics, 2008.

=== Secondary works ===
* ''[[Ibn Khallikan]]'s Biographical Dictionary'', trans. [[William MacGuckin, Baron de Slane]], vol. 1. Paris, 1842.
* Hassan Abbas, ''Usama ibn Munqidh: Hayatuhu wa-Atharuhu''. Cairo: al-Hay'a al-Misriya al-'Ama li'l-Kitab, 1981.
* Niall Christie, &quot;Just a bunch of dirty stories? Women in the memoirs of Usamah ibn Munqidh.&quot; Eastward Bound: Travel and Travellers, 1050–1550, ed. Rosamund Allen. Manchester: Manchester University Press, 2004, pp.&amp;nbsp;71–87.
* Paul M. Cobb, ''Usama ibn Munqidh: Warrior-Poet in the Age of Crusades'' Oxford: Oneworld, 2005.
* Paul M. Cobb, &quot;Infidel dogs: hunting crusaders with Usamah ibn Munqidh.&quot; Crusades 6 (2007).
* Lawrence I. Conrad, &quot;Usama ibn Munqidh and other witnesses to Frankish and Islamic medicine in the era of the crusades.&quot; ''Medicine in Jerusalem throughout the Ages'', ed. Zohar Amar et al. Tel Aviv: C. G. Foundation, 1999.
* [[Carole Hillenbrand]], ''The Crusades: Islamic Perspectives''. Routledge, 2000.
* R. S. Humphreys, ''Munkidh, Banu''. [[Encyclopaedia of Islam]], 2nd. ed., vol. VII (Leiden: Brill, 1960–2002).
* [[Robert Graham Irwin|Robert Irwin]], &quot;Usama ibn Munqidh: an Arab-Syrian gentleman at the time of the Crusades reconsidered.&quot; ''The Crusades and their sources: essays presented to Bernard Hamilton'' ed. John France, William G. Zajac (Aldershot: Ashgate, 1998) pp.&amp;nbsp;71–87.
* Adnan Husain, &quot;Wondrous Crusade Encounters: Usamah ibn Munqidh's Book of Learning by Example,&quot; in Jason Glenn (ed), ''The Middle Ages in Texts and Texture: Reflections on Medieval Sources'' (Toronto, University of Toronto, 2012),
* D. W. Morray, &quot;The genius of Usamah ibn Munqidh: aspects of ''Kitab al-I'tibar'' by Usamah ibn Munqidh.&quot; Working Paper. University of Durham, Centre for Middle Eastern and Islamic Studies, Durham, 1987.
* I. Schen, &quot;Usama ibn Munqidh's Memoirs: some further light on Muslim Middle Arabic.&quot; ''Journal of Semitic Studies'' 17 (1972), and ''Journal of Semitic Studies'' 18 (1973).
* G. R. Smith, &quot;A new translation of certain passages of the hunting section of Usama ibn Munqidh's I'tibar.&quot; ''Journal of Semitic Studies'' 26 (1981).
* Stefan Wild, &quot;Open questions, new light: Usama ibn Munqidh's account of his battles against Muslims and Franks.&quot; ''The Frankish Wars and their Influence on Palestine'', edd. Khalil Athamina and Roger Heacock (Birzeit, 1994), pp.&amp;nbsp;9–29.
* ''The Chronicle of [[Ibn al-Athir]] for the Crusading Period from al-Kamil i'l-Ta'rikh, Part 2: The Years 541–589/1146–1193: The Age of Nur al-Din and Saladin'', trans. D.S. Richards. Crusade Texts in Translation 15. Aldershot: Ashgate, 2007.

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
{{wikiquote}}
* [http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/source/usamah2.html Excerpts from Usamah's Autobiography]
* [http://www.deremilitari.org/RESOURCES/ARTICLES/christie.htm Niall G. F. Christie: The Presentation of the Franks in Selected Muslim Sources from the Crusades of the 12th Century]
* [[Hartwig Derenbourg]], ''[http://books.google.ca/books?id=HTxbAAAAQAAJ Ousâma ibn Mounkidh, un émir syrien au premier siècle des croisades]'', pt. 1, ''vie d'Ousâma''; pt. 2, [http://books.google.ca/books?id=u84OAAAAQAAJ Arabic text of the Kitab al-I'tibar].

{{good article}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Munqidh, Usama Ibn}}
[[Category:1095 births]]
[[Category:1188 deaths]]
[[Category:Crusade literature]]
[[Category:Muslim poets]]
[[Category:Syrian historians]]
[[Category:12th-century writers]]
[[Category:12th-century historians]]
[[Category:12th-century Arab people]]</text>
      <sha1>ehqgbqngigenl9m3oidvkzyt0j6q7z7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
