<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.28.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2600" case="first-letter">Topic</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Valkyrie</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>70798</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744150637</id>
      <parentid>734982689</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-13T12:17:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* References */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="58959">{{other uses}}
{{Redirect|Göl|the carpet motif|Gul (design)}}
[[File:The Ride of the Valkyrs.jpg|thumb|300px|''The Ride of the Valkyrs'' (1909) by [[John Charles Dollman]].]]

In [[Norse mythology]], a '''valkyrie''' (from [[Old Norse]] ''valkyrja'' &quot;chooser of the slain&quot;) is one of a host of female figures who choose those who may die in battle and those who may live. Selecting half of those who die in battle, the valkyries bring their chosen to the afterlife hall of the slain, [[Valhalla]], ruled over by the god [[Odin]] (the other half go to the goddess [[Freyja]]'s afterlife field [[Fólkvangr]]). There, the deceased warriors become [[einherjar]] ([[Old Norse]] &quot;single (or once) fighters&quot;&lt;ref name=ORCHARD36LINDOW104&gt;Orchard (1997:36) and Lindow (2001:104).&lt;/ref&gt;). When the einherjar are not preparing for the events of [[Ragnarök]], the valkyries bear them [[mead]]. Valkyries also appear as lovers of heroes and other mortals, where they are sometimes described as the daughters of royalty, sometimes accompanied by [[raven]]s and sometimes connected to [[swan]]s or horses.

Valkyries are attested in the ''[[Poetic Edda]]'', a book of poems compiled in the 13th century from earlier traditional sources; the ''[[Prose Edda]]'' and ''[[Heimskringla]]'' (by [[Snorri Sturluson]]), and ''[[Njáls saga]]'', a [[Sagas of Icelanders|Saga of Icelanders]], all written in the 13th century. They appear throughout the poetry of [[skald]]s, in a 14th-century [[Magical formula|charm]], and in various [[runic inscriptions]].

The [[Old English]] [[Cognate (etymology)|cognate]] terms ''wælcyrge'' and ''wælcyrie'' appear in several Old English manuscripts, and scholars have explored whether the terms appear in Old English by way of Norse influence, or reflect a tradition also native among the [[Anglo-Saxon paganism|Anglo-Saxon pagans]]. Scholarly theories have been proposed about the relation between the valkyries, the [[norns]], and the [[dísir]], all of which are supernatural figures associated with fate. Archaeological excavations throughout Scandinavia have uncovered amulets theorized as depicting valkyries. In modern culture, valkyries have been the subject of works of art, musical works, video games and poetry.

==Etymology==
The word ''valkyrie'' derives from [[Old Norse]] ''valkyrja'' (plural ''valkyrjur''), which is composed of two words; the noun ''valr'' (referring to the slain on the battlefield) and the verb ''kjósa'' (meaning &quot;to choose&quot;). Together, they mean &quot;chooser of the slain&quot;. The Old Norse ''valkyrja'' is cognate to [[Old English]] ''wælcyrge''.&lt;ref name=&quot;BYOCK142-143&quot;&gt;Byock (2005:142–143).&lt;/ref&gt; Other terms for valkyries include ''óskmey'' (Old Norse &quot;wish maid&quot;), appearing in the poem ''[[Oddrúnargrátr]]'' and  ''Óðins meyjar'' (Old Norse &quot;[[Odin]]'s maids&quot;), appearing in the ''[[Nafnaþulur]]''. ''Óskmey'' may be related to the [[List of names of Odin|Odinic name ''Óski'']] (Old Norse, roughly meaning &quot;wish fulfiller&quot;), referring to the fact that Odin receives slain warriors in Valhalla.&lt;ref name=&quot;SIMEK254+349&quot;&gt;Simek (2007:254 and 349).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Old Norse attestations==

===''Poetic Edda''===
Valkyries are mentioned or appear in the ''[[Poetic Edda]]'' poems ''[[Völuspá]]'', ''[[Grímnismál]]'', ''[[Völundarkviða]]'', ''[[Helgakviða Hjörvarðssonar]]'', ''[[Helgakviða Hundingsbana I]]'', ''[[Helgakviða Hundingsbana II]]'' and ''[[Sigrdrífumál]]''.

====''Völuspá'' and ''Grímnismál''====

In stanza 30 of the poem ''[[Völuspá]]'', a [[völva]] (a travelling [[seeress]] in Germanic society) tells Odin that &quot;she saw&quot; valkyries coming from far away who are ready to ride to &quot;the realm of the gods&quot;. The völva follows this with a list of six valkyries: [[Skuld]] (Old Norse, possibly &quot;debt&quot; or &quot;future&quot;) who &quot;bore a shield&quot;, [[Skögul]] (&quot;shaker&quot;), [[Gunnr]] (&quot;war&quot;), [[Hildr]] (&quot;battle&quot;), [[Göndul]] (&quot;[[wand]]-wielder&quot;) and [[Geirskögul]] (&quot;Spear-Skögul&quot;). Afterwards, the völva tells him she has listed the &quot;ladies of the War Lord, ready to ride, valkyries, over the earth&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;DRONKE15ORCHARD193-195&quot;&gt;Dronke (1997:15). Valkyrie name etymologies from Orchard (1995:193–195).&lt;/ref&gt;

In the poem ''[[Grímnismál]]'', Odin (disguised as ''[[List of names of Odin|Grímnir]]''), tortured, starved and thirsty, tells the young [[Agnarr Geirröðsson|Agnar]] that he wishes that the valkyries [[Hrist]] (&quot;shaker&quot;) and [[Mist (valkyrie)|Mist]] (&quot;cloud&quot;) would &quot;bear him a [drinking] [[drinking horn|horn]]&quot;, then provides a list of 11 more valkyries who he says &quot;bear [[ale]] to the [[einherjar]]&quot;; [[Skeggjöld]] (&quot;axe-age&quot;), Skögul, Hildr, [[Þrúðr]] (&quot;power&quot;), [[Hlökk]] (&quot;noise&quot;, or &quot;battle&quot;), [[Herfjötur]] (&quot;host-fetter&quot;), [[Göll]] (&quot;tumult&quot;), [[Geirahöð]] (&quot;spear-fight&quot;), [[Randgríð]] (&quot;shield-truce&quot;), [[Ráðgríð]] (&quot;council-truce&quot;) and [[Reginleif]] (&quot;power-truce&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;LARRINGTON57ORCHARD193-195&quot;&gt;Larrington (1999:57). Valkyrie name etymologies from Orchard (1995:193–195).&lt;/ref&gt;

====''Völundarkviða''====

A prose introduction in the poem ''[[Völundarkviða]]'' relates that the brothers [[Slagfiðr]], [[Agilaz|Egil]] and [[Wayland Smith|Völund]] dwelt in a house sited in a location called Úlfdalir (&quot;wolf dales&quot;). There, early one morning, the brothers find three women spinning linen on the shore of the lake Úlfsjár (&quot;wolf lake&quot;), and &quot;near them were their swan's garments; they were valkyries&quot;. Two, daughters of King [[Hlödvér]], are named [[Hlaðguðr svanhvít]] (&quot;swan-white&quot;) and [[Hervör alvitr]] (possibly meaning &quot;all-wise&quot; or &quot;strange creature&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ORCHARD83&quot;&gt;Orchard (1997:83).&lt;/ref&gt;); the third, daughter of [[Kjárr]] of [[Valland]], is named [[Alruna|Ölrún]] (possibly meaning &quot;[[beer]] [[runic alphabet|rune]]&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SIMEK251&quot;&gt;Simek (2007:251).&lt;/ref&gt;). The brothers take the three women back to their hall with them—Egil takes Ölrún, Slagfiðr takes Hlaðguðr svanhvít and Völund takes Hervör alvitr. They live together for seven winters, until the women fly off to go to a battle and do not return. Egil goes off in snow-shoes to look for Ölrún, Slagfiðr goes searching for Hlaðguðr svanhvít and Völund sits in Úlfdalir.&lt;ref name=&quot;LARRINGTON102&quot;&gt;Larrington (1999:102).&lt;/ref&gt;

====''Helgakviða Hjörvarðssonar''====

In the poem ''[[Helgakviða Hjörvarðssonar]]'', a prose narrative says that an unnamed and silent young man, the son of the Norwegian King Hjörvarðr and Sigrlinn of Sváfaland, witnesses nine valkyries riding by while sitting atop a [[Tumulus#Scandinavia|burial mound]]. He finds one particularly striking; this valkyrie is detailed later in a prose narrative as [[Sváfa|Sváva]], king [[Eylimi]]'s daughter, who &quot;often protected him in battles&quot;. The valkyrie speaks to the unnamed man, and gives him the name ''[[Helge (name)|Helgi]]'' (meaning &quot;the [[hallow|holy]] one&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ORCHARD81&quot;&gt;Orchard (1997:81).&lt;/ref&gt;). The previously silent Helgi speaks; he refers to the valkyrie as &quot;bright-face lady&quot;, and asks her what gift he will receive with the [[Germanic name|name]] she has bestowed upon him, but he will not accept it if he cannot have her as well. The valkyrie tells him she knows of a hoard of swords in Sigarsholm, and that one of them is of particular importance, which she describes in detail.&lt;ref name=&quot;LARRINGTON125&quot;&gt;Larrington (1999:125).&lt;/ref&gt; Further into the poem, [[Atli Iðmundsson|Atli]] [[flyting|flytes]] with the female [[jötunn]] [[Hrímgerðr]]. While flyting with Atli, Hrímgerðr says that she had seen 27 valkyries around Helgi, yet one particularly fair valkyrie led the band:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
:[[Numbers in Germanic paganism|Three times nine girls]], but one girl rode ahead,
:white-skinned under her helmet;
:the horses were trembling, from their manes
:dew fell into the deep valleys,
:hail in the high woods;
:good fortune comes to men from there;
:all that I saw was hateful to me.&lt;ref name=&quot;LARRINGTON128&quot;&gt;Larrington (1999:128).&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
After Hrímgerðr is turned to stone by the daylight, a prose narrative continues that Helgi, who is now king, goes to Sváva's father—King Eylimi—and asks for his daughter. Helgi and Sváva are betrothed and love one another dearly. Sváva stays at home with King Eylimi, and Helgi goes raiding, and to this the narrative adds that Sváva &quot;was a valkyrie just as before&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;LARRINGTON129&quot;&gt;Larrington (1999:129).&lt;/ref&gt; The poem continues, and, among various other events, Helgi dies from a wound received in battle. A narrative at the end of the poem says that Helgi and his valkyrie wife Sváva &quot;are said to be reincarnated&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;LARRINGTON130-131&quot;&gt;Larrington (1999:130–131).&lt;/ref&gt;

====''Helgakviða Hundingsbana I''====

In the poem ''[[Helgakviða Hundingsbana I]]'', the hero [[Helgi Hundingsbane]] sits in the corpse-strewn battlefield of Logafjöll. A light shines from the [[fell]], and from that light strike bolts of lightning. Flying through the sky, helmeted valkyries appear. Their waist-length [[Mail (armour)|mail armour]] is drenched in blood; their spears shine brightly:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
:Then light shone from Logafell,
:and from that radiance there came bolts of lightning;
:wearing helmets at Himingvani [came the valkyries].
:Their byrnies were drenched in blood;
:and rays shone from their spears.&lt;ref name=&quot;LARRINGTON116&quot;&gt;Larrington (1999:116).&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
In the stanza that follows, Helgi asks the valkyries (who he refers to as &quot;southern goddesses&quot;) if they would like to come home with the warriors when night falls (all the while arrows were flying). The battle over, the valkyrie [[Sigrún]] (&quot;victory-[[runic alphabet|rune]]&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ORCHARD194&quot;&gt;Orchard (1997:194).&lt;/ref&gt;), informs him from her horse that her father [[Högni]] has betrothed her to [[Höðbroddr]], the son of king [[Granmar]] of the [[Nibelung|Hniflung]] clan, who Sigrún deems unworthy. Helgi assembles an immense host to ride to wage battle at Frekastein against the Hniflung clan to assist Sigrún in her plight to avoid her betrothment.&lt;ref name=&quot;LARRINGTON116-117&quot;&gt;Larrington (1999:116–117).&lt;/ref&gt; Later in the poem, the hero [[Sinfjötli]] [[flyting|flyts]] with Guðmundr. Sinfjötli accuses Guðmundr of having once been female, and gibes that Guðmundr was &quot;a witch, horrible, unnatural, among Odin's valkyries&quot;, adding that all of the einherjar &quot;had to fight, headstrong woman, on your account&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;LARRINGTON119&quot;&gt;Larrington (1999:119).&lt;/ref&gt; Further in the poem, the phrase &quot;the valkyrie's airy sea&quot; is used for &quot;[[mist]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;LARRINGTON120&quot;&gt;Larrington (1999:120).&lt;/ref&gt;

Towards the end of the poem, valkyries again descend from the sky, this time to protect Helgi amid the battle at Frekastein. After the battle, all the valkyries fly away but Sigrún and wolves (referred to as &quot;the [[troll]]-woman's mount&quot;) consume corpses:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
:Helmeted valkyries came down from the sky
:—the noise of spears grew loud—they protected the prince;
:then said Sigrun—the wound-giving valkyries flew,
:the [[troll]]-woman's mount was feasting on the fodder of ravens:&lt;ref name=&quot;LARRINGTON121&quot;&gt;Larrington (1999:121).&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
The battle won, Sigrún tells Helgi that he will become a great ruler and pledges herself to him.&lt;ref name=&quot;LARRINGTON122&quot;&gt;Larrington (1999:122).&lt;/ref&gt;

====''Helgakviða Hundingsbana II''====

At the beginning of the poem ''[[Helgakviða Hundingsbana II]]'', a prose narrative says that King [[Sigmund]] (son of [[Völsung]]) and his wife [[Borghild]] (of Brálund) have a son named Helgi, who they named for Helgi Hjörvarðsson (the antagonist of the earlier ''Helgakviða Hjörvarðssonar'').&lt;ref name=&quot;LARRINGTON132&quot;&gt;Larrington (1999:132).&lt;/ref&gt; After Helgi has killed  King Hunding in stanza 4, a prose narrative says that Helgi escapes, consumes the raw meat of cattle he has slaughtered on a beach, and encounters Sigrún. Sigrún, daughter of King Högni, is &quot;a valkyrie and rode through air and sea&quot;, and she is the valkyrie Sváva reincarnated.&lt;ref name=&quot;LARRINGTON133&quot;&gt;Larrington (1999:133).&lt;/ref&gt; In stanza 7, Sigrún uses the phrase &quot;fed the [[goose|gosling]] of Gunn's sisters&quot;. Gunnr and her sisters are valkyries, and these goslings are [[raven]]s, who feed on the corpses left on the battlefield by warriors.&lt;ref name=&quot;LARRINGTON133+281&quot;&gt;Larrington (1999:133 and 281).&lt;/ref&gt;

After stanza 18, a prose narrative relates that Helgi and his immense fleet of ships are heading to Frekastein, but encounter a great storm. Lightning strikes one of the ships. The fleet sees nine valkyries flying through the air, among whom they recognise Sigrún. The storm abates, and the fleets arrive safely at land.&lt;ref name=&quot;LARRINGTON135&quot;&gt;Larrington (1999:135).&lt;/ref&gt; Helgi dies in battle, yet returns to visit Sigrún from Valhalla once in a burial mound, and at the end of the poem, a prose epilogue explains that Sigrún later dies of grief. The epilogue details that &quot;there was a belief in the pagan religion, which we now reckon [is] an old wives' tale, that people could be reincarnated&quot; and that &quot;Helgi and Sigrun were thought to have been reborn&quot; as another Helgi and valkyrie couple; Helgi as Helgi Haddingjaskaði and Sigrún as the daughter of [[Halfdan]]; the valkyrie [[Kára]]. The epilogue details that further information about the two can be found in the (now lost) work ''[[Káruljóð]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;LARRINGTON141&quot;&gt;Larrington (1999:141).&lt;/ref&gt;

====''Sigrdrífumál''====

In the prose introduction to the poem ''[[Sigrdrífumál]]'', the hero [[Sigurd]] rides up to Hindarfell and heads south towards &quot;the land of the [[Franks]]&quot;. On the mountain Sigurd sees a great light, &quot;as if fire were burning, which blazed up to the sky&quot;. Sigurd approaches it, and there he sees a ''skjaldborg'' with a banner flying overhead. Sigurd enters the ''skjaldborg'', and sees a warrior lying there—asleep and fully armed. Sigurd removes the helmet of the warrior, and sees the face of a woman. The woman's [[corslet]] is so tight that it seems to have grown into the woman's body. Sigurd uses his sword [[Gram (mythology)|Gram]] to cut the corslet, starting from the neck of the corslet downwards, he continues cutting down her sleeves, and takes the corslet off of her.&lt;ref name=&quot;THORPE180&quot;&gt;Thorpe (1907:180).&lt;/ref&gt;

The woman wakes, sits up, looks at Sigurd, and the two converse in two stanzas of verse. In the second stanza, the woman explains that Odin placed a sleeping spell on her she could not break, and due to that spell she has been asleep a long time. Sigurd asks for her name, and the woman gives Sigurd a [[drinking horn|horn]] of [[mead]] to help him retain her words in his memory. The woman recites a heathen [[prayer]] in two stanzas. A prose narrative explains that the woman is named [[Sigrdrífa]] and that she is a valkyrie.&lt;ref name=&quot;LARRINGTON166-167&quot;&gt;Larrington (1999:166–167).&lt;/ref&gt;

A narrative relates that Sigrdrífa explains to Sigurd that there were two kings fighting one another. Odin had promised one of these—Hjalmgunnar—victory in battle, yet she had &quot;brought down&quot; Hjalmgunnar in battle. Odin pricked her with a sleeping-thorn in consequence, told her she would never again &quot;fight victoriously in battle&quot;, and condemned her to marriage. In response, Sigrdrífa told Odin she had sworn a great oath that she would never wed a man who knew fear. Sigurd asks Sigrdrífa to share with him her wisdom of all worlds. The poem continues in verse, where Sigrdrífa provides Sigurd with knowledge in inscribing [[runic alphabet|runes]], mystic wisdom, and prophecy.&lt;ref name=&quot;LARRINGTON167&quot;&gt;Larrington (1999:167).&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Prose Edda''===

In the ''[[Prose Edda]]'', written in the 13th century by [[Snorri Sturluson]], valkyries are first mentioned in chapter 36 of the book ''[[Gylfaginning]]'', where the enthroned figure of [[High, Just-As-High, and Third|High]] informs [[Gylfi|Gangleri]] (King [[Gylfi]] in disguise) of the activities of the valkyries and mentions a few goddesses. High says &quot;there are still others whose duty it is to serve in Valhalla. They bring drink and see to the table and the ale cups.&quot; Following this, High gives a stanza from the poem ''Grímnismál'' that contains a list of valkyries. High says &quot;these women are called valkyries, and they are sent by Odin to every battle, where they choose which men are to die and they determine who has victory&quot;. High adds that [[Gunnr]] (&quot;war&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ORCHARD194&quot;/&gt;), [[Róta]], and Skuld—the last of the three he refers to as &quot;the youngest [[norns|norn]]&quot;—&quot;always ride to choose the slain and decide the outcome of battle&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;BYOCK44-45&quot;&gt;Byock (2005:44–45).&lt;/ref&gt; In chapter 49, High describes that when Odin and his wife [[Frigg]] arrived at the funeral of their slain son [[Baldr]], with them came the valkyries and also [[Hugin and Munin|Odin's ravens]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BYOCK67&quot;&gt;Byock (2005:67).&lt;/ref&gt;

References to valkyries appear throughout the book ''[[Skáldskaparmál]]'', which provides information about skaldic poetry. In chapter 2, a quote is given from the work ''[[Húsdrápa]]'' by the 10th century skald [[Úlfr Uggason]]. In the poem, Úlfr describes mythological scenes depicted in a newly built hall, including valkyries and ravens accompanying Odin at Baldr's funeral feast:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
:There I perceive valkyries and ravens,
:accompanying the wise victory-tree [Odin]
:to the drink of the holy offering [Baldr's funeral feast]
:Within have appeared these motifs.&lt;ref name=&quot;FAULKES68&quot;&gt;Faulkes (1995:68).&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Further in chapter 2, a quote from the anonymous 10th century poem ''[[Eiríksmál]]'' is provided (see the ''Fagrskinna'' section below for more detail about the poem and another translation):
&lt;blockquote&gt;
:What sort of dream is that, Odin?
:I dreamed I rose up before dawn
:to clear up Val-hall for slain people.
:I aroused the Einheriar,
:bade them get up to strew the benches,
:clean the beer-cups,
:the valkyries to serve wine
:for the arrival of a prince.&lt;ref name=&quot;FAULKES69&quot;&gt;Faulkes (1995:69).&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
In chapter 31, poetic terms for referring to a woman are given, including &quot;[a] woman is also referred to in terms of all Asyniur or valkyries or norns or ''dísir''&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;FAULKES94&quot;&gt;Faulkes (1995:94).&lt;/ref&gt; In chapter 41, while the hero [[Sigurd]] is riding his horse [[Grani]], he encounters a building on a mountain. Within this building Sigurd finds a sleeping woman wearing a helmet and a [[Mail (armour)|coat of mail]]. Sigurd cuts the mail from her, and she awakes. She tells him her name is Hildr, and &quot;she is known as [[Brynhildr]], and was a valkyrie&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;FAULKES102&quot;&gt;Faulkes (1995:102).&lt;/ref&gt;

In chapter 48, poetic terms for &quot;battle&quot; include &quot;weather of weapons or shields, or of Odin or valkyrie or war-kings or their clash or noise&quot;, followed by examples of compositions by various [[skald]]s that have used the name of valkyries in said manner ([[Þorbjörn Hornklofi]] uses &quot;Skögul's din&quot; for &quot;battlefield&quot;, [[Bersi Skáldtorfuson]] uses &quot;Gunnr's fire&quot; for &quot;sword&quot; and &quot;Hlökk's snow&quot; for &quot;battle&quot;, [[Einarr Skúlason]] uses &quot;Hildr's sail&quot; for &quot;shield&quot; and &quot;Göndul's crushing wind&quot; for &quot;battle&quot; and [[Einarr Helgason|Einarr skálaglamm]] uses &quot;Göndul's din&quot;). Chapter 49 gives similar information when referring to weapons and armor (though the term &quot;death-maidens&quot;—Old Norse ''valmeyjar''—instead of &quot;valkyries&quot; is used here), with further examples.&lt;ref name=&quot;FAULKES117-119&quot;&gt;Faulkes (1995:117–119).&lt;/ref&gt; In chapter 57, within a list of names of [[ásynjur]] (and after alternate names for the goddess [[Freyja]] are provided), a further section contains a list of &quot;Odin's maids&quot;; valkyries: Hildr, Göndul, Hlökk, Mist, Skögul. And then an additional four names; Hrund, [[Eir]], Hrist and Skuld. The section adds that &quot;they are called norns who shape necessity&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;FAULKES157&quot;&gt;Faulkes (1995:157).&lt;/ref&gt;

Some manuscripts of the feature ''[[Nafnaþulur]]'' section of ''Skáldskaparmál'' contain an extended list of 29 valkyrie names (listed as the &quot;valkyries of [[List of names of Odin|Viðrir]]&quot;—a name of Odin). The first stanza lists: Hrist, Mist, Herja, Hlökk, Geiravör, Göll, Hjörþrimul, Guðr, Herfjötra, Skuld, Geirönul, Skögul and Randgníð. The second stanza lists: Ráðgríðr, Göndul, Svipul, Geirskögul, Hildr, Skeggöld, Hrund, Geirdriful, Randgríðr, Þrúðr, Reginleif, Sveið, Þögn, Hjalmþrimul, Þrima and Skalmöld.&lt;ref name=&quot;JÓNSSON678&quot;&gt;Jónsson (1973:678).&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Hrafnsmál''===

The fragmentary skaldic poem ''[[Hrafnsmál]]'' (generally accepted as authored by 9th century Norwegian skald [[Þorbjörn Hornklofi]]) features a conversation between a valkyrie and a raven, largely consisting of the life and deeds of [[Harald I of Norway]]. The poem begins with a request for silence among noblemen so that the skald may tell the deeds of Harald Fairhair. The narrator states that they once overheard a &quot;high-minded&quot;, &quot;golden-haired&quot; and &quot;white-armed&quot; maiden speaking with a &quot;glossy-beaked raven&quot;. The valkyrie considers herself wise, understands the speech of birds, is further described as having a white-throat and sparkling eyes, and she takes no pleasure in men:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
:Wise thought her the valkyrie; were welcome never
:men to the bright-eyed one, her who the birds' speech knew well.
: Greeted the light-lashed maiden, the lily-throated woman,
:The [[ymir|hymir]]'s-skull-cleaver as on cliff he was perching.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
The valkyrie, previously described as fair and beautiful, then speaks to the gore-drenched and corpse-reeking raven:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
:&quot;How is it, ye ravens—whence are ye come now
:with beaks all gory, at break of morning?
:Carrion-reek ye carry, and your claws are bloody.
:Were ye near, at night-time, where ye knew of corpses?&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;HOLLANDER54&quot;&gt;Hollander (1980:54).&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
The black raven shakes himself, and he responds that he and the rest of the ravens have followed Harald since hatching from their eggs. The raven expresses surprise that the valkyrie seems unfamiliar with the deeds of Harald, and tells her about his deeds for several stanzas. At stanza 15, a question and answer format begins where the valkyrie asks the raven a question regarding Harald, and the raven responds in turn. This continues until the poem ends abruptly.&lt;ref name=&quot;HOLLANDER54-57&quot;&gt;Hollander (1980:54–57).&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Njáls saga''===

In chapter 157 of ''[[Njáls saga]]'', a man named Dörruð witnesses 12 people riding together to a stone hut on [[Good Friday]] in [[Caithness]]. The 12 go into the hut and Dörruð can no longer see them. Dörruð goes to the hut, and looks through a chink in the wall. He sees that there are women within, and that they have set up a particular [[loom]]; the heads of men are the weights, the entrails of men are the [[warp (weaving)|warp]] and [[weft]], a sword is the [[Shuttle (weaving)|shuttle]], and the [[reel]]s are composed of arrows. The women sing a song called ''[[Darraðarljóð]]'', which Dörruð memorizes.&lt;ref name=&quot;HOLLANDER66&quot;&gt;Hollander (1980:66).&lt;/ref&gt;

The song consists of 11 stanzas, and within it the valkyries weave and choose who is to be slain at the [[Battle of Clontarf]] (fought outside [[Dublin]] in 1014 [[Common Era|CE]]). Of the 12 valkyries weaving, six have their names given in the song: Hildr, [[Hjörþrimul]], [[Sanngriðr]], [[Svipul]], [[Guðr]] and Göndul. Stanza 9 of the song reads:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
:Now awful it is to be without,
:as blood-red rack races overhead;
:is the welkin gory with warriors' blood
:as we valkyries war-songs chanted.&lt;ref name=&quot;HOLLANDER68&quot;&gt;Hollander (1980:68).&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
At the end of the poem, the valkyries sing &quot;start we swiftly with steeds unsaddled—hence to battle with brandished swords!&quot;&lt;ref name=HOLLANDER68/&gt; The prose narrative picks up again, and says that the valkyries tear their loom down and into pieces. Each valkyrie holds on to what she has in her hands. Dörruð leaves the chink in the wall and heads home, and the women mount their horses and ride away; six to the south and six to the north.&lt;ref name=HOLLANDER66/&gt;

===''Heimskringla''===

At the end of the ''[[Heimskringla]]'' saga ''[[Hákonar saga góða]]'', the poem ''[[Hákonarmál]]'' by the 10th century [[skald]] [[Eyvindr skáldaspillir]] is presented. The saga relates that king [[Haakon I of Norway]] died in battle, and although he is Christian, he requests that since he has died &quot;among heathens, then give me such burial place as seems most fitting to you&quot;. The saga relates that shortly after Haakon died on the same slab of rock that he was born upon, he was greatly mourned by friend and foe alike, and that his friends moved his body northward to Sæheim in North [[Hordaland]]. Haakon was buried there in a large burial mound in full armour and his finest clothing, yet with no other valuables. Further, &quot;words were spoken over his grave according to the custom of heathen men, and they put him on the way to Valhalla&quot;. The poem ''Hákonarmál'' is then provided.&lt;ref name=&quot;HOLLANDER124-125&quot;&gt;Hollander (2007:124–125).&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''Hákonarmál'', Odin sends forth the two valkyries Göndul and Skögul to &quot;choose among the kings' kinsmen&quot; and who in battle should dwell with Odin in Valhalla. A battle rages with great slaughter, and part of the description employs the [[kenning]] &quot;Skögul's-stormblast&quot; for &quot;battle&quot;. Haakon and his men die in battle, and they see the valkyrie Göndul leaning on a spear shaft. Göndul comments that &quot;groweth now the gods' following, since Hákon has been with host so goodly bidden home with holy godheads&quot;. Haakon hears &quot;what the valkyries said&quot;, and the valkyries are described as sitting &quot;high-hearted on horseback&quot;, wearing helmets, carrying shields and that the horses wisely bore them.&lt;ref name=&quot;HOLLANDER125&quot;&gt;Hollander (2007:125).&lt;/ref&gt; A brief exchange follows between Haakon and the valkyrie Skögul:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
:''Hákon said:''
:&quot;Why didst Geirskogul grudge us victory?
:though worthy we were for the gods to grant it?&quot;
:''Skogul said:''
:&quot;'Tis owing to us that the issue was won
: and your foemen fled.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;HOLLANDER126&quot;&gt;Hollander (2007:126).&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Skögul says that they shall now ride forth to the &quot;green homes of the godheads&quot; to tell Odin the king will come to Valhalla. The poem continues, and Haakon becomes a part of the einherjar in Valhalla, awaiting to do battle with the monstrous wolf [[Fenrir]].&lt;ref name=&quot;HOLLANDER126-127&quot;&gt;Hollander (2007:126–127).&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Fagrskinna''===

In chapter 8 of ''[[Fagrskinna]]'', a prose narrative states that, after the death of her husband [[Eric Bloodaxe]], [[Gunnhild Mother of Kings]] had a poem composed about him. The composition is by an anonymous author from the 10th century and is referred to as ''[[Eiríksmál]]''. It describes Eric Bloodaxe and five other kings arriving in Valhalla after their death. The poem begins with comments by Odin (as Old Norse ''Óðinn''):
&lt;blockquote&gt;
:'What kind of a dream is it,' said Óðinn,
:in which just before daybreak,
:I thought I cleared Valhǫll,
:for coming of slain men?
:I waked the Einherjar,
:bade valkyries rise up,
:to strew the bench,
:and scour the beakers,

:wine to carry,
:as for a king's coming,
:here to me I expect
:heroes' coming from the world,
:certain great ones,
:so glad is my heart.&lt;ref name=&quot;FINLAY58&quot;&gt;Finlay (2004:58).&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
The god [[Bragi]] asks where a thundering sound is coming from, and says that the benches of Valhalla are creaking—as if the god Baldr had returned to Valhalla—and that it sounds like the movement of a thousand. Odin responds that Bragi knows well that the sounds are for Eric Bloodaxe, who will soon arrive in Valhalla. Odin tells the heroes [[Sigmund]] and [[Sinfjötli]] to rise to greet Eric and invite him into the hall, if it is indeed he.&lt;ref name=&quot;FINLAY59&quot;&gt;Finlay (2004:59).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ragnhild Tregagás charm===
A [[Witch-hunt|witchcraft trial]] held in 1324 in [[Bergen]], [[Norway]], records a spell used by the accused [[Ragnhild Tregagás]] to end the marriage of her former lover, a man named Bárd. The charm contains a mention of the valkyrie [[Göndul]] being &quot;sent out&quot;:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
:I send out from me the spirits of (the valkyrie) Gondul.
:May the first bite you in the back.
:May the second bite you in the breast.
:May the third turn hate and envy upon you.&lt;ref name=&quot;MACLEOD37&quot;&gt;MacLeod (2006:37).&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Old English attestations==
[[File:Sermo Lupi.jpg|thumb|A page from ''[[Sermo Lupi ad Anglos]]'']]
The Old English ''wælcyrge'' and ''wælcyrie'' appear several times in Old English manuscripts, generally to translate foreign concepts into Old English. In the sermon ''[[Sermo Lupi ad Anglos]]'', written by [[Wulfstan II]], ''wælcyrie'' is used, and considered to appear as word for a human &quot;sorceress&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;NORTH106&quot;&gt;North (1997:106).&lt;/ref&gt; An early 11th-century manuscript of Aldhelm's ''De laudis virginitatis'' (Oxford, Bodleian library, Digby 146) [[gloss (annotation)|glosses]] ''ueneris'' with ''wælcyrge'' (with ''gydene'' meaning &quot;goddess&quot;). ''Wælcyrge'' is used to translate the names of the [[Classical mythology|classical]] [[Erinyes|furies]] in two manuscripts ([[Cotton Cleopatra]] A. iii, and the older ''Corpus Glossary''). In the manuscript Cotton Cleopatra A. iii, ''wælcyrge'' is also used to gloss the [[Roman mythology|Roman goddess]] [[Bellona (goddess)|Bellona]]. A description of a raven flying over the Egyptian army appears as ''wonn wælceaseg'' (meaning &quot;dark one choosing the slain&quot;). Scholarly theories debate whether these attestations point to an indigenous belief among the Anglo-Saxons shared with the Norse, or if they were a result of later Norse influence (see section below).&lt;ref name=&quot;NORTH106&quot;/&gt;

==Archaeological record==

===Female figures and cup and horn-bearers===

[[Viking Age]] stylized silver amulets depicting women with long gowns, their hair pulled back, sometimes bearing forth [[drinking horn]]s have been discovered throughout Scandinavia. These figures are commonly considered to represent valkyries or dísir.&lt;ref name=&quot;SILVERFIGURES&quot;&gt;Orchard (1997:172) and Lindow (2001:96).&lt;/ref&gt; According to Mindy MacLeod and Bernard Mees, the amulets appear in Viking Age graves, and were presumably placed there because &quot;they were thought to have protective powers&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;MACLEOD37&quot;/&gt;

The [[Tjängvide image stone]] from the island of [[Gotland]], Sweden features a rider on an eight-legged horse, which may be Odin's eight-legged horse [[Sleipnir]], being greeted by a female, which may be a valkyrie at Valhalla.&lt;ref name=&quot;LINDOW276&quot;&gt;Lindow (2001:276).&lt;/ref&gt; The 11th century [[runestone]] [[Sigurd stones#U 1163|U 1163]] features a carving of a female bearing a horn that has been interpreted as the valkyrie Sigrdrífa handing the hero Sigurd (also depicted on the stone) a drinking horn.&lt;ref name=&quot;WESSEN621&quot;&gt;Wessén &amp; Jansson (1953–58:621).&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2013, a small figure dated at around 800 AD was discovered in [[Hårby]], [[Denmark]] by three amateur archaeologists. The figurine portrays a woman with long hair in a ponytail carrying a sword and a shield. Commenting on the figure, archaeologist Mogens Bo Henriksen said that &quot;there can hardly be any doubt that the figure depicts one of Odin's valkyries as we know them from the sagas as well as from Swedish picture stones from the time around AD700&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;KENNEDY-2013&quot;&gt;Kennedy (2013).&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;gallery widths=&quot;175px&quot; heights=&quot;180px&quot; perrow=&quot;4&quot;&gt;
File:Valkyrie.jpg|A silver figure of a woman holding a drinking horn found in [[Birka]], [[Björkö, Ekerö|Björkö]], [[Uppland]], [[Sweden]].
File:Silver figure with hair and silver figure with horse.jpg|Both silver, a female figure touches her hair while facing forward (left) and a figure sits atop a horse, facing another figure with a shield (right).
File:Arrival at Valhalla.jpg|A female figure bears a horn to a rider on an eight-legged horse on the [[Tjängvide image stone]] in Sweden.
File:U 1163, Drävle (Sigrdrífa).JPG|A female figure bearing a horn on runestone [[Sigurd stones#U 1163|U 1163]].
&lt;/gallery&gt;

===Runic inscriptions===
[[File:Rökstenen.jpg|thumb|The [[Rök Runestone]]]]
Specific valkyries are mentioned on two [[runestones]]; the early 9th century [[Rök Runestone]] in [[Östergötland]], [[Sweden]], and the 10th-century [[Karlevi Runestone]] on the island of [[Öland]], [[Sweden]], which mentions the valkyrie [[Þrúðr]].&lt;ref name=&quot;MACLEOD37&quot;/&gt; On the Rök Runestone, a [[kenning]] is employed that involves a valkyrie riding a wolf as her steed:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
:That we tell the twelfth, where the horse of the Valkyrie [literally &quot;the horse of [[Gunnr|Gunn]]&quot;] sees food on the battlefield, where twenty kings are lying.&lt;ref name=&quot;ANDRÉN11&quot;&gt;Andrén (2006:11).&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Among the [[Bryggen inscriptions]] found in [[Bergen]], [[Norway]], is the &quot;valkyrie stick&quot; from the late 14th century. The stick features a [[Runic alphabet|runic inscription]] intended as a charm. The inscription says that &quot;I cut cure-runes&quot;, and also &quot;help-runes&quot;, once against [[elf|elves]], twice against [[trolls]], thrice against [[jötunn|thurs]] and then a mention of a valkyrie occurs:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
:Against the harmful ''skag''-valkyrie,
:so that she never shall, though she never would -
:evil woman! - injure (?) your life.&lt;ref name=&quot;MACLEOD34-35&quot;&gt;MacLeod (2006:34–35).&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
This is followed by &quot;I send you, I look at you, wolfish perversion, and unbearable desire, may distress descend on you and ''jöluns'' wrath. Never shall you sit, never shall you sleep ... (that you) love me as yourself.&quot; According to Mindy MacLeod and Bernard Mees, the inscription &quot;seems to begin as a benevolent formulation before abruptly switching to the infliction of distress and misery, presumably upon the recipient of the charm rather than the baleful valkyrie&quot;, and they posit the final line appears &quot;to constitute a rather spiteful kind of charm aimed at securing the love of a woman&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;MACLEOD34-37&quot;&gt;MacLeod (2006:34–37).&lt;/ref&gt;

MacLeod and Mees state that the opening lines of the charm correspond to the ''Poetic Edda'' poem ''Sigrdrífumál'', where the valkyrie Sigrdrífa provides runic advice, and that the meaning of the term ''skag'' is unclear, but a cognate exists in ''Helgakviða Hundingsbana I'' where Sinfjötli accuses Guðmundr of having once been a &quot;''skass''-valkyrie&quot;. MacLeod and Mees believe the word means something like &quot;supernatural sending&quot;, and that this points to a connection to the Ragnhild Tregagás charm, where a valkyrie is also &quot;sent forth&quot;.&lt;ref name=MACLEOD34-37/&gt;

==Valkyrie names==
{{main|List of valkyrie names}}
The Old Norse poems ''[[Völuspá]]'', ''[[Grímnismál]]'', ''[[Darraðarljóð]]'' and the ''[[Nafnaþulur]]'' section of the ''[[Prose Edda]]'' book ''[[Skáldskaparmál]]'', provide lists of valkyrie names. In addition, some valkyrie names appear solely outside of these lists, such as ''[[Sigrún]]'' (who is attested in the poems ''[[Helgakviða Hundingsbana I]]'' and ''[[Helgakviða Hundingsbana II]]''). Many valkyrie names emphasize associations with battle and, in many cases, on the spear—a weapon heavily associated with the god Odin.&lt;ref name=&quot;DAVIDSON96&quot;&gt;Davidson (1988:96).&lt;/ref&gt; Some scholars propose that the names of the valkyries themselves contain no individuality, but are rather descriptive of the traits and nature of war-goddesses, and are possibly the descriptive creations of [[skalds]].&lt;ref name=&quot;DAVIDSON+SIMEK&quot;&gt;Examples include Davidson (1988:96–97) and Simek (2007:349).&lt;/ref&gt;

Some valkyrie names may be descriptive of the roles and abilities of the valkyries. The valkyrie name ''[[Herja]]'' has been theorised as pointing to a connection to the name of the goddess ''[[Hariasa]]'', who is attested from a stone from 187 [[Common Era|CE]].&lt;ref name=&quot;SIMEK143AND131&quot;&gt;Simek (2007:143). For Hariasa, Simek (2007:131).&lt;/ref&gt; The name ''[[Herfjötur]]'' has been theorised as pointing to the ability of the valkyries to place fetters.&lt;ref name=&quot;SIMEK142&quot;&gt;Simek (2007:142).&lt;/ref&gt; The name ''[[Svipul]]'' may be descriptive of the influence the valkyries have over [[wyrd|wyrd or ørlog]]—a [[Germanic paganism|Germanic]] concept of [[Destiny|fate]].&lt;ref name=&quot;SIMEK308&quot;&gt;Simek (2007:308).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Theories==

===Old English ''wælcyrge'' and Old English charms===
[[File:Sutton Hoo Burial Mound.jpg|thumb|An Anglo-Saxon [[tumulus|burial mound]] at [[Sutton Hoo]] in [[Suffolk]], [[England]]]]
Richard North says that the description of a raven flying over the [[Egypt]]ian army (glossed as ''wonn wælceaseg'') may have been directly influenced by the Old Norse concept of Valhalla, the usage of ''wælcyrge'' in ''De laudibus virginitatis'' may represent a loan or loan-translation of Old Norse ''valkyrja'', but the Cotton Cleopatra A. iii and the ''Corpus Glossary'' instances &quot;appear to show an [[Anglo-Saxons|Anglo-Saxon]] conception of ''wælcyrge'' that was independent of contemporary [[Scandinavia]]n influence&quot;.&lt;ref name=NORTH106/&gt;

Two [[Old English literature|Old English]] charms mention figures that are theorised as representing an Anglo-Saxon notion of valkyries or valkyrie-like female beings; ''[[Wið færstice]]'', a charm to cure a sudden pain or stitch, and ''[[For a Swarm of Bees]]'', a charm to keep [[honey bee]]s from [[Swarming (honey bee)|swarming]]. In ''Wið færstice'', a sudden pain is attributed to a small, &quot;shrieking&quot; spear thrown with supernatural strength (Old English ''mægen'') by &quot;fierce&quot; loudly flying &quot;mighty women&quot; (Old English ''mihtigan wif'') who have ridden over a burial mound:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
:They were loud, yes, loud,
:when they rode over the (burial) mound;
:they were fierce when they rode across the land.
:Shield yourself now, you can survive this strife.
:Out, little spear, if there is one here within.
:It stood under/behind lime-wood (i.e. a shield), under a light-coloured/light-weight shield,
:where those mighty women marshalled their powers, and they send shrieking spears.&lt;ref name=&quot;HALL1-2&quot;&gt;Hall (2007:1–2).&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Theories have been proposed that these figures are connected to valkyries.&lt;ref name=&quot;GREENFIELD257&quot;&gt;Greenfield (1996:257).&lt;/ref&gt; Richard North says that &quot;though it is not clear what the poet takes these women to be, their female sex, riding in flight and throwing spears suggest that they were imagined in England as a female being analogous to the later Norse ''valkyrjur''.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;NORTH105&quot;&gt;North (1997:105).&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hilda Ellis Davidson]] theorizes that ''Wið færstice'' was originally a battle spell that had, over time, been reduced to evoke &quot;a prosaic stitch in the side&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;DAVIDSON63&quot;&gt;Davidson (1990:63).&lt;/ref&gt; Towards the end of ''For a Swarm of Bees'', the swarming bees are referred to as &quot;victory-women&quot; (Old English ''sigewif''):
&lt;blockquote&gt;
:Settle down, victory-women,
:never be wild and fly to the woods.
:Be as mindful of my welfare,
:as is each man of eating and of home.&lt;ref name=&quot;GREENFIELD256&quot;&gt;Greenfield (1996:256).&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
The term &quot;victory women&quot; has been theorised as pointing to an association with valkyries. This theory is not universally accepted, and the reference has also been theorised as a simple metaphor for the &quot;victorious sword&quot; (the stinging) of the bees.&lt;ref name=GREENFIELD256/&gt;

===Merseburg Incantation, fetters, dísir, ''idisi'' and norns===

One of the two [[Old High German]] [[Merseburg Incantations]] call upon female beings—''[[Idisi]]''—to bind and hamper an army. The incantation reads:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
:Once the Idisi sat, sat here and there,
:some bound fetters, some hampered the army,
:some untied fetters:
:Escape from the fetters, flee from the enemies.&lt;ref name=&quot;SIMEK171&quot;&gt;Simek (2007:171).&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
The ''Idisi'' mentioned in the incantation are generally considered to be valkyries. Rudolf Simek says that &quot;these Idisi are obviously a kind of valkyrie, as these also have the power to hamper enemies in Norse mythology&quot; and points to a connection with the valkyrie name ''[[Herfjötur]]'' (Old Norse &quot;army-fetter&quot;).&lt;ref name=SIMEK171/&gt; Hilda R. Davidson compares the incantation to the Old English ''Wið færstice'' charm and theorises a similar role for them both.&lt;ref name=DAVIDSON63/&gt;

Simek says that the [[West Germanic languages|West Germanic]] term ''Idisi'' (Old Saxon ''idis'', Old High German ''itis'', Old English ''ides'') refers to a &quot;dignified, well respected woman (married or unmarried), possibly a term for any woman, and therefore glosses exactly Latin ''[[Matres and Matrones|matrona]]''&quot; and that a link to the [[North Germanic languages|North Germanic]] term ''dísir'' is reasonable to assume, yet not undisputed. In addition, the place name [[Idistaviso|Idisiaviso]] (meaning &quot;plain of the Idisi&quot;) where forces commanded by [[Arminius]] fought those commanded by [[Germanicus]] at the [[Battle of the Weser River]] in 16 AD. Simek points to a connection between the name ''Idisiaviso'', the role of the Idisi in one of the two Merseburg Incantations and valkyries.&lt;ref name=&quot;SIMEK171&quot;/&gt;

Regarding the dísir, Simek states that Old Norse ''dís'' appears commonly as simply a term for &quot;woman&quot;, just as Old High German ''itis'', Old Saxon ''idis'' and Old English ''ides'', and may have also been used to denote a type of goddess. According to Simek, &quot;several of the Eddic sources might lead us to conclude that the ''dísir'' were valkyrie-like guardians of the dead, and indeed in ''[[Guðrúnarkviða]]'' I 19 the valkyries are even called ''Herjans dísir'' &quot;Odin's dísir&quot;. The ''dísir'' are explicitly called dead women in ''[[Atlamál]]'' 28 and a secondary belief that the ''dísir'' were the souls of dead women (see ''[[Fylgja|fylgjur]]'') also underlies the ''[[landdísir]]'' of [[Scandinavian folklore|Icelandic folklore]].&lt;ref name=&quot;SIMEK61-62&quot;&gt;Simek (2007:61–62).&lt;/ref&gt; Simek says that &quot;as the function of the [[Matres and Matrones|matrons]] was also extremely varied—fertility goddess, personal guardians, but also warrior-goddesses—the belief in the ''dísir'', like the belief in the valkyries, norns and matrons, may be considered to be different manifestations of a belief in a number of female (half-?) goddesses.&quot;&lt;ref name=SIMEK61-62/&gt;

[[Jacob Grimm]] states that, though the norns and valkyries are similar in nature, there is a fundamental difference between the two. Grimm states that a dís can be both norn and a valkyrie, &quot;but their functions are separate and usually the persons. The norns have to pronounce the fatum [fate], they sit on their chairs, or they roam through the country among mortals, fastening their threads. Nowhere is it said that they ride. The valkyrs ''ride'' to war, decide the issues of fighting, and conduct the fallen to heaven; their riding is like that of heroes and gods [...].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;GRIMM421&quot;&gt;Grimm (1882:421).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Origins and development===
[[File:Die Nornen (1889) by Johannes Gehrts.jpg|thumb|''The Norns'' (1889) by [[Johannes Gehrts]]]]
Various theories have been proposed about the origins and development of the valkyries from Germanic paganism to later Norse mythology. Rudolf Simek suggests valkyries were probably originally viewed as &quot;demons of the dead to whom warriors slain on the battlefield belonged&quot;, and that a shift in interpretation of the valkyries may have occurred &quot;when the concept of Valhalla changed from a battlefield to a warrior's paradise&quot;. Simek says that this original concept was &quot;superseded by the [[Shieldmaiden|shield girls]]—Irish female warriors who lived on like the ''einherjar'' in Valhall.&quot; Simek says that the valkyries were closely associated with Odin, and that this connection existed in an earlier role as &quot;demons of death&quot;. Simek states that due to the shift of concept, the valkyries became popular figures in [[Poetic Edda#Heroic lays|heroic poetry]], and during this transition were stripped of their &quot;demonic characteristics and became more human, and therefore become capable of falling in love with mortals [...].&quot; Simek says that the majority of the names of the valkyries point to a warlike function, that most of [[List of valkyrie names in Norse mythology|valkyrie names]] do not appear to be very old, and that the names &quot;mostly come from poetic creativity rather than from real folk-belief.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SIMEK349&quot;/&gt;

MacLeod and Mees theorise that &quot;the role of the corpse-choosing valkyries became increasingly confused in later Norse mythology with that of the [[Norns]], the supernatural females responsible for determining human destiny [...].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;MACLEOD39&quot;&gt;MacLeod (2006:39).&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Hilda Ellis Davidson]] says that, regarding valkyries, &quot;evidently an elaborate literary picture has been built up by generations of poets and storytellers, in which several conceptions can be discerned. We recognise something akin to Norns, spirits who decide destinies of men; to the [[Völva|seeresses]], who could protect men in battle with their spells; to the powerful female guardian spirits attached to certain families, bringing luck to youth under their protection; even to certain women who armed themselves and fought like men, for whom there is some historical evidence from the regions round the [[Black Sea]]&quot;. She adds that there may also be a memory in this of a &quot;priestess of the god of war, women who officiated at the sacrificial rites when captives were put to death after battle.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;DAVIDSON61&quot;&gt;Davidson (1990:61).&lt;/ref&gt;

Davidson places emphasis on the fact that ''valkyrie'' literally means &quot;chooser of the slain&quot;. She compares Wulfstan's mention of a &quot;chooser of the slain&quot; in his ''Sermo Lupi ad Anglos'' sermon, which appears among &quot;a blacklist of sinners, witches and evildoers&quot;, to &quot;all the other classes whom he [Wulfstan] mentions&quot;, and concludes as those &quot;are human ones, it seems unlikely that he has introduced mythological figures as well.&quot; Davidson points out that [[Arab]] traveller [[Ibn Fadlan]]'s detailed account of a 10th-century [[Rus' (people)|Rus]] ship funeral on the [[Volga River]] features an &quot;old [[Huns|Hunnish]] woman, massive and grim to look upon&quot; (who Fadlan refers to as the &quot;Angel of Death&quot;) who organises the killing of the slave girl, and has two other women with her that Fadlan refers to as her daughters. Davidson says that &quot;it would hardly be surprising if strange legends grew up about such women, who must have been kept apart from their kind due to their gruesome duties. Since it was often decided by lot which prisoners should be killed, the idea that the god &quot;chose&quot; his victims, through the instrument of the priestesses, must have been a familiar one, apart from the obvious assumption that some were chosen to fall in war.&quot; Davidson says that it appears that from &quot;early times&quot; the [[Germanic peoples]] &quot;believed in fierce female spirits doing the command of the war god, stirring up disorder, taking part in battle, seizing and perhaps devouring the slain.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;DAVIDSON61-62&quot;&gt;Davidson (1990:61–62).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Freyja and Fólkvangr===
[[File:Freya by C. E. Doepler.jpg|thumb|''Freya'' (1882) by [[Carl Emil Doepler]]]]
The goddess [[Freyja]] and her afterlife field [[Fólkvangr]], where she receives half of the slain, has been theorized as connected to the valkyries. Britt-Mari Näsström points out the description in ''Gylfaginning'' where it is said of Freyja &quot;whenever she rides into battle she takes half of the slain&quot;, and interprets ''Fólkvangr'' as &quot;the field of the Warriors&quot;. Näsström notes that, just like Odin, Freyja receives slain heroes who have died on the battlefield, and that her house is [[Sessrumnir]] (which she translates as &quot;filled with many seats&quot;), a dwelling that Näsström posits likely fills the same function as Valhalla. Näsström comments that &quot;still, we must ask why there are two heroic paradises in the Old Norse view of afterlife. It might possibly be a consequence of different forms of initiation of warriors, where one part seemed to have belonged to Óðinn and the other to Freyja. These examples indicate that Freyja was a war-goddess, and she even appears as a valkyrie, literally 'the one who chooses the slain'.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;NÄSSTRÖM61&quot;&gt;Näsström (1999:61).&lt;/ref&gt;

Siegfried Andres Dobat comments that &quot;in her mythological role as the chooser of half the fallen warriors for her death realm Fólkvangr, the goddess Freyja, however, emerges as the mythological role model for the Valkyrjar {{Sic}} and the dísir.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;DOBAT186&quot;&gt;Dobat (2006:186).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Modern influence==
[[File:Jugend-magazine-valkyrie-rheingold-advertisement-I.jpg|thumb|A valkyrie examines a bottle of [[Söhnlein]]'s &quot;Rheingold&quot; [[Sparkling wine#Sekt|sekt]] in a 1901 [[Art Nouveau|Jugendstil]] advertisement]]

Valkyries have been the subjects of various poems, works of art and musical works. In poetry, valkyries appear in &quot;Die Walküren&quot; by H. Heine (appearing in ''Romanzero'', 1847), &quot;Die Walküren&quot; (1864) by H. v. Linge, &quot;Sköldmon&quot; (appearing in ''Gömda Land'', 1904).&lt;ref name=&quot;SIMEK349&quot;&gt;Simek (2007:349).&lt;/ref&gt;  The &quot;Ride of the Valkyries&quot; ({{lang-de|Walkürenritt ''or'' Ritt der Walküren|links=no}}) (1856) is the popular term for the beginning of act 3 of ''[[Die Walküre]]'', one of  [[Richard Wagner]]'s best-known pieces, (the piece is well known in popular culture for its use in the 1979 film [[Apocalypse Now]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Ride of the Valkyries: Orchestral Music by Wagner|url=http://www.songfacts.com/detail.php?id=28202|website=Song facts|accessdate=15 August 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Works of art depicting valkyries include &quot;Die Walküren&quot; (sketch, 1818) by J. G. Sandberg, &quot;Reitende Walküre&quot; ([[fresco]]), previously located in [[Munich]] palace but now destroyed, 1865-66 by M. Echter, &quot;Valkyrien&quot; and &quot;Valkyriens død&quot; (paintings, both from 1860), &quot;Walkürenritt&quot; ([[etching]], 1871) by A. Welti, &quot;Walkürenritt&quot; ([[woodcut]], 1871) by T. Pixis, &quot;Walkürenritt&quot; (1872) by A. Becker (reproduced in 1873 with the same title by A. v. Heyde), &quot;Die Walkyren&quot; ([[charcoal]], 1880) and &quot;Walkyren wählen und wecken die gefallenen Helden (Einherier), um sie vom Schlachtfield nach Walhall zu geleiten&quot; (painting, 1882) and &quot;Walkyrenschlacht&quot; (oil painting, 1884) by K. Ehrenberg, &quot;Walkürenritt&quot; (oil painting, 1888, and etching, 1890) by A. Welti, &quot;Walküre&quot; (statue) by H. Günther, &quot;Walkürenritt&quot; (oil painting) by H. Hendrich, &quot;Walkürenritt&quot; (painting) by F. Leeke, &quot;Einherier&quot; (painting, from around 1900), by K. Dielitz, &quot;The Ride of the Valkyries&quot; (painting, from around 1900) by J. C. Dollman, &quot;Valkyrie&quot; (statue, 1910) and &quot;Walhalla-freeze&quot; (located in the [[Ny Carlsberg Glyptotek]], [[Copenhagen]], 1886–87), &quot;Walkyrien&quot; (print, 1915) by A. Kolb, and &quot;Valkyrier&quot; (drawing, 1925) by E. Hansen.&lt;ref name=&quot;SIMEK349-350&quot;&gt;Simek (2007:349–350).&lt;/ref&gt;

===In popular culture===
Valkyries have also been depicted in popular culture, including in comic books and video games. [[Square Enix]] and [[Tri-Ace]] created the popularly and critically acclaimed [[Valkyrie Profile (series)|''Valkyrie Profile'' series]] of video games, centered around a trio of Valkyries - Lenneth (''VP1/Lenneth''), Silmeria (''VP2'') and Hrist - including exploring their origins as they fight in the divine war leading to Ragnarok. Meanwhile, comic makers [[Stan Lee]] and [[Jack Kirby]] created the [[Valkyrior]], who serve a similar function to the Valkyries as well as having a similar name, in [[Marvel Comics]] as part of the Marvel adaptation of Norse mythology that includes [[Thor (comics)|Thor]] beginning with ''Thor #133'' in October 1966.

===Illustrations===
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Hild, Thrud and Hløkk by Frølich.jpg|The valkyries Hildr, Þrúðr and Hlökk bearing ale in Valhalla (1895) by [[Lorenz Frølich]]
File:Walkyrien by Emil Doepler.jpg|''Walkyrien'' (c. 1905) by [[Emil Doepler]]
File:ValkyrieOnHorse.jpg|''Valkyrie'' (1908) by [[Stephan Sinding]] located in [[Churchillparken|Churchill Park]] at [[Kastellet, Copenhagen|Kastellet]] in [[Copenhagen]], Denmark
File:Helgi Hundingsbane and Sigrún by Robert Engels.jpg|[[Helgi Hundingsbane]] and Sigrún (1919) by [[Robert Engels]]
File:Helgi und Sigrun by Johannes Gehrts.jpg|''Helgi und Sigrun'' (1901) by [[Johannes Gehrts]]
File:Ring48.jpg|The valkyrie [[Sigrdrífa]] says a [[Norse paganism|pagan Norse]] prayer in ''[[Sigrdrífumál]]''. Illustration (1911) by [[Arthur Rackham]].
File:Valkyrie (1834-1835) by H. W. Bissen.jpg|''Valkyrie'' (1835) by [[Herman Wilhelm Bissen]]
File:Valkyrie and raven.jpg|A valkyrie speaks with a raven (1862) by [[Anthony Frederick Augustus Sandys]]
File:Henry De Groux001.jpg|''Ride of the Valkyries'' (around 1890) by [[Henry De Groux]]
File:The Valkyrie's Vigil.jpg|''The Valkyrie's Vigil'' (1906) by [[Edward Robert Hughes]]
File:Heimdallr and valkyries by Frølich.jpg|An illustration of valkyries encountering the god [[Heimdallr]] as they carry a dead man to Valhalla (1906) by [[Lorenz Frølich]]
File:Walhall by Emil Doepler.jpg|''Valhalla'' (1905) by Emil Doepler
File:Idise by Emil Doepler.jpg|''Idise'' (1905) by Emil Doepler
File:The Dises by Hardy.jpg|''The Dises'' (1909) by [[Dorothy Hardy]]
File:The Ride of the Valkyrs.jpg|''The Ride of the Valkyrs'' (1909) by [[John Charles Dollman]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
*[[Valravn]], a supernatural &quot;raven of the slain&quot; appearing in 19th century Danish folk songs

==Notes==
{{Reflist|3}}

==References==
{{Refbegin}}
* Andrén, A.; Jennbert, K.; Raudvere, C. (2006) &quot;[https://books.google.com/books?id=gjq6rvoIRpAC&amp;pg=PA11 Old Norse Religion: Some Problems and Prospects]&quot; in ''Old Norse Religion in Long Term Perspectives: Origins, Changes and Interactions, an International Conference in Lund, Sweden, 3–7 June 2004''. Nordic Academic Press. ISBN 91-89116-81-X
* Byock, Jesse (Trans.) (2006). ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=EWgTAAAACAAJ The Prose Edda]''. [[Penguin Classics]]. ISBN 0-14-044755-5
* [[Hilda Ellis Davidson|Davidson, Hilda Roderick Ellis]] (1988). ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=RerIAAAAIAAJ Myths and Symbols in Pagan Europe: Early Scandinavian and Celtic Religions]''. [[Manchester University Press]]. ISBN 0-7190-2579-6
* Davidson, Hilda Roderick Ellis (1990). ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=O1faK2QkRvwC Gods and Myths of Northern Europe]''. [[Penguin Books]]. ISBN 0-14-013627-4
* Dobat, Siegfried Andres (2006). &quot;[https://books.google.com/books?id=gjq6rvoIRpAC&amp;pg=PA184 Bridging mythology and belief: Viking Age functional culture as a reflection of the belief in divine intervention]&quot; in Andren, A.; Jennbert, K.; Raudvere, C. ''Old Norse Religion in Long Term Perspectives: Origins, Changes and Interactions, an International Conference in Lund, Sweden, 3–7 June 2004.'' Nordic Academic Press. ISBN 91-89116-81-X
* [[Ursula Dronke|Dronke, Ursula]] (Trans.) (1997). ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=iDpcAAAAMAAJ The Poetic Edda: Volume II: Mythological Poems]''. [[Oxford University Press]]. ISBN 0-19-811181-9
* Faulkes, Anthony (Trans.) (1995). ''Edda''. [[Everyman's Library|Everyman]]. ISBN 0-460-87616-3
* Finlay, Alison (2004). ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=SmJ8v1ENhg4C Fagrskinna, a Catalogue of the Kings of Norway: A Translation with Introduction and Notes]''. [[Brill Publishers]]. ISBN 90-04-13172-8
* Greenfield, Stanley B.; Calder, Daniel Gillmore; Lapidge, Michael (1996). ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=kreGLK6VbqwC A New Critical History of Old English Literature]''. [[New York University Press]]. ISBN 0-8147-3088-4
* [[Jacob Grimm|Grimm, Jacob]] (1882) translated by James Steven Stallybrass. ''[[Deutsche Mythologie|Teutonic Mythology: Translated from the Fourth Edition with Notes and Appendix by James Stallybrass]]''. Volume I. London: George Bell and Sons.
* Hall, Alaric (2007). ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=G1V2N0GAkHQC Elves in Anglo-Saxon England]''. [[Boydell Press]]. ISBN 1-84383-294-1
* Kennedy, Maev (2013). &quot;Flight of the valkyrie: the Viking figurine that's heading for Britain&quot;. [[Theguardian.com]], Monday 4 March 2013. Online: [http://www.theguardian.com/culture/2013/mar/04/viking-valkyrie-figurine-british-museum]
* [[Lee M. Hollander|Hollander, Lee Milton]] (1980). ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=PUzazIlboAcC Old Norse Poems: The Most Important Nonskaldic Verse Not Included in the Poetic Edda]''. Forgotten Books. ISBN 1-60506-715-6
* Hollander, Lee Milton (Trans.) (2007). ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=qHpwje7-wNkC Heimskringla: History of the Kings of Norway]''. [[University of Texas Press]]. ISBN 978-0-292-73061-8
* [[Finnur Jónsson]] (1973). ''Den Norsk-Islandske Skjaldedigtning''. Rosenkilde og Bagger. {{da icon}}
* Larrington, Carolyne (Trans.) (1999). ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=nBzuQZ4MCPIC The Poetic Edda]''. [[Oxford World's Classics]]. ISBN 0-19-283946-2
* [[John Lindow|Lindow, John]] (2001). ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=KlT7tv3eMSwC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false Norse Mythology: A Guide to the Gods, Heroes, Rituals and Beliefs]''. [[Oxford University Press]]. ISBN 0-19-515382-0
* MacLeod, Mindy; Mees, Bernard (2006). ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=hx7UigqsTKoC Runic Amulets and Magic Objects]''. [[Boydell Press]]. ISBN 1-84383-205-4
* Näsström, Britt-Mari (1999). &quot;[https://books.google.com/books?id=TU_H79-CtucC&amp;pg=PA57 Freyja: The Trivalent Goddess]&quot;  in Sand, Reenberg Erik; Sørensen, Jørgen Podemann (1999). ''Comparative Studies in History of Religions: Their Aim, Scrope and Validity''. Museum Tusculanum Press. ISBN 87-7289-533-0
* North, Richard (1997). ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=X_LKUIqNvPQC Heathen Gods in Old English Literature]''. [[Cambridge University Press]]. ISBN 0-521-55183-8
* Orchard, Andy (1997). ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=5hbPHQAACAAJ Dictionary of Norse Myth and Legend]''. [[Orion Publishing Group|Cassell]]. ISBN 0-304-34520-2
* [[Rudolf Simek|Simek, Rudolf]] (2007) translated by Angela Hall. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=Zni8GwAACAAJ Dictionary of Northern Mythology]''. [[Boydell &amp; Brewer|D.S. Brewer]] ISBN 0-85991-513-1
* Wessén, Elias; Sven B.F. Jansson (1953–58). ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=SJ0eOgAACAAJ Sveriges runinskrifter: IX. Upplands runinskrifter del 4.]'' Stockholm: Kungl. Vitterhets Historie och Antikvitets Akademien. {{ISSN|0562-8016}} {{Sv icon}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Valkyries}}
*{{Cite EB1911 |last=Chadwick |first=Hector Munro |authorlink=Hector Munro Chadwick |wstitle=Valkyries |short=x}}

{{Valkyries}}
{{Norse mythology}}
{{Anglo-SaxonPaganism}}

{{good article}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Valkyries| ]]
[[Category:Female legendary creatures]]
[[Category:Textiles in mythology and folklore]]</text>
      <sha1>531o3qtw2ninakbqpeci51hlr9j3gs6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
