<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.28.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2600" case="first-letter">Topic</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>I Corps (United States)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>223102</id>
    <revision>
      <id>740439231</id>
      <parentid>737030162</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-21T02:32:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>McChizzle</username>
        <id>14623160</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Organization */ Added SSI</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="46912">{{About|the current U.S. Army formation|the Union Army formation in the Civil War|I Corps (Union Army)|other formations with similar names|I Corps (disambiguation)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2011}}
{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name=I Corps
|image=[[File:USICorpsSSI.svg|200px|alt=A black circle outline with a smaller, filled in black circle inside it.]]
|caption=Shoulder sleeve insignia of I Corps
|dates=1918–present
|country={{flagicon|USA}} [[United States]]
|allegiance=
|branch={{army|United States}}
|type=[[Corps]]
|role=
|size=
|command_structure=[[United States Army Forces Command]]
|current_commander=Lt. Gen. [[Stephen R. Lanza]]
|garrison=[[Joint Base Lewis-McChord]] (Forward at [[Camp Zama]], Japan)
|ceremonial_chief=
|nickname=&quot;Eye Corps&quot;
|patron=
|motto=''America's Corps''&lt;ref name=&quot;TIOH&quot;/&gt;
|colors=
|march=
|mascot=
| website        = [https://www.army.mil/icorps/?from=wiki Official Website]
|battles=World War I&lt;br/&gt;World War II&lt;br/&gt;[[Korean War]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Iraq War]]
|notable_commanders=
|anniversaries=
|identification_symbol=[[File:ICorpsCSIB.jpg|150px]]
|identification_symbol_label=[[Combat service identification badge]]
|identification_symbol_2=[[File:USICorpsDUI.PNG|150px|A gold device containing a gold letter I superimposed over an erupting volcano, with the words &quot;America's Corps&quot; at the bottom]]
|identification_symbol_2_label= [[Distinctive unit insignia]]
}}
{{US Corps
|previous=
|next=[[II Corps (United States)|II Corps]]
}}
'''I Corps''' &quot;America's Corps&quot; is a [[corps]] of the [[United States Army]] headquartered in [[Joint Base Lewis-McChord]], [[Washington (U.S. state)|Washington]]. It is a major [[formation (military)|formation]] of [[United States Army Forces Command]].

I Corps' current mission is part of the United States' [[Asia-Pacific]] Shift. The [[Pacific Rim]] Rebalance will involve several combined and joint military exercises in [[Japan]], [[Korea]], [[Thailand]], [[Philippines]], and [[Australia]]. Part of I Corps' objectives for these exercises will be Joint [[Task Force]] certification in support of [[United States Pacific Command]] missions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Public Affairs|first=I Corps|title=I Corps to re-focus on Asia-Pacific|url=http://www.nwguardian.com/2012/11/15/14337/i-corps-to-re-focus-on-asia-pacific.html|accessdate=30 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Activated in [[World War I]] in [[France]], I Corps oversaw US Army divisions as they repelled several major German offensives and led them into Germany. The corps was deactivated following the end of the war.

Reactivated for service in [[World War II]], the corps took command of divisions in the south Pacific, leading US and Australian forces as they pushed the [[Empire of Japan|Japanese]] army out of [[New Guinea]]. It went on to be one of the principal leading elements in the [[Battle of Luzon]], liberating the [[Philippines]]. It then took charge as one of the commanding headquarters in the occupation of Japan.

Deployed to Korea at the start of the [[Korean War]], the corps was one of three corps that remained in the country for the entire conflict, commanding US, British, and South Korean forces through three years of back-and-forth campaigns against North Korean and Chinese forces. Following the end of the war, it remained in Korea for almost 20 years guarding the [[Korean Demilitarized Zone]]. Active today, the corps acts as a subordinate headquarters of United States Army Forces Command, and has also seen deployments in support of [[Operation Iraqi Freedom]] and [[Operation Enduring Freedom]].

==History==

===World War I===
Following the American declaration of war on Germany, on 6 April 1917, I Corps was organized and activated on 15–20 January 1918, in the [[National Army (USA)|National Army]] in [[Neufchâteau, Vosges|Neufchâteau]], France, the first of several corps-sized formations intended to command [[division (military)|divisions]] of the [[American Expeditionary Force]] in Europe during World War I.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lineage&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.history.army.mil/html/forcestruc/lineages/branches/army/001cp.htm |title=Lineage and Honors Information: I Corps|publisher=[[United States Army Center of Military History]] |accessdate=19 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Assisted by the [[French XXXII Corps]], the headquarters was organized and trained; on 20 January, Major General [[Hunter Liggett]] took command.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistWWI&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lewis-mcchord.army.mil/icorps/icorps-history.html |title=I Corps History: World War I |publisher=I Corps Public Affairs Office |accessdate=19 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:FlagCorps.PNG|alt=A blue and white flag with gold trim, with the division insignia on it.|thumb|Organizational flag]]
In February, the corps consisted of the [[U.S. 1st Infantry Division|1st]], [[U.S. 2d Infantry Division|2nd]], [[26th Infantry Division (United States)|26th]], [[U.S. 32d Infantry Division|32nd]], [[41st Infantry Division (United States)|41st]], and [[U.S. 42d Infantry Division|42nd]] Infantry Divisions. From February to July, 1918, the [[German Army (German Empire)|German Army]] launched four major [[Offensive (military)|offensive]]s, attempting to secure victory before the full American forces could be mobilized. The final offensive, started in July 1918, was an attempt to cross the [[Marne]], in the area of [[Château-Thierry]], but I Corps and other formations on the American lines held, and the attack was rebuffed.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistWWI&quot;/&gt;

With the defeat of these German drives, I Corps conducted its first offensive mission, participating in the [[Second Battle of the Marne]] from 18 July until 6 August, which resulted in the reduction of the more important salients driven into Allied lines by the German offensives.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistWWI&quot;/&gt; After a brief period in the defensive sectors of [[Champagne, France|Champagne]] and [[Lorraine (region)|Lorraine]] between 7 August and 11 September, the corps took part in the [[Battle of Saint-Mihiel|St. Mihiel attack]] on 12 September, which reduced the German [[Salients, re-entrants and pockets|salient]] there during the next four days. Then followed another period on the defense in Lorraine as preparations advanced for what was to be the final Allied offensive of the war. On 26 September, I Corps troops began the attack northward that opened the [[Meuse-Argonne Offensive]]. From that day until 11 November 1918 when the war ended, I Corps was constantly moving forward.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistWWI&quot;/&gt;

The I Corps [[shoulder sleeve insignia]] was first worn by members of I Corps after approval from the AEF on 3 December 1918, but it was not officially approved until 1922.&lt;ref name=&quot;TIOH&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tioh.hqda.pentagon.mil/Heraldry/ArmyDUISSICOA/ArmyHeraldryUnit.aspx?u=3243 |title=I Corps |publisher=The Institute of Heraldry |accessdate=6 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; I Corps continued to train in France, until it was demobilized on 25 March 1919.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lineage&quot;/&gt;

During its time in World War I, I Corps commanded the [[1st Infantry Division (United States)|1st]], [[U.S. 2nd Infantry Division|2nd]], [[U.S. 3rd Infantry Division|3rd]], [[4th Infantry Division (United States)|4th]], [[5th Infantry Division (United States)|5th]], [[6th Infantry Division (United States)|6th]], [[26th Infantry Division (United States)|26th]], [[28th Infantry Division (United States)|28th]], [[32nd Infantry Division (United States)|32nd]], [[35th Infantry Division (United States)|35th]], [[36th Infantry Division (United States)|36th]], [[41st Infantry Division (United States)|41st]], [[43rd Infantry Division (United States)|43rd]], [[77th Infantry Division (United States)|77th]], [[78th Infantry Division (United States)|78th]], [[80th Division (United States)|80th]], [[U.S. 82nd Infantry Division|82nd]], [[90th Infantry Division (United States)|90th]], [[91st Infantry Division (United States)|91st]], [[92nd Infantry Division (United States)|92nd]] Infantry Divisions at one point or another.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistWWI&quot;/&gt; Also assigned to the corps were the French 62nd, 167th and 5th Cavalry Divisions.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistWWI&quot;/&gt;

===World War II===
On 15 August 1927, [[XX Corps (United States)|XX Corps]] was reconstituted in the Regular Army. Two months later, on 13 October 1927, the XX Corps was redesignated as I Corps.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lineage&quot;/&gt; However, the corps headquarters remained inactive during peacetime, until the US Army's buildup following the outbreak of War in Europe. On 1 November 1940, I Corps was reactivated at [[Columbia, South Carolina]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Lineage&quot;/&gt; For the next nine months, the corps supervised training and large scale divisional maneuvers.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistWWII&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lewis.army.mil/corps-history-ww2.asp |title=I Corps History: World War II |publisher=I Corps Public Affairs Office |accessdate=18 June 2009 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060710092000/http://www.lewis.army.mil/corps-history-ww2.asp |archivedate=10 July 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== New Guinea Campaign ====
On 6 July 1942 [[Lieutenant General]] [[Robert L. Eichelberger]] took command of the corps which he would lead through the majority of its service in the war. In the summer of 1942 the corps was ordered to Australia, closing into the area at [[Rockhampton, Queensland|Rockhampton]] on 17 October 1942.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistWWII&quot;/&gt; This move was to be part of a larger overall offensive in the south Pacific region.&lt;ref&gt;Horner, p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt; The corps at this time comprised the 41st and 32nd Divisions, engaged in the defense of [[British New Guinea]], the beginning of the [[New Guinea campaign]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Pimlott128&quot;&gt;Pimlott, p. 128.&lt;/ref&gt; Though the Japanese advanced rapidly at first, a number of factors slowed their progress against the Allied forces. Stubborn resistance from two Australian brigades bought time for I Corps reinforcements to arrive while the terrain proved more difficult than the Japanese had anticipated.&lt;ref&gt;Marston, p. 126.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wilmott, p. 108.&lt;/ref&gt; Supplies, which were already insufficient for the Japanese forces, were shortened even more as Japan's high command diverted them to the [[Guadalcanal]] campaign.&lt;ref&gt;Willmott, p. 111.&lt;/ref&gt; The Japanese attack stalled, and once the threat of a Japanese invasion of Australia was abated, I Corps launched an offensive to push back the Japanese.&lt;ref&gt;Horner, p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Marston, p. 127.&lt;/ref&gt; With the 32nd Division and the [[163rd Infantry Regiment (United States)|163rd Infantry Regiment]] of the 41st Division, the offensive was launched across the [[Owen Stanley Mountains]] of New Guinea.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pimlott128&quot;/&gt; This force, later augmented by the [[Australian 7th Division]], fought the [[Battle of Buna-Gona]], slowly advancing north against a tenacious enemy under harsh weather and terrain conditions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pimlott128&quot;/&gt; Overstretched Japanese forces, low on supplies, were eventually overcome by US and Australian forces.&lt;ref&gt;Horner, p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt; Despite being surrounded, trapped, and outnumbered, the Japanese forces continued to fight until they were completely wiped out by Allied forces.&lt;ref&gt;Willmott, p. 110.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Buna, Papua New Guinea|Buna]], on the north coast of the island, fell on 22 January 1943. The campaign was the first major Allied victory against the Japanese Army, and I Corps received the [[Presidential Unit Citation (United States)|Presidential Unit Citation]]. This victory marked the turn of the tide in the ground war against Japan.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistWWII&quot;/&gt;

[[File:USNHC-Photo SC 264436 Hollandia.jpg|thumb|250px|left|[[Landing Vehicle Tracked|LVTs]] head for the invasion beaches at [[Yos Sudarso Bay|Humboldt Bay]], Netherlands New Guinea, during the [[Operations Reckless and Persecution|Hollandia landing]] in the campaign|alt=A harbor with a number of amphibious ships racing from battleships out to sea to the shore]]
After this campaign I Corps returned to Rockhampton, where it was engaged in the training of the Allied forces beginning to arrive in that area for the coming campaigns. From February 1943 until March 1944 I Corps prepared for its next assignment, [[Operation Cartwheel]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Pimlott128&quot;/&gt;  That mission was the capture of [[Jayapura|Hollandia]] on the north coast of Dutch New Guinea; the units allocated to the corps for this task were the [[24th Infantry Division (United States)|24th]] and 41st Infantry Divisions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pimlott129&quot;&gt;Pimlott, p. 129.&lt;/ref&gt; The Task Force established itself ashore after a successful amphibious assault on 19 April 1944. It then began an offensive in that area to remove Japanese forces, before establishing air bases there.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistWWII&quot;/&gt;  The battle was a vicious one; the jungles and swamps made difficult fighting ground, and it was not until 6 June that the area was secured.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pimlott128&quot;/&gt;  The entire [[Japanese 18th Army]] was cut off from its bases by the force. Following this campaign the corps directed the seizure of the island of [[Biak]], which was secured by 24 June, to complete the advances necessary for the subsequent invasion of the [[Philippine Islands]]. On 20 August Major General [[Innis P. Swift]] succeeded General Eichelberger as commander of the corps.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pimlott129&quot;/&gt;

==== Luzon ====
The corps was assigned to the [[Sixth United States Army]] in preparation for the [[Battle of Luzon|offensive in the Philippines]] from the assets of the Philippine Commonwealth Army, Philippine Constabulary and the recognized guerrilla units. On 9 January 1945, I Corps successfully landed on the coast of the [[Lingayen Gulf]] in Northern [[Luzon]] with the mission of establishing a base for future operations to the north and of denying the enemy northern access to the [[South China Sea]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Pimlott206&quot;&gt;Pimlott, p. 206.&lt;/ref&gt; As a part of the Sixth Army with an overall force of 175,000 men, the American forces faced over 260,000 Japanese in Luzon.&lt;ref name=&quot;Horner60&quot;&gt;Horner, p. 60.&lt;/ref&gt; In a sustained drive of thirty-four days which covered over 100 miles, I Corps crossed central Luzon and thus separated the Japanese forces in the north from those in southern Luzon, destroying Japanese armored units along the way.&lt;ref&gt;Pimlott, p. 207.&lt;/ref&gt; Additional landings at [[Samar]] and [[Palawan]] were conducted in February, reducing the pressure on the forces of I Corps.&lt;ref&gt;Willmott, p. 181.&lt;/ref&gt; Following this accomplishment, the corps turned northward and began the systematic reduction of the enemy positions on the approach to the [[Cagayan Valley]]. The breakthrough into the valley was followed by a swift exploitation that took the corps to the north coast. This advance covered two hundred miles in little over 100 days; eliminating effective enemy resistance in northern Luzon.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistWWII&quot;/&gt; [[Manila]] was recaptured by the Allies after heavy fighting that ravaged the city.&lt;ref&gt;Willmott, p. 182.&lt;/ref&gt; The intense fighting that ensued cost 8,000 killed and 30,000 wounded in the Sixth Army, compared to 190,000 dead for Japan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Horner60&quot;/&gt; As the Sixth Army finished off the Japanese on Luzon, the [[Eighth United States Army]] in the south sent units all throughout the Philippines to eliminate remaining Japanese resistance on the islands.&lt;ref name=&quot;Horner60&quot;/&gt; The [[Tenth United States Army]] in the north commenced securing [[Okinawa]] and [[Iwo Jima]].&lt;ref&gt;Horner, p. 61.&lt;/ref&gt; With the defeat of the Japanese at each of these places, the US forces had locations from which to launch attacks into mainland Japan.&lt;ref&gt;Willmott, p. 183.&lt;/ref&gt;

Allied forces then began preparing for the invasion of mainland Japan, [[Operation Downfall]]. I Corps was assigned as one of four Corps under the command of the Sixth Army, with a strength of 14 divisions.&lt;ref&gt;Marston, p. 229.&lt;/ref&gt; I Corps was to lead the assault on [[Miyazaki Prefecture|Miyazaki]], in southern [[Kyūshū]], with the 25th, 33rd, and 41st Infantry Divisions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mars230&quot;&gt;Marston, p. 230.&lt;/ref&gt; Opposing them would be the Japanese 57th Army, with the 154th, 156th, and 212th Japanese Infantry Divisions. Before the assault could be launched, Japan surrendered, following the use of [[Atomic bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki|nuclear weapons on Hiroshima and Nagasaki]].&lt;ref&gt;Marston, p. 236.&lt;/ref&gt;

During World War II, the [[6th Infantry Division (United States)|6th]], [[8th Infantry Division (United States)|8th]], [[9th Infantry Division (United States)|9th]], [[24th Infantry Division (United States)|24th]], [[25th Infantry Division (United States)|25th]], [[30th Infantry Division (United States)|30th]] (during training in U.S. only?), [[32nd Infantry Division (United States)|32nd]], [[33rd Infantry Division (United States)|33rd]], [[37th Infantry Division (United States)|37th]], [[41st Infantry Division (United States)|41st]], [[43rd Infantry Division (United States)|43rd]], [[77th Infantry Division (United States)|77th]] and [[98th Infantry Division (United States)|98th Infantry Division]]s were assigned to I Corps at one time or another, along with the [[2nd Marine Division (United States)|2nd Marine Division]], [[7th Division (Australia)|7th Australian Division]], and elements of the [[11th Airborne Division]].&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistWWII&quot;/&gt;

==== Occupation of Japan ====
[[File:Sto1001.jpg|thumb|Occupation forces in Tokyo, 1946.|alt=A large Japanese city with American soldiers patrolling the streets]]
After the end of hostilities, I Corps was assigned to [[Occupied Japan|occupation]] duty in Japan. On 19 September 1945 the corps, with the assigned 33rd Infantry Division, sailed from Lingayen Gulf for Japan, landing on the island of [[Honshū]] on 25 September, three weeks after Japan's formal surrender.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistoc&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lewis.army.mil/corps-history-occupation.asp |title=I Corps History: Occupation |publisher=I Corps Public Affairs Office |accessdate=18 June 2009 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20051112163440/http://www.lewis.army.mil/corps-history-occupation.asp |archivedate=12 November 2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The next few years were a period during which the terms of the surrender were supervised and enforced; Japanese military installations and material were seized, troops were disarmed and discharged, and weapons of warfare disposed of. The duties of the occupation force included conversion of industry, repatriation of foreign nationals, and supervision of the complex features of all phases of Japanese government, economics, education, and industry.&lt;ref&gt;Marston, p. 237.&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1948, as the purely occupational mission was accomplished, troops of the corps focused more military training and field exercises designed to prepare them for combat. Its force was eventually downsized to the [[24th Infantry Division (United States)|24th Infantry Division]] on Kyūshū and [[25th Infantry Division (United States)|25th Infantry Division]] on mid-Honshū. The US Army continued a slow and steady process of post-war drawdown and demobilization on its own, and on 28 March 1950, the corps was formally inactivated in Japan, and its command consolidated with other units.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistoc&quot;/&gt;

===Korean War===
Only a few months later, the [[Korean War]] began, and units from Japan began streaming into [[South Korea]]. The [[Eighth United States Army]], taking charge of the conflict, requested the activation of three corps headquarters for its growing command of U.N. forces. I Corps was reactivated at [[Fort Bragg, North Carolina]], on 2 August 1950.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lineage&quot;/&gt;

==== Pusan Perimeter ====
[[File:Naktong Defense.jpg|thumb|defense of the Pusan Perimeter|alt=A map of a perimeter on the southeastern tip of a land mass]]
Advance elements of the headquarters took their place in the [[Pusan perimeter]] on 27 August. The headquarters, designated &quot;Task Force Jackson&quot;, assumed control of the [[I Corps (South Korea)|South Korean I Corps]], the [[21st Infantry Regiment (United States)|21st Regimental Combat Team]], and the 3rd Battalion Combat Team of the [[9th Infantry Regiment]]. On 12 September, under command of Lieutenant General [[Frank W. Milburn]], the corps became operational.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistorykorea&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lewis.army.mil/corps-history-korean.asp |title=I Corps History: Korea |publisher=I Corps Public Affairs Office |accessdate=18 June 2009 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060710092045/http://www.lewis.army.mil/corps-history-korean.asp |archivedate=10 July 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It took command of the [[1st Cavalry Division (United States)|1st Cavalry Division]], 24th Infantry Division, and [[1st Infantry Division (South Korea)|South Korean 1st Infantry Division]], along with the [[27th British Commonwealth Brigade]], defending the [[Naktong River]] area against attacking North Korean units.&lt;ref&gt;Varhola, p. 86.&lt;/ref&gt;

Amphibious [[Battle of Inchon|landings at Inchon]] by [[X Corps (United States)|X Corps]] hit North Korean forces from behind, allowing I Corps and [[IX Corps (United States)|IX Corps]] to break out of Pusan. Four days later I Corps troops pushed northward against crumbling enemy opposition to establish contact with forces of the [[7th Infantry Division (United States)|7th Infantry Division]] driving southward from the beachhead. Major elements of the North Korean Army were destroyed and cut off in this aggressive penetration; the link-up was effected south of [[Suwon]] on 26 September.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistorykorea&quot;/&gt; The offensive was continued northwards, past [[Seoul]], and across the [[38th parallel north|38th Parallel]] on 1 October. The momentum of the attack was maintained, and the race to the North Korean capitol, [[Pyongyang]], ended on 19 October when elements of the [[1st Infantry Division (South Korea)|South Korean 1st Infantry Division]] and U.S. [[1st Cavalry Division (United States)|1st Cavalry Division]] both entered the city. The advance continued, but against unexpectedly stiffening enemy resistance. On 25 October the first Chinese prisoners on the Eighth Army front were taken by I Corps troops. By the end of October the city of [[Chongju, North Korea|Chongju]], forty miles from the [[Yalu River]] border of North Korea, had been captured.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistorykorea&quot;/&gt;

==== Chinese Intervention ====
On 27 November, China entered the war on the side of North Korea against the UN. Massed Chinese attacks were immediately launched against troops of the corps. The Eighth Army suffered heavy casualties, ordering a complete withdraw to the [[Imjin River]], south of the 38th parallel, having been devastated by the overwhelming Chinese force.&lt;ref name=&quot;Var14&quot;&gt;Varhola, p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt; In the wake of the retreat, the disorganized Eighth Army regrouped and re-formed. I Corps relinquished command of the 1st Cavalry Division, the 24th Infantry Division, and the 27th British Brigade, taking command of the 3rd Infantry Division and the 25th Infantry Division in their place.&lt;ref name=&quot;Var87&quot;&gt;Varhola, p. 87.&lt;/ref&gt; On 1 January 1951, 500,000 Chinese troops attacked the Eighth Army's line at the Imjin River, forcing them back 50 miles and allowing the Chinese to capture Seoul.&lt;ref name=&quot;Var14&quot;/&gt; The Chinese eventually advanced too far for their supply lines to adequately support them, and their attack stalled. The Eighth Army, battered by the Chinese assault, began to prepare spring offensives to retake lost ground.&lt;ref&gt;Varhola, p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the establishment of defenses south of the capital city, General [[Matthew B. Ridgway]] ordered I, IX, and X Corps to conduct a general counteroffensive against the Chinese forces, Operation Thunderbolt.&lt;ref name=&quot;Var19&quot;&gt;Varhola, p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt; Between February and March, the corps participated in [[Operation Killer]], pushing Chinese forces north of the [[Han River (Korea)|Han River]].&lt;ref&gt;Varhola, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; This operation was quickly followed up with [[Operation Ripper]], which retook Seoul in March.&lt;ref&gt;Varhola, p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt; After this, [[Operation Courageous#Operations Rugged and Dauntless|Operations Rugged and Dauntless]] in April saw Eighth Army forces advance north of the 38th parallel and reestablish themselves along the Kansas Line and Utah Line, respectively.&lt;ref name=&quot;Var19&quot;/&gt;

As I Corps troops approached the [[Iron Triangle (Korea)|Iron Triangle]] formed by the cities of [[Chorwon]], [[Kumhwa]], and [[Pyongyang]], Chinese resistance increased.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistorykorea&quot;/&gt; By that time, the 1st South Korean Infantry Division was relieved from the corps and assigned to one of the Korean corps. The 1st Cavalry Division was returned to the corps in its place.&lt;ref name=&quot;Var87&quot;/&gt;

In late April, the Chinese launched a major counterattack.&lt;ref&gt;Malkasian, p. 41.&lt;/ref&gt; Though the 24th and 25th Infantry Divisions were able to hold their ground against the Chinese 9th Chinese People's Volunteers (CPV) Army Corps, the [[6th Infantry Division (South Korea)|South Korean 6th Infantry Division]], to the east, was destroyed by the 13th CPV Army Corps, which penetrated the line and threatened to encircle the American divisions.&lt;ref&gt;Catchpole, p. 120.&lt;/ref&gt; The 1st Marine Division and [[27th British Commonwealth Brigade]] were able to drive the 13th Army Corps back while the 24th and 25th Divisions withdrew on 25 April.&lt;ref name=&quot;Malk42&quot;/&gt; The line was pushed back to Seoul but managed to hold.&lt;ref name=&quot;Malk42&quot;&gt;Malkasian, p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Stalemate ====
[[File:M39-AUV-Korea-19521001.jpg|thumb|South Korean soldiers reinforce defenses along Old Baldy Hill|alt=A group of Korean soldiers building fortifications out of wood]]
In September, the UN Forces launched another counteroffensive with the 24th Infantry Division at the center of the line, west of the [[Hwachon Reservoir]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Malk50&quot;&gt;Malkasian, p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt; Flanked by the South Korean 2nd and 6th Divisions, the 24th advanced past Kumwha, engaging the 20th and 27th CPV Armies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Malk50&quot;/&gt; In November, the Chinese attempted to counter this attack, but were unsuccessful. It was at this point, after several successive counteroffensives that saw both sides fighting intensely over the same ground, that the two sides started serious peace negotiations.&lt;ref&gt;Malkasian, p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt; In late 1951, the 1st Cavalry Division, depleted after having suffered 16,000 casualties so far in the conflict, was relegated to the Far East reserve to rebuild. It was replaced by the [[45th Infantry Division (United States)|45th Infantry Division]] of the [[Oklahoma Army National Guard]], which was newly arrived in the theater.&lt;ref name=&quot;Var87&quot;/&gt;

In March 1952, the corps grew in size as the 25th Infantry Division was relieved from its command and it gained command of [[1st British Commonwealth Division]] and the South Korean 1st Division, [[8th Infantry Division (South Korea)|8th Division]], and [[9th Infantry Division (South Korea)|9th Divisions]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Var87&quot;/&gt; In June 1952, a ten-day attack against 45th Infantry Division outposts was repulsed.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistorykorea&quot;/&gt; September 1952 began with renewed enemy attacks against the outposts that protected the main line. Enemy attacks up to regimental size against garrisons of platoon and company strength were turned back by Corps troops. Outposts at Bunker Hill, [[Battle of the Hook|The Hook]], Kelly, [[Old Baldy Hill]], Nori, and [[Battle of Pork Chop Hill|Pork Chop Hill]] were defended in heavy fighting within I Corps' area of responsibility. All along the front, the enemy was driven back with thousands of casualties.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistorykorea&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Bruce C Clarke.jpg|thumb|left|150px|Lieutenant General Bruce Clarke, last commander of I Corps of the Korean War|alt=An aged Caucasian man in military uniform, with a large number of ribbons and medals]]
In January 1953, the corps underwent its last major reorganization of the war, losing command of the US 3rd, 24th, and 45th Infantry Divisions, the South Korean 8th and 9th Infantry Divisions, and the British 1st Commonwealth Division, while taking command of the US 2nd, 7th, and 25th Infantry Divisions and the [[1st Marine Division (United States)|1st Marine Division]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Var87&quot;/&gt; On 23 January 1953, the first major action of the year was initiated with a raid by aggressive infantrymen of the South Korean 1st Infantry Division against the enemy's Big Nori positions. The next months saw many such raids which harassed the enemy, captured prisoners, and destroyed defensive works. Beginning in March, the Communists continually attacked the corps outposts. In that month, troops on Old Baldy were withdrawn, on orders from I Corps, after suffering heavy casualties from the Chinese. On 10 April 1953 Lieutenant General [[Bruce C. Clarke]], who was to see the corps through the remainder of its combat, assumed command.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistorykorea&quot;/&gt;

The fighting on the outposts continued; the 7th Infantry Division stopped wave after wave of troops that the Chinese threw against Pork Chop Hill. Troops of the [[Turkish Brigade]], attached to the 25th Infantry Division, defended Outposts Berlin, Vegas, Carson, and Elko in fierce hand-to-hand combat. They were ordered to evacuate all but the Berlin position at the end of May. The [[1st British Commonwealth Division]] ejected the Chinese after their assault on the Hook. The 1st ROK Division troops were ordered off the positions on Queen, Bak, and Hill 179 when heavy enemy assaults divested them of their tactical value. The closing days of the fighting saw the 7th Infantry Division withdrawn from Pork Chop and the 1st Marine Division ordered to evacuate the Berlin positions for the same reason.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistorykorea&quot;/&gt;

=== Cold War ===
[[File:Korean dmz map.png|thumb|The Korean DMZ along the 38th parallel|alt=A defensive line in the middle of a landmass]]
After the 1953 armistice, the defense of the [[Korean Demilitarized Zone]] was handled by the South Korean and American armies. The eastern half of the border was handled by the South Korean Army while I Corps took charge in the west. For the next 18 years, the corps oversaw US forces on the DMZ, seeing only occasional incidents with the North Korean army.&lt;ref name=&quot;Var87&quot;/&gt; In 1971, under Nixon's détente policy, the 7th Infantry Division was withdrawn, leaving the 2nd Infantry Division as the only US Army unit in Korea. I Corps remained in Korea as a two-division formation until 1972 when it was reduced to zero strength and was replaced in 1982 by the Third Republic of Korea Army (TROKA).&lt;ref name=&quot;Var87&quot;/&gt;

In 1980, [[Fort Lewis, Washington]] was notified of a major change of structure. A corps headquarters was to be activated in March 1982. I Corps was formally activated on 1 October 1981, much earlier than expected.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lineage&quot;/&gt; On 1 August 1983, the corps expanded its operational control of active Army units outside Fort Lewis, to include the [[7th Infantry Division (United States)|7th Infantry Division]] at [[Fort Ord, California]], and the [[172nd Infantry Brigade (United States)|172nd Infantry Brigade]] in [[Alaska]], which then became part of the [[6th Infantry Division (United States)|6th Infantry Division]].&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistpres&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lewis.army.mil/corps-history-present.asp |title=I Corps History: 1980 – present |publisher=I Corps Public Affairs Office |accessdate=18 June 2009}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1988, the [[distinctive unit insignia]] was approved for the corps. This was the fourth design held by the corps, with previous versions being approved then retracted in 1942, 1970, and 1982.&lt;ref name=&quot;TIOH&quot;/&gt;

=== Gulf War ===
Following the end of the Cold War in 1989, the US government conducted careful restructuring of national priorities and of the defense establishment. Fort Lewis, ideally located to act as a base for mobilization and power projection into the Pacific region, was one of few military bases that did not downsize with the US military overall. Thus, while most of the Army was downsizing, Fort Lewis began to grow, however, several tenant units such as the [[9th Infantry Division (United States)|9th Infantry Division]] were downsized.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistpres&quot;/&gt;

The 3rd Brigade, 9th Infantry Division became the [[199th Infantry Brigade]], attached to I Corps, remaining under I Corps until its redesignation as the [[2nd Armored Cavalry Regiment]], and its departure for [[Fort Polk, Louisiana]] in 1993.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistpres&quot;/&gt;

Also in 1990, the U.S. intervened in the Middle East with [[Operation Desert Storm]]. During that intervention, Fort Lewis deployed 34 active and 25 reserve component units to Saudi Arabia. I Corps also contributed to the command structure, with the I Corps Commander, LTG [[Calvin A. H. Waller]] and the Deputy I Corps Commander, MG [[Paul R. Schwartz]], assisting General [[H. Norman Schwarzkopf]], the Commander of the American Forces. I Corps expanded its contingency missions and became a quick-response corps. For several months, I Corps was the nation's worldwide contingency corps, while the [[XVIII Airborne Corps]] was engaged in the [[Gulf War]]. This caused a good deal of activity on Fort Lewis, as the post restructured itself to support the corps' new mission, and to insure that it had a smooth, rapid departure in case they were needed anywhere in the world. This duty was returned to XVIII Airborne Corps upon its return to the United States. The corps then began to convert to a permanently structured, no-mobilization contingency corps and was placed under the operational control of the [[United States Army Forces Command]]. This entailed the addition of a number of active component corps units.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistpres&quot;/&gt;

In preparation for these new requirements, Fort Lewis began to receive new corps support units which were coming out of Europe. One of these was the 7th Engineer Brigade which was inactivated on 16 January 1992 and immediately reactivated as the [[555th Engineer Group]]. On 16 February 1992 the [[210th Field Artillery Brigade]], also from Europe, was activated. In 1997, the [[35th Air Defense Artillery Brigade]] moved to [[Fort Bliss, Texas]], to join other air defense brigades. The corps and Fort Lewis would see a reshuffling of units in and out of the area through 2000.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistpres&quot;/&gt; Plans were drawn up for emergency operations for I Corps should a major conflict emerge in the Pacific region. Plans exist for I Corps to rapidly deploy in defense of Japan or [[South Korea]].&lt;ref name=&quot;GSO&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/agency/army/i-corps.htm |title=GlobalSecurity.org: I Corps |work=[[Globalsecurity]] |accessdate=19 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== War on Terrorism ===
With the events of 11 September 2001, I Corps began providing support for Army units deploying in support of the [[War on Terrorism]]. Its assets were active in providing [[combat support]] and [[combat service support]] missions, including [[Operation Enduring Freedom]] in Afghanistan, [[Operation Iraqi Freedom]] in Iraq and the domestic [[Operation Noble Eagle]].&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistpres&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Army mil-34630-2009-04-07-130411.jpg|thumb|250px|I Corps uncases its colors in Iraq|alt=A group of soldiers unrolls a flag]]
On 4 February 2004, I Corps forward headquarters deployed to Iraq. The element, called Task Force Olympia, deployed to [[Mosul]], Iraq in January 2004, where it assumed its mission from the [[101st Airborne Division]] to form a headquarters to exercise command and control of all coalition and Iraqi forces in northern Iraq. It coordinated the efforts of both of the active [[Stryker Brigade Combat Team]]s, attached engineers, civil affairs, signal, and other supporting units as well as Iraqi security forces, eventually numbering more than 12,000. The Iraqi security forces included four Civil Defense Corps battalions, three Border Police battalions, several thousand members of the Iraq Facility Protection Security Forces and an Armed Forces battalion. After more than a year in Iraq, the corps forward headquarters handed over responsibility for northern Iraq to the soldiers of Task Force Freedom and [[11th Armored Cavalry Regiment]] in February 2005.&lt;ref name=&quot;corpshistpres&quot;/&gt;

In 2008, it was announced that I Corps was to deploy to Iraq in 2009, to replace XVIII Airborne Corps in support of Operation Iraqi Freedom. Soldiers of the corps trained for a year in preparation for the deployment, which began on 9 April 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;Iraq&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mnf-iraq.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=26022&amp;Itemid=128 |title=I Corps Soldiers relieve Fort Bragg troops (Baghdad) |publisher=Multi-national Force Iraq Public Affairs Office |accessdate=19 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; I Corps filled the role of [[Multi-National Corps - Iraq]] at [[Al-Faw Palace]]. In January 2010, [[Multi-National Corps - Iraq]] integrated with [[Multi-National Forces - Iraq]] (MNF-I) and [[Multi-National Security Transition Command – Iraq]] (MNSTC-I) to form [[United States Forces - Iraq]] (USF-I). Over its one-year deployment, the corps oversaw the responsible drawdown of major components of US Forces in Iraq.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.army.mil/-news/2009/04/17/19843-i-corps-deputy-commander-tasked-with-overseeing-drawdown-in-iraq/ |title=I Corps deputy commander tasked with overseeing drawdown in Iraq |publisher=United States Army |accessdate=19 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; I corps returned from Iraq in March 2010 following their RIP/TOA with III Corps.&lt;ref name=&quot;Redeploy&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thesubtimes.com/2010/03/11/i-corps-hq-returns-from-iraq-sunday/ |title=I Corps HQ returns from Iraq Sunday |publisher=The Suburban Times |accessdate=11 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Operation Enduring Freedom ===
I Corps headquarters deployed to Afghanistan to serve as the headquarters of the [[International Security Assistance Force]] Joint Command (IJC) for a period of one year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.army.mil/article/58846/I_Corps_ready_for_challenges_in_Afghanistan/ |title=I Corps ready for challenges in Afghanistan |publisher=The United States Army |work=Army.mil |date= |accessdate=1 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The commander of I Corps, LTG Scaparrotti, served concurrently as the commander of the International Security Assistance Force Joint Command and Deputy Commander, U.S. Forces – Afghanistan from July 11, 2011&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.isaf.nato.int/about-isaf/leadership/lieutenant-general-curtis-scaparrotti.html |title=Lieutenant General Curtis Scaparrotti &amp;#124; ISAF - International Security Assistance Force |publisher=Isaf.nato.int |date=2011-07-11 |accessdate=1 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; to July 11, 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dvidshub.net/image/600331/change-command-ceremony#.T--d4BdfG84 |title=DVIDS - Images - Change of command ceremony [Image 2 of 3&amp;#93; |publisher=Dvidshub.net |date= |accessdate=1 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Asia-Pacific Shift ===
I Corps shifted its mission to the [[Asia-Pacific]] region in mid-2012. I Corps Commander Lt. Gen. Robert Brown announced this [[Pacific Rim]] rebalance during his Change-of-Command Ceremony at [[Joint Base Lewis-McChord]]. In late 2011, President [[Barack Obama]] and Secretary of Defense [[Leon Panetta]] signaled the [[Asia-Pacific]] pivot and have made several trips to the region.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=I Corps Public Affairs Team|title=Panetta Aims to Fortify Alliances on Asia-Pacific Tour|url=http://www.defense.gov/News/NewsArticle.aspx?ID=118487|publisher=Armed Forces Press Services|accessdate=30 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Organization==
[[File:I Corps US Army.png|thumb|right|500px|I Corps structure]]

I Corps is unique among the active US Army corps in that it is composed of a mixture of active duty and [[US Army Reserve]] units in 47 of the 50 U.S. states, for a total of around 20,000 active duty and 20,000 army reserve forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;GSO&quot;/&gt;

[[File:US I Corps.png|30px]] '''I Corps''', [[Joint Base Lewis-McChord|Fort Lewis]], [[Washington (U.S. state)|Washington]]
* [[File:7th ID SSI.svg|25px]] [[7th Infantry Division (United States)|7th Infantry Division]]
** 1st [[Stryker]] Brigade Combat Team, [[2nd Infantry Division (United States)|2nd Infantry Division]]
** 2nd Stryker Brigade Combat Team, 2nd Infantry Division
** [[2nd Infantry Division Artillery (United States)|2nd Infantry Division Artillery]]
** [[16th Combat Aviation Brigade (United States)|16th Combat Aviation Brigade]]
** [[17th Field Artillery Brigade (United States)|17th Field Artillery Brigade]]
** [[555th Engineer Brigade (United States)|555th Engineer Brigade]]
** [[201st Battlefield Surveillance Brigade|201st Military Intelligence Brigade]]
*[[File:593rd Sustainment Brigade.jpg|25px]] [[593rd Expeditionary Sustainment Command]]
** [[42nd Military Police Brigade (United States)|42nd Military Police Brigade]]
** [[62nd Medical Brigade (United States)|62nd Medical Brigade]]

==Honors==
The I Corps was awarded seven [[campaign streamer]]s for service in World War I, three campaign streamers and two [[Awards and decorations of the United States military|unit decoration]]s in World War II, ten campaign streamers and one unit decoration in the Korean War, one unit award during Operation Iraqi Freedom, and one unit award in peacetime, for a total of 20 campaign streamers and five unit decorations in its operational history.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lineage&quot;/&gt;

===Unit decorations===

===Campaign streamers===

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;float:left;&quot;
|- style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot;
! Conflict
! Streamer
! Year(s)
|-
|| World War I
|| Champagne-Marne
|| 1917
|-
|| World War I
|| Aisne-Marne
|| 1917
|-
|| World War I
|| St. Mihiel
|| 1917
|-
|| World War I
|| Meuse-Argonne
|| 1917
|-
|| World War I
|| Ile de France
|| 1918
|-
|| World War I
|| Champagne
|| 1918
|-
|| World War I
|| Lorraine
|| 1918
|-
|| World War II
|| [[New Guinea|Papua]]
|| 1943
|-
|| World War II
|| [[New Guinea]]
|| 1944
|-
|| World War II
|| [[Luzon]]
|| 1945
|-
|| [[Korean War]]
|| UN Defensive
|| 1950
|-
|| [[Korean War]]
|| UN Offensive
|| 1950
|-
|| [[Korean War]]
|| CCF Intervention
|| 1950
|-
|| [[Korean War]]
|| First UN Counteroffensive
|| 1950
|-
|| [[Korean War]]
|| CCF Spring Offensive
|| 1951
|-
|| [[Korean War]]
|| UN Summer-Fall Offensive
|| 1951
|-
|| [[Korean War]]
|| Second Korean Winter
|| 1951–1952
|-
|| [[Korean War]]
|| Korea, Summer-Fall 1952
|| 1952
|-
|| [[Korean War]]
|| Third Korean Winter
|| 1952–1953
|-
|| [[Korean War]]
|| Korea, Summer 1953
|| 1953
|-
|| [[Iraq War]]
|| Iraqi Sovereignty
|| 2009 - 2010
|-
|| [[War in Afghanistan (2001–present)|Afghanistan War]]
|| Consolidation III
|| 2011 - 2012
|}
{{Clear}}

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;float:left;&quot;
|- style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot;
! Ribbon
! Award
! Year
! Notes
|-
||[[File:Presidential Unit Citation ribbon.svg|50px|alt=Dark blue ribbon with a gold border]]
||'''[[Presidential Unit Citation (US)|Presidential Unit Citation]] (Army)'''
||1942–1944
||for fighting in the [[New Guinea campaign]]
|-
||[[File:Philippines Presidential Unit Citation.png|50px|alt=Vertical tricolor ribbon (blue, white, red) with gold border]]
||'''[[Philippine Presidential Unit Citation]]'''
||1944–1945
||for service in the Philippines during World War II
|-
||[[File:Korean Presidential Unit Citation.png|50px|alt=White ribbon with vertical green and red stripes on its edges and a red and blue circle in the middle]]
||'''[[Republic of Korea Presidential Unit Citation]]'''
||1950–1953
||for service in Korea
|-
||[[File:Army Superior Unit Award ribbon.svg|50px|alt=A red ribbon with a vertical green stripe running down the center]]
||'''[[Superior Unit Award]]'''
||1999–2000
||
|-
||[[File:Meritorious Unit Commendation ribbon.svg|50px|alt=Red ribbon]]
||'''[[Meritorious Unit Commendation]]'''
|| 2009–2010
||for service in Iraq&lt;ref name=&quot;WOT&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.history.army.mil/html/forcestruc/wotawards.html |title=The War on Terror: Unit Award Orders &amp; Citations; Department of the Army Permanent Order 133-19|publisher=[[United States Army Center of Military History]] |accessdate=4 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
||[[File:Meritorious Unit Commendation ribbon.svg|50px|alt=Red ribbon]]
||'''[[Meritorious Unit Commendation]]'''
|| 2011–2012
||for service in Afghanistan&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Meritorious Unit Citation awarded to I Corps for service in Afghanistan|url=https://www.hrc.army.mil/site/assets/awards/2012/212-12.pdf|publisher=I Corps Public Affairs Office|accessdate=30 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
|}
{{Clear}}

==See also==
*[[Fort Lewis Museum]]
* [[List of commanders of I Corps (United States)|Complete list of commanders]]
* [[I Corps (Union Army)]]
* [[First Corps, Army of Northern Virginia|I Corps (Army of Northern Virginia, CSA)]]
* [[First Corps, Army of Tennessee|I Corps (Army of Tennessee, CSA)]]
* [[III Corps (United States)]]
* [[V Corps (United States)]]
* [[XVIII Airborne Corps (United States)]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==Sources==
*{{cite book|first=Brian |last=Catchpole |title=The Korean War |year=2001 |publisher=[[Robinson Publishing]] |isbn=978-1-84119-413-4}}
*{{cite book|first=David |last=Horner |authorlink=David Horner |title=The Second World War, Vol. 1: The Pacific  |year=2003 |publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]] |isbn=978-0-415-96845-4}}
*{{cite book|first=Carter |last=Malkasian |title=The Korean War |year=2001 |publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]] |isbn=978-1-84176-282-1}}
*{{cite book|first=Daniel |last=Marston |title=The Pacific War Companion: from Pearl Harbor to Hiroshima |year=2005 |publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]] |asin=B002ARY8KO}}
*{{cite book|first=John |last=Pimlott |title=The Historical Atlas of World War II  |year=1995 |publisher=[[Henry Holt and Company]] |isbn=978-0-8050-3929-0}}
*{{cite book|first=Michael J. |last=Varhola |title=Fire and Ice: The Korean War, 1950–1953 |publisher=[[Da Capo Press]] |year=2000 |isbn=978-1-882810-44-4}}
*{{cite book|first=H.P. |last=Willmott |title=The Second World War in the Far East  |year=2004 |publisher=Smithsonian Books |isbn=978-1-58834-192-1}}

==External links==
* [http://www.lewis-mcchord.army.mil/ICorps I Corps website]
* [http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/agency/army/i-corps.htm GlobalSecurity.org: I Corps]

{{Good article}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:001}}
[[Category:Corps of the United States Army|01]]
[[Category:Corps of the United States in World War II|01]]
[[Category:Military units and formations in Washington (state)]]
[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1918]]
[[Category:United States Army units and formations in the Korean War|USCorps0001]]
[[Category:1918 establishments in the United States]]
[[Category:Military units of the United States Army in South Korea]]
[[Category:Military units and formations of the United States in the Cold War]]</text>
      <sha1>b5w5a5tl88u9mgs751njdejxdrwezbz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
