<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.28.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2600" case="first-letter">Topic</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Milagro (The X-Files)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>17205519</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738774868</id>
      <parentid>707959289</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-11T00:24:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[User:Green Cardamom/WaybackMedic 2|WaybackMedic 2]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27024">{{Use mdy dates|date=November 2012}}
{{good article}}
{{DISPLAYTITLE:Milagro (''The X-Files'')}}
{{Infobox television episode 
| Title = Milagro
| Series = [[The X-Files]]

| Season = [[The X-Files (season 6)|6]]
| Episode = 18
| Image = [[Image:Milagro x files.jpg|250px|Milagro|alt=A man holds his beating heart.]]
| Caption = Phillip Padgett rips out his own beating heart. The sequence utilized a rubber heart. Later shots of beating hearts were created with air pumps.
| Airdate = April 18, 1999
| Production = 6ABX18&lt;ref name=&quot;DVD&quot;/&gt;
| Teleplay = [[Chris Carter (screenwriter)|Chris Carter]]
| Story = [[John Shiban]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Frank Spotnitz]]
| Director = [[Kim Manners]]
| Length = 45 minutes&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The X-Files, Season 6|url=http://itunes.apple.com/gb/tv-season/the-x-files-season-6/id283986520|work=[[iTunes Store]]|publisher=[[Apple Inc.|Apple]]|accessdate=August 28, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| Guests =
*[[John Hawkes (actor)|John Hawkes]] as Phillip Padgett
*[[Nestor Serrano]] as Ken Naciamento
*Angelo Vacco as Kevin
*[[Jillian Bach]] as Maggie&lt;ref name=&quot;plot&quot;&gt;[[#Meisler|Meisler (2000)]], pp. 224–235&lt;/ref&gt;
| Prev = [[Trevor (The X-Files)|Trevor]]
| Next = [[The Unnatural (The X-Files)|The Unnatural]]
| Episode list = [[List of The X-Files episodes|List of ''The X-Files'' episodes]]
}}
&quot;'''Milagro'''&quot; is the eighteenth episode of the [[The X-Files (season 6)|sixth season]] of the American [[science fiction on television|science fiction]] television series ''[[The X-Files]]''. It originally aired on the [[Fox Broadcasting Company|Fox]] network on April 18, 1999. The episode's teleplay was written by [[Chris Carter (screenwriter)|Chris Carter]] from a story by [[John Shiban]] and [[Frank Spotnitz]], and directed by [[Kim Manners]]. The episode is a &quot;[[List of Monster-of-the-Week characters in The X-Files|Monster-of-the-Week]]&quot; story, unconnected to the series' wider [[Mythology of The X-Files|mythology]]. &quot;Milagro&quot; earned a [[Nielsen rating|Nielsen household rating]] of 9, being watched by 15.2 million people upon its initial broadcast. The episode received mixed to positive reviews from television critics.

The show centers on [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]] special agents [[Fox Mulder]] ([[David Duchovny]]) and [[Dana Scully]] ([[Gillian Anderson]]) who work on cases linked to the paranormal, called [[X-File]]s. Mulder is a believer in the paranormal, while the skeptical Scully has been assigned to debunk his work. In this episode, Mulder and Scully investigate a series of murders in which the heart has been removed from the victims. A writer who lives next door to Mulder is writing a novel about the murders before they actually happen and soon, Scully finds herself confused and drawn to the writer, who has a romantic interest in her.

&quot;Milagro&quot; was inspired by the idea of someone thinking of something so much that it becomes a reality, a topic Shiban later noted was &quot;familiar&quot; to anyone who had written a script. The part of Phillip Padgett had been written specifically for the actor [[John Hawkes (actor)|John Hawkes]]. In addition, the production for &quot;Milagro&quot; was decidedly low-budget due to its &quot;intimate and personality-driven&quot; nature. The episode's title means &quot;miracle&quot; in [[Spanish language|Spanish]]. The episode has been analyzed for its use of symbolism, its exploration of motive, and the role reversal of Mulder and Scully.

==Plot==
[[List of Monster-of-the-Week characters in The X-Files|Phillip Padgett]] ([[John Hawkes (actor)|John Hawkes]]), a fledgling author, sits at a desk, suffering from [[writer's block]]. He eventually retires to the bathroom to discard a spent cigarette. Without warning or concern, the man suddenly reaches into his chest and removes a bloody [[heart]]. Later, he walks down metal stairs into a cluttered basement, and opens the door of an incinerator. Noticing a beating heart amidst the flames, and unfazed by the vision, he nonchalantly tosses in a paper bag.

Dana Scully ([[Gillian Anderson]]) later encounters the stranger as she walks into an elevator. Both ride in silence up to the fourth floor, with Scully somewhat unsettled by the experience. At [[Fox Mulder]]'s ([[David Duchovny]]) apartment, Mulder and Scully begin discussing a case the pair are working on, wherein the heart of the victim had been removed with the absence of any significant physical evidence. Mulder believes the heart was removed with a technique known as [[psychic surgery]]. Meanwhile, Padgett, who is Mulder's neighbor, stands on a chair with his ear to an air vent, listening to the conversation.

Later that night, two teenagers get into a fight in the woods. The girl, named Maggie ([[Jillian Bach]]), runs into the woods to be alone and Kevin (Angelo Vacco), her boyfriend, gives chase. However, he is attacked and his heart is removed. Meanwhile, the writer intensely transcribes the event on his typewriter. The next day, Mulder and Scully discuss this latest incident via phone. An unmarked envelope is discovered by Scully in the office containing a [[Milagro (votive)|milagro]], a type of pendant. While she examines the pendant, a voice-over from the writer describes Scully's most intimate feelings as she examines the unsolicited gift.

Scully later runs into the author at a [[Catholic church|church]]. He admits sending Scully the pendant and discusses with her the [[Sacred Heart of Jesus]]. She leaves, visibly shaken. Scully meets Mulder and relays her most recent encounter with the writer to Mulder. Later, Padgett woos Scully into his apartment with more character revelations. Mulder bursts in and arrests him based on accurate descriptions of the case murders in his novel, which he secretly read after discovering it in the mail. While Padgett is in custody, Maggie is murdered in the same fashion as Kevin. This establishes a ''de facto'' [[alibi]] for the author. Lacking concrete and connective evidence to the murders, and hoping Padgett might lead them to his partner in crime, Mulder releases Padgett from custody.

Back at his apartment, Padgett converses with the killer from his book, a deceased [[Brazil]]ian surgeon named [[List of Monster-of-the-Week characters in The X-Files|Ken Naciamento]] ([[Nestor Serrano]]). It is revealed that through some sort of psychic connection, Padgett's Naciamento has come back to life and has been removing hearts from victims. The two discuss motivations for the killings. Realizing that his novel prognosticates Scully's murder, Padgett heads to the incinerator to destroy his novel. Mulder intercepts him, thinking Padgett is instead simply destroying incriminatory evidence. Meanwhile, Naciamento accosts Scully. After hearing gunshots, Mulder runs toward his apartment and shockingly finds Scully on the ground, covered in blood but alive. The episode closes with a voice over from the author, explaining his final actions. The stranger lies stricken on the basement floor in front of the incinerator, his beating heart in hand, having &quot;... given what he could not receive&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;plot&quot;/&gt;

==Production==

===Writing and casting===
[[File:JohnHawkesHS2009.jpg|thumb|right|175px|The part of author Phillip Padgett was written for John Hawkes, who was chosen for his &quot;dignity and simplicity&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;m236&quot;/&gt;|alt=A man in a black shirt with a mustache looks into the camera.]]
The idea behind the episode occurred during a conversation between [[John Shiban]] and [[Frank Spotnitz]]. The two were discussing about the particular stress of their jobs. The episode's theme of someone thinking of something so much that it becomes real was &quot;familiar&quot; to anyone who had written a script, Shiban later explained.&lt;ref name=&quot;m235&quot;/&gt; Shiban and Spotnitz created a rough draft for the episode and then sent it to series creator [[Chris Carter (screenwriter)|Chris Carter]], who was busy shooting the pilot for the new television series ''[[Harsh Realm]]''. Carter re-wrote portions of the script, including the ending, to show that the writer, although confused, does indeed have love in his heart.&lt;ref name=&quot;m235&quot;&gt;[[#Meisler|Meisler (2000)]], p. 235&lt;/ref&gt;

Spotnitz later called the episode &quot;personal&quot;.&lt;ref name=ft/&gt; He noted that the cards that hang on Padgett's wall were put up to emulate the original writing style of ''The X-Files'', saying, &quot;in fact, that the cards that are on the writer’s wall are the same format that we wrote ''The X-Files'' in. We would use those same cards when figuring out stories for the series.&quot;&lt;ref name=ft/&gt; Later, Spotnitz noted that the cards were also in his handwriting &quot;because the prop guy couldn’t do it as well as we could because that’s really the way we did it. It’s a very emotional love story and it’s really about our love for these characters as writers&quot;.&lt;ref name=ft/&gt;&lt;ref name=biglight&gt;{{cite web|last=Spotnitz|first=Frank|title=Oh, Milagro|url=http://biglight.com/blog/oh-milagro/|publisher=BigLight.com|accessdate=October 13, 2012|date=September 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The writers eventually settled on the title of &quot;Milagro,&quot; which means ''miracle'' in Spanish.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Meaning of 'Milagro'|url=http://www.mydictionary.net/?word=milagro&amp;from=spanish&amp;to=english|publisher=MyDictionary|accessdate=January 23, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The part of Philip Padgett had been written specifically for the actor [[John Hawkes (actor)|John Hawkes]]. Several weeks before the casting for &quot;Milagro&quot; began, Hawkes had auditioned for the part of Pinker Rawls in the episode &quot;[[Trevor (The X-Files)|Trevor]]&quot;. Both Chris Carter and Frank Spotnitz felt that Hawkes was not right for the part; however, they believed he possessed a &quot;dignity and simplicity&quot; that would prevent the main character in &quot;Milagro&quot; from becoming a simple [[caricature]].&lt;ref name=&quot;m236&quot;&gt;[[#Meisler|Meisler (2000)]], p. 236&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, the script was written to suit Hawkes' characterization.&lt;ref name=&quot;m236&quot;/&gt;

===Filming and effects===
The production for &quot;Milagro&quot; was decidedly low-budget due to its &quot;intimate and personality-driven&quot; nature.&lt;ref name=&quot;m236&quot;/&gt; Director [[Kim Manners]] sought to film most of the episode &quot;very simply&quot;, because he wanted &quot;the characters to carry it&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Manners|Manners]], 12:46&lt;/ref&gt; Manners wanted to frame the opening scene in a way that told &quot;the story […] in a series of images&quot;, and so, he utilized quick cuts between shots.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Manners|Manners]], 0:32–0:40&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the scenes, such as the opening pan, were created by means of a [[crane shot]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Manners|Manners]], 0:14&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Manners|Manners]], 27:56&lt;/ref&gt;

The sequence wherein Mulder runs was shot on a motorcycle. Manners recalled that, because Duchovny had been able to outrun two horses in the [[The X-Files (season 4)|fourth season]] episode &quot;[[Tunguska (The X-Files)|Tunguska]]&quot;, he needed something faster to film the scene with.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Manners|Manners]], 35:20–35:32&lt;/ref&gt; Several locations that were scouted for the episode proved difficult to use.&lt;ref name=&quot;m236&quot;/&gt; Two churches that had been selected for the episode pulled out just before filming began and replacements had to be found immediately.&lt;ref name=&quot;m236&quot;/&gt; The scenes in the woods were filmed at [[Griffith Park]] in [[Los Angeles, California|Los Angeles]]. The location was chosen because it possessed &quot;probably the only pine trees in Los Angeles&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Manners|Manners]], 6:33–6:44&lt;/ref&gt; Due to the fact that the actual park is rather sparsely populated by brush, the foliage was all created by the crew of the series.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Manners|Manners]], 7:51–7:57&lt;/ref&gt; Manners shot several of the forest scenes with a 200 millimeter lens, so that the lights of Los Angeles would be disguised in the distance.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Manners|Manners]], 7:26–7:33&lt;/ref&gt; Padgett's furnace was filmed on a set called the red/blue room. It had originally been created for the sixth seasoner opener &quot;[[The Beginning (The X-Files)|The Beginning]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Manners|Manners]], 2:35–2:43&lt;/ref&gt; The jail set was constructed in a large warehouse by a different production company.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Manners|Manners]], 31:15–31:35&lt;/ref&gt; ''The X-Files'' rented the space for several days for filming, for five thousand dollars.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Manners|Manners]], 36:10–36:27&lt;/ref&gt; Finding a graveyard with &quot;old-fashioned vertical tombstones&quot; proved a challenge for locations manager Ilt Jones. Eventually one was found in [[Altadena, California]], east of Los Angeles.&lt;ref name=&quot;m236&quot;/&gt; The fog in the cemetery was created by burying small &quot;misters&quot; that produced water vapor. The vapor was cold so that it would stay low to the group and emulate the properties of actual fog.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Manners|Manners]], 33:30–33:40&lt;/ref&gt;

The sequence in which Hawkes rips his heart out was created by using a rubber heart. The fact that the faux blood begins leaking through his shirt was added to &quot;hide the fact that [the crew was] doing a little sleight of hand&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Manners|Manners]], 2:02–2:17&lt;/ref&gt; The image of the beating heart in the furnace was created by overlapping a shot of a fake beating heart and a shot of actual fire. The two were then merged in post-production by animator John Wash, because the fire would have melted the actual heart model.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Manners|Manners]], 2:50–3:11&lt;/ref&gt; The beating of the hearts of Naciamento's victims was created via a pump that was operated off-screen.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Manners|Manners]], 8:07–8:12&lt;/ref&gt; The actual milagro prop was crafted several times because, according to Manners, the face was particularly difficult to get right.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Manners|Manners]], 11:25–11:34&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, the second time the medallion appears in the episode, it is a different prop.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Manners|Manners]], 20:30–20:35&lt;/ref&gt;

===Music and cultural references===
For his score, [[Mark Snow]] used the sound of recorded human heartbeats to go along with the conceit of the episode.&lt;ref name=&quot;m237&quot;/&gt; During the graveyard scene, one of the tombstones is marked &quot;Salinger,&quot; with the names &quot;Nicholas&quot; and &quot;Diana&quot; visible underneath, a [[fictional crossover|reference]] to the parents of Charlie, Bailey, Julia, Claudia, and Owen in the Fox television series ''[[Party of Five]]''.&lt;ref name=smi/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;news&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Bianculli|first=David|title=Extras, Read All About 'em Readers Looking Sharp With Batch Of In-Jokes|url=http://articles.nydailynews.com/1999-06-23/entertainment/18108492_1_tombstone-jokes-episode|accessdate=January 2, 2012|newspaper=[[Daily News (New York)|New York Daily News]]|publisher=[[Mortimer Zuckerman]]|date=June 23, 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt; The date on the tombstone reads 1994, the date the series premiered.&lt;ref name=&quot;news&quot;/&gt; P.K. Simonds, writer and executive producer for the show was initially unaware that the tombstone made an appearance.&lt;ref name=smi&gt;{{cite web|title=Simonds Interview|url=http://partyoffive.tktv.net/simonds3.html|publisher=TKTV|date=June 1999|accessdate=January 2, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Others, including Spotnitz, believed the tombstone to be a joking reference to famous author [[J.D. Salinger]].&lt;ref name=&quot;m237&quot;&gt;[[#Meisler|Meisler (2000)]], p. 237&lt;/ref&gt;

==Themes==
[[File:Miraculous medal.jpg|thumb|right|225px|A medallion featuring the [[Sacred Heart]]; the symbol serves an important part in the episode.|alt=The image is of a small gold medallion with religious symbols carved on it.]]
Margaret Kaner, in the book ''The X-Files and Literature'', notes that, instead of merely utilizing symbolism, &quot;Milagro&quot; makes &quot;symbolism as a subject&quot;.&lt;ref name=kaner1/&gt; Kaner points out that the Christian symbol of the burning human heart is infused into the episode in a variety of different ways—hearts are both removed from human victims, as well as burned in furnaces. The episode's plot and the Christian symbol are connected when Padgett leaves Scully the milagro charm.&lt;ref name=kaner1/&gt;

The concept of motive is also explored.&lt;ref name=kaner2/&gt;&lt;ref name=bush1&gt;[[#Bush|Bush (2008)]], p. 86&lt;/ref&gt; When confronting Padgett, Mulder asks him why he is murdering his victims. Padgett, in turn, admits that he cannot answer the question. Kaner suggests that Padgett is representative of a version of Mulder, and that there is a direct parallel between being a criminal [[Criminal profiler|profiler]]—who must think like the criminal—and a writer—who must think like his characters.&lt;ref name=kaner2/&gt; In the end, however, Padgett sacrifices his personal quest—his manuscript—in order to be free. This presents a distinct contrast to Mulder, who will never truly give up his obsession.&lt;ref name=bush1/&gt;&lt;ref name=bush2&gt;[[#Bush|Bush (2008)]], p. 87&lt;/ref&gt; Michelle Bush, in her book ''Myth-X'', also notes that the episode sheds light on Scully's motive throughout the series: she wants to gain Mulder's attention, something she feels she does not have. Padgett eventually realizes this, and sacrifices himself for her love.&lt;ref name=bush1/&gt;

The episode also presents a temporary role reversal for Mulder and Scully. When discussing the lack of evidence at the crime scenes, Scully points out that &quot;a crime is only as perfect as the man […] Even if he made not one mistake, there still is a motive. If you find his motive, you find the murderer&quot;. Kaner argues that this logic is more in line with what Mulder has subscribed to throughout the series.&lt;ref name=kaner1&gt;[[#Kaner|Kaner (2007)]], p. 237&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, after Mulder discovers Padgett's manuscript, he arrests him &quot;without a second thought&quot;.&lt;ref name=kaner2/&gt; By relying on empirical logic, Mulder is acting in the way Scully normally thinks.&lt;ref name=kaner2&gt;[[#Kaner|Kaner (2007)]], p. 238&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reception==

===Ratings===
&quot;Milagro&quot; first aired in the [[United States]] on {{nowrap|April 18, 1999}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;DVD&quot;&gt;{{cite DVD notes |title=The X-Files: The Complete Sixth Season |titlelink=The X-Files (season 6) |origyear=1998–1999 |others=[[Kim Manners]], et al |type=booklet |publisher=[[Fox Broadcasting Company]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; This episode earned a [[Nielsen rating]] of 9, with a 14 share, meaning that roughly {{nowrap|9 percent}} of all television-equipped households, and {{nowrap|14 percent}} of households watching television, were tuned in to the episode.&lt;ref name=&quot;ratings&quot;/&gt; It was viewed by {{nowrap|15.2 million}} viewers.&lt;ref name=&quot;ratings&quot;&gt;[[#Meisler|Meisler (2000)]], p. 294&lt;/ref&gt; The episode aired in the [[United Kingdom]] and [[Ireland]] on [[Sky1]] on June 27, 1999 and received 0.85 million viewers, making it the second most watched episode that week.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.barb.co.uk/whats-new/weekly-top-10/? |title=BARB's multichannel top 10 programmes |publisher=barb.co.uk |accessdate=January 1, 2012}} Note: Information is in the section titled &quot;w/e June 21–27, 1999&quot;, listed under Sky 1&lt;/ref&gt; Fox promoted the episode with the tagline &quot;Someone's trying to steal Scully's heart... literally.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite sign |title= Milagro |year=1999 |type=Promotional Flyer |publisher=[[Fox Broadcasting Company]] |location=[[Los Angeles, California]]|url=http://i550.photobucket.com/albums/ii421/maurisap/xfiles%20forum/104stealscullysheart.jpg}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reviews===
&quot;Milagro&quot; received mixed to positive reviews from critics. Tom Kessenich, in his book ''Examination: An Unauthorized Look at Seasons 6–9 of the X-Files'' gave the episode a positive review, writing &quot;The power of ['Milagro's] revelations was stunning. As was the episode.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;mess&quot;&gt;[[#Kessenich|Kessenich (2002)]], p. 58&lt;/ref&gt; [[Robert Shearman]] and [[Lars Pearson]], in their book ''Wanting to Believe: A Critical Guide to The X-Files, Millennium &amp; The Lone Gunmen'', rated the episode five stars out of five, calling it &quot;a study of overwriting with all the mistakes left in&quot; and &quot;one of the most remarkable&quot; episodes of the series.&lt;ref name=&quot;shearman&quot;/&gt; Shearman and Pearson also felt that Anderson's performance was &quot;revelatory&quot;, and also praised guest star Hawkes as &quot;both sinister and sympathetic&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;shearman&quot;&gt;[[#shearman|Shearman and Pearson (2009)]], pp. 183–184&lt;/ref&gt; The Munchkyn Zone reviewer [[Sarah Stegall]] rated the episode 6 stars out of 5, writing &quot;my congratulations to Carter, Shiban and Spotnitz on a daring experiment for commercial television&quot;.&lt;ref name=munchkynzone&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.munchkyn.com/xf-rvws/milagro.html|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080703160246/http://www.munchkyn.com/xf-rvws/milagro.html|title=The Empty Heart|work=The Munchkyn Zone|author=Stegall, Sarah|date=1999|archivedate=July 3, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The character of Ken Naciamento has been listed as one of the best guest roles of the series, with ''[[TV Guide]]'' and [[UGO Networks]] both listing him amongst the greatest monster-of-the-week characters in ''The X-Files''.&lt;ref name=&quot;TVGuide&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.tvguide.com/PhotoGallery/Scariest-X-Files-Monsters-1885#5468 |title=X Files Scariest Monsters Pictures, Milagro Photos – Photo Gallery: The Scariest X-Files Monsters |accessdate=March 1, 2012 |work=[[TV Guide]]|publisher=United Video Satellite Group}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;UGO&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.ugo.com/movies/top-xfiles-monsters-ken-naciemento | title=Ken Naciemento (The Brazilian  Psychic Surgeon) – Top X-Files Monsters |date=July 21, 2008 |accessdate= March 1, 2012 |work=[[UGO Networks]]|publisher=[[IGN Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Zack Handlen gave the episode a &quot;B–&quot; and wrote that &quot;works far better than it deserves to&quot;, due largely to the performance of Hawkes and the &quot;bat shit weirdness&quot; of the plot.&lt;ref name=avclub/&gt; He was particularly critical of the &quot;self-serious&quot; and &quot;pompous&quot; tone of the episode.&lt;ref name=avclub/&gt; Handlen concluded that the episode was &quot;like watching someone's [[fan fiction]] getting brought to life&quot;.&lt;ref name=avclub/&gt; He did, however, write that &quot;there is something strangely fascinating about&quot; the premise; in particular, he was pleased with the conclusion, calling it the moment when &quot;things pick up&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;avclub&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Handlen|first=Zack|title='Milagro'/'Bardo Thodol' {{!}} The X-Files/Millennium {{!}} TV Club {{!}} TV|url=http://www.avclub.com/articles/milagrobardo-thodol,86213/|work=[[The A.V. Club]]|publisher=[[The Onion]]|accessdate=October 13, 2012|date=October 13, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Paula Vitaris from ''[[Cinefantastique]]'' gave the episode a negative review and awarded it one-and-a-half stars out of four.&lt;ref name=&quot;cinepaula&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Vitaris|first=Paula|title=Sixth Season Episode Guide|journal=[[Cinefantastique]]|date=October 1999|volume=31|issue=8|pages=26–42}}&lt;/ref&gt; Vitaris, despite noting the potential in the episode's theme of the relationship between writer and their characters, felt that &quot;Milagro&quot; betrayed Scully's personality and featured her doing things that were out of character.&lt;ref name=cinepaula/&gt;

Kim Manners was pleased with the episode; he noted that he &quot;felt it was a very interesting character study&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Manners|Manners]], 5:40–5:45&lt;/ref&gt; He later called it &quot;one of my favorite episodes&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Manners|Manners]], 10:35–10:37&lt;/ref&gt; Frank Spotnitz considered &quot;Milagro&quot; to have been an &quot;underappreciated&quot; episode. For this reason, it was later included on the ''X-Files Essentials'' DVD compilation, along with seven other episodes.&lt;ref name=&quot;ft&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Frank Spotnitz on 'The X-Files Essentials'|url=http://www.forteantimes.com/reviews/films/1257/frank_spotnitz_on_the_xfiles_essentials.html|accessdate=January 2, 2012|newspaper=[[Fortean Times]]|publisher=[[Dennis Publishing Ltd]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Scully's portrayal in the episode was given special attention. Stegall noted that &quot;if 'Milagro' has one message about perception, it is shown in Scully, who is seen through everyone's eyes (Mulder, Padgett, even Naciamento) but her own. Ultimately, we can't know which ones of these portraits of her character are 'right'. Maybe none of them are. It's a bravura performance from Gillian Anderson, well matched by Duchovny's low-key Mulder, acting on his instincts.&quot;.&lt;ref name=munchkynzone/&gt; Handlen argued that the episode reduces Scully &quot;to a victim waiting to find out which handsome man will rescue her.&quot;&lt;ref name=avclub/&gt; Elyce Rae Helford, in her book ''Fantasy Girls: Gender in the New Universe of Science Fiction and Fantasy Television'', accused the show of &quot;reinforc[ing] the stereotype […] of independent women as lonely, neurotic, and nostalgic for sexual attention from men.&quot;&lt;ref name=fantasy/&gt; Anderson herself felt that the character needed to &quot;loosen up&quot;.&lt;ref name=fantasy/&gt; She was once approached by a fan who applauded Scully as the &quot;epitome of womanhood&quot; because she is a character who &quot;not only can kick ass but she […] works with Mulder without jumping him.&quot;&lt;ref name=fantasy/&gt; Anderson, in return jokingly replied, &quot;So the epitome of womanhood is sexual restraint? […] I don't think so.&quot;&lt;ref name=fantasy&gt;[[#Helford|Helford (2000)]], p. 73&lt;/ref&gt; The episode was particularly analyzed by fans of the show, and the fact that Scully was almost seduced provoked &quot;lively internet discussion&quot;.&lt;ref name=fantasy/&gt;

==References==

===Footnotes===
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

===Work cited===
{{refbegin|2}}
*{{cite book |title=Myth-X |last=Bush |first=Michelle |isbn=9781435746886 | year=2008 |publisher=Lulu|ref=Bush}}
*{{cite book|last=Helford|first=Elyce Rae|title=Fantasy Girls: Gender in the New Universe of Science Fiction and Fantasy Television|year=2000|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|isbn=9780847698356|ref=Helford}}
*{{cite book|author=Kaner, Margaret|editor=Yang, Sharon|title=The X-Files and Literature: Unweaving the Story, Unraveling the Lie to Find the Truth|year=2007|publisher=Cambridge Scholars Publishing|isbn=9781847182395|chapter=Believing the Lie|ref=Kaner}}
* {{cite book | last= Kessenich |first= Tom | title = Examination: An Unauthorized Look at Seasons 6–9 of the X-Files  | publisher = [[Trafford Publishing]] | year = 2002 | isbn = 9781553698128 |ref=Kessenich}}
*{{Cite journal| last = Manners | first = Kim | title = &quot;Milagro&quot;: Commentary | publisher = [[20th Century Fox Home Entertainment]] |medium=DVD |location=''[[The X-Files (season 6)|The X-Files: The Complete Sixth Season]]'' |year=2005 | ref=Manners| postscript = &lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;&amp;#123;&amp;#123;inconsistent citations&amp;#125;&amp;#125; }}
*{{cite book | year=2000 | last=Meisler|first= Andy | title= The End and the Beginning: The Official Guide to the X-Files Season 6  |isbn= 9780061075957 |publisher=HarperCollins |ref=Meisler }}
*{{cite book | year=2009 | first1=Robert |last1=Shearman |first2=Lars |last2=Pearson | title=Wanting to Believe: A Critical Guide to The X-Files, Millennium &amp; The Lone Gunmen|publisher=Mad Norwegian Press|isbn=9780975944691|ref=shearman}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote|The_X-Files|TXF Season 6}}
* {{imdb episode|0751159|Milagro}}
* [http://www.tv.com/shows/the-xfiles/milagro-625/ &quot;Milagro&quot;] at [[TV.com]]

{{TXF episodes|6}}

[[Category:The X-Files (season 6) episodes]]
[[Category:1999 television episodes]]</text>
      <sha1>4h8yajd2ysx5c485xmhjejserkyhfke</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
