<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Nemesis (Resident Evil)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2332130</id>
    <revision>
      <id>737855792</id>
      <parentid>730595258</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-05T12:11:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[User:Green Cardamom/WaybackMedic 2|WaybackMedic 2]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27551">{{DISPLAYTITLE:Nemesis (''Resident Evil'')}}
{{Infobox VG character
| name = The Nemesis
| image = [[File:Nemesis0.png]]
| caption = Nemesis in ''[[Resident Evil 3: Nemesis]]''
| firstgame = ''[[Resident Evil 3: Nemesis]]''
| series = ''[[Resident Evil]]''
| creator =
| artist =
| voiceactor = Tony Rosato
| liveactor = [[Matthew G. Taylor]] (film)&lt;ref name=&quot;jeremy&quot; /&gt; 
}}

The '''Nemesis''', also called the '''Pursuer'''&lt;ref name=REUC /&gt; or {{nihongo|'''Chaser'''|追跡者|Tsuisekisha}},&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Biohazard 3 Last Escape Official Guide Book: Complete Conquest of Nemesis Edition |author=Studio BentStuff Co., Ltd. |date=31 July 2002 |publisher=Enterbrain, Inc. |isbn=4-7577-1143-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Biohazard 3 Last Escape Official Guide Book: Fulfillment of Her Escape Edition |author=Studio BentStuff Co., Ltd. |date=31 July 2002 |publisher=Enterbrain, Inc. |isbn=4-7577-1142-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt; is a [[fictional character]] in [[Capcom]]'s ''[[Resident Evil]]'' franchise. Although smaller than other [[Tyrant (Resident Evil)|tyrant]] models, the creature dwarfs a typical human, and possesses vastly superior intelligence and physical dexterity than its [[undead]] peers. It features in ''[[Resident Evil 3: Nemesis]]'' as a titular main villain before later emerging in other titles and [[cameo appearance|cameo]] roles. It is also featured on various merchandise and in the 2004 film ''[[Resident Evil: Apocalypse]]''. The character is voiced by Tony Rosato in the game, and portrayed by [[Matthew G. Taylor]] in the film.

Since the Nemesis' introduction, the character has received a positive reception, and has come to be regarded as one of the series' most popular characters. Some publications have praised its role as an intimidating villain, while others have noted it as one of their favourite and most terrifying monsters in video games.

==Conception and design==
Introduced in ''Resident Evil 3'', the Nemesis was designed under the concept of a &quot;huge, overpowering monster that could use weapons and intelligently track you anywhere&quot;. During development, many different designs were considered. Although some elements remained constant among them, the early designs featured several different degrees of surface damage, as well as different options for clothing such as a [[Ballistic vest|protective vest]] instead of a coat or a nude design similar to the original [[Tyrant (Resident Evil)|Tyrant]] from ''[[Resident Evil (1996 video game)|Resident Evil]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Resident Evil Archives |last=Capcom Staff |authorlink=Capcom |year=2005 |publisher=[[BradyGames]]/[[Capcom]] |isbn=0-7440-0655-4 |page=223}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the series' story, the Nemesis is the result of infecting a Tyrant — a humanoid [[bio-weapon]] created to be the ultimate lifeform&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Resident Evil Archives |last=Capcom Staff |authorlink=Capcom |year=2005 |publisher=[[BradyGames]]/[[Capcom]] |isbn=0-7440-0655-4 |page=156}}&lt;/ref&gt;—with a parasitic organism designed to increase its intelligence. Upon infection, the parasite takes control of the Tyrant's nervous system, forming its own brain and enabling it to follow precise instructions and make decisions without a need for constant direction. Clothed in black trousers, an overcoat, boots, and gloves, the Nemesis is armed with a [[FIM-92 Stinger|rocket launcher]] mounted on its left arm.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemesis-overview&quot; /&gt; To emphasize its design as a [[prototype]], the game developers left exposed muscles on its body and added stitches to cover the right eye.&lt;ref name=&quot;guidebook-bh3&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Biohazard 3 Last Escape Official Guide Book |last=''Resident Evil 3'' development team |authorlink=Capcom |date=1999-11-13 |publisher=[[Aspect Co., Ltd.]]/[[Capcom]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Upon spotting its target, it says the target's name out loud and attacks.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemesis-overview&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Resident Evil Archives |last=Capcom Staff |authorlink=Capcom |year=2005 |publisher=[[BradyGames]]/[[Capcom]] |isbn=0-7440-0655-4 |pages=159–160}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The secretions from the parasite give the Nemesis massively heightened regenerative abilities, which result in the creature being almost impervious to damage; although it can be put down with enough fire from small arms, eventually it ''will'' repair itself and resume the pursuit of its targets. However, this resulted in unexpected side effects, including damage to the skin and the emergence of additional tentacles, as well as unpredictable [[mutations]] caused by further attacks.&lt;ref name=nemREUC&gt;{{cite video game|title=[[Resident Evil: The Umbrella Chronicles]]|developer=[[Capcom]] |publisher=Capcom |date=2007-11-13 |platform=Nintendo Wii |version= |level=Nemesis T-Type (Pursuer) Notes}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''Resident Evil 3'', the creature's survival instincts eventually override Nemesis' programming, causing the host's body to reject the parasite and transform into a giant digestive organ. Featuring large central bone protrusions and elongated tentacles, it crawls looking for prey, yet continues trying to complete its mission despite its now diminished intelligence.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemesis-overview&quot; /&gt; This design proved to be the most difficult for the game's development team, as they worked to try to make it appear as unique as possible.&lt;ref name=&quot;guidebook-bh3&quot; /&gt;

==Appearances==

===In video games===
The Nemesis, named after the [[Nemesis (mythology)|Goddess of Vengeance]] from [[Greek mythology]], first appears in the 1999 [[PlayStation (console)|PlayStation]] game ''[[Resident Evil 3: Nemesis]]'' as the game's title character and primary antagonist. The product of years of research,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=The Wesker Report |developer=[[Capcom]] |publisher=[[Capcom]] |date=2001-03-22|platform=[[Dreamcast]] |quote=Albert Wesker: It was our 11th summer since we arrived at the Arclay Laboratory. A few days later, in the middle of the night, a parcel arrived from Europe via various transit points. It arrived to our heliport in a small box. &quot;Nemesis Prototype&quot;...}}&lt;/ref&gt; the prototype is deployed by the Umbrella Corporation to hunt and kill the STARS police team as a field test, and as revenge for the destruction of the original Tyrant.&lt;ref name=&quot;guidebook-bh3&quot; /&gt; The game’s protagonist, [[Jill Valentine]], first encounters the Nemesis outside Raccoon City’s police station where it kills [[Brad Vickers]] and then pursues her, uttering &quot;''STARS...''&quot; on sight. The Nemesis continues to stalk Valentine throughout the game, attacking with physical blows and grabs, and later, armed with a rocket launcher. After losing its overcoat as a result of heavy damage, the Nemesis mutates, and gains the ability to attack with long, extendable tentacles. Despite later being doused in acid, the Nemesis continues its pursuit, and mutates into a much larger monster after absorbing a dead Tyrant, gaining the ability to spew poison. Jill finally defeats the Nemesis using a [[Railgun|rail cannon]], and then depending on the choice of the player, she either kills it once and for all by unloading her weapons into it, or leaves it to die in the nuclear explosion that destroys Raccoon City.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Resident Evil Archives |last=Capcom Staff |authorlink=Capcom |year=2005 |publisher=[[BradyGames]]/[[Capcom]] |isbn=0-7440-0655-4 |pages=61–69, 160}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Nemesis also appears in ''[[Resident Evil Code: Veronica#Survivor 2|Resident Evil Survivor 2 Code: Veronica]]'', chasing the player if they fail to complete a level before the time limit expires and killing them instantly if it hits them; it can also be fought as a secret [[boss (video game)|boss]] armed with a rocket launcher if the player has met the proper conditions upon completing the game.&lt;ref name=&quot;flyer&quot;&gt;{{cite manual |url=http://arcadeflyers.com/?page=flyer&amp;db=videodb&amp;id=2424&amp;image=1 |location=[[United Kingdom]] |year=2001 |title=Gun Survivor 2 - Biohazard Code: Veronica |publisher=[[Capcom]] |accessdate=2009-01-09}}{{dead link|date=July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Nemesis returns for the ''Resident Evil 3'' chapter of ''[[Resident Evil: The Umbrella Chronicles]]'', in which it pursues Jill in the same manner as the original game and mutates into its secondary form as a boss.&lt;ref name=REUC&gt;{{cite video game|title=[[Resident Evil: The Umbrella Chronicles]]|developer=[[Capcom]] |publisher=Capcom |date=2007-11-13 |platform=Nintendo Wii |version= |level= |isolang= |quote=Resident Evil 3 Digest 1 (Archive): A black-coated monster stood between them and their freedom. Nemesis{{sic}}, or the Pursuer, was intent on wiping out every last member of S.T.A.R.S.. Nemesis{{sic}} had already made short work of Brad and continued to track Jill down to accomplish its mission objectives.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Alongside Jill, the Nemesis also appears in the Capcom title ''[[Under the Skin (video game)|Under the Skin]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ps2.ign.com/objects/664/664730.html |title=Under the Skin |publisher=IGN |accessdate=2008-12-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; and serves as a boss the player must steal coins from in a Raccoon City-inspired level.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Bramwell, Tom |date=2004-10-18 |url=http://www.eurogamer.net/articles/r_undertheskin_ps2 |title=Under the Skin Review |publisher=Eurogamer |accessdate=2009-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Character cards for the Nemesis additionally appear in ''[[SNK vs. Capcom: Card Fighters Clash|SVC: Card Fighters' Clash 2 Expand Edition]]'' and its [[Nintendo DS]] sequel.&lt;ref name=&quot;NDS&quot;&gt;{{cite video game| title = [[SNK vs. Capcom: Card Fighters DS]]| developer = [[SNK Playmore]]| date = 2007-04-24| platform = Nintendo DS| level = Nemesis card description| quote = Official name: Nemesis Type T. A parasite was successfully added to the Tyrant model bioweapon who stalks STARS}}&lt;/ref&gt; In an interview, ''[[Marvel vs. Capcom 3: Fate of Two Worlds]]'' producer Ryouta Niitsuma stated a desire to use the Nemesis in the title as a &quot;monster-type&quot; character from the ''Resident Evil'' series, but was dropped after considering it too &quot;grotesque and disgusting&quot; and in consideration of [[Entertainment Software Rating Board|ESRB]] ratings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |accessdate=2010-04-25 |url=http://www.ausgamers.com/features/read/2889094 |title=Marvel Vs Capcom 3: Fate of Two Worlds Details and Interview |publisher=Ausgamers |author=Farrelly, Steve |date=2010-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; The character would instead appear briefly in the game's ending sequence for [[Hulk (comics)|the Hulk]]. However, despite the initial concerns about his inclusion, the Nemesis appears as a playable character in ''[[Ultimate Marvel vs. Capcom 3]]'', an updated version of ''Marvel vs. Capcom 3''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://comic-con.gamespot.com/story/6324583/ultimate-marvel-vs-capcom-3-roster-leaked GameSpot - Ultimate Marvel vs. Capcom 3 roster leaked]&lt;/ref&gt; The Nemesis also appears in ''[[Resident Evil: Operation Raccoon City]]''. In the game, the Nemesis' programming is damaged and the USS is tasked with finding a parasite to repair it. Once the parasite is found, the players must defeat the Nemesis and inject it with the parasite. The Nemesis in the game uses a gatling gun for the fight and is mainly based on his film counterpart, however once the mission is completed, the Nemesis awakes to find his rocket launcher and utters his famous line, &quot;STARS...&quot; The Nemesis also appears in the tactical role-playing game ''[[Project X Zone]]'' as a rival unit.

===In film===
The Nemesis is featured in the 2004 film, ''[[Resident Evil: Apocalypse]]'', portrayed by [[Matthew G. Taylor]]. The character's design was left relatively unchanged, brandishing a rocket launcher and similar attire, but with the addition of a forearm-mounted rail gun,&lt;ref name=&quot;jeremy&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Downey, Ryan J. |date=2004-02-12 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20051124080906/http://mtvasia.com/News/200402/17007720.html |archivedate=2005-11-24 |url=http://www.mtvasia.com/News/200402/17007720.html |title=Milla Jovovich Battles Zombies, Bloody Hands On 'Resident Evil: Apocalypse' Set |publisher=[[MTV|MTV Asia]] |accessdate=2009-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; modeled after a heavily modified [[minigun]]. Director [[Paul W. S. Anderson]] noted that the gun's addition was inspired by the idea of the Nemesis &quot;walking around with a gigantic, powerful weapon in each hand and almost indecisive as to which one to use&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;jeremy&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author=Walker, Jeremy |url=http://www.jeremywalker.com/pages/films/imagesnote/Resident_Evil_Apocalypse_notes.doc |title=Resident Evil: Apocalypse - Production Notes |format=[[DOC (computing)|DOC]] |publisher=Jeremy Walker &amp; Associates |accessdate=2009-01-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; The costume for Nemesis was created by Kropserkel Inc. and PJFX Studios, and stands roughly {{height|ft=7|in=3|abbr=mos}} tall,&lt;ref name=&quot;krop&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.kropserkel.com/Nemesis.htm |title=Resident Evil: Apocalypse Nemesis costume |publisher=Kropserkel |accessdate=2008-12-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; weighing nearly {{convert|100|lb|kg}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;spina&quot; /&gt; After production of ''Apocalypse'' was completed, the costume was restored and put on display at Kropserkel's offices.&lt;ref name=&quot;spina&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.tomspinadesigns.com/Displays.html |title=Custom Display Services |publisher=Tom Spina Designs |accessdate=2008-12-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While The Nemesis' design remained similar, the character itself was expanded upon, now portrayed as a [[tragic villain]]. Formerly '''Matt Addison''' (portrayed by [[Eric Mabius]]), a survivor of the events of the [[Resident Evil (film)|first film]], he was infected with the T-virus after being scratched by a Licker and later captured and experimented upon by the Umbrella Corporation. Transformed into the Nemesis, it is sent to kill the surviving members of STARS, but remembers its humanity after fighting [[List of Resident Evil characters#Alice|Alice]], and fights alongside the protagonists towards the film's conclusion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Collura, Scott |date=2007-09-21 |url=http://stars.ign.com/articles/822/822250p2.html |title=Resident Evil Movies Character Rundown |publisher=IGN |accessdate=2008-12-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Nemesis is eventually crushed beneath a crashing helicopter, and is later killed by the nuclear explosion that destroys Raccoon City.&lt;ref name=&quot;book&quot; /&gt;

===In printed adaptations===
[[File:Biohazard3-comic-Nemesis.jpg|thumb|In contrast to [[Resident Evil: Apocalypse|the film]], literary depictions of the character have retained its role as an imposing [[antagonist]]]]

The Nemesis appears in a 1999 [[Hong Kong]] [[manhua]] adaptation of ''Resident Evil 3'' by Lee Chung Hing, ''Biohazard 3: Last Escape'', which is named after the game's Japanese title. The 27-issue series adds to the Nemesis' backstory, detailing its origin by showing the infection and transformation of the original Tyrant by the Nemesis parasite. Some elements are changed for its design, such as the Nemesis retaining both eyes initially, and then losing the right eye and gaining cranial staples only after an encounter with Jill.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite comic| title = BioHazard 3: Last Escape| volume = 1| date = 1999| publisher = Lee Chung Hing| location = [[Hong Kong]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The comic also introduces characters from ''Resident Evil 2'' into the storyline, which results in a face-off between the Nemesis and the mutated [[William Birkin]] towards the end of the series.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite comic| title = BioHazard 3: Last Escape| volume = 21| date = 1999| publisher = Lee Chung Hing| location = [[Hong Kong]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2000, [[Simon &amp; Schuster]] published a [[novelization]] of ''Resident Evil 3'', written by [[S. D. Perry]]. Though left unchanged for the most part, the Nemesis is immediately recognized as a modified Tyrant in the novel,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Resident Evil: Nemesis |last=Perry |first=S. D. |authorlink=S. D. Perry|year=2000 |publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |isbn=0-671-78496-X |page=60}}&lt;/ref&gt; which Jill Valentine dubs the &quot;Nemesis&quot; after thinking about why it hunts her.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Resident Evil: Nemesis |last=Perry |first=S. D. |authorlink=S. D. Perry|year=2000 |publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |isbn=0-671-78496-X |page=72}}&lt;/ref&gt; Instead of mutating due to having taken damage, the Nemesis transforms voluntarily towards the conclusion of the story in its pursuit of Jill,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Resident Evil: Nemesis |last=Perry |first=S. D. |authorlink=S. D. Perry|year=2000 |publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |isbn=0-671-78496-X |page=148}}&lt;/ref&gt; with its second form from the game being its actual appearance beneath the coat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Resident Evil: Nemesis |last=Perry |first=S. D. |authorlink=S. D. Perry|year=2000 |publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |isbn=0-671-78496-X |page=140}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A novelization of ''Apocalypse'' was released in 2004, written by [[Keith R. A. DeCandido]]. In the book, Matt and the Nemesis act as separate personalities in the same body, both aware, but with the Nemesis dominant. Matt eventually regains control after his body is impaled on a metal shard while fighting Alice, by showing the Nemesis his memories of Umbrella's experimentation upon &quot;them&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;book&quot;&gt;[[Keith R. A. DeCandido|DeCandido, By Keith R. A.]] (2004), ''Resident Evil: Apocalypse''. [[Simon &amp; Schuster]]. ISBN 0-7434-9937-9. pp. 148-149, 247, 257&lt;/ref&gt; The Nemesis is later mentioned in the 2007 novelization of ''[[Resident Evil: Extinction]]'', in which antagonist Doctor Isaacs considers the Nemesis both his greatest success and his greatest failure, hating mention of it and blaming its defection and destruction upon Umbrella's desire to immediately field test it.&lt;ref&gt;[[Keith R. A. DeCandido|DeCandido, By Keith R. A.]] and [[Paul W. S. Anderson]] (2007), ''Resident Evil: Extinction''. [[Simon &amp; Schuster]]. ISBN 1-4165-4498-4. pp. 18-19&lt;/ref&gt;

==Promotion and merchandise==
Nemesis appears on the cover of every version of ''Resident Evil 3'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mobygames.com/game/resident-evil-3-nemesis/cover-art |title=Resident Evil 3: Nemesis - Cover Art |publisher=[[MobyGames]] |accessdate=2009-01-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is mentioned prominently on flyers for ''Resident Evil: Survivor 2''.&lt;ref name=&quot;flyer&quot; /&gt; Capcom has also released commercial products modeled on the character, such as an adult size [[Halloween]] [[mask]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.halloweenmask.com/asp/iteminfo.asp?I=DP6771263&amp;R=&amp;H= |title=Resident Evil Deluxe Nemesis Mask |publisher=HalloweenMask.com |accessdate=2008-12-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; and later a silver ring modeled after Nemesis's head available for purchase through their Japanese online store.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.capcomshop.jp/shop/goods/goods.asp?goods=1262692 |script-title=ja:バイオハザード　シルバーリング　&quot;追跡者&quot; |publisher=[[Capcom]] |accessdate=2009-06-16 |language=Japanese |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071028160346/http://www.capcomshop.jp/shop/goods/goods.asp?goods=1262692 |archivedate=2007-10-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Palisades Toys used its likeness to create a posable [[action figure]], which was released alongside several other ''Resident Evil''-based action figures, packaged with a base and equipable rocket launcher.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Staff |url=http://www.toymania.com/columns/spotlight/palresevilone.shtml |title=Resident Evil Action Figures (Series One) by Palisades |publisher=toymania.com |accessdate=2009-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moby Dick released its own line of ''Resident Evil'' action figures bundled in pairs of a playable character and enemy. Included in the series were Nemesis's first and second form, with the first form featuring an alternate head and equipable rocket launcher. Each set additionally includes a part of an action figure of Nemesis's third form, which measures 24&amp;nbsp;inches (60&amp;nbsp;cm) long when completed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20010505080724/http://www.mobydick.co.jp/B3_RSAF/lineup/boxlineup.html |url=http://www.mobydick.co.jp/B3_RSAF/lineup/boxlineup.html |archivedate=2001-05-05 |title=BOX TYPE LINEUP |language=Japanese |publisher=Moby Dick |accessdate=2009-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mobydick.co.jp/biohazard/ACTION_FIGURE/index.html |title=BIOHAZARD |language=Japanese |publisher=Moby Dick |accessdate=2009-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reception==
[[File:Otakon 2006 Nemesis.jpg|thumb|Cosplay Nemesis in 2006.]]
Following the game's debut in 1999, the Nemesis became one of the most recognizable and popular characters in the ''[[Resident Evil]]'' series. [[G4 (U.S. TV channel)|G4's]] ''[[Filter (TV series)|Filter]]'' named the Nemesis one of the top ten videogame villains of all time as selected by viewers, placing fifth on the list.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video |people=Mizota, Diane |date=2002-06-25 |title=[[Filter (TV series)|Filter]] |type=video |publisher=[[G4 (U.S. TV channel)|G4]]|time=Top 10 Villains list }}&lt;/ref&gt; IGN noted it as their favorite aspect of ''Resident Evil 3'', stating, &quot;The point is, he's a bad-ass, and he's got plenty of surprises in store for you besides just fast feet and a big gun&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Perry, Doug |date=1999-11-11 |url=http://psx.ign.com/articles/161/161482p1.html |title=Resident Evil 3 Review |publisher=IGN |accessdate=2008-12-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; In another article, IGN noted the Nemesis as one of their favorite video game monsters of all time, but felt disdain for its presentation in the film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Schedeen, Jesse |date=2008-10-31 |url=http://stars.ign.com/articles/925/925158p7.html |title=The Monsters of Gaming |publisher=IGN |accessdate=2008-12-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; They also named him one of the series' best bosses, calling it &quot;what may be Umbrella's most fearsome creation ever&quot; and comparing it to ''[[Terminator 2: Judgment Day]]''{{'}}s [[T-1000]], and later one of the top 100 video game villains of all time, placing 59th and described as horrific not for its appearance or attacks but its persistence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://stars.ign.com/articles/961/961553p10.html |title=Best Resident Evil Bosses |publisher=IGN |accessdate=2009-11-02 |author=Schedeen, Jesse |date=2009-03-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |publisher=IGN |title=Big Boss of the Day: Resident Evil's Nemesis |url=http://stars.ign.com/articles/105/1050309p1.html |author=Schedeen, Jesse |date=2009-11-30 |accessdate=2009-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ign.com/videogame-villains/59.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120410050624/http://www.ign.com/videogame-villains/59.html | archivedate=10 April 2012 |title=Nemesis is number 59 |publisher=[[IGN Entertainment]] |work=[[IGN]] |accessdate=2010-05-20 |date=2010-05-03 |author=Staff}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[1UP.com]] named the battle against the Nemesis one of the &quot;25 of the Most Badass Boss Fights of All Time&quot;, saying &quot;There are plenty of bosses worth mentioning from the ''Resident Evil'' series... but the one that to this day most people point to as the biggest badass of the bunch is Nemesis{{sic}}&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Staff |date=2009-03-17 |url=http://www.1up.com/do/feature?pager.offset=1&amp;cId=3173294 |title=25 of the Most Badass Boss Fights of All Time |work=[[1UP.com]] |publisher=[[UGO Networks]] |accessdate=2009-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[GamePro]]'' ranked the Nemesis 29th on their list of the &quot;47 Most Diabolical Video Game Villains of All Time&quot;, noting the character &quot;made ''RE3'' memorable even among the other, superior installments in the series&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first=GamePro (Online) | last=Staff | coauthors= | title=The 47 Most Diabolical Video-Game Villains of All Time | date=2008-02-24 | publisher=[[PC World (magazine)|PC World]] | url =http://www.pcworld.idg.com.au/index.php/id;338891934;pp;2 | work = | pages = | accessdate = 2008-06-18 }}{{dead link|date=July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; It ranked fourth on ''[[Electronic Gaming Monthly]]'s'' &quot;Top Ten Badass Undead&quot; article, which described its role as a simple, yet effective villain.&lt;ref&gt;Scott Sharkey, “EGM’s Top Ten Badass Undead: Thriller Night,” ''[[Electronic Gaming Monthly]]'' 233 (October 2008): 106.&lt;/ref&gt; [[GameSpot]] featured Nemesis in a &quot;Reader's Choice&quot; edition of their &quot;Top 10 Video Game Villains&quot; article, placing eighth on the list and noting the character's high popularity among fans when compared to the Tyrant.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Staff |url=http://www.gamespot.com/features/vgs/universal/tenspot_villainsreader/p9_01.html |title=TenSpot Reader's Choice: Top Ten Video Game Villains |publisher=[[GameSpot]] | archiveurl=http://www.gamespot.com/features/vgs/universal/tenspot_villainsreader/p9_01.html | archivedate=January 20, 2007 |accessdate=2008-12-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; He has also been voted by [[GamesRadar]]'s readers as the 99th &quot;most dastardly ne'er-do-wells&quot; villain in video games in their &quot;top 100&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.gamesradar.com/top-100-villains-video-games/ | title=100 best villains in video games | date=May 17, 2013 | publisher=[[GamesRadar]] | accessdate=July 28, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[GameDaily]] listed it as one of their favorite Capcom characters of all time, stating &quot;The ''Resident Evil'' series has a slew of memorable bad guys to choose from... but Nemesis is our favorite.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Workman, Robert |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090408020352/http://www.gamedaily.com/articles/galleries/top-25-capcom-characters-of-all-time?page=12&amp;cp=3 |archivedate=2009-04-08 |url=http://www.gamedaily.com/articles/galleries/top-25-capcom-characters-of-all-time?page=12&amp;cp=3 |title=Top 25 Capcom Characters of All Time |work=[[GameDaily]] |publisher=[[AOL]] |accessdate=2008-12-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Nemesis additionally ranked fifth on their list of &quot;Top 25 Scariest Video Game Monsters&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Workman, Robert |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081210075928/http://www.gamedaily.com/articles/galleries/top-25-scariest-video-game-monsters/?page=21 |archivedate=2008-12-10 |url=http://www.gamedaily.com/articles/galleries/top-25-scariest-video-game-monsters/?page=21 |title=Top 25 Scariest Video Game Monsters |work=[[GameDaily]] |publisher=[[AOL]] |accessdate=2008-12-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!-- and was also named one of their favorite [[undead]] characters in video games.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Staff |url=http://www.gamedaily.com/articles/galleries/halloween-zombie-awards/?page=9 |title=Halloween Zombie Awards |work=[[GameDaily]] |publisher=[[AOL]] |accessdate=2008-12-25}} {{Dead link|date=July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; NOTE: I tried but I couldn't, so if someone can archive the source, feel free to unhide this sentence --&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* [http://www.kropserkel.com/Nemesis.htm Details behind the Nemesis costume used in ''Apocalypse'']

{{Resident Evil series}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2011}}

{{good article}}

[[Category:Capcom antagonists]]
[[Category:Cyborg characters in video games]]
[[Category:Fictional characters with multiple personalities]]
[[Category:Fictional hybrid life forms]]
[[Category:Fictional mass murderers]]
[[Category:Fictional super soldiers]]
[[Category:Fictional weapons]]
[[Category:Genetically engineered characters in video games]]
[[Category:Mutant characters in video games]]
[[Category:Resident Evil characters]]
[[Category:Zombie and revenant characters in video games]]
[[Category:Video game bosses]]
[[Category:Video game characters in comics]]
[[Category:Video game characters in film]]
[[Category:Video game characters in literature]]
[[Category:Video game characters introduced in 1999]]
[[Category:Video game characters with accelerated healing]]
[[Category:Video game characters with superhuman strength]]</text>
      <sha1>qxaqxxvv40pgthiubxm1b2h8608hsay</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
