<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Strasbourg tramway</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>11311122</id>
    <revision>
      <id>733653787</id>
      <parentid>732936238</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-09T07:42:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>John of Reading</username>
        <id>11308236</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Future extensions */Typo fixing, replaced: that that → that using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="49985">{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2015}}
{{Infobox Public transit
| name           = Strasbourg tramway
| image          = 
| imagesize      = 
| image2         = TramStrasbourg lineA HommeFer versIllkirch.JPG
| imagesize2     = 275px
| caption2       = 
| native_name    = ''Tramway de Strasbourg''
| owner          = [[Urban Community of Strasbourg|CUS]]
| locale         = [[Strasbourg]], [[Alsace]], [[France]]
| transit_type   = [[Tram]]
| lines          = 6&lt;ref name=&quot;network-map&quot; /&gt;
| stations       = 72&lt;ref name=&quot;network-map&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cts-strasbourg.eu/export/sites/default/pdf/04SeDeplacer/03PlansReseau/Affiche-plan-tram-31x43-BD.pdf |title=Tram Réseau |language=French |trans_title=Tram Network (Map) |accessdate=13 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lalsace.fr/fr/region/alsace/article/4221924,208/Un-nouveau-troncon-depuis-la-place-de-la-Gare-de-Strasbourg.html ''Un nouveau tronçon depuis la place de la Gare de Strasbourg ''] (in French), L'Alsace, 28 November 2010&lt;/ref&gt;
| ridership      = 300,000 (2010)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.strasbourg.eu/deplacement/realisations_projets/realisations_projets?ItemID=2079180156 |title=Official website of Strasbourg city |language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| operator       = [[Compagnie des Transports Strasbourgeois|CTS]]
| began_operation= 1994
| vehicles       = 94
| system_length  = {{convert|57.5|km|mi|1|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=&quot;home&quot; /&gt;
| track_gauge    = {{RailGauge|sg|allk=on}}
| notrack        = 2
| el             = 750 [[Volt|V]] [[Direct current|DC]] [[Overhead line]]
| map            = [[File:Strasbourg - Straßenbahn - Netzplan.png|thumb|center|275px|Map of Strasbourg tramway]]
}}
The '''Strasbourg tramway''' ({{lang-fr|Tramway de Strasbourg}}), run by the [[Compagnie des Transports Strasbourgeois|CTS]], consists of six tramlines, A, B, C, D, E and F that operate in the city of [[Strasbourg]] in [[Alsace]], [[France]].&lt;ref name=&quot;network-map&quot; /&gt; The first tram line in Strasbourg, which was originally [[Horse-drawn vehicle|horse-drawn]], opened in 1878. After 1894, when an electric powered tram system was introduced, a widespread network of tramways was built, including several longer distance lines on both sides of the Rhine.  The decline of the tramways system began in the 1930s, and ended with the retirement of the service in 1960 in parallel to the closure of many such systems in France and the rest of the world. However, a strategic reconsideration of the city's public transport requirements led to the reconstruction of the system, a development whose success led to other large French cities reopening their tramways, such as [[Montpellier tramway|Montpellier]] and [[Nice tramway|Nice]]. Lines A and D were opened in 1994, lines B and C were opened in 2000, line E was opened in 2007 and line F was opened in 2010. It is regarded as a remarkable example of the tramway's rebirth in the 1990s. Together with the success seen in [[Nantes tramway|Nantes]] since 1985, the Strasbourg experiment resulted in the construction of tramways in multiple other French urban areas, and the expansion of tramway systems remains an ongoing project in Strasbourg and throughout France.

== History ==

The first tram line in Strasbourg, which was originally [[Horse-drawn vehicle|horse-drawn]], opened in 1878. After 1894, when an electric powered tram system was introduced, a widespread network of tramways was built in the largest city of [[Alsace]], including also several longer distance lines on both sides of the Rhine.  The decline of the tramways system began in the 1930s, and ended with the retirement of the service in 1960.  After a long drawn out communal political decision process, the tram was reintroduced in 1994.  As part of the redevelopment of the city, a track of a total 33&amp;nbsp;km distance was built, on which 5 tram line services have been developed.

=== Horse-drawn trams ===

On 5 April 1877 the ''Strasbourg Horse Railway Company'' (&quot;Straßburger Pferde-Eisenbahngesellschaft&quot;) was founded, and the name changed on 25 April 1888 to the ''Strasbourg Tramway Company'' (&quot;Straßburger Straßenbahngesellschaft&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;Zur Geschichte der Straßenbahn: Groneck, ''Straßenbahnen'', S. 66 und Eckehard Frenz: ''Das Stadtbahn-Projekt von Strasbourg.'' In: ''Der Stadtverkehr'' 4/1980, S. 155-158.&lt;/ref&gt;  Since May 1897, the [[AEG]] electrical manufacturing company was the main shareholder. In 1912 the company was transferred to the possession of the city of Strasbourg.  When Alsace became part of France in November 1918, the name of the company was translated into French, &quot;Compagnie des tramways strasbourgeois“ (CTS). In this form it still exists today.

Public transport in Strasbourg had begun in 1848 with horse-drawn omnibuses and carriages. The first standard gauge tracks of the Horse/Railway Company were opened on 20 July 1878. These passed through the areas of &quot;[[Hœnheim|Hönheim]]&quot; and &quot;zur Kehler Brücke&quot;. In the inner city, horses were used. In the suburbs, small steam locomotives drew the carriages. By 1885 further lines to the suburbs of [[Straßburg-Koenigshoffen|Königshofen]], [[Straßburg-Robertsau|Robertsau]], [[Straßburg-Neuhof|Neuhof]] and [[Wolfisheim]] were opened, and in 1886 the meter gauge was first used in extending the track to [[Illkirch-Graffenstaden|Grafenstaden]].

=== Electric trams (1894–1960) ===

The electric company of [[AEG]] was engaged to install electric traction of that{{clarify|date=September 2015}} line in December 1894. Though the contract between town and company had included the maintaining of standard gauge, since 1897, the standard gauge tracks were converted to one-meter gauge. New lines were built and run to [[Straßburg-Cronenbourg|Kronenburg]], [[Lingolsheim]] and [[Breuschwickersheim]]. In addition to the network in town, an overland network was built, mainly worked with steam traction, extending from Strasbourg to the [[Vosges Mountains]], [[Colmar]] and across the [[Rhine]] into [[Baden]].

After in 1918 Strasbourg had become French, the 1920 all lines east of the Rhine (almost 50% of the overland network or 35% of the total network) were taken over at first by the shortly founded general German railway company of [[Deutsche Reichsbahn|Deutsche Reichseisenbahnen]], then in 1922 by the regional [[Mittelbadische Eisenbahnen]] (Central [[Baden]] Railways).

In 1930, the network comprised 234&amp;nbsp;km of track, about 100&amp;nbsp;km in town and 130&amp;nbsp;km overland lines, all in France.  There were 55 million passengers in 1930 and 71.5 million passengers in 1943.

=== The closing of the original tramway ===

In the 1950s, the tram, already weakened by [[World War II]], faced competition from other modes of transport such as the [[bus]], the [[bicycle]] and the private [[automobile]].  The tram system was abandoned in 1960 and replaced by buses; the last tram ran on 1 May 1960.  Much of the traffic was absorbed by the private automobile.

== Reintroduction (1994) ==

=== The debate: tram or light metro? ===
Due to increasing traffic and pollution, the [[Urban Community of Strasbourg]] considered building a [[Véhicule Automatique Léger]] network with two lines. The choice of rapid transit system became a major point of debate at the [[French municipal elections, 1989|1989 municipal elections]], with the incumbent [[Right-wing politics|right-wing]] majority favouring the [[Véhicule Automatique Léger|VAL]], while the opposition Socialists campaigned for a modern tramway.&lt;ref name=&quot;Strasbourg, les étapes&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Strasbourg, les étapes|url=http://www.vision-unit.fr/strasbourg/strasetapes/frameset.htm|accessdate=14 April 2012|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mon itinéraire&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Ries|first=Roland|title=Mon itinéraire|url=http://rolandries.eu/?page_id=5|accessdate=14 April 2012|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Shopkeepers in the city centre were also in favour of the VAL, on the grounds that the construction of the tramway and subsequent loss of parking spaces would deter customers. Meanwhile, the opposition campaigning for the tramway emphasised its cost-efficiency relative to the VAL (1 kilometre of VAL track cost as much to build as 4 kilometres of tramway) and the revitalization and pedestrianization of the city centre that the construction of the tramway entailed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Origines du projet&quot;&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://leportailferroviaire.free.fr/urbain/strasbo.htm | title= À l'origine du projet de tramway| work=Le portail ferroviaire | accessdate=1 January 2012}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Victory of the tramway ===
With [[Catherine Trautmann|Catherine Trautmann's]] election as mayor of Strasbourg, the VAL project was abandoned in favour of the tramway.&lt;ref name=wansbeek&gt;{{cite journal|last=Wansbeek|first=C.J.|title=Strasbourg: Interurban tram strategy strengthens city system|journal=Tramways and Urban Transit|date=March 2003|url=http://www.lrta.info/articles/art0303.html|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110720114224/http://lrta.info/articles/art0303.html| archivedate = 20 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first line, line A, opened on 25 November 1994. At 9.8 kilometres long, it signalled the tramway's return to Strasbourg. The line ran from the western suburb of Hautepierre to [[Illkirch-Graffenstaden]] (''Baggersee'' station). In order to cross the railway lines near the [[Strasbourg railway station|Gare de Strasbourg]], a 1&amp;nbsp;400&amp;nbsp;m long tunnel was dug with a [[tunnel boring machine]] between the ''Rotonde'' and ''Ancienne Synagogue/Les Halles'' stations. The ''Gare Centrale'' station, serving Strasbourg's railway station, is situated 17&amp;nbsp;m underground in this tunnel.

Artists were commissioned to create artworks relating to the city. In particular, the [[Oulipo]] was responsible for writing short texts on the columns in the stations, but with the following four constraints:

* ''Homophonic variations'': sentences formed from the syllables in the sentence ' ''Le tramway de Strasbourg'' ' (e.g. ''Les trois mouettes de Strauss: pour'') form the basis of a short story ending with the aforementioned sentence.
* ''Toponymic inscriptions'': written in the style of a dictionary entry, they present a fictional etymology for each station name.
* The ''récit au beau présent'' is a story written only with the letters present in the station name.
* Finally, there are proverbs which have been transformed by the addition of the word 'tram' or 'tramway'.&lt;ref name=&quot;Troll de tram&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=L'Oulipo et la Ville|url=http://classes.bnf.fr/ecrirelaville/ressources/oulipo.htm#1|accessdate=14 April 2012|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The network's construction was accompanied by town planning operations, with the intention of promoting city centre access by tram. Park and ride facilities were also built near suburban stations in order to encourage motorists to use the tram.&lt;ref name=&quot;Park &amp; Ride&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Park &amp; Ride|url=http://www.cts-strasbourg.fr/en/Services/Parkride.aspx|accessdate=14 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Indeed, the rationale behind the tramway's reintroduction was the perceived negative effect of the automobile's omnipresence in the city (pollution, congestion, disorderly parking). With the construction of the tramway, the city centre was pedestrianised and parking in the city centre was reduced via out-of-town park and ride facilities. Access to the city centre was closed off to cars in 1992.&lt;ref name=&quot;Déplacements et commerces: Impacts du tramway sur le commerce dans l'agglomération strasbourgeoise&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Déplacements et commerces: Impacts du tramway sur le commerce dans l'agglomération strasbourgeoise|url=http://lara.inist.fr/bitstream/handle/2332/907/CERTU_deplcom_strasbourg.pdf|accessdate=14 April 2012|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Extensions ==

=== First phase (1998) ===
On 4 July 1998, a first extension began: line A was extended 2.8&amp;nbsp;km further south into [[Illkirch-Graffenstaden]]. Just under two months later, on 31 August 1998, line D (''Rotonde - Étoile - Polygone'') entered service thanks to a short branch near the Place de l'Étoile. This new line uses the line A track for most of its journey, enabling higher tram frequencies in the city centre.&lt;ref name=Strasbourg-Tramways&gt;{{cite web|title=Strasbourg-Tramways|url=http://www.amtuir.org/05_htu_tw_france_new/reseau_tw_ren_france/strasbourg/texte_ren_st.htm|accessdate=14 April 2012|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Second phase (2000) ===
The network was further extended on 1 September 2000 as line B and C (total length: 11.9&amp;nbsp;km) entered service. They both originate from the same terminus, situated in Elsau, a residential area. They share a trunk line which leads to the city centre, crossing it from the south-east to the north-west. At the ''Homme de Fer'' station, the lines cross the track of lines A and D. This junction became the centre of the network. The two lines diverge at the ''République'' station: line C leads to the terminus in the Esplanade district via the [[University of Strasbourg|university area]], while line B heads north, serving the Wacken exhibition centre. It then passes through the communes of [[Schiltigheim]] and [[Bischheim, Bas-Rhin|Bischheim]] before reaching the ''Hoenheim'' terminus, in the commune of [[Hoenheim]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Strasbourg passe au tout-tram&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Gauthier|first=Nicole|title=Strasbourg passe au tout-tram|url=http://www.liberation.fr/societe/0101345110-strasbourg-passe-au-tout-tram|accessdate=14 April 2012|newspaper=Libération|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Link with regional rail (2002) ===
In September 2002, the ''Hoenheim'' terminus was linked to the [[TER Alsace|Alsace regional train (TER)]] on the Strasbourg-Lauterbourg line. A year later, a new exchange was created at ''Krimmeri-Meinau'': a railway station was built next to the eponymous tram stop, allowing transfers between line A (and line E in 2007) and regional trains running on the Strasbourg-Offenburg line.&lt;ref name=&quot;DESSERTES PÉRIURBAINES DES GRANDES AGGLOMÉRATIONS&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=DESSERTES PÉRIURBAINES DES GRANDES AGGLOMÉRATIONS|url=http://www.certu.fr/fr/_Syst%C3%A8mes_de_transports-n26/Transports_publics-n71/Transports_publics_urbains_et_peri_urbains-n701/IMG/pdf/monographie_strasbourg_vweb.pdf|accessdate=15 April 2012|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Third phase (2007) ===
The tramway remained largely unchanged until 2007, when a new wave of extensions was completed. These extensions should have been finished in 2006, but were delayed by appeals lodged by several associations and three individuals (including two [[The Greens (France)|Green Party]] councillors)&lt;ref name=&quot;La troisième phase d'extension du tram de Strasbourg&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Collin|first=Jean|title=La troisième phase d'extension du tram de Strasbourg|journal=Rail Passion|date=October 2007|issue=120|pages=22–26|language=French|issn=1261-3665}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 25 August 2007 lines C and D were extended, and line E entered service.  Line D was extended to a new terminus (''Aristide Briand''), while line C was lengthened by 4.2&amp;nbsp;km, taking it into the heart of Neuhof, which had previously been enclaved in southern Strasbourg.  The two lines share a common track for 600m between ''Landsberg'' and ''Jean Jaures'' stations. The extensions also created a new north-south route serving the eastern part of the city. Meanwhile, line E brought about a major change in the network, since it was the first branch line. Sharing track with the other lines between ''Wacken'' and ''Baggersee'', one of its objectives was to reduce transfer traffic at ''Homme de Fer'', a station not served by the line.&lt;ref name=&quot;Strasbourg inaugure son nouveau réseau de tramway&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Strasbourg inaugure son nouveau réseau de tramway|url=http://www.europe1.fr/Politique/Strasbourg-inaugure-son-nouveau-reseau-de-tramway-29842/|accessdate=15 April 2012|newspaper=Europe 1|date=25 August 2007|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Line E was extended by 2.5&amp;nbsp;km from ''Wacken'' to a new terminus, ''Robertsau Boecklin'', on 23 November 2007, thus servicing buildings in the European district, such as the [[European Parliament]].

=== Fourth phase (2008) ===
Line B was extended in two phases in 2008. The first extension, shifting the southern terminus from ''Elsau'' to ''Ostwald Hotel de Ville'', was completed on January 30, 2008. The second phase was completed on May 22, 2008, further extending this part of the line to ''Lingolsheim Tiergaertel''. The total length of these two extensions is 4.9&amp;nbsp;km, and the entire 2007-2008 extension project was completed at a cost of €397.5m.&lt;ref name=&quot;Strasbourg Light Rail, France&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Strasbourg Light Rail, France|url=http://www.railway-technology.com/projects/strasbourg/|accessdate=15 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

These extensions transformed a cross-shaped network, centred on ''Homme de Fer'', into a lattice shape, with two lines running in tandem along key routes in the city centre. This enabled more transfers and more direct links between stations, along with greater frequency in the city centre.&lt;ref name=&quot;DESSERTES PÉRIURBAINES DES GRANDES AGGLOMÉRATIONS&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Envied the World Over, Strasbourg’s Tram Expands Again&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Freeman|first=Yonah|title=Envied the World Over, Strasbourg’s Tram Expands Again|url=http://www.thetransportpolitic.com/2010/11/29/envied-the-world-over-strasbourgs-tram-expands-again/|accessdate=15 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This scheme is unique in France, but similar to systems in Switzerland and Germany.&lt;ref name=&quot;Strasbourg, une longueur d'avance sur les transports durables&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Grangié|first=Elodie|title=Strasbourg, une longueur d'avance sur les transports durables|url=http://lexpansion.lexpress.fr/economie/strasbourg-premiere-ville-ecolo-de-france_204706.html|accessdate=15 April 2012|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On considerable sections of track, the current network retraces the old network: ''Porte de l’hopital - Campus d’Illkirch'' (line A); ''Etoile Polygone - Aristide Briand'' (line D); ''Graviere - Neuhof Rudolphe Reuss'' (line C); ''Montagne Verte - Homme de Fer - Gallia'' (line F); ''place de Bordeaux - Wacken'' and ''Droits de l’Homme - Robertsau Boecklin'' (line E); ''Gare centrale - Pont de Saverne'' (line C) and ''Pont de Saverne - Homme de Fer'' (line A) - around 14.4&amp;nbsp;km in total.  The ''Homme de Fer'' station did not exist on the old network: there was a station nearby in the Rue de la Haute Montée,  currently crossed by lines B, C and F, while the Place Kléber was the main hub. ''Place de la République'' and ''place du Polygone'' were important nodes in the old network. Trams crossed the city centre from north to south via the Rue des Grandes Arcades and the Rue du Vieux Marché aux Poissons: otherwise, the current line A is a reconstitution of the old line 6/16, taken out of service on January 1, 1960.

=== First tram-train phase (2010) ===
Two new sections were finished in 2010: ''Gare Centrale - Homme de Fer'' via ''Faubourg de Saverne'', and ''Observatoire - Place d’Islande''. The latter was built in anticipation of the tram-train line, which entered service on the November 27, 2010. Line C abandoned the ''Homme de Fer-Elsau'' section, taking the ''Homme de Fer - Faubourg de Saverne - Gare Centrale'' route instead. Just the next day, a citizen’s initiative prompted Line F’s introduction, serving the ''Elsau-Place d’Islande'' route, which included the ''Homme de Fer - Elsau'' section that line C had abandoned.&lt;ref name=&quot;Une révolution sur le réseau tram&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Gambet|first=Aude|title=Une révolution sur le réseau tram|url=http://www.dna.fr/actualite/2010/09/17/une-revolution-sur-le-reseau-tram|accessdate=17 April 2012|newspaper=DNA|date=17 September 2010|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Further extensions (2013 onwards) ===
In 2013, both line A and line D were extended in the northwest. New tracks were built for both lines on {{convert|1|km|mi}} for each. Line D saw the opening of three new stations (''Paul Éluard'', ''Marcel Rudloff'' and '''Poteries''') and line A, of two new stations (''Le Galet'' and ''Parc des Sports''). The name of ''Hautepierre Maillon'' station on line A was changed to ''Cervantès''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cts-strasbourg.eu/export/sites/default/pdf/04SeDeplacer/03PlansReseau/CTS2013_DEPLIANT-RESEAU-EXTENSIONS-LIGNES_HD.pdf ''Dépliant réseau extensions''] on cts-strasbourg.eu {{fr icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lalsace.fr/bas-rhin/2013/11/28/l-offre-s-etoffe-a-strasbourg ''Transports en commun: L’offre s’étoffe à Strasbourg''], [[L'Alsace-Le Pays|L'Alsace]], 28 November 2013 {{fr icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In late 2013, work started on a further extension of line A, from Illkirch-Lixenbuhl to the town centre of  [[Illkirch-Graffenstaden]]. The extension opened on 23 April 2016, providing {{convert|1.8|km}} of extra route and three extra stops. It cost [[Euro|€]]37m, of which the [[Strasbourg Eurométropole]] provided €29m, the French government contributed €5·3m, and €1·5m came from the [[Bas-Rhin département]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.cts-strasbourg.eu/fr/la-cts/projets-dextension/ | title = Projet d'extension du tram A au centre-ville d'Illkirch-Graffenstaden | language = French | trans_title = Project to extend tram A to the town centre of Illkirch-Graffenstaden | publisher = CTS | accessdate = 11 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.illkirch-graffenstaden.fr/projets-realisations/projets/le-tram-au-centre-ville | title = Le tram au centre-ville | language = French | trans_title = The tram to the town centre | publisher = Commune of Illkirch-Graffenstaden | accessdate = 11 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=rgstnes&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.railwaygazette.com/news/urban/single-view/view/strasbourg-tram-network-extends-south.html | title = Strasbourg tram network extends south | work = Railway Gazette | date = 25 April 2015 | accessdate = 25 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Current network ==
As of November 30, 2013, the current network has 6 lines&lt;ref name=&quot;network-map&quot; /&gt; and a total [[Network length (transport)|line length]] of {{convert|57.5|km|mi}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;home&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cts-strasbourg.eu/en/ |title=Home - CTS |publisher=Compagnie des Transports Strasbourgeios |year=2013 |accessdate=13 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{update after|2016|04|23}} However, due to the fact that many lines overlap with each other, the [[Network length (transport)|route length]] is only {{convert|40.7|km|mi|abbr=on}}.{{citation needed|date=September 2013}}{{update after|2016|04|23}} The system's hub is Homme de Fer, a station in the city centre where 5 of the 6 lines intersect. In the pedestrianized city centre, the tram shares space with pedestrians and bicycles. In the suburbs, the tram shares the road with automobiles, but trams are not subjected to the rules of the road, in common with other French tramways. Instead, the tram uses its own dedicated signalling system, benefitting from priority over other traffic at all junctions.&lt;ref name=&quot;wansbeek&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Trams making way for light rail transit&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Hattori|first=Shigenori|title=Trams making way for light rail transit|journal=Japan Railway &amp; Transport Review|date=March 2004|issue=38|pages=30–31|url=http://www.jrtr.net/jrtr38/pdf/f30_hat.pdf|accessdate=17 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The six lines are:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.cts-strasbourg.eu/export/sites/default/pdf/04SeDeplacer/03PlansReseau/plan-detaille-sept2015.pdf | title = Plan détaillé du réseau urbain | language = French | trans_title = Detailed plan of the urban network | publisher = CTS | date = September 2015 | accessdate = 11 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:TramStrasbourg lineA lineD HommedeFer Station2.JPG|thumb|''Homme de Fer'']]
{| class=wikitable
| style=&quot;text-align:center; color: white; background-color: #CC3333&quot; |'''A'''
|Parc des Sport - Le Galet - Cervantès - Dante - Hôpital de Hautepierre - Ducs d'Alsace - Saint-Florent - Rotonde - Gare Centrale (underground) - Ancienne Synagogue Les Halles - Homme de Fer - Langstross Grand Rue - Porte de l'Hôpital - Etoile Bourse - Etoile Polygone - Schluthfeld - Krimmeri Stade de la Meinau - Émile Mathis - Hohwart - Baggersee - Colonne - Leclerc - Campus d'Illkirch - Illkirch Lixenbuhl - Illkirch Graffenstaden
|15.3&amp;nbsp;km&lt;ref name=rgstnes/&gt;
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center; color: white; background-color: #0066FF&quot;|'''B'''
|Lingolsheim Tiergaertel - Lingolsheim Alouettes - Borie - Ostwald Hôtel de Ville - Wihrel - Elmerforst - Martin Schongauer - Elsau - Montagne Verte - Laiterie - [[Strasbourg Museum of Modern and Contemporary Art|Musée d'Art Moderne]] - Faubourg National - Alt Winmärik (Vieux Marché aux Vins) - Homme de Fer - [[Place Broglie]] - République -  Parc du Contades - [[Lycée Kléber]] - Wacken - Rives de l'Aar - Futura Glacière - Le Marais - Pont Phario - Lycée Marc Bloch - Le Ried - Général de Gaulle - Hoenheim Gare
|14.7&amp;nbsp;km
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center; color: white; background-color: #ED930A&quot;|'''C'''
|Gare Centrale - Faubourg de Saverne - Homme de Fer - Place Broglie - République - Gallia - Universités - Observatoire - Esplanade - Winston Churchill - Landsberg - Jean Jaurès - Lycée Jean Monnet - Gravière - Kibitzenau - Saint Christophe - Neuhof Rodolphe Reuss
|8.1&amp;nbsp;km
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center; color: white; background-color: #339933&quot;|'''D'''
|Poteries - Marcel Rudloff - Paul Eluard - Dante - Hôpital de Hautepierre - Ducs d'Alsace - Saint-Florent - Rotonde - Gare Centrale (souterrain) - Ancienne Synagogue Les Halles - Homme de Fer - Langstross Grand Rue - Porte de l'Hôpital - Etoile Bourse - Etoile Polygone - Landsberg - Jean Jaurès - Aristide Briand
|8.7&amp;nbsp;km
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center; color: white; background-color: #660099&quot;|'''E'''
|Baggersee - Hohwart - Lycée Couffignal - Krimmeri Meinau - Schluthfeld - Etoile Polygone - Landsberg - Winston Churchill - Esplanade - [[Observatory of Strasbourg|Observatoire]] - Université - Gallia - République - Parc du Contades - Lycée Kléber - Wacken - Parlement Européen - Droits de L'Homme - Robertsau Boecklin
|10.6&amp;nbsp;km
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center; color: white; background-color: #7CFC00&quot;|'''F'''
|Elsau - Montagne Verte - Laiterie - Musée d'Art Moderne - Faubourg National - Alt Winmärik (Vieux Marché aux Vins) - Homme de Fer - Place Broglie - République - Gallia - Universités - Observatoire - Place d'Islande
|5.62&amp;nbsp;km
|}

Some stations connect to the bus network, run by the [[Compagnie des Transports Strasbourgeois|CTS]].

== Schedules ==
Service generally starts at the termini closest to the depot, between 0404 and 0434, picking up at the other end of the line between 0436 and 0457. In this way, stations closest to the depots (''Rotonde'' for lines A and D, ''Elsau'' for lines B and F, ''Martin Schongauer'' for line B headed to ''Ostwald'', ''Kibitzenau'' for line C and ''Landsberg'' for line E). On Sundays and public holidays, service starts an hour later than usual. Service ends at the same time every day; the last departures from termini take place between 0002 and 0015 (except for line C, where the last tram leaves ''Gare Centrale'' at 0035). After this, trams are stored in the depots; there is no reduced night-time service.

The service is equally frequent across all lines except line F, which has much lower frequency. All lines have an enhanced service period, from around 0600 to 2000. During this period, tram frequencies on lines A, B, C, D and E are one every 6 minutes on Mondays - Fridays, one every 7 minutes on Saturdays and every 12–15 minutes on Sundays. On line F, tram frequency is one every 10 minutes Monday - Friday, one every 13.5 minutes on Saturdays and one every 20 minutes on Sundays and public holidays.

Outside the enhanced service period, trams follow published timetables on all lines except line A. Depending on the time of day, tram frequency is one every 10–15 minutes on lines B, C, D and E. On line A, it is possible that trams run only every 20 minutes in the early mornings and late evenings, while the frequency on line F is only one every 20–30 minutes at these times. This is not problematic for users, since its purpose is to reinforce service on other lines (aside the final 600m, ''Observatoire - Place d’Islande'').

Stations served by two different lines will have a tram stop every 3 minutes on weekdays, according to the schedules described above. On Saturdays, this gap grows to 3.5 minutes, while frequency averages one tram every 6 - 7.5 minutes on Sundays and public holidays. There are some exceptions: ''Elsau - Homme de Fer'' is served less often, since only lines B and F travel this route. On the other hand, the two sections served by three lines (''Homme de Fer - République'' and ''République-Observatoire'') are travelled by 26 trams every hour in each direction, Monday to Friday.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.cts-strasbourg.fr/LinkClick.aspx?fileticket=vHaTTWbzggk%3d&amp;tabid=593&amp;language=fr-FR | title=Horaire de la ligne A, du 4 septembre 2011 au 24 juin 2012 }} ; {{cite web | url=http://www.cts-strasbourg.fr/LinkClick.aspx?fileticket=pCo7IneNDf4%3d&amp;tabid=593&amp;language=fr-FR| title=Horaire de la ligne B, du 4 septembre 2011 au 24 juin 2012}} ; {{cite web | url=http://www.cts-strasbourg.fr/LinkClick.aspx?fileticket=_9_cCJZm0gQ%3d&amp;tabid=593&amp;language=fr-FR | title=Horaire de la ligne B, du 4 septembre 2011 au 24 juin 2012}} ; {{cite web | url=http://www.cts-strasbourg.fr/LinkClick.aspx?fileticket=5_WglcZKapY%3d&amp;tabid=593&amp;language=fr-FR | title=Horaire de la ligne D, du 4 septembre 2011 au 24 juin 2012}} ; {{cite web | url=http://www.cts-strasbourg.fr/LinkClick.aspx?fileticket=DVKj9JB113s%3d&amp;tabid=593&amp;language=fr-FR| title=Horaire de la ligne E, du 4 septembre 2011 au 24 juin 2012}} ; et {{cite web | url=http://www.cts-strasbourg.fr/LinkClick.aspx?fileticket=dBnieoHtLd0%3d&amp;tabid=593&amp;language=fr-FR | title=Horaire de la ligne F, du 4 septembre 2011 au 24 juin 2012}} sur le site {{cite web | url=http://www.cts-strasbourg.fr | title=CTS (site officiel) | accessdate=19 December 2011}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The network as a whole boasts one of the highest transit frequencies of all French urban areas with over 250 000 inhabitants.&lt;ref name=certu_frequency&gt;{{cite web|title=Panorama des transports collectifs urbains dans les agglomérations de plus de 250 000 habitants|url=http://www.localtis.info/cs/BlobServer?blobcol=urldata&amp;blobtable=MungoBlobs&amp;blobkey=id&amp;blobwhere=1250166725642&amp;blobheader=application%2Fpdf&amp;blobnocache=true|accessdate=18 April 2012|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;

What is unique about the Strasbourg service is the fact that service at morning and evening rush hours is not more frequent than other services throughout the day. This is particularly noticeable in the early mornings, where service is reduced in most large cities; this is not the case in Strasbourg. The trams have no separate evening timetable, while bus schedules are modified only slightly. Both modes of transport have their timetables co-ordinated as to ensure transfers are always possible, even in the late evenings.

From the beginning of July to the end of August, the CTS uses a summer timetable, with slightly lower tram frequencies. Details of this are however not published, only arrival and departure times at major stations. Journey times are not identical across all services, varying by up to 3–4 minutes on line A, regardless of the time of day. Overall, the trams recorded an average service speed of 19&amp;nbsp;km/h in 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;L’année 2010 des transports urbains&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=L’année 2010 des transports urbains|url=http://www.gart.org/content/download/18159/181316/file/208x210_AnneeTransports2010_HD(6).pdf|accessdate=16 April 2012|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Passenger Information Systems ==

Every station has displays providing real-time passenger information: the destination of the next tram due at the station and its estimated time of arrival. Each station is linked to a central command post, and there is a [[Public address|PA system]] in the case of major disruptions.

The trams themselves are also equipped with passenger information systems. Displays show a map of the line the tram is serving, indicating the final destination and the next station. Between stations, a public address system announces the next stop, accompanied by a musical jingle unique to each station, composed by the singer-songwriter Rodolphe Burger.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rencontre entre Gilles Tiberghien et Rodolphe Burger&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Tiberghien|first=Gilles A.|title=Rencontre entre Gilles Tiberghien et Rodolphe Burger|journal=Vacarme|year=2001|volume=5|issue=14|url=http://www.vacarme.org/article90.html|accessdate=16 April 2012|language=French|issn=1253-2479}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Rolling stock ==
{{multiple image
   | width     = 200
   | footer    = 
   | image1    =TramStrasbourg lineA Htepierre versLixenbuhl2.JPG
   | alt1      = 
   | caption1  = Alstom Citadis 403
   | image2    = Tramways Strasbourg 06.JPG
   | alt2      = 
   | caption2  = Eurotram
  }}

===  Eurotram ===
{{see also|Eurotram}}
When the new network was first built in 1994, new rolling stock was designed. The city wanted fully low-floor trams with a novel design. A partnership called Eurotram was formed between CTS and [[Socimi]], an Italian company. Stringent standards were set on ergonomics and aesthetics: the city insisted on a fully low-floor design, with wide doors and electric wheelchair ramps in order to facilitate access and cater for the elderly and the disabled. Air conditioning was installed, despite advice from the manufacturers that it was unnecessary. The curved front windscreen covers the entire front of the tram, giving it a futuristic appearance. Similarly, large windows were included on the sides of the tram, with the aim of giving passengers the impression of travelling on a ‘moving pavement’. Eurotram also had a modular construction, with the head units being connected to passenger units, linked to each other by power units resting on their own axles.  Another notable feature is that there is no separation between passenger cars; the inside of the tram is one continuous space.&lt;ref name=&quot;wansbeek&quot; /&gt;

Twenty-six Eurotrams, built by Socimi, were delivered for service on line A between 1994 and 1995. These trams are 33.1m long, have 8 axles and a maximum capacity of 210 passengers. Each tram consists of 3 passenger cars and twelve motors, developing a total of 336&amp;nbsp;kW. The CTS placed a second order, this time for twenty-seven units, which were delivered between 1998 and 2000. The order included ten 8-axle trams and seventeen 10-axle trams. These ten-axle trams, nicknamed ‘jumbos’, are 43.05 m long, weigh 51 t and can carry up to 270 passengers in their 4 passenger cars. Total power is 424&amp;nbsp;kW, produced by sixteen motors.&lt;ref name=&quot;Strasbourg Light Rail, France&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fiche Technique Eurotram&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Fiche Technique Eurotram de Strasbourg|url=http://florent.brisou.pagesperso-orange.fr/Fiche%20Eurotram.htm|accessdate=17 April 2012|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the Eurotram’s design has generally been applauded for its user-friendliness, it has also received some criticism. For instance, the doors have been criticised for being too slow to open/close (they are single doors), lengthening the time spent in stations. Additionally, the large window over and around the driver’s cabin can result in the cabin becoming too hot, a problem that was remedied with sun blinds.&lt;ref name=&quot;wansbeek&quot; /&gt;

=== Alstom Citadis ===
{{Main article|Alstom Citadis}}
New rolling stock was required to operate on the 2005 extensions, so the city launched a call for bids in 2003 for new tram units. On July 15, 2003, [[Alstom]] was announced as the winner with its Citadis tram. Forty-one Citadis 403 trams were delivered from 2005 onwards. These units are 43.05 m long, carry 288 passengers and have ten axles. They weigh 53.2 t and are powered by three motor units, delivering a total of 720&amp;nbsp;kW.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tramway CITADIS de Strasbourg&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Tramway CITADIS de Strasbourg|url=http://florent.brisou.pagesperso-orange.fr/Fiche%20Strasbourg.htm|accessdate=17 April 2012|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At CTS’s request, the trams were restyled to look like the Eurotrams.&lt;ref name=&quot;Strasbourg Light Rail, France&quot;/&gt; The axle distribution is different on the Citadis, and the Citadis has an additional bogie under the driver’s cab. One of the Citadis’ advantages over the Eurotram is the inclusion of double doors which allow faster opening and closure, minimising time spent in stations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Strasbourg, un véritable réseau&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Yves|first=Alain|title=Strasbourg, un véritable réseau|journal=Connaissance du Rail|date=October–November 2007|language=French|issn=0222-4844}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014, CTS signed a framework agreement with Alstom for the supply of a further 50 Citadis trams. An initial 12 trams, worth €41 000 000, are expected to enter service by the end of 2016. The trams will meet [[BOStrab]] standards for operation into [[Germany]], and will be used on the cross-border line D extension to [[Kehl]], as well as line A.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.railwaygazette.com/news/news/europe/single-view/view/strasbourg-orders-citadis-trams.html?sword_list%5B%5D=Strasbourg&amp;no_cache=1 | title = Strasbourg orders Citadis trams | date = 20 October 2014 | work = Railway Gazette | accessdate = 11 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Maintenance ==
Given the network’s size and daily usage, maintenance is practically constant. Two ‘Aspirail’ trucks run the route daily, sucking up any debris that may be clogging the tracks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Strasbourg: Services de réparation, d'entretien et services connexes liés au transport ferroviaire et à d'autres équipements&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Strasbourg: Services de réparation, d'entretien et services connexes liés au transport ferroviaire et à d'autres équipements|url=http://ted.europa.eu/udl?uri=TED:NOTICE:352196-2010:TEXT:FR:HTML|accessdate=17 April 2012|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt; In case of an accident, the CTS has a fleet of [[road-rail vehicle]]s available, including tractors, a [[Unimog]] and [[cherry picker]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cmar. Au petits soins des centres-villes&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Cmar. Au petits soins des centres-villes|url=http://www.lejournaldesentreprises.com/dyn/imprimer.php?link=/editions/49/actualite/entreprise-du-mois/cmar-aux-petits-soins-des-centres-villes-05-11-2010-106290.php|accessdate=17 April 2012|language=French|year=2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In periods where ridership is lower (mainly summer), more major works are regularly carried out. CTS teams and contractors renew the tracks, points, signals and stations. The most major works bring about temporary suspension of the relevant tram service and buses are made available as replacements. This happened in April 2011, when the points at Rotonde were replaced.&lt;ref name=&quot;Trams A et D en partie neutralisés&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Trams A et D en partie neutralisés|url=http://www.20minutes.fr/strasbourg/709921-strasbourg-trams-partie-neutralises|accessdate=17 April 2012|newspaper=20 Minutes|date=April 2011|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Clear}}

== Future extensions ==
[[Image:Chamsin Kehl.jpg|thumb|Construction of the bridge across the Rhine to Kehl]]
An extension of line D from the current terminus at Aristide-Briande to [[Kehl]] in [[Germany]] is currently under construction. Construction on this extension, which involves the building of a new bridge  across the [[Rhine]], started in February 2014, and opening is planned in two phases. The first phase is planned to open in April 2017 and will involve the French part of the extension, the bridge over the Rhine and a temporary terminus at Kehl station. A further extension to Kehl Rathaus is planned to open by the end of 2017. The full extension will include three new stops in France and three in Germany.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.railwaygazette.com/news/urban/single-view/view/urban-rail-news-in-brief-april-2014.html?sword_list%5B%5D=Strasbourg&amp;no_cache=1 | title = Urban rail news in brief | date = April 2014 | work = Railway Gazette | accessdate = 11 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.cts-strasbourg.eu/fr/la-cts/projets-dextension/ | title = Projet d'extension du tram D à Kehl en Allemagne | language = French | trans_title = Project to extend tram D to Kehl in Germany | publisher = CTS | accessdate = 11 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = https://kehl.de/stadt/tram/index.php | title = Verlängerung der Tramlinie D nach Kehl | language = German | trans_title = Extension of tram line D to Kehl | publisher = City of Kehl | accessdate = 11 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{update after|2017|04|31}}

Other extensions are planned:
* An extension of lines A and D to [[Koenigshoffen]] and [[Oberhausbergen]] (northwest), planned for 2014.{{update after|2014|12|31}}{{citation needed|date=September 2015}}
* An extension of line E for {{convert|1|km}} into ''Robertsau'', planned for 2015.{{update after|2015|12|31}}{{citation needed|date=September 2015}}

A new [[tram-train]] system for Strasbourg has also been proposed. This would run over railway tracks from [[Gresswiller]] and [[Barr, Bas-Rhin|Barr]] to the Gare Centrale, where it would connect to the CTS system using new tunnel connections under the station, continuing to destinations in central and eastern Strasbourg. However [[Jacques Bigot (politician)|Jaques Bigot]], president of the [[Urban Community of Strasbourg]], has been quoted as saying that the proposed tram-train passing under the station &quot;will never happen&quot;, because of the high level of expenditure needed to build the connecting tunnels.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.railwaygazette.com/news/single-view/view/strasbourg-light-rail-expansion-resumes.html?sword_list%5B%5D=Strasbourg&amp;no_cache=1 | title = Strasbourg light rail expansion resumes | date = 1 June 2007 | work = Railway Gazette | accessdate = 11 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.20minutes.fr/strasbourg/1180221-20130626-questions-autour-differenciation | title = Questions autour d'une &quot; différenciation &quot; | language = French | trans_title = Questions about a &quot;differentiation&quot; | first = Thomas | last = Calinon | date = 12 September 2014 | publisher = 20 Minutes France SAS | work = www.20minutes.fr | accessdate = 11 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Fares ==
The CTS has several different tickets available to satisfy different needs. There is no division of the network into pricing zones; instead, a single fare is offered, costing €1.60, allowing the holder to travel from any station to another, including transfers, regardless of distance. Tickets are not valid after the journey; they are stamped at the station just before entering the tram (on bus services, tickets are stamped inside the bus). They are sold individually and in packs of ten and thirty, at a discount of 15% and 19% respectively. A ticket is sold for €3.90 (or €30.90 for the pack of ten) which works like regular system, but also allows travel on the TER train to [[Strasbourg Airport]]. There are also return tickets, which are 10% cheaper than the price of two singles. The ‘24h individuel Alsa’ ticket allows one person to make an unlimited number of journeys in a period of 24 hours at a cost of €4 while the ‘24h Trio’ ticket provides the same service to three people, at a price of €5.70. These last two tickets are also valid on TER trains travelling in the Urban Community of Strasbourg and include the nearby town of Kehl. Tram tickets are sold at numerous points in the city, such as newsagents, post offices, tobacconists etc.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tickets-Tarifs 2012&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Tickets-Tarifs 2012|url=http://www.cts-strasbourg.fr/Tarifs/TicketsTarifs2012/tabid/691/language/fr-FR/Default.aspx|accessdate=16 April 2012|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Monthly and yearly passes also exist, with the yearly pass costing the same as ten monthly ones. As of February 2012, the price of an annual pass for an adult (age 26–64 years) is €456; persons aged under 25 pay a price of €228, and pensioners (65 years old and over) pay €205.20.&lt;ref name=&quot;Abonnements Mensuels&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Abonnements Mensuels|url=http://www.cts-strasbourg.fr/Tarifs/Abonnements/Mensuels/tabid/600/language/fr-FR/Default.aspx|accessdate=16 April 2012|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Abonnements Annuels&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Abonnements Annuels|url=http://www.cts-strasbourg.fr/Tarifs/Abonnements/Annuels/tabid/601/language/fr-FR/Default.aspx|accessdate=16 April 2012|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since 2010 the CTS has offered so-called ''Tarification Solidaire'', i.e. reduced-price monthly and yearly passes to those in low income brackets. This reduction is calculated based on the ''quotient familial'' of the subscriber. The [[:fr:Politique familiale française#Quotient familial de l'impôt sur le revenu|''quotient familial'' (page in French)]] is a measure used by the French administration and is roughly equal to 1/12 of a household's annual income divided by the number of fiscal members in the household for tax purposes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calcul de quotient familial&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Calcul de quotient familial|url=http://www.caf.fr/ma-caf/caf-de-loire-atlantique/partenaires/tous-partenaires-calcul-du-quotient-familial-des-caf|accessdate=3 September 2012|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt; For subscribers with a ''quotient familial'' of less than €750 reductions are calculated on a scale from 50% reduction to 90% reduction in price of the monthly pass.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tarification solidaire&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Tarification Solidaire|url=http://www.cts-strasbourg.fr/Tarifs/Tarificationsolidaire/tabid/597/language/fr-FR/Default.aspx|accessdate=3 September 2012|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Badgéo smart card, costing €4, allows the user to purchase any ticket or subscription from tram stations, [[Crédit Mutuel]] branches and some other approved vendors. The card is then used like a ticket, allowing the user to travel according to the ticket or subscription that has been purchased. Monthly and yearly passes can only be bought in Badgéo form, as the paper forms of these passes have been discontinued.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carte a puce BADGEO&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Carte a puce BADGEO|url=http://www.cts-strasbourg.fr/Tarifs/Carte%C3%A0puceBadgeo/tabid/598/language/fr-FR/Default.aspx|accessdate=16 April 2012|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Strasbourg tram tickets, when bought in a pack of ten, are more expensive than the average of other French cities whose population exceeds 450,000 (excluding Paris), although they are not the most expensive. On the other hand, the price of a monthly subscription is in line with the average for large French cities.&lt;ref name=&quot;L’année 2010 des transports urbains&quot;/&gt;

== Financing ==

Up to the year 2000, 477 million euro had been spent building the network, and 304 million euro were earmarked in 2002 for the construction of the third phase of extensions; around 23.5 million per kilometre of track. This value is relatively high when compared to the cost of similar tracks in Germany, where 15 million euro are spent per kilometre of track in the city centre, and 10 million in suburban areas. The difference is due to the significant urban renewal projects undertaken in Strasbourg as part of the tramway’s construction.

The rolling stock cost 216.3 million euro: 118 million for the Eurotram units and 98.3 million for the Citadis trams. Investment in the Strasbourg tramway is mainly financed with the versement transport (VT), a tax levied in Strasbourg at 2% of payrolls, the highest rate allowed.&lt;ref name=&quot;L’année 2010 des transports urbains&quot;/&gt;

In the nine French urban areas with more than 450 000 inhabitants (excluding Paris), income from ticket sales covers on average 24% of costs, while the VT contributes 44%. Local authorities cover a further 31% of costs, while the remaining 1% is a direct state subsidy. In smaller cities, ticket sales make up an even smaller proportion of total funding.

The mean cost per passenger transported in these nine urban areas is €1.3, but varies between 0.8 euro and 2 euro.&lt;ref name=&quot;L’année 2010 des transports urbains&quot;/&gt; This value of 1.3 euro corresponds to the price of a pack of ten tickets (€12.7). For comparison, the CTS reported mean profits of €0.5 per journey in 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rapport d'Activités 2009&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Rapport d'Activités 2009|url=http://www.cts-strasbourg.fr/LinkClick.aspx?fileticket=eMh5av4I0DA%3d&amp;tabid=153&amp;language=fr-FR|accessdate=16 April 2012|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The overall financing of the CTS, and thus the current operation of the tramway is heavily subsidized by local authorities. In 2009, the CTS reported income of €194,194,702 and costs of €192,014,173, generating a profit of €2,180,528. The total amount of subsidies paid in 2009 by the [[Urban Community of Strasbourg]] and the [[Bas-Rhin|Bas-Rhin Département]] was €120,720,000.

== See also ==
* [[Trams in France]]
* [[List of town tramway systems in France]]

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Trams in Strasbourg|Strasbourg tramway}}
* {{Official website|http://www.cts-strasbourg.eu/en/ }}
* [http://www.trams-in-france.net/reload.htm?strasbourg.htm Pictures and informations on Strasbourg's tramway]
* [http://www.planum.net/4bie/main/m-4bie-strasbourg.htm The art programme for the Strasbourg tramway]

{{France Metro Tramway}}

{{coord|48|35|39|N|7|44|09|E|display=title|region:FR-A_type:landmark_source:dewiki}}

[[Category:Tram transport in France|Strasbourg]]
[[Category:Transport in Strasbourg]]
[[Category:750 V DC railway electrification]]
[[Category:Town tramway systems by city|Strasbourg]]</text>
      <sha1>n1qlz31nt2y06599c0augg0o9wyzi1h</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
