<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.28.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2600" case="first-letter">Topic</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Towson United Methodist Church</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>15128582</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738712299</id>
      <parentid>734156716</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-10T16:29:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[User:Green Cardamom/WaybackMedic 2|WaybackMedic 2]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="33437">{{Infobox church
| denomination     = [[United Methodist Church]]
| name             = Towson United Methodist Church
| image            = Towson Methodist Church (Maryland).jpg
| landscape        = yes
| imagesize        = 280
| caption          = The west exterior and {{convert|235|ft|m|0|adj=on}} spire, viewed from I-695
| imagealt         = The exterior and spire of Towson United Methodist Church
| country          = {{USA}}
| location         = 501 Hampton Lane&lt;br&gt;Towson, MD 21286
| website          = {{URL|http://www.towsonumc.org}}
| former name      = Towson Methodist Episcopal Church&lt;br&gt;(later First Methodist Church)&lt;br&gt;Towson Methodist Protestant Church&lt;br&gt;(later Second Methodist Church)
| founded date     = {{start date|1871|10|26}}
| architect        = J. Alfred Hamme
| style            = [[Georgian architecture|Georgian]]
| groundbreaking   = October 7, 1956
| completed date   = May 11, 1958
| district         = Baltimore−Washington Conference
| bishop           = Rev. Dr. Marcus Matthews
| minister         = Rev. Dr. Roderick J. Miller, [[Pastor|Lead Pastor]]&lt;br&gt;Rev. Margery Schammel, Minister of Discipleship
| organistdom      = Rev. Douglas Hollida
| businessmgr      = Kim Ayres
| reledu           = 
| youthmin         =  
| musicgroup       = Chancel and Joyful Noise Choirs, Alleluia Singers and children's choirs
| color            = &amp;#35;ADD8E6
}}

'''Towson United Methodist Church''' is a large [[United Methodist Church]] in the historic [[Baltimore County, Maryland]] suburb of [[Towson, Maryland|Towson]]. Its past, rooted in 19th century [[United States|America]], and subsequent growth in the two centuries since then, have closely paralleled the nation's political and sociological trends. It was a congregation split asunder in 1861 on the eve of the [[American Civil War]] in a [[Border states (Civil War)#Maryland|border state]] of divided loyalties, which eventually reunited and built a church in the post-[[World War II]] era of the 1950s, a time of reconciliation and rapid growth by [[Mainline (Protestant)|mainline Protestant denominations]], especially in the more affluent suburbs.

The 1,000-member church, currently pastored by Rev. Roderick Miller, has a number of community outreach programs, including an accredited child care center and a [[Boy Scouts of America|Boy Scout]] troop, and actively supports a [[home for unwed mothers]], overseas missions, and [[Habitat for Humanity International|Habitat for Humanity]] projects. The congregation worships in a 1,000-seat sanctuary built in 1958. The large building's prominent {{convert|235|ft|m|0|adj=on}} spire and cupola, a landmark visible for miles from the nearby Baltimore Beltway ([[Interstate 695 (Maryland)|Interstate 695]]),  has been called &quot;the beacon of Towson&quot;.&lt;ref name=beacon&gt;{{cite news|title=Lofty Goal|work=Towson Times|date=April 9, 2014|page=6|quote=The spire is often referred to as 'the beacon of Towson', as the steeple can be seen from the Beltway}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Towson United Methodist set to unveil restored steeple|last=Perl|first=Larry|url=
http://www.baltimoresun.com/news/maryland/baltimore-county/towson/ph-tt-steeple-0513-20150511-story.html
|accessdate=June 15, 2015|work=[[Baltimore Sun]]|date=May 11, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Towson United Methodist Church is located on Hampton Lane at interchange #27B of the Baltimore Beltway and [[Maryland Route 146|Dulaney Valley Road (Md. Route 146)]], one-half mile (one km) west of [[Hampton National Historic Site]]. The church's land was originally part of the vast 18th century Hampton estate.

==History==

===The beginning; 1750s&amp;ndash;1850s===
First settled by brothers William and Thomas Towson in 1752, the hamlet now bearing their name remained mostly farmland until the 1830s, with no churches and little more than a roadside inn/tavern for travelers on [[Maryland Route 45|York Road (now Md. Route 45)]].&lt;ref name=Arcadia&gt;{{Cite book|author=Brook Gunning and Molly O'Donovan |title=Towson and the Villages of Ruxton and Lutherville |publisher=Arcadia Publishing |location=Charleston, SC |year=1999 |isbn=0-7385-0226-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1790s, Rebecca Dorsey Ridgely, the wife of [[Charles Ridgely III]] and described as an ardent [[Methodist]], began holding [[prayer meeting]]s at the Ridgelys' grandiose [[Hampton National Historic Site|Hampton Mansion]], located one-half mi (one km) east of the present church site.&lt;ref name=Connor&gt;{{Cite news|author=Joseph P. Connor |title=History of Methodism in Towson |publisher=''The Towson Topics'' |date=October 1950}}&lt;/ref&gt; By 1825, the first [[Sunday School]] was started in a private home near a blacksmith's shop on York Road.&lt;ref name=Connor /&gt; In 1839, the citizenry of sparsely populated Towsontown, as the village was called by then, built the tiny community's first church in a wooded location north of Joppa Road and east of Dulaney Valley Road.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.immaculateconception.net/parish/history/History_page_1.htm |title=Parish History |accessdate=2008-02-10 |publisher=Church of the Immaculate Conception, Towson, Maryland |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20080131185120/http://immaculateconception.net/parish/history/History_page_1.htm |archivedate = January 31, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The site was previously used for a [[Magazine (artillery)|powder magazine]] built by [[Nathan Towson|Gen. Nathan Towson]] prior to the British attack on Baltimore in September 1814, during the [[War of 1812]].&lt;ref name=Epsom&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://external.bcpl.lib.md.us/hcdo/cfdocs/photopage.cfm?id=3361  |title=Epsom Chapel |accessdate=2008-02-12 |work= Baltimore County Legacy Web |publisher= [[Baltimore County Public Library]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Called ''Epsom Chapel'', the {{convert|1000|sqft|m2|0|sing=on}} structure was built of stones salvaged from the arsenal. Led by [[Methodist Episcopal Church|Methodist Episcopal]] minister Daniel Helpler, Epsom Chapel was dedicated and opened for Towsontown's first public church service on Sunday, November 10, 1839.&lt;ref name=Armstrong&gt;{{Cite book|author=Mary Lee Armstrong |title=Methodism in Towson 1871&amp;ndash;1971 |publisher=Towson United Methodist Church |year=1971 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In line with Methodist practice of the time in rural areas, [[Circuit rider (religious)|circuit rider]] ministers would travel on horseback to preach to the villagers at Epsom Chapel. With the designation of Towson as the county seat in 1854, the town began to grow more rapidly.&lt;ref name=Arcadia /&gt; The small chapel was shared with other denominations until the 1870s, when Towson's increasing population spurred the construction of larger churches.&lt;ref name=Epsom /&gt;

===Division and separate churches; 1860s&amp;ndash;1950s===
[[File:Epsom Chapel in 1899.png|thumb|280px|The congregation at Epsom Chapel in 1899]]
The Methodist movement was growing rapidly in pre-[[American Civil War|Civil War]] America, but was beset by disputes about slave-holding and the rule over the church by [[bishop]]s, resulting in a formal split into two groups in 1844. The faction in favor of giving church authority to a [[hierarchy]] of bishops called themselves the [[Methodist Episcopal Church]] and took an anti-slavery stance in the north. Those in opposition formed the [[Methodist Protestant Church]] in the United States. As the impending Civil War loomed over the nation in the 1850s, local Towson Methodists continued to worship together at Epsom Chapel.&lt;ref name=Armstrong /&gt;

This ended in 1861, when a [[Melodeon (organ)|reed organ]] was purchased for Epsom Chapel, sparking a disagreement over the use of musical instruments in worship.&lt;ref name=Armstrong /&gt; A minority opposed to the idea joined the southern-leaning Methodist Protestant Church, withdrawing from Epsom Chapel to worship at Towson's [[Independent Order of Odd Fellows|Odd Fellows Hall]] during the Civil War. In 1867, the Methodist Protestants returned to Epsom Chapel, but met separately on Sunday afternoons.&lt;ref name=Armstrong /&gt;

====Towson Methodist Episcopal Church (First Methodist Church)====
The northern-leaning Methodist Episcopal congregation, which continued worshiping at Epsom Chapel during the Civil War, began building their own church nearby, with the laying of a cornerstone on August 14, 1869.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=G. Custer Cromwell|title=A Brief History|publisher=First Methodist Church|date=November 1950|location=Towson, Md.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Towson Methodist Episcopal (M.E.) Church'', a [[neo-Gothic]] brick structure, was located on York Road next to the present Prospect Hill Cemetery, one block north of the intersection with Joppa and Dulaney Valley Roads. Designed by [[Edmund George Lind]] and built at a cost of $29,000, the 350-seat church was completed and dedicated on October 26, 1871.&lt;ref name=TMEC&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://external.bcpl.lib.md.us/hcdo/cfdocs/photopage.cfm?id=13545 |title=Towson Methodist Episcopal Church (c. 1913) |accessdate=2008-02-12 |work= Baltimore County Legacy Web |publisher= [[Baltimore County Public Library]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Towson Methodist Episcopal Church.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Towson Methodist Episcopal Church, built in 1871]]
The M.E. Church's eighty-seven members soon found themselves in financial difficulties, however, having gone heavily in debt to build their new sanctuary. The chairman of the church's building committee had advanced his personal funds to complete the construction, thereafter becoming embroiled in years of litigation with the church.&lt;ref name=Armstrong /&gt; By 1874, the church was drawing larger crowds under then-pastor Joseph Stitt, who was described as an &quot;excellent leader of singing&quot;.&lt;ref name=diamond&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Diamond Jubilee, 1871&amp;ndash;1946 |publisher=First Methodist Church |date=October 27, 1946 |location=Towson, Maryland}}&lt;/ref&gt; An afternoon Sunday school session was particularly popular, &quot;principally devoted to learning new hymns, which attracted many of the young people of the town, especially the young men&quot;, noted one account.&lt;ref name=diamond /&gt; When the ME church held its twenty-fifth anniversary celebration in 1896, it opened with prayer and a piano concert, &quot;favored with a beautiful selection sung by Mrs. Randolph Murphy&quot;, said a contemporary report.&lt;ref name=diamond /&gt;

Although the two Methodist congregations had remained estranged since the split in 1861, both groups did come together in 1895 for a &quot;Great Revival&quot; in Towson. The joint services were attended by throngs and the &quot;preaching was with power&quot;, newspapers commented.&lt;ref name=Connor /&gt; At the beginning of the 20th century, the increasingly large and prosperous congregation added eleven [[stained glass windows]] to the M.E. church, including ''Christ the Good Shepherd'' by [[Heinrich Hofmann (painter)|Heinrich Hofmann]]. In 1921, a new [[pipe organ]] was installed by [[M. P. Moller|M. P. Möller]].&lt;ref name=Armstrong /&gt;&lt;ref name=diamond /&gt;

====Towson Methodist Protestant Church (Second Methodist Church)====
[[File:Towson MP Church 1920s.jpg|thumb|220px|Towson Methodist Protestant Church in the 1920s]]
The Methodist Protestant group continued to use Epsom Chapel until 1908, when they built a $6,000 church seating 150 persons at the corner of Allegheny and Bosley Avenues.&lt;ref name=TMPC&gt;{{Cite web|url= http://external.bcpl.lib.md.us/hcdo/cfdocs/photopage.cfm?id=25233 |title=Towson Methodist Protestant Church |accessdate=2008-02-12 |work= Baltimore County Legacy Web |publisher= [[Baltimore County Public Library]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Located in the heart of Towson near the County Circuit Courthouse, the ''Towson Methodist Protestant Church'' was constructed of stone with a slate roof and a bell tower.&lt;ref name=Armstrong /&gt;&lt;ref name=Gunts&gt;{{Cite news|author=Edward Gunts|title=New owners sought for old synagogue, two churches|publisher=''[[The Baltimore Sun]]''|date=January 3, 2005|url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/baltsun/access/773209641.html?dids=773209641:773209641&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS |accessdate=2008-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With the merger in 1939 of the Methodist Episcopal (M.E.) and Methodist Protestant (M.P.) denominations in the U.S., Towson's Methodist Episcopal and Methodist Protestant churches were known thereafter as First Methodist Church and Second Methodist Church, respectively.&lt;ref name=Connor /&gt;

===The reunited church; 1950s&amp;ndash;present===
Following the reunification of the two branches of Methodism in 1939, First Methodist Church and Second Methodist Church of Towson continued as separate entities for another thirteen years. After the end of [[World War II]] in 1945, [[mainline Protestant]] church attendance increased significantly in the U.S.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Hadaway|first=C. Kirk|title=Is the Episcopal Church Growing (or Declining)?|year=2004|publisher=The Episcopal Church Center|url=http://www.episcopalchurch.org/documents/2004GrowthReport(1).pdf|format=pdf|page=11|accessdate=2009-11-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; By early 1952, faced with facilities fast becoming inadequate for the burgeoning population of suburbia in the [[Post-war|postwar]] period and with a boom in modern commercial development of Towson's core area starting to displace older buildings, the two churches formed a joint committee to evaluate a merger.&lt;ref name=1952Sun&gt;{{Cite news|title=Towson Methodists plan to merge two churches|publisher=''[[The Baltimore Sun]]''|date= April 18, 1952}}&lt;/ref&gt; The committee recommended that the two churches become one, concluding:

{{Quotation|&quot;The properties of the First and Second Churches are located in close proximity to each other&amp;nbsp;...&amp;nbsp;the identical objectives, program and methods of work of the two churches, will continue to make competition and overlapping inevitable&amp;nbsp;...&amp;nbsp;by pooling their resources and unifying&amp;nbsp;...&amp;nbsp;they can better serve the community and the Kingdom of God&quot;.{{spaces|20}}&amp;mdash; ''Joint Committee Report, 1952''&lt;ref name=Armstrong /&gt;}}

In April 1952, more than ninety years after the two churches split, the congregations of both finally voted to reunite, merging on {{nowrap|June 1, 1952,}} and adopting the name ''Towson Methodist Church''.&lt;ref name=1952Sun /&gt; The members of both Methodist churches then began worshiping together at the First Methodist Church.&lt;ref name=Spire&gt;''High Spire'', Towson United Methodist Church, January, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Plans to construct a much larger building with ample parking were announced when the two churches merged and {{convert|16|acre|m2}} of undeveloped land, originally part of the Ridgelys' Hampton estate and north of the planned alignment of the Baltimore Beltway ([[Interstate 695 (Maryland)|I-695]]), were purchased soon thereafter from [[Goucher College]].&lt;ref name=Arcadia /&gt; [[File:Towson Methodist groundbreaking.jpg|thumb|left|200px|Groundbreaking for the new church, October 7, 1956]] A groundbreaking ceremony was held on October 7, 1956, and construction of the new church was completed by the John K. Ruff Company in May 1958, with a service of dedication held on May 11, 1958.&lt;ref name=Arcadia /&gt;&lt;ref name=Spire /&gt; A crowd of 1,250 attended the ceremonies in the new sanctuary, with an overflow of 550&amp;nbsp;persons watching by [[closed-circuit television]] in the lower level Fellowship Hall.&lt;ref name=5-1958Sun&gt;{{Cite news|title=New Church Consecrated |publisher=''[[The Baltimore Sun]]'' |date=May 12, 1958 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The old First M.E. Church structure adjacent to Prospect Hill Park Cemetery on McCurdy Avenue (now Investment Place) and York Road was abandoned and eventually demolished in 1965.&lt;ref name=TMEC /&gt; An illuminated display of the [[stained glass]] windows in the former church is located in the foyer of the current building.&lt;ref name=5-1958Sun /&gt; The Second M.P. Church structure was sold in 1954 to the Women's Club of Towson and still stands today&amp;mdash;in 2005, the building was resold to an office development firm and is now used by an insurance agency.&lt;ref name=TMPC /&gt;&lt;ref name=Gunts /&gt; The erstwhile Epsom Chapel eventually became a meeting hall for Boy Scout troops in the 1920s&amp;ndash;1930s.&lt;ref name=Arcadia /&gt; It was subsequently abandoned and finally demolished in 1952 to make way for construction of a parking lot for the old [[Hutzler's]] department store, now a [[Barnes &amp; Noble]] store near the present [[Macy's|Macy's department store]] and [[Towson Town Center|Towson Town Center mall]].&lt;ref name=Epsom /&gt; No trace of Epsom Chapel exists today, except for an [[historical marker]] placed near the site by the Baltimore County Historical Society, designating it as the &quot;cradle of Methodism in Towson&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Epsom Chapel Marker|work=Historical Marker Database|date=November 7, 2009|url=http://www.hmdb.org/marker.asp?marker=36851 |accessdate=2011-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The current name, ''Towson United Methodist Church'', was adopted in 1968 to reflect the merger in that year of the Methodist and [[Evangelical United Brethren Church|Evangelical United Brethren]] denominations in the U.S.&lt;ref name=Armstrong /&gt; On [[Pentecost Sunday]], May 11, 2008, the fiftieth anniversary of the present sanctuary's completion was celebrated by a reenactment of the original May 11, 1958, dedication service.

==Current building and facilities==
[[File:Towson Methodist Church2 (Maryland).jpg|thumb|280px|Sanctuary interior viewed from the balcony, the organ pipework and windchests are concealed behind the altar screen&lt;/center&gt;]]
Towson United Methodist Church is an L-shaped structure, with the main sanctuary on a north-south axis. Designed by architect J. Alfred Hamme and completed in 1958, the church is built of [[brick|red brick]] in the [[Georgian architecture|Georgian architectural style]], with a prominent, floodlighted spire surmounted by a {{convert|9|ft|m|0|sing=on}} [[Vitreous enamel|porcelain enamel]] gold cross visible at 3–5&amp;nbsp;mi (5–8&amp;nbsp;km) distance on the Beltway.&lt;ref name=Sun58&gt;{{Cite news|title=$950,000 church built |date=November 23, 1958 |publisher=''[[The Baltimore Sun]]'' }}&lt;/ref&gt; The imposing front facade is of cut stone from [[Pennsylvania]], with the {{convert|18|ft|m|0|sing=on}} high main entranceway capped by a curved stone [[pediment]].&lt;ref name=Armstrong /&gt; Inside, the sanctuary has three aisles with a rear balcony and can accommodate up to one thousand persons. Rows of [[Corinthian order|Corinthian columns]] standing on {{convert|4|ft|cm|0|sing=on}} bases flank the pews along both side aisles. The pulpit and doors are made of [[mahogany]].

The 3-story east-west wing has classrooms, offices, a chapel, and the John D. Hoffman library featuring an exhibit of memorabilia and historical artifacts along with archival records.&lt;ref name=TUMC&gt;{{Cite web|title=Towson United Methodist Church (official website)|url=http://www.towsonumc.org/ |accessdate=2008-01-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Construction of the church cost $950,000 in 1958 (equivalent to almost $7&amp;nbsp;million in 2008), not including the expense of land acquisition.&lt;ref name=Sun58 /&gt;

===Organ and carillon===
Towson United Methodist Church has a 3-manual, 49-rank [[Casavant Frères|Casavant]] [[pipe organ]] of 2,516&amp;nbsp;pipes, including seven ranks of 16&amp;nbsp;ft. pipes and [[Tubular bells|tubular chimes]]. It was dedicated in memory of S. Clayton Seitz by then-organist John Duwane Hoffman on May 11, 1958.&lt;ref name=TMC58 /&gt; Hoffman, the church's esteemed virtuoso organist and Minister of Music between 1957&amp;ndash;1988, was a graduate of [[Union Theological Seminary in the City of New York|Union Theological Seminary]]'s renowned [[Master of Sacred Music]] degree program, after having earned [[Bachelor of Music]] and [[Master of Music]] degrees at the [[University of Denver]]. At Union, Hoffman studied the organ with Clarence Dickinson and Vernon De Tar.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Church appoints music minister |date=October 21, 1957 |publisher=''[[The Baltimore Sun]]'' }}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to serving as the church's organist and choral director, Hoffman was professor of organ at [[Towson State University]]. He died unexpectedly on July 4, 1988 of complications following [[Coronary artery bypass surgery|heart bypass surgery]]. The church library is named in his memory. Hoffman was succeeded by Kathie Metz, a graduate of [[Marshall University]], as Director of Music and Organist 1988&amp;ndash;2012. The current Director of Music and Organist since July, 2013, is Douglas Hollida. An ordained minister, Rev. Hollida studied music at [[Shepherd University]], graduating with a Bachelor of Arts degree, and then earned a Master of Divinity degree from [[Trinity Episcopal School for Ministry]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Rev. Doug Hollida (profile)|publisher=zoominfo.com|date=June 17, 2013 |url=http://www.zoominfo.com/p/Doug-Hollida/815837501|accessdate=2013-10-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; World-famous concert organists who have performed at the church's organ include [[Pierre Cochereau]], [[Flor Peeters]], and Marilyn Mason.&lt;ref name=Armstrong /&gt;

A 2-octave Schulmerich [[Carillon#Musical characteristics|electronic carillon]] of twenty-five bells was installed in the tower in June 1958.&lt;ref name=Armstrong /&gt; It was played from the organ console by a carillonneur on Sunday mornings before and after services, as well as on special occasions, such as Christmas Eve and as part of the traditional noontime nationwide peal of church bells on the [[Independence Day (United States)|Fourth of July]]. Hymns were also played daily on the carillon by a [[music roll]] until it was discontinued in the 1990s.

===Renovation and expansion project===
Towson United Methodist Church is in the midst of a $3&amp;nbsp;million phased renovation and expansion project started in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Community Profiles, Towson-Loch Raven, Baltimore County-RPD 315|publisher=Baltimore Metropolitan Council|year=2007|url=http://www.baltometro.org/CP/RPD315CP.pdf|accessdate=2008-01-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the first phase, completed in 2007, an elevator and additional facilities were installed for improved disabled accessibility, along with a new [[fire sprinkler system]] and replacement of the building's [[HVAC|climate control system (HVAC)]]. Additional classrooms in an expanded education wing are planned in future phases of a multiyear master plan adopted by the church in 2005.
[[File:Towson United Methodist Church3.jpg|thumb|left|upright|''Foreground:'' the church's wooded property, part of which was proposed for development in 2008]]
To help fund the future works, the church announced plans in January 2008 to sell {{convert|3.5|acre|m2}} of undeveloped, wooded property it owns on Hampton Lane to Shelter Development Corp. for construction of a senior citizen housing complex.&lt;ref name=sale&gt;{{Cite news|author=Laura Barnhardt |title=Hampton residents fight development |publisher=[[The Sun (Baltimore)|''The Baltimore Sun'']] |date=2008-02-18 |url=http://www.baltimoresun.com/news/local/baltimore_county/bal-md.co.hampton18feb18,0,5243251.story |accessdate=2008-02-19 }} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; A zoning change application was submitted to Baltimore County officials to allow sixteen residential units per acre (current zoning limits density to two residential units per acre) for a total of 80&amp;ndash;100&amp;nbsp;beds. The Hampton Improvement Association, representing neighboring [[Hampton, Maryland]] residents, said they &quot;&amp;nbsp;...oppose[d] zoning changes that would allow higher density residential development and require trees to be knocked down&quot;.&lt;ref name=sale /&gt; Then-pastor David Cooney told the [[The Sun (Baltimore)|''Baltimore Sun'']], &quot;We entered into this with Shelter, believing this is a good use for the land &amp;mdash; that this is a good company and a needed service&quot;.&lt;ref name=sale /&gt; In the face of community objections, however, Shelter and the church subsequently announced on March 3, 2008, that the development plans had been dropped.&lt;ref name=drops&gt;{{Cite news|author=Loni Ingraham |title=Developer drops plan for Hampton Lane |publisher=''Towson Times'' |date=2008-03-12 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A Shelter official said that his company and Towson United Methodist Church had jointly come to the conclusion that &quot;this is not something we are going to pursue&quot;.&lt;ref name=drops /&gt; Pastor Cooney said, &quot;It had become clear that we weren't going to be able to reach a compromise and we certainly don't want to be at war with our neighbors&quot;.&lt;ref name=drops /&gt; In the wake of the plan's shelving, the president of the Hampton Improvement Association told the ''Towson Times'' that his group wishes to work with Towson United Methodist Church to find an alternative use for the land besides commercial development, as they &quot;don't want to preclude the church from trying to get some money out of it.&quot;&lt;ref name=drops /&gt; In April 2008, Dr. Cooney said that the church &quot;did not set out to sell this land; the proposal came to us, and we have no other plans to sell or develop the land&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;David Cooney, ''High Spire'', April 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ministry==
Roderick J. Miller is Lead Pastor of Towson United Methodist Church, succeeding David S. Cooney in July, 2011. Miller grew up in Pennsylvania, where he graduated from [[Allegheny College]] in 1976, receiving a [[B.A.]] in Religion. He then studied at [[Wesley Theological Seminary]] in [[Washington, D.C.]], earning a [[Master of Divinity]] degree in 1982. While ministering at Union Chapel United Methodist Church in [[Joppa, Maryland]], Miller continued his postgraduate studies, receiving a [[Doctor of Ministry]] degree in Church Revitalization from [[Chicago]]'s [[McCormick Theological Seminary]] in 1992. He was later Lead Pastor at Bethany UMC church in [[Ellicott City, Maryland]] (1994&amp;ndash;2005), after which he was named Director of Connectional Ministries for the denomination's Baltimore-Washington Conference, serving in that role 2005&amp;ndash;2011.

The mission statement of Towson United Methodist Church is: ''&quot;To proclaim the Word of God and to make disciples of Jesus Christ&quot;''. The church's staff of twelve includes assistant ministers, directors of music and education, and building and administrative personnel. It is a part of the denomination's Baltimore-Washington Conference (district).&lt;ref name=TUMC /&gt; In addition to Sunday morning worship services, the 1,200&amp;nbsp;member congregation participates in graded Sunday school classes, various adult Bible study classes, youth activities, and a midweek &quot;Praise, Prayer &amp; Healing&quot; service. The music program includes both adult and youth choirs, as well as handbell ringers.&lt;ref name=TUMC /&gt; The church's ''Alleluia Singers'', a 50&amp;ndash;voice ensemble of high school-age young people, sings frequently for weekly worship services and tours the eastern U.S. each summer.

===Previous ministers===
David Cooney was Senior Pastor of Towson United Methodist Church between September 1, 2001&amp;ndash;June 30, 2011. He earned a Master of Divinity degree from Wesley Theological Seminary and a [[Doctor of Philosophy|Ph.D.]] from [[Iliff School of Theology]] in [[Denver, Colorado]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title=Pastors &amp;mdash; Rev. Dr. David S. Cooney, Senior Pastor |publisher=Towson United Methodist Church |date=December 2007|url=http://www.towsonumc.org/pastors.htm|accessdate=2007-12-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; He is the son of Rev. C. Douglas Cooney (1928&amp;ndash;2003), who was also a Methodist minister at various churches, including the First Methodist Church of [[Hyattsville, Maryland]], as well as an official of the Methodist denomination.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|author=Jacques Kelly |title=The Rev. C. Douglas Cooney, 75, Methodist pastor, church official |date=February 18, 2003 |publisher=''[[The Baltimore Sun]]'' |url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/baltsun/access/290328501.html?dids=290328501:290328501&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS |accessdate=2008-03-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other former senior ministers of Towson Methodist Church and its predecessor First Methodist Church, with their years of appointment, are:&lt;ref name=TMC58&gt;''Consecration'', Towson Methodist Church, 1958.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;float:left;width:50%;&quot;&gt;
::*John W. Cornelius (1871-1872)
::*Joseph R. Stitt (1872-1874)
::*C. Herbert Richardson (1874-1877)
::*N. F. B. Rice (1877-1880)
::*James N. Davis (1880-1882)
::*W. T. D. Clem (1882-1885)
::*Watson Case (1885-1887)
::*Page Milburn (1887-1891)
::*Randolph R. Murphy (1891-1892)
::*Asbury R. Riley (1892-1897)
::*Edward C. Gallager (1897-1900)
::*John R. Edwards (1900-1905)
::*Thomas E. Copes (1905-1910)
::*John L. Walsh (1910-1914)
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;float:right;width:50%;&quot;&gt;
::*Samuel M. Alford (1914-1917)
::*Richard G. Koontz (1917-1923)
::*Mark Depp (1923-1927)
::*Walter F. Atkinson (1927-1929)
::*Edgar Cordell Powers (1929-1932)
::*William A. Keese (1932-1935)
::*Clifford H. Richmond (1936-1941)
::*Asbury Smith (1941-1947)
::*G. Custer Cromwell (1947-1951)
::*Lewis F. Ransom (1951-1965)&lt;ref&gt;Rev. Lewis F. Ransom, senior minister of Towson's First Methodist Church at the time of the two churches' merger in 1952 and subsequently first minister of the unified Towson Methodist Church during its construction and first decade, was later shot and killed during a robbery on March 22, 1988, as the 76-year-old clergyman returned to his car after making a nighttime pastoral visit to patients at a downtown Baltimore hospital. References:&lt;br/&gt;{{Cite news|author=John Rivera |title=Man enters 2nd guilty plea in slaying |date=January 18, 1992 |publisher=''[[The Baltimore Sun]]'' |url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/baltsun/access/113486392.html?dids=113486392:113486392&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS |accessdate=2008-04-15}}&lt;br/&gt;{{Cite news|author=Joel McCord |title=Retrial ordered in slaying of minister in city in '88 |date=March 2, 1991 |publisher=''[[The Baltimore Sun]]'' |url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/baltsun/access/113704007.html?dids=113704007:113704007&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS |accessdate=2008-04-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
::*John Bayley Jones IV (1965-1976)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=The Rev. John Bayley Jones IV, 95, longtime United Methodist pastor|publisher=''[[The Baltimore Sun]]''|date=June 14, 2003|url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/baltsun/access/347744631.html?dids=347744631:347744631&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS |accessdate=2008-01-14 | first=Sandy | last=Alexander}}&lt;/ref&gt;
::*Walter C. Smith, Jr. (1976-1995)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Walter C. Smith Jr., 73, Towson United Methodist pastor|publisher=''[[The Baltimore Sun]]''|date=June 22, 2003|url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/baltsun/access/350723871.html?dids=350723871:350723871&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS |accessdate=2008-01-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
::*Stephen C. Rettenmayer (1995-2001)
&lt;/div&gt;{{Clear}}

===Community outreach===
Towson United Methodist Church sponsors a [[Boy Scouts of America|Boy Scout]] troop, overseas missions, the Susanna Wesley House for unwed mothers, and actively participates in [[Habitat for Humanity International|Habitat for Humanity]] projects.&lt;ref name=TUMC /&gt; Over the years, members of the Towson Methodist Men's group and Women's Society of Christian Service (now United Methodist Women) have supported [[Meals on Wheels]], the [[League of Women Voters]], and [[Head Start Program|Head Start]], as well as serving as volunteers at local hospitals and the [[Maryland School for the Blind]].&lt;ref name=Armstrong /&gt; For more than thirty years, the church has hosted a weekly meeting of [[Alcoholics Anonymous]].

The large size of the sanctuary and its convenient location make it well-suited for community gatherings attracting sizable crowds, such as concerts by the [[Handel Choir of Baltimore]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|author=Tim Smith|title=Choir concludes a rebuilding year|work=[[The Baltimore Sun]]|date=May 9, 2005|url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/baltsun/access/834937951.html?dids=834937951:834937951&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS |accessdate=2008-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The church hosts an annual memorial service for fallen Baltimore County firefighters and rescue personnel. Senior Baltimore County officials, including the County Executive and Fire Chief, participate in the service's memorial wreath laying and the tolling of a bell, as part of the commemoration.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|author=Laura Barnhardt|title=Service to honor county firefighters|work=[[The Baltimore Sun]]|date=September 24, 2004|url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/baltsun/access/698853831.html?dids=698853831:698853831&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS |accessdate=2008-01-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Towson church to host county's fire service memorial ceremony|work=[[The Baltimore Sun]]|date=September 20, 2013|url= 
http://www.baltimoresun.com/news/maryland/baltimore-county/towson/bal-towson-fire-memorial-20130920,0,3299544.story|accessdate=2013-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nationally-known guest speakers, such as [[Tony Campolo]] and Millie Dienert, have also spoken there.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Hare|first=Mary Gail|title=Forum on gays centers on tolerance|work=[[The Baltimore Sun]]|date=October 18, 1998|url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/baltsun/access/35281326.html?dids=35281326:35281326&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS|page=6B|accessdate=2009-11-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Towson United Methodist Church started the Hampton Lane Child Development Center in 1978. An accredited child care center, it now serves approximately fifty children ages 2–5 years old.&lt;ref name=TUMC /&gt;

==Notes and references==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.towsonumc.org/ Official website]

{{Good article}}
{{Coord|39.41437|N|76.59886|W|display=title}}

[[Category:United Methodist churches in Maryland]]
[[Category:Churches in Baltimore County, Maryland]]
[[Category:Secession crisis of 1860–61]]
[[Category:1839 establishments in Maryland]]
[[Category:Towson, Maryland]]</text>
      <sha1>pvr7ucb4yg1o03k9tbdv9s9wvm5b3or</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
