<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.28.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2600" case="first-letter">Topic</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Violet wand</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>853524</id>
    <revision>
      <id>736605112</id>
      <parentid>736555755</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-28T16:56:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Drmies</username>
        <id>5183450</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted to revision 736341267 by [[Special:Contributions/Drmies|Drmies]] ([[User talk:Drmies|talk]]): Again rv promotional interests. next time it's an admin board and a request for a block. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="4618">[[File:Erotec-violet-wand.png|right|250px|thumb|Erotec Violet Wand, from 2000]]

'''Violet wands''' are modern electrical sexual or kink stimulation toys.  They are used for the application of low current, high voltage (min 35&amp;nbsp;kV to max 65&amp;nbsp;kV typically), high-frequency electricity to the body.  They are most commonly used in [[BDSM]] though erotic sensation play is also possible with them.

==Description==
A violet wand typically consists of a hand held &quot;wand&quot; made of plastic which encases a high voltage electrical transformer. The base of the handle has a permanently attached electrical cord which plugs directly into a wall outlet. The use of a [[GFCI]] is recommended to protect users from failures or breaks in the case that could expose them to the high-current input voltage. The wand has an intensity level control and sometimes an on/off switch, usually located near where the electrical cord is attached. Some models operate on an electromagnetic disruptive discharge circuit while others are powered by electronic circuitry (called solid state wands) or combinations of the two.

Various electrodes are inserted into and used with the violet wand to provide the sensations.  A violet wand electrode is usually made of clear tempered glass which is sealed and evacuated and back-filled with a noble gas, typically argon and sometimes neon, in a process similar to the manufacturing of [[neon sign]]s.  The high voltage current causes the plasma inside the electrode to excite, emitting a glowing color when the wand operates and through which the spark emits. The appearance and process is identical to [[plasma globe]]s, though the net discharge is higher in order to create spark streamers external to the glass which cause the desired sensation to the skin.

[[File:Violet-wand-internal-electrodes.png|right|250px|thumb|An assortment of erotic use insertable Violet Wand attachments known as electrodes. The tempered and evacuated glass tubes are back-filled with noble gas, causing them to emit sparks and glow with various colors when the violet wand is powered.]]

One popular misconception is that violet wands produce [[ultraviolet]] light, and sometimes violet wands are erroneously called &quot;ultraviolet wands&quot;.  Violet wands do not produce measurable amounts of ultraviolet light, except at the point of the full-spectrum spark external to the glass electrode. With sufficient time in one spot, redness or mild burns can result from the arc's heat. The arcs do generate [[ozone]] and [[nitrogen oxide]]s, giving the skin the well known &quot;ozone smell&quot; similar to the smell of a lightning storm.  Violet wands can possibly ignite flammable materials and melt artificial fabrics such as pantyhose with certain accessories and settings.

==Methods of use==
A violet wand creates shock sensation when there is a gap between the electrode or the attachment and the body. As the wand is held near to the body, the spark will jump, providing the sensation. Full contact with an accessory creates a slightly warm sensation, but a violet wand provides a wide range of physical sensation properties with different settings and attachments. Some typical uses for a violet wand include temporary or permanent branding of the skin for [[body modification]], electrically charged impact with paddles or other conductive implements, electrified touch or massage, or erotic stimulation of the genitalia. Violet Wands can be used anywhere on the body but should not be used around the eyes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Juice&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|last= Abdul |first= Uncle |title= Juice: Electricity for Pleasure and Pain |year= 1998 |publisher= Greenery Press |location=San Francisco |isbn= 1-890159-06-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The following 'terms for techniques' were standardized by the International Violet Wand Guild c. 2005.

===Direct===
Users employ a violet wand by using various accessories which emit sparks for different physical sensations and purposes. These accessories include electrodes made of glass or metal and other conductive accessories and attachments.

===Indirect===
Utilizing a body contact accessory the person holding the contact becomes electrified to the touch. Any part of the body can be used to pass the arc to the recipient. Additionally the person holding the contact can utilize any conductive material as an accessory.

==See also==
{{commons category|Violet wand machines}}
* [[Erotic electrostimulation]]
* [[Glass dildo]]
* [[Sybian]]
* [[Transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{BDSM}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Violet Wand}}
[[Category:Sex toys]]
[[Category:BDSM equipment]]</text>
      <sha1>ajzwtnqgviniwo5ish2thbhrrlzoflf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
