<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>6262889</id>
    <revision>
      <id>700211422</id>
      <parentid>471380343</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-01-17T02:59:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cyberbot II</username>
        <id>16283967</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16214">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject GeorgiaUS|class=B|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Atlantic Coast Conference|class=B|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject College football|class=B|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Tennis|class=B|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject Georgia Tech|class=B|importance=High|sport=yes}}
}}
{{todo|3}}
==College Football WikiProject==
Articles about a school's athletics in general do not belong in the College football WikiProject. --[[User:Mecu|&lt;font color=&quot;CEBE70&quot;&gt;'''MECU'''&lt;/font&gt;]]≈&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Mecu|talk]]&lt;/small&gt; 15:45, 5 August 2006 (UTC)
:If there was an article about Georgia Tech football, though, you'd take it? —[[User:Disavian|Disavian]] ([[User talk:Disavian|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/Disavian|&lt;sub&gt;contribs&lt;/sub&gt;]]) 17:48, 8 November 2006 (UTC)

==Football Head Coaches==
This is the list I have so far, taken from {{t1|GTFootballCoach}}:
[[Chan Gailey]], [[Mac McWorter]], [[George O'Leary]], [[Bill Lewis (football)]], [[Bill Curry]], [[Pepper Rodgers]], [[Bill Fulcher]], [[Bud Carson]], [[Bobby Dodd]], [[William Alexander (football coach)]], [[John Heisman]], [[John McKee (football coach)]], [[Dr. Cyrus W. Strickler]], Collier, [[R.B. Nalley]], Finnegan, Borleske, [[Ernest E. West (football)]]

Anyone have a first name for the three that aren't wiki'd? —[[User:Disavian|Disavian]] ([[User talk:Disavian|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/Disavian|&lt;sub&gt;contribs&lt;/sub&gt;]]) 17:48, 8 November 2006 (UTC)

:Yeah, I purposely did not put their first names 'cause they were pretty unworthy of wikipedia.  But here they are:  Stanley E. &quot;Stan&quot; Borleske &amp; Casey C. Finnegan (1893-1894), no coach (assorted games 1896-1903), and a Mr. Collier (1899).  Collier was never named anything in the box scores besides &quot;Mr. Collier&quot; and Borleske and Finnegan were co-headcoaches.  Between the three men there were only 12 games and only 2 victories.  [[User:Excaliburhorn|Excaliburhorn]] 18:47, 8 November 2006

== [[2007 Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets basketball team]] ==

I really like the article on the [[2006 Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets football team]]; perhaps we can do the same job for basketball. I was going to link to [[The Technique]] article on the 2007 basketball lineup, but I can't find it. —[[User:Disavian|Disavian]] ([[User talk:Disavian|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/Disavian|&lt;sub&gt;contribs&lt;/sub&gt;]]) 04:35, 12 November 2006 (UTC)
:Found it! [http://technique.library.gatech.edu/pdfs/sports-2006-11-03.pdf 2007 Basketball Lineup] —[[User:Disavian|Disavian]] ([[User talk:Disavian|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/Disavian|&lt;sub&gt;contribs&lt;/sub&gt;]]) 04:38, 12 November 2006 (UTC)
::I'll start work on the '06-'07 basketball season once more people join the wikiproject and get more templates out there.  It's a bit of a hassle to set up all of the tables and such.  Sorry for being lazy.  -[[user:Excaliburhorn|Excaliburhorn]] 00:33 11/13/06 (UTC)
:::Can you link to the WikiProject and templates in question? —[[User:Disavian|Disavian]] ([[User talk:Disavian|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/Disavian|&lt;sub&gt;contribs&lt;/sub&gt;]]) 14:37, 13 November 2006 (UTC)
::::[[Wikipedia:WikiProject_College_Basketball|NCAA Bball Wikiproject]] not nearly as developed as [[Wikipedia:WikiProject_College_Football|NCAA Fball Wikiproject]].  It's not really kicked off yet but I'm sure it will once people stop focusing on football in a couple months.  I'll start up the GT bball page sooner or later.-[[user:Excaliburhorn|Excaliburhorn]] 03:18 11/14/06 (UTC)
:::::I am highly amused at the moment... I discovered that there are/were actually ''two'' college basketball projects. I categorized all of their resources, and threw a couple merge tags on that mess. :p —[[User:Disavian|Disavian]] ([[User talk:Disavian|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/Disavian|&lt;sub&gt;contribs&lt;/sub&gt;]]) 00:32, 16 November 2006 (UTC)

== GT Basketball ==

Just so you know, in the basketball section, with the information bar (what is it called anyways?), I added basketball to the end of where it said &quot;Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets&quot;. So now it says &quot;Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets Basketball&quot;. The reason for the change is I thought it was confusing.[[User:Bensp92|Bensp92]]
:Good call.  The formatting needs some severe help too.  There is way too much dead space and I'd also like to think that baseball and football deserve similar tables. [[user:Excaliburhorn|Excaliburhorn]] 18:20, 3-27-07
::I agree that the infobox looks bad there. I think fixing it requires removing the template or making [[Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets football]] and [[Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets basketball]]. —[[User:Disavian|Disavian]] ([[User talk:Disavian|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/Disavian|&lt;sub&gt;contribs&lt;/sub&gt;]]) 00:15, 28 March 2007 (UTC)
:::Fixed by making the latter article. —[[User:Disavian|Disavian]] ([[User talk:Disavian|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/Disavian|&lt;sub&gt;contribs&lt;/sub&gt;]]) 18:30, 20 May 2007 (UTC)

==All-Time Football Team==

I'm deleting the All-Time Football team because of two reasons: 1) It's very dated.  Not mentioning [[Calvin Johnson (American football)]], [[Marco Coleman]], [[Shawn Jones]], [[Joe Hamilton]], or [[Keith Brooking]] in an all-time list, to me, automatically debunks its credibility.  2) We need a [[Georgia Tech Football|GT Football]] article for things this specific.  Those are my thoughts. --[[User:Excaliburhorn|Excaliburhorn]] 00:57, 6 August 2007 (UTC)

:disagee. Just because you think it is date does not deter its relevance. On my page you said it was a &quot;list of players&quot;. Now you have changed your view. I don't think players who have come along does anything to debunk its credibility. This team can be found in the 2007 GT Media Guide. The SID of GT thinks it is relevant. I think the SID's opinion is more authoritative than Excaliburhorn. There will be a time where a new All-time team will be chosen, but the posting specifically says that it was chosen in 1991. Anyone would know that those who played after would not be eligble. I think it is relevant, useful, and interesting. I think other collegiate sites know all the &quot;ins and outs&quot; of picking all-time teams. I think the only one with a credibility issue is he who keeps deleting it. It does not have some guys he likes so he dismisses it. leave it alone. It is a piece of GT history. It is a historic fact. It is credible on its face and doubly so by GT keeping it is nthe media guide for 17 years.[[User:72.0.36.36|72.0.36.36]] 01:23, 6 August 2007 (UTC)

::A lot more people than me think of those guys I mentioned as GT greats.  I still think the list is dated and much too specific for this article.  The media guide lists a lot of different lists.  If we wanted to go the route you're proposing, we should be much more thorough and list all of the All-Americans, All-Academics, award winners, Heisman finalists, etc.. To me, Heisman finalists would be a better list because those guys were important on the national stage not just a GT fan poll.  It is interesting that they haven't updated that list in 17 years, however, but put Marco, Ken Swilling, and Little Joe in a 50th Anniversary Team in the same media guide.  I still think it's way too dated and specific for a Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets article.  If we make a GT football article, then I think it would be perfect.--[[User:Excaliburhorn|Excaliburhorn]] 01:50, 6 August 2007 (UTC)

:::I actually really like the idea of listing the multiple All-Americans and Heisman finalists just because those are more notable than a 17-year old GT fan poll that's only published in the GT media guide.  That would include people like [[Clint Castleberry]], Calvin, Eddie Lee, and more.  I think that'd give us a better perspective of history and it would make more sense to the casual reader.--[[User:Excaliburhorn|Excaliburhorn]] 02:30, 6 August 2007 (UTC)

::::Disagree. While listing AAs and heisman would be a good addition this is not an either/or situation. I think people have given out the real reason you don't want it on the site:  It does not contain certain recent players that you may be more familiar with. To me, that is not a valid reason for deletion. I think the example of other sites (many in the SEC and ACC) do have such entries. It shows what fans thought at the time--it is ahistorical and perfect for a georgia Tech Yellowjacket Article. IT is noted that it was chosen in 1991. That lets readers know when the poll tool place. What could be more fair?[[User:72.0.36.36|72.0.36.36]] 02:41, 6 August 2007 (UTC)

:::::[[Georgia Bulldogs]], [[Miami Hurricanes]], [[Clemson Tigers]], [[Duke Blue Devils]], [[NC State Wolfpack]], [[Maryland Terrapins]], [[Virginia Cavaliers]], [[Virginia Tech Hokies]], [[North Carolina Tar Heels]], [[Boston College Eagles]], and [[Florida State Seminoles]] do not list anything like that.  Wake Forest doesn't have an athletics page.  None of those teams list &quot;All-Time Teams&quot; and most of them are much better than this page.  This is an Athletic Department article not a football history page.  We NEED a GT Football page and this can be something we put on it.  Until another ACC team or ugag lists an All-Time team, I think we should leave it off.
::::::Secondly, I think that there are some people that are far more important to GT football that are not listed in that list.  To leave off Clint Castleberry is an injustice to GT football (the only retired number and Heisman finalist).  Shawn Jones and Joe Hamilton destroyed all of GT's QB records and were All-Americans.  Shawn WON a national title.  Joe was a Heisman runner-up.  Calvin Johnson destroyed all of GT's receiving records and was consensus All-American all 3 years.  That list in the media guide is just bad listing Scott Sisson over Luke Manget (most prolific GT kicker ever) or Jim Preas (222-0 kicker).  These aren't people I think are more important.  History, statistics, and the rest of the world think they are more notable but some GT fan poll in the early 90's is more important than what everyone else in the college football world thinks about GT (for all we know that poll could have 10 voters).--[[User:Excaliburhorn|Excaliburhorn]] 03:35, 6 August 2007 (UTC)

:::::::Okay after a little research, I found that this list really doesn't appreciate GT's rich football tradition but is rather a tribute to Bobby Dodd's players.  The oldest player on the list is George Morris of 1952.  So we're automatically excluding every player from Alexander and Heisman's coaching days, which includes two of our National Titles.  10 out of 24 of the players are from Bobby Dodd's tenure.  6 are from Pepper Rodgers' reign.  8 are from Carson, Curry, and Ross' tenures.  Historically speaking, this All-time list is terrible in that it crops out 60 years of pre-Dodd football and does not include any of O'Leary or Gailey's players.--[[User:Excaliburhorn|Excaliburhorn]] 04:08, 6 August 2007 (UTC)

==Proposed GT Football Article==
Here's a proposed format for the GT Football Article -
*The Beginning - The story of GT Football's beginnings with Leonard Wood and others.
*Heisman Comes to Tech - self explanatory
**National Title
**Stadium Construction
*The Plan - The story of William Alexander's tenure.
**National Title
*Dodd's Eight in a Row - Bobby Dodd's dominance in college football begins and ends.
**National Title
**'61 Alabam Incident
*Coaching Turnstyles - Carson, Fulcher, Rodgers, Curry
**Eddie McAshan
**Black Watch Defense
*Return to Glory and Scandal - 1990 UPI Title and O'Leary's resume debacle
*Modern Stuff - Chan Gailey Era

We can build off of this skeleton.  We need to include key games, major award winners, and stuff like that.  We need to search for some good archive photos, too. --[[User:Excaliburhorn|Excaliburhorn]] 04:15, 6 August 2007 (UTC)
:Sounds pretty comprehensive. I also need to work on the basketball article- I got started on it, then started to work on other projects and left it incomplete. Aside from a history section, what other topics would the history article cover? —[[User:Disavian|Disavian]] ([[User talk:Disavian|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/Disavian|&lt;sub&gt;contribs&lt;/sub&gt;]]) 05:07, 6 August 2007 (UTC)

==School songs==
Do these really need to be included? We have an article on [[Ramblin' Wreck from Georgia Tech]], and as for the others, I might suggest discussing them in the [[Georgia Tech traditions]] article instead. At the very least, it might be wise to develop some brief prose in lieu of the song lyrics as they don't really add anything to the article. Thoughts? [[User:LaMenta3|LaMenta3]] 14:24, 2 October 2007 (UTC)
:Each should have its own article. —[[User:Disavian|Disavian]] ([[User talk:Disavian|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/Disavian|&lt;sub&gt;contribs&lt;/sub&gt;]]) 15:57, 2 October 2007 (UTC)
::I considered that for about 2 seconds until I realized that &quot;Up With the White and Gold&quot; and the Alma Mater aren't really culturally notable enough on their own (as opposed to &quot;Ramblin' Wreck&quot; which is a widely-used and recognized fight song) to warrant articles of their own, which is why I suggested adding prose about them to an existing article. Also, as I'm fuzzy on the publication history of UWTWAG, there may also be copyright concerns over printing the lyrics. The Alma Mater is probably sufficiently old enough such that it's not a concern for that song, but every school has an Alma Mater song and few if any are really all that notable on their own. [[User:LaMenta3|LaMenta3]] 16:36, 2 October 2007 (UTC)
:::Good point. Thankfully, the lyrics were all written by the early 1920s and are therefore PD. —[[User:Disavian|Disavian]] ([[User talk:Disavian|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/Disavian|&lt;sub&gt;contribs&lt;/sub&gt;]]) 16:46, 2 October 2007 (UTC)

== New subarticles ==

We should make more subarticles/redirects, if only for disambiguation purposes, which would then let more content filter back into this article. I'm thinking the following should exist:
* [[Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets football]]
* [[Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets men's basketball]]
* [[Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets women's basketball]]
* [[Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets baseball]]
* [[Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets men's baseball]]
* [[Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets softball]]
* [[Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets women's softball]]
* [[Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets men's golf]]
* [[Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets volleyball]] (model: [[Hawaii Rainbow Wahine volleyball]])
* [[Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets women's volleyball]]
* [[Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets men's tennis]]
* [[Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets women's tennis]]
* [[Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets men's swimming and diving]]
* [[Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets women's swimming and diving]]
* [[Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets men's track and field]]
* [[Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets women's track and field]]
* [[Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets men's cross country]]
* [[Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets women's cross country]]
Am I missing any? [[User:Disavian|Disavian]] ([[User talk:Disavian|talk]]) 20:34, 14 January 2012 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=700211421 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20080507151251/http://www.irp.gatech.edu:80/apps/factbook/?page=18 to http://www.irp.gatech.edu/apps/factbook/?page=18

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 02:59, 17 January 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>3dzrh7ce58h2o7wupvd8bz4un7sqgk3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
