<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Moby-Dick</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>514385</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749525447</id>
      <parentid>749487738</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-14T20:08:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MackyBeth</username>
        <id>18286345</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Happy anniversary */ like a snow-hill</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9849">{{afd-merged-from|Fast-Fish and Loose-Fish|Fast-Fish and Loose-Fish|05 January 2015}}
{{Skip to talk}}
{{Talkheader}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 140K
|counter = 3
|minthreadsleft = 2
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Moby-Dick/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Auto archiving notice |bot=MiszaBot I |age= 90|units= days}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=19:38, 28 October 2008
|action1link=Talk:Moby-Dick/GA1
|action1result=not listed
|action1oldid=248240373
|currentstatus=FGAN
|topic=literature
}}
{{Vital article|level=4|topic=Art|class=B}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Novels|class=B|importance=Top|past-collaboration=May 1, 2007–June 1, 2007 |19thC-task-force=yes }}
{{WikiProject United States|class=B|importance=high|Cape-Cod=yes|Cape-Cod-importance=high}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2004-10-18|oldid1=6791631|date2=2004-11-14|oldid2=16335489|date3=2005-10-18|oldid3=25825270|date4=2006-10-18|oldid4=82115448|date5=2007-10-18|oldid5=164958864|date6=2008-10-18|oldid6=245679488|date7=2009-10-18|oldid7=320592003|date8=2010-10-18|oldid8=391356201|date9=2013-10-18|oldid9=577531511}}
{{User:WildBot/m04|sect={{User:WildBot/m03|1|prophet#Prophets in the Tanakh (Hebrew Bible)|Biblical prophet}}|m04}}
{{Auto archiving notice|bot=MiszaBot I|age=30|dounreplied=yes}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=Talk:Moby-Dick/Archive index
|mask=Talk:Moby-Dick/Archive &lt;#&gt;
|leading_zeros=0
|indexhere=yes}}

== What happened to the plot summary? ==

MackyBeth asks &quot;what happened to the plot summary in the last year or so?&quot; Just for reference, the changes from January 1, 2015 to earlier this month can be seen [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Moby-Dick&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=710818150&amp;oldid=641361533 in this comparison]. Cheers! [[User:CWH|ch]] ([[User talk:CWH|talk]]) 20:59, 20 March 2016 (UTC)
:Thanks! This is very convenient. Cheers MackyBeth
::You're very welcome! I now realize, looking at the section above, that it would be more useful to have  &quot;[https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Moby-Dick&amp;diff=711121479&amp;oldid=620902758 this comparison with August 2015].&quot; 

::Bear in mind that [[MOS:PLOT]] does not call for an &quot;elaborate&quot; plot summary, so we do not need to restore one. Also, quotations should not be used (or only sparingly) if they simply add color or flavor. ::The MOS here also says: 
:::Plot summaries can be written from the real-world perspective by referring to specific works or parts of works (&quot;In the first book&quot;, &quot;In Act II&quot;) or describing things from the author or creator's perspective (&quot;The author introduces&quot;, &quot;The story describes&quot;).
::A relevant application here is that it would be OK to avoid the question of who the narrator is. The first sentence of &quot;Plot&quot; could be something like &quot;The novel opens with Ishmael traveling from Manhatten to NB to sign on as a sailor on a whaling ship.&quot; For Cetology&quot;, instead of saying &quot;Ishmael discusses...,&quot; we could say &quot;The Chapter 'Cetology' discusses the natural history of the whale. The crew members are....&quot;[[User:CWH|ch]] ([[User talk:CWH|talk]]) 04:33, 21 March 2016 (UTC)
::Let me be clear that I have no intention of restoring the plot summary of 2014. You have been making sensible tightening edits that were needed. A host of other users have also been tinkering with it, however, so I just plan to check if no errors were introduced, nothing more. The wording you proposed to avoid the impression that Ishmael's role as narrator is never interrupted is worth taking up by introducing terms as Ahab's soliloquy etc [[User:MackyBeth|MackyBeth]] ([[User talk:MackyBeth|talk]]) 09:14, 21 March 2016 (UTC)
:::The book is big, and I think the reader will expect a lengthy plot summary. If it is useful to break the plot summary down to sections, I propose we use the 1851 British three-decker as a point of reference, so that three different sections are created: Volume 1 (Ch.....), Volume 2 etc. In that way we have a historically justified division rather than something by the page editors's own arbitrary judgment. [[User:MackyBeth|MackyBeth]] ([[User talk:MackyBeth|talk]]) 15:08, 23 March 2016 (UTC)
:::Good to be thinking about this creatively, but first, I'm not clear why the reader needs a longer plot summary -- to be sure, we agree that MD needs and deserves more than ''The Old Man and the Sea''! But we also don't want a Reader's Digest version that includes everything that happens. The advice on plot summaries [[WP:PLOTSUM]] is sensible, though not strict policy:
::::''The description should be thorough enough for the reader to get a sense of what happens and to fully understand the impact of the work and the context of the commentary about it. The summary must be concise because Wikipedia's coverage of works of fiction should be about more than just the plot. Plot summaries that are too long and too detailed can be hard to read and are as unhelpful as those that are too short. Finding the right balance requires careful editorial discretion and discussion.''

::::This guideline also warns against &quot;spoilers,&quot; though I think it's OK to reveal that Ishmael survived!
:::We should thank MackyBeth once again for thinking &quot;outside the box,&quot; but I'm also not clear why a reader would find it helpful to have the plot summary organized by the volumes of the British edition, which they are not likely to have at hand. The present organization might be improved by more attention to the topic sentences of each paragraph, so that readers could run theirs eyes down the page and see how the plot runs along.
:::::Once again, I have no intention of making the plot summary any longer than it already is. I am just suggesting that if anyone should find that the current one should be broken down into sections, then this is an objective way to do it. I studied the guidelines for plot summaries carefully when I wrote the plot summary, which is precisely why the plot summary contains some quotations. The main things are, first MD is twice as long as most other novels, and two it does not have a plot at all, just a sequence of events. That makes it hard to tell which events are more important than others. So I used Robert Gale's book as a guide for the plot summary, to make sure nothing important is left out. As the guidelines say, the plot summary should enable readers to follow the rest of the article, and amends may be made accordingly. Some elements still not touched upon when the article is ready for GA review may eventually be removed from the summary, while others now missing can be added if touched upon in other sections. [[User:MackyBeth|MackyBeth]] ([[User talk:MackyBeth|talk]]) 17:50, 23 March 2016 (UTC)

*{{ping|MackyBeth}} Could you please explain why 'plot' section [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Moby-Dick&amp;oldid=prev&amp;diff=744768758#Plot does not need] to be referenced? --[[User:Mhhossein|&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Aharoni&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#002E63&quot;&gt;M&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#2E5894&quot;&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#318CE7&quot;&gt;hossein&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Mhhossein|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#056608&quot;&gt;'''talk'''&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 13:13, 17 October 2016 (UTC)
** No problem, [[User:Mhhossein|Mhhossein]]. In [[MOS:PLOT]], the next-to-last paragraph begins: ''The plot summary for a work, on a page about that work, does not need to be sourced with in-line citations, as it is generally assumed that the work itself is the primary source for the plot summary.'' Plot summaries are the only section in articles on novels/plays/films that need not have sources, and should provide a basic summary with zero interpretative/analytic remarks, not even something incontestible as &quot;Ishmael, who takes his name from the Old Testament&quot;. [[User:MackyBeth|MackyBeth]] ([[User talk:MackyBeth|talk]]) 15:05, 17 October 2016 (UTC)
*** Thanks a lot [[User:MackyBeth|MackyBeth]], I didn't know that. --[[User:Mhhossein|&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Aharoni&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#002E63&quot;&gt;M&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#2E5894&quot;&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#318CE7&quot;&gt;hossein&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Mhhossein|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#056608&quot;&gt;'''talk'''&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 15:55, 17 October 2016 (UTC)

== Ahab's previous voyage ==

In the opening paragraph, it states, &quot;...revenge on Moby Dick, the white whale which on the previous whaling voyage destroyed his ship and severed his leg at the knee.&quot;

That's incorrect. Ahab's boat was destroyed (a common-enough occurrence that it is probably not worth mentioning in the article), but not his ship. Was his ship at that time not this self-same Pequod? Did not Bildad and Peleg serve under Old Thunder himself on that very ship? Hast thou clapped eyes on the book, shipmate? 

http://www.powermobydick.com/Moby018.html, Bildad says to Peleg,
&quot;...Tell me, when this same Pequod here had her three masts overboard in that typhoon on Japan, that same voyage when thou went mate with Captain Ahab, did'st thou not think of Death and the Judgment then?&quot;

[[User:Eshafto|Eshafto]] ([[User talk:Eshafto|talk]]) 22:28, 26 October 2016 (UTC)

:Keen eye, everybody else overlooked this error. Of course the ship could not have been destroyed at the previous voyage, because in that case it would not have been the previous but the last voyage.[[User:MackyBeth|MackyBeth]] ([[User talk:MackyBeth|talk]]) 17:04, 27 October 2016 (UTC)

== Happy anniversary ==

Today Moby-Dick is 165 years old. [[User:MackyBeth|MackyBeth]] ([[User talk:MackyBeth|talk]]) 15:31, 14 November 2016 (UTC)
::Aye, and when he blows, let his blast blow out the candles, the three spemacetti candles and a few more![[User:CWH|ch]] ([[User talk:CWH|talk]]) 16:24, 14 November 2016 (UTC)
:::There she blows!-there she blows--A hump like a snow-hill! [[User:MackyBeth|MackyBeth]] ([[User talk:MackyBeth|talk]]) 20:08, 14 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>2ngvagbr9gwzvv91xtefffntovkf4g7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
