<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:War and Peace</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>155944</id>
    <revision>
      <id>739390073</id>
      <parentid>709616526</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-14T11:44:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot (v1.2.4)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14319">{{Talk header}}
{{Vital article|level=4|topic=Art|class=B}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Novels|class=B|importance=Top|19thC-task-force=yes|19thC-importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Russia|class=B|importance=Top|lit=yes}}
{{WikiProject Philosophy|importance=mid|class=c|literature=yes}}
{{WikiProject Pritzker-GLAM|class=B |importance=top }}
{{WP1.0|v0.7=pass|class=B|category=Langlit|importance=High}}
}}
{{Napoleonic fiction}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{talkarchivenav}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 2
|algo = old(365d)
|archive = Talk:War and Peace/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Auto archiving notice |bot=MiszaBot I |age= |units= 1 year}}
== Discussion of whether the title of the book is translated properly and related issues ==

This section may need some reordering, as it combines several parallel discussions, '''all of it eventually resolved in the obvious direction of maintaining ''War and Peace'' as the title of Lev Tolstoy's famous novel.'''  If you feel you must say more about it, this is the section to do so.  --[[User:Levalley|Levalley]] ([[User talk:Levalley|talk]]) 20:11, 15 March 2009 (UTC)LeValley



'''This section really needs to be pared down, it interrupts the larger discussion.'''--[[User:Levalley|Levalley]] ([[User talk:Levalley|talk]]) 22:01, 16 March 2009 (UTC)LeValley


The &quot;War and the World&quot; idea is a ridiculous urban legend long postdating Tolstoy's time, and there is not a shred of evidence for it; if it is to be included in the article, it should be moved to the &quot;Popular Culture&quot; section and its legendary status made clear. [[User:Languagehat|Languagehat]] ([[User talk:Languagehat|talk]]) 18:18, 5 July 2008 (UTC)



[[Image:Tolstoy - War and Peace - third edition, 1873.png|Third edition, decades before the Soviets|thumb]] 
: This is a popular urban legend in Russia, but it's too good to be true.  The book was originally titled ВОЙНА И МИРЪ.  It's true that the '[[Hard sign|Ъ]]' was dropped, but the title was always a И and not an I.  It's plausible because the word for society (or ''the people'' or, in some senses, ''the world'') really did change into the same word as peace.  It's just the book was never titled with that word.  Here's another picture purportedly of a first edition binding[http://www.theworldsgreatbooks.com/tolstoi.htm]. --[[User:JayHenry|JayHenry]] ([[User talk:JayHenry|talk]]) 01:57, 15 August 2008 (UTC)





I think &quot;secular society&quot; is something of an overtranslation. Would you really say that &quot;secular society&quot; was the primary meaning of &quot;міръ&quot;? The meaning is &quot;world,&quot; which may be used as a way of referring to secular society. This connection carries across into English. See for example [4] 5a, 5b, also many Bible verses [5] such as John 17.9. The adjective &quot;worldly&quot; illustrates the association of &quot;world&quot; with the secular part of humanity. This sense of the word &quot;world&quot; has come to English and Russian from the Greek &quot;cosmos,&quot; which was used with the same range of meanings in the New Testament. Therefore, the English word &quot;world&quot; includes the meaning you're trying to get across for &quot;мир.&quot; The current text is misleading, since it makes it appear that &quot;міръ&quot; exclusively meant &quot;secular society.&quot; The primary meaning &quot;world&quot; is totally lost. --[[User:Reuben|Reuben]] 01:06, 8 June 2006 (UTC)
:The topic of the section is confusion is between the two described meanings ''as it is described there''. Any other meanings of the word &quot;mir&quot; are irrelevant. Your change was misinformed, based on general linguistic considerations, rather than on events, therefore it was reverted. On the other hand, the text is unreferenced, so I added the &quot;fact&quot; tag.  `'[[user:mikkalai|mikka]] [[user talk:mikkalai|(t)]] 01:08, 8 June 2006 (UTC)
::&quot;My change&quot; was simply a revert of somebody else's edit, which had been made without comment or explanation.  As a compromise, I suggest restoring &quot;world&quot; and making note of the fact that this word includes within its range of meaning &quot;secular society&quot; (as the English word &quot;world&quot; also does).  The current text is quite misleading to anyone who doesn't already have some familiarity with these words.  As for sources, I'm not sure what you think needs to be supported.  From the placement of the &quot;fact&quot; tag, it looks like you want a source for the existence of the urban legend.  However, it seems likely that you instead want something confirming that the urban legend is wrong.  Please clarify this, and see the first link under &quot;Other information.&quot;  Do you find that inadequate? --[[User:Reuben|Reuben]] 01:23, 8 June 2006 (UTC)
:::I have found a reputable reference, which quite probably was the source of


I have just reverted an edit by [[User:Riphead]] removing the final hard mark from мир in the title, on the basis that Tolstoy himself spelled it миръ (it was the spelling reform of 1918 which abolished final hard marks). But I would like to enquire whether there's a general policy regarding spelling reforms (in any language, not just Russian). When (as in this case) a work, or indeed a person, predates a spelling reform, should we be giving their names using modern spelling conventions or using the spelling which prevailed at the time? I have come across this issue elsewhere, without ever finding out whether there is in fact a Wikipedia policy on this. Does anyone know? [[User:Vilcxjo|Vilĉjo]] 16:20, 19 September 2007 (UTC)

::I cannot find any policy on orthographic changes (in Cyrillic or elsewhere).  However, since 1918, Russians have used the new orthography - although the ''pronunciation'' of words proceeded as it always does, with language passed on in language communities (and Moscow dialect and Petersburg dialect remaining, as usual, almost indistinguishable except to very discerning ears).  Ultimately, it doesn't matter, sound-wise, which orthography is used - although it is possible that in the deep past, the word &quot;Mir&quot; was pronounced differently (indeed, it's very likely, sense sound changes are systematic).  If anyone knows of a Wikipolicy on this, please advise.  I'd assume that all modern languages get to have their own spellings, and that if Russians spell it without the hard sign, we should too (no different from changing theatre to theater).--[[User:Levalley|Levalley]] ([[User talk:Levalley|talk]]) 18:35, 15 March 2009 (UTC)LeValley

A Russian academic friend of mine has pointed out that the actual translation of Leo Tolsoy’s novel is not “War and Peace”, but rather – “War and Society”. 
 
In older Russian language, before the reform of 1918, there were two types of “I”;
 
1). Hard “I”, in Russian -  МИР (sounds “MIR”), meaning “peace”.
 
2). Soft “I”,  in Russian - МIР (sounds “MIR” but somewhat softer), a different word, meaning “society”.  

A little bombshell, perhaps? [[User:Rif Winfield|Rif Winfield]] ([[User talk:Rif Winfield|talk]]) 23:31, 27 May 2012 (UTC)
::That's an urban legend, see comments above or an article in Russian. I really think there should be a special section in main article (something like &quot;disputes on title&quot;), because the legend seems to persist.  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/81.200.30.144|81.200.30.144]] ([[User talk:81.200.30.144|talk]]) 08:39, 7 April 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== length of the novel--not seventh longest ==

The article currently says:
War and Peace is well known as being one of the longest novels ever written, though not the longest. It is actually the seventh longest novel ever written in a Latin or Cyrillic based alphabet and is subdivided into four books or volumes, each with sub parts containing many chapters.

The word longest is a hyperlink to https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Longest_novel which lists it as the 16th longest book.  I do not know enough about the alphabets used in the longer books, although eleven books are longer as English or English translations.

I do not intend to edit the article since my expertise is too limited in this area, but I wanted to point out an apparent inaccuracy.
[[User:Jfehribach|Jfehribach]] ([[User talk:Jfehribach|talk]]) 23:45, 14 October 2013 (UTC)

== audio in Russian ==
I found this with War and Peace read aloud in Russian.  All Russian; the French, Italian and German are not reproduced.  http://finz.ru/music/%D2%EE%EB%F1%F2%EE%E9+%C2%EE%E9%ED%E0+%C8+%CC%E8%F0+%D2%EE%EC+1
[[Special:Contributions/71.163.117.143|71.163.117.143]] ([[User talk:71.163.117.143|talk]]) 20:06, 28 January 2014 (UTC)
: There is another version here: https://archive.org/details/Tolstoy_Lev_-_Voyna_i_mir_Klyukvin_Aleksandr_2013 [[Special:Contributions/108.18.136.147|108.18.136.147]] ([[User talk:108.18.136.147|talk]]) 13:07, 24 February 2015 (UTC)

== Plot Summary and Book Structure ==

I am having trouble following this article's plot summary and how it describes ''War and Peace'' is structured.  As someone reading this book, I have two main problems with the Plot Summary section:

1.  The article records four volumes, not three.  Both copies of War and Peace that I have seen - the 1982 Penguin's Classics (might be 1978, my memory is a bit fuzzy on that) and the 1993 Wordsworth Classics editions - are organized into three volumes split into fifteen books and hundreds of chapters total, not including the two epilogues.  Unsurprisingly, because of this there are parts of the summary in the incorrect places compared to my copies.  For example, for me Nikolenka Bolkonsky is born in Volume I, Book IV and Pierre joins the Freemasons in the next book after, but the article implies both are well into Volume II.  Are there more qualified alternative versions of this book that I'm unaware of that have the article's version?

2.  The Plot Summary seems to focus on introducing characters and their personality over the novel's actual plot/action.  Now, granted, I'm new to Wikipedia and ''War and Peace'' has lots of characters to know.  But I have a feeling that this is a bit anomalous to most other novel summaries here.

I haven't made any edits yet for several reasons. It feels like too big of a change without establishing any kind of agreement or consensus first.  And like I said, I'm also new here and I haven't finished the book yet, so I don't feel too qualified to do anything like this by myself yet.  - [[User:Borderlandor|Borderlandor]] ([[User talk:Borderlandor|talk]]) 05:46, 16 May 2015 (UTC)

EDIT: This whole page's structure is pretty irregular too.  I went ahead and made a few small changes to the plot summary section.  [[User:Borderlandor|Borderlandor]] ([[User talk:Borderlandor|talk]]) 03:25, 4 August 2015 (UTC)
:Hi, the standard critical edition in Russian is divided into four volumes, not three (the Zaidenshnur text I think). I've reverted it to a 4-book format. Your editions, the Penguin and the Wordsworth, are based on outdated editions of the novel. [[User:DORC|DORC]] ([[User talk:DORC|talk]]) 15:40, 2 November 2015 (UTC)

¶ I have very deliberately deleted an altogether unjustified &quot;citation needed&quot; immediately after the comment, in the summary of Book 4, that Pierre's wife, the Countess Helene, died of an overdose of an abortifacient, expressed in an unambiguous euphemism.  The reading of the text of the novel itself shows that no citation is necessary.  This from the beginning of chapter 2 of book 12 (&quot;1812&quot;):

::Officially, at large gatherings, everyone said that Countess Bezukhova had died of a terrible attack of angina pectoris, but in intimate circles details were mentioned of how the private physician of the Queen of Spain had prescribed small doses of a certain drug to produce a certain effect; but Helene, tortured by the fact that the old count suspected her and that her husband to whom she had written (that wretched, profligate Pierre) had not replied, had suddenly taken a very large dose of the drug, and had died in agony before assistance could be rendered her. It was said that Prince Vasili and the old count had turned upon the Italian, but the latter had produced such letters from the unfortunate deceased that they had immediately let the matter drop.

Res ipsa loquitur. [[User:Sussmanbern|Sussmanbern]] ([[User talk:Sussmanbern|talk]]) 07:47, 10 February 2016 (UTC)

== Comparing translations ==

I am sure that there must be dozens of academics, scholars and critics with views on the relative merits of the various different translations of War and Peace into English but, at the moment, the 'Comparing Translations' section contains just one person's opinion.  If this represents a general consensus then some evidence of this should be provided, if not then I feel there should be a wider discussion
[[User:RichWA|RichWA]] ([[User talk:RichWA|talk]]) 19:28, 18 January 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:2|one external link|2 external links}} on [[War and Peace]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=739390071 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Replaced archive link https://web.archive.org/web/2008-12-20/http://www.sharedexperience.org.uk/whatson3.asp?levone=1&amp;levtwo=68&amp;levthree=87&amp;allowRev=0 with https://web.archive.org/web/20081220045244/http://www.sharedexperience.org.uk:80/whatson3.asp?levone=1&amp;levtwo=68&amp;levthree=87&amp;allowRev=0 on http://www.sharedexperience.org.uk/whatson3.asp?levone=1&amp;levtwo=68&amp;levthree=87&amp;allowRev=0
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.pacificaradioarchives.org/05funddrive/war.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 11:44, 14 September 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>og3tr6j11ook4j34rao62qp5u5gijlw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
