<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:The Invisible Man</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>277593</id>
    <revision>
      <id>717469882</id>
      <parentid>717469492</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-04-27T22:13:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dhtwiki</username>
        <id>9475572</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>putting sections in better chronological order</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10412">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Novels |class=B |importance=High |19thC-task-force=yes |listas=Invisible Man, The}}
{{WikiProject Television |class=B |importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Science Fiction |class=B |type=Article |importance=High}}
{{WikiProject United Kingdom}}
}}

__TOC__
This page contains an error that I cannot correct as I do not know how to create a new page. The error lies in the statement that &quot;The Invisible Man&quot; is also the title of a book by Ralph Ellison. However, a quick perusal of any credible list of his works will reveal that the book's title is, in fact, &quot;Invisible Man.&quot; The article 'the' is not included in the title of Ellison's novel. A small but important point.

:Details on creating new pages are listed [[Wikipedia:How_to_start_a_page|here]]. - [[User:Hephaestos|Hephaestos]] 06:37 26 Jul 2003 (UTC)

== Book ==

This article doesn't mention any thing about the book by H. G. Wells.

The first name Hawley is an attribution of Alan Moore in the &quot;League of Extraordinary Gentlemen&quot;, not from the Wells scientific romance.

Quite right -- I've removed the reference after checking the book -- he's just &quot;Griffin&quot; in the original. [[User:Arcoddath|AxS]] 15:07, 10 Jun 2005 (UTC)

It's true that this article doesn't talk about the book itself. Very odd, as the book should be the primary focus of such an article. [[User:Sheehan|Sheehan]] 10:45, 11 January 2006 (UTC)

It's my opinion that this page needs to be fleshed out. (No pun intended.) A full plot synopsis should be created, among references to other literary creations, like &quot;League of Extraordinary Gentlemen&quot;. Also, a separate page should be created for the movies/TV series. It doesn't do justice to one of science fiction's classics to be briefly mentioned in one paragraph, then devote the rest of the page to the video creations. 

And if no one else will do it, then I will when I have time. [[User:JiangWei23|JiangWei23]] 21:30, 6 May 2006 (UTC)

The 1970s BBC TV series starring David McCallum seems not to be not mentioned here. Even though this article is linked from the David McCallum article in Wikipedia! I leave it to those maintaining to look into this and update as appropriate.

==&quot;Project Quicksilver&quot;==
What exactly is the ridiculous article [[Project Quicksilver]] about? I'm removing the link; if it's about a TV show, book or movie, it should make that clear instead of this [[false document]] stuff. -[[User:DynSkeet|DynSkeet]] [[User talk:DynSkeet|(talk)]] 14:35, August 29, 2005 (UTC)

== &quot;Reign of Terror&quot; ==

Is this phrase capitalized in the novel?  It seems to me it should be lower case, as [[Reign of Terror]] capitalized generally refers to the bloody reprisals of the revolutionary government under Robespierre in the French Revolution. [[User:Canonblack|Canonblack]] 01:07, 3 August 2006 (UTC)

I believe it is, though I'm not sure. I know at one point he refers to his reign as &quot;the Terror&quot;, with the word capitalized. [[User:JiangWei23|JiangWei23]] 07:18, 26 November 2006 (UTC)

It is capitalized. &quot;Not wanton killing, but a judicious laying. The point is, they know there is an Invisible Man--as well as we know there is an Invisible Man. And that Invisible Man, Kemp, must now establish a Reign of Terror. Yes; no doubt it's startling. But I mean it. A Reign of Terror,&quot; (p. 135). [[User:MelissaDRuhl|MelissaDRuhl]] ([[User talk:MelissaDRuhl|talk]]) 20:57, 13 December 2012 (UTC)

== Invisible Man characters ==

There are a number of Wikipedia articles about characters from the novel--there are 13 in the category &quot;The Invisible Man characters&quot;, though some of them are from the movie version.  Many of these are very minor characters, as indicated by the fact that a bunch of them don't need to be mentioned in the main article's plot summary.  For those characters that are mentioned, including [[Griffin (The Invisible Man)]], the articles are mostly plot summary, leading to considerable duplication.

I'm thinking that most if not all of these articles can't really justify their independent existence--that they should be turned into a character section in this article, or if that seems awkward, perhaps a separate [[Invisible Man characters]] article. [[User:Nareek|Nareek]] 04:50, 9 September 2006 (UTC)

: I agree. I am a fan of the film and the book but I think that the separate character articles are prime candidates indeed for 'articles for deletion'. [[User:Colin4C|Colin4C]] 09:17, 11 September 2006 (UTC)

Additionally, in Chapter 6 Mr. Hall is refered to as &quot;George&quot; by his wife, while Mrs. Hall is refered to as &quot;Janny' (likely an unconfirmed 'dialect' spelling of Jenny). --[[User:Redknight|RedKnight]] ([[User talk:Redknight|talk]]) 17:20, 12 October 2010 (UTC)

== The Invisible Man's eyes ==

Apologies, I just reverted the statement about the Invisible Man's eyes remaining visible. I was under the impression that only that cat upon which he performed the experiment retained visibility in the eyes, but I just checked the book and he does indeed state that an 'attenuated pigment' still remains. Sorry for the confusion. [[User:Mosquitor|Mosquitor]] Saturday 14 October 2006, 1.43 pm (UTC)

After reviewing the passages in the book in which Griffen speaks of the state of his/the cat's eyes after turning invisible, it seems that only the [[Tapetum lucidum]] (which is a a reflecting layer behind the retina) remains.
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Yes, the tapetum. It didn't go. After I'd given the stuff to bleach the blood and done certain other things to her, I gave the beast opium, and put her and the pillow she was sleeping on, on the apparatus. And after all the rest had faded and vanished, there remained two little ghosts of her eyes.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
He refers to it as iridescent (which it is, like the Blue Morpho's wings which the tapetum article refers to), and I would assume that the 'attenuated pigment' also refers to the tapetum. Note that Griffen states that the 'attenuated pigment' &lt;blockquote&gt;
still remained ''behind the retina'' of my eyes, fainter than mist.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
And thus, not synonymous with the retina.

Also, the quote/phrase &quot;colored part of the back of his eyes&quot; does not appear anywhere in the book to my knowledge. Where did it come from? I'm removing these statements about Griffen being able to see (scientifically).
'''-Spike (I don't have an account)'''&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/67.70.10.187|67.70.10.187]] ([[User talk:67.70.10.187|talk]]) 23:48, 6 January 2007‎&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;

== Characters ==

There's no need for each minor character to have their own section, or even for them to be detailed at all. For example, there's little value in stating ''Mrs. Hall is a very friendly, down-to-earth woman who enjoys socializing with her guests''. Virtually all articles about novels that have become Featured Articles don't have these character details, and neither do other articles about H.G. Wells novels, so they should be removed to bring this article into line with other novel articles and allow for improvement in other areas. Any relevant character information should be mentioned in the plot summary. [[User:Magiclite|Magiclite]] 20:30, 13 September 2007 (UTC)

:The whole bio section on Griffin is just additional plot details. Since there is already a main article, that needs to be gutted and rewritten. --[[User:Tysto|Tysto]] ([[User talk:Tysto|talk]]) 14:39, 12 December 2007 (UTC)
: I went ahead and did this. --[[User:Tysto|Tysto]] ([[User talk:Tysto|talk]]) 15:08, 12 December 2007 (UTC)

::There's still too much duplicated plot information in the character descriptions.  There are also a lot of irrelevant references to Alan Moore and the various adaptations of the book, all of which have their own articles.  The film and television serial sections about Kemp belong in the 'Adaptations' heading if they belong anywhere. --[[Special:Contributions/90.214.206.203|90.214.206.203]] ([[User talk:90.214.206.203|talk]]) 11:34, 5 May 2009 (UTC)

==278 pages?==
That's a lot of pages for a [[novella]]. The version I read was 150 pages and I doubt it was abridged. On Amazon.com, Signet Classics' version has 192 pages and Dover Thrift Editions' version has 112 and neither are abridged.[[Special:Contributions/70.225.37.67|70.225.37.67]] ([[User talk:70.225.37.67|talk]]) 22:32, 11 April 2010 (UTC)
:Different size distinctions for works of text are defined by number of words, not number of pages.  The number of words is invariable (barring condensation or revision).  The number of pages is dependent upon all of the following:
{{quote|* the size of the paper
* the size of the margins
* the size of the type face used
* the chosen kerning (space between characters and words, which is variable)
* the chosen leading (space between lines of text, also variable)
* the style of paragraph formatting used (is the first line indented, is a line of space left between paragraphs, how is the text justified, etc.)
* the use and number of interstitial or blank pages within the layout, including flyleafs, prefaces, introductions, dedications, tables of contents and title pages, not all of which are present in all editions}}
:The notation of 149 pages in the infobox is presumably for the first hardcover edition, a fairly trivial factoid that is certainly not accurate for all subsequent editions. [[Special:Contributions/12.233.147.42|12.233.147.42]] ([[User talk:12.233.147.42|talk]]) 21:22, 26 April 2016 (UTC)

== The Introduction Paragraphs ==

I think that to reveal that the main character &lt;nowiki&gt;&quot;********* ************** *** ****** *** *******&quot;&lt;/nowiki&gt; at the end of the history is a massive spoiler to the book, i'm deletimg that part. [[User:Nicrorus|Nicrorus]] ([[User talk:Nicrorus|talk]]) 04:04, 7 February 2012 (UTC)

==Plot mistake blood visible is not a plot mistake==

I've removed the line about it being a plot mistake that you can see the invisible man's blood.  He himself explains &quot;Gets visible as it coagulates, I see.&quot;  That is to say it is made visible by a chemical change  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/92.21.0.203|92.21.0.203]] ([[User talk:92.21.0.203|talk]]) 17:34, 14 April 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;</text>
      <sha1>ccu9kcydlkjfzrzzq7wkwx8ythlrg2u</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
