<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Ultrasonic welding</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>6762594</id>
    <revision>
      <id>664525717</id>
      <parentid>664525630</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-05-29T06:25:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SineBot</username>
        <id>4936590</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Signing comment by [[Special:Contributions/50.104.194.10|50.104.194.10]] - &quot;Crowd Control Weapons seen to act via ultrasound technlogy&quot;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9431">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Engineering|class=B|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Metalworking|class=B|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Physics|class=B|importance=low|acoustics=yes}}
{{WikiProject Technology|class=B|importance=High| b1 = y| b2 = y | b3 = y | b4 = y | b5 = y | b6 = y}}
}}

==Pictures==
{{Image requested|of=ultrasonic welding equipment|technology}}

I reworked the history section, but this article is still seriously lacking pictures.  If someone would add some it would be much appreciated.[[User:Marylee23|Marylee23]] ([[User talk:Marylee23|talk]]) 14:30, 9 April 2008 (UTC)

==History and Pictures==
The reference article for &quot;the first ultrasonic welded car&quot; is unverifiable. A car is never mentioned in that article. I was never able to find a reference to a vehicle made entirely out of ultrasonic plastic welding.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Mazerinth|Mazerinth]] ([[User talk:Mazerinth|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Mazerinth|contribs]]) 18:37, 30 November 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
I was hoping someone would be able to help me flush out the history section and maybe add some pictures.  Let me know what you think.--[[User:Marylee23|Marylee23]] 01:28, 5 March 2008

:The earliest reference I can find from the US Patent Office is Patent #2891180 issued in June 1959.  The patent shows the original design, and confirm that this was indeed awarded to Aeroprojects (now Sonobond).  I can't confirm if there were designs before this or if something like this existed in another country, but the above listed patent is the earliest I could find.  There are some pictures in this patent as well, but I would suggest using more recent ultrasonic welding device patents for a picture.  I actually have a picture of the process in my manufacturing textbook, but I don't know if it would be legal to scan that in or what.  [[Special:Contributions/128.180.77.6|128.180.77.6]] ([[User talk:128.180.77.6|talk]]) 03:12, 7 April 2010 (UTC)

::Unfortunately scanning images is illegal unless it was printed before 1923 in the US. Same goes for patents. I've got an ultrasonic press here at work that I can try and take a picture of when I get a chance. [[User:Wizard191|Wizard191]] ([[User talk:Wizard191|talk]]) 12:40, 7 April 2010 (UTC)

:::After doing a little more patent digging, I found that #2891180 is a vibration mount, and is not the earliest such device.  The method for ultrasonic welding seems to be first mentioned in #2,522,082 in Feb 1945.  Raytheon has a patent for a general vibration device (#2,651,148) from Nov. 1949 which they claim can be used for &quot;bonding plastics and other materials by localized heating&quot;, among other things.  The first patent to use ultrasonic welding with respect to metals was Aeroprojects (Sonobond) in April 1956, but they do not seem to be the first to pioneer this process in any other regard. I will continue to read up on patent searches and let you know how it goes.  [[Special:Contributions/128.180.55.169|128.180.55.169]] ([[User talk:128.180.55.169|talk]]) 01:15, 9 April 2010 (UTC)

::::Cool! Thanks for the research. [[User:Wizard191|Wizard191]] ([[User talk:Wizard191|talk]]) 12:26, 9 April 2010 (UTC)

==Possible Additions==

I would like to make some changes to this article possibly including changing the history section or adding a section.  Please let me know what you think.  --[[User:Marylee23|Marylee23]] 05:49, 19 February 2008

==Uhhm==

&quot;Although there is heating, it is not enough to melt the base materials. Vibrations are introduced along the joint being welded.....Ultrasonic welding appeared in the mid 60's and is rapidly developing. In its infancy, only hard plastics could be welded because their properties were the only fitting—they were acoustically conductive and had a low melting point.&quot;


sooo....--[[User:Deglr6328|Deglr6328]] 09:15, 30 August 2006 (UTC)

:Yes, that quote seems self-contradictory. Also ''&quot;The vibrations are introduced across the joint to be welded. ... Vibrations are introduced along the joint being welded.&quot;'' also seems self-contradictory.
: Could someone clarify this?
: Is it really true that ultrasonic welding of metals is so very different from ultrasonic welding of thermoplastics?
: --[[User:68.0.120.35|68.0.120.35]] 23:49, 25 April 2007 (UTC)


The difference between ultrasonic plastics welding and metals welding is one of 90 degrees.  In a plastics welder the parts are vibrated in a compressive manner.  In most cases, the plastics welder is a pneumatic press although it could be hydraulic or mechanical.  The parts are squeezed together with a certain amount of static force.  Then an ultrasonic vibration in line with the compressive force is introduced.  Crudely put, it's like a very low-amplitude, very fast, jack hammer.  The plastic at the mating surfaces melts and is squashed together. 

A metals welder vibrates the material in a shear or scrubbing manner.  The joint most always will be some form of a lap joint.  The press squeezes the two overlapping pieces together just as in the plastics welder.  However, instead of &quot;hammering&quot; in-line with the force, the vibration is introduced at right angles to the clamping force.  So as the materials are being squeezed together (say, vertically), they are also being ultrasonically scrubbed at the mating surfaces (horizontally).  The metal never melts.  It just gets plastic like putty.  The mating surfaces rapidly diffuse together,all in less than a second, generally.  

The various manufacturers of metals welders predominantly derive their metals welders from their plastics welder designs.  One manufacturer does it uniquely differently but it's somewhat more complicated.  Common uses for ultrasonic metals welders are wire splicing, foil splicing, welding electrical contacts to internal components of things like relays, capacitors, and circuit breakers, and some uses for sealing refrigeration tubing in the manufacturing of refrigerators and freezers.[[User:Chucktronix|Chucktronix]] 19:39, 7 August 2007 (UTC)

== Redundancy ==

&quot;Ultrasonic acoustic vibrations&quot; in the first line is redundant. Should be &quot;ultrasonic  vibrations&quot; with a parenthetical link to Acoustics if desired.

== Definition ==

I think, the main point should not be &quot;industrial technique&quot; (this is nearly everything) but &quot;type of [[friction welding]]&quot; as it is seen by FW and USW specialists.--[[User:UtzOnBikeEN|UtzOnBikeEN]] ([[User talk:UtzOnBikeEN|talk]]) 19:50, 11 August 2008 (UTC)

== Not ultrasonic... ==

15kHz/20kHz are not ultrasonic frequencies.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/12.117.176.190|12.117.176.190]] ([[User talk:12.117.176.190|talk]]) 18:53, 20 December 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
Comparison between Ultrasonic welding and Heat Staking?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Sureshchandrasekaran|Sureshchandrasekaran]] ([[User talk:Sureshchandrasekaran|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Sureshchandrasekaran|contribs]]) 11:01, 7 August 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== WHAT IS THE RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN ULTRASONIC WELDING AND HEAT STAKING? ==

?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Sureshchandrasekaran|Sureshchandrasekaran]] ([[User talk:Sureshchandrasekaran|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Sureshchandrasekaran|contribs]]) 08:59, 8 August 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
==Crowd Control Weapons, Covert Uses==
From my own personal experience as a victim of directed energy technology, is that they are using ultrasound energy, as I have used lead, iron and aluminum for shielding but with no effect, but fuzzy materials tend to diminish the energy. In addition, the energy seems to be focused on the surface of the target, that is to say the fuzzy shielding inches away from the target surface do not provide protection. Aaron Alexis and Richard Weston Jr each claimed to be victims of directed energy, but the news reports discredit those claims as they also were reported to hear voices. I point out three flaws 1)that sleep deprivation from these devices can cause outward symptoms of mental illness, 2) sound communication can be modulated by this technology, 3) there is no rule that prohibits these devices to be covertly used on the mentally ill.  My guess is that pulsed microwaves or pulsed lasers are being used to generate ultrasound vibrations in distant targets. 

Another point is that even though the crowd control devices have been in field testing since at least 1998, they have not been marketed in public view to police departments despite clearly crowd control problems. I say this in an effort to make the public aware of this covert activity, please do not delete it.  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/50.104.194.10|50.104.194.10]] ([[User talk:50.104.194.10|talk]]) 06:24, 29 May 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;</text>
      <sha1>13xn3zjfwft12bz59iccz1w09z5jk26</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
