<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Plovdiv</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>4075919</id>
    <revision>
      <id>743846742</id>
      <parentid>743723323</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-11T16:15:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Doug Weller</username>
        <id>1304678</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Age of Poldiv redux */ r</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13261">{{Talk header}}
{{WikiProject Bulgaria|class=B|importance=top}}
{{WikiProject Cities|class=B|importance=top}}
{{Archives|auto=yes|search}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
| algo=old(60d)
| archive=Talk:Plovdiv/Archive %(counter)d
| counter=2
| maxarchivesize=100K
| archiveheader={{Automatic archive navigator}}
| minthreadsleft=0
| minthreadstoarchive=1
}}

== Edit war about History ==

Given the recent edit war with [[User:Murku]] about the history of the city I am posting a link to a page from the official source I have used stating that the earliest signs of life in Plovdiv are recorded from 8000 BC and the first settlements are founded in 6th century BC: Philippopolis Album, Kesyakova Elena, Raytchev Dimitar, Hermes, Sofia, 2012, p.5, ISBN 978-954-26-1117-2 /   [https://www.book.store.bg/prdfile/fls/83475/107945/filipopol-luksozen-album-stranici-ot-tozi-album.jpg web link]--[[User:Realsteel007|Realsteel007]] ([[User talk:Realsteel007|talk]]) 12:19, 16 September 2016 (UTC)

The Neolithic period and all Stone Ages ended in 2000 BC, you got it? I am tired to repeat the same multiple times. The link you provided does not even state the dates you are writing about. [[User:Murku|Murku]] ([[User talk:Murku|talk]]) 20:00, 17 September 2016 (UTC)

No one is talking about 2000 BC. I am talking about 6000 BC and 8000 BC. The link provides info about the 6th millenium BC and the 8th millenium BC--[[User:Realsteel007|Realsteel007]] ([[User talk:Realsteel007|talk]]) 08:17, 18 September 2016 (UTC)

[[User:Murku|Murku]] are we on the same page now: [[Plovdiv]]  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Realsteel007|Realsteel007]] ([[User talk:Realsteel007#top|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Realsteel007|contribs]]) 08:34, 19 September 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Realsteel, please try to replace several pictures without showing the same dubious view several times. And the strange dates you continue replacing are not claimed by the trivia. I hope this is a sufficient compromise to solve the dispute. Thanks. [[User:Murku|Murku]] ([[User talk:Murku|talk]]) 00:47, 20 September 2016 (UTC)

Specify the view you have problem with? Specify the exact dates as well.--[[User:Realsteel007|Realsteel007]] ([[User talk:Realsteel007|talk]]) 11:43, 20 September 2016 (UTC)

1) Please, stop reverting that nonsense and stop acting as illiterate: &quot;Plovdiv is continuously inhabited since the 6th century BC when the first Neolithic settlements were established.[3][37] Plovdiv has settlement traces including necropolises dating from the Neolithic, roughly 6000 BC&quot; . The statement contradicts itself and is impossible.
2) Showing the same mosque two times on the collage is superfluous.
Can you explain this time how this illiterate statement and images are justified in the text?[[User:Murku|Murku]] ([[User talk:Murku|talk]]) 07:09, 21 September 2016 (UTC)

Point 1: Fixed.
Point 2: If you find a better picture of the roman stadium that fits the frame I will change it. Nevertheless, I don't think that showing a mosque is an issue.--[[User:Realsteel007|Realsteel007]] ([[User talk:Realsteel007|talk]]) 09:38, 21 September 2016 (UTC)

[[User:Murku|Murku]] I made changes to the photoframe as well. I think we have reached a consensus.--[[User:Realsteel007|Realsteel007]] ([[User talk:Realsteel007|talk]]) 11:18, 21 September 2016 (UTC)

Thanks![[User:Murku|Murku]] ([[User talk:Murku|talk]]) 18:09, 21 September 2016 (UTC)

== Age of Poldiv redux ==

That there were people living in the area for thousands of years is fact.
But I see no evidence that it is one of the world's oldest cities. &quot;The project &quot;From here begins Plovdiv&quot; states:[http://arheologymap.weebly.com/1062107710831080-10851072-1087108810861077108210901072-1080-10921080108510721085108910801088107210851077.html]
Based on known explored and partially documented prehistoric mounds and settlements map provides information for these periods in the development of the city:

1. Home of settled life in today's Plovdiv - middle Neolithic - Late Neolithic / sixth - fifth millennium BC. / 

2. Permanent generic settlements of today's Plovdiv - Late Neolithic - Eneolith / fifth - the fourth millennium BC. / 

3. Generic-tribal settlements and villages in the first three hills in Plovdiv - Eneolith - Early Bronze / fourth - the third millennium BC. / 

4. Thracian mounds living in today's Plovdiv - early - medium bronze / third - the second millennium BC. / 

5. Villages of Orphic societies and municipality with fortifications Kendrissos - late Bronze - early Iron Age / second-first millennium BC. / 
6. Mestozhivelishta

The other sources have been moved around and the dates changed so much it's hard to see what actually references what, but the two ITIAM sources are from 1963, 53 years old, far too old to use for this. Philippopolis Album“, Kesyakova Elena, Raytchev Dimitar, Hermes, Sofia, 2012 is hard to verify although it exists. I can find [http://popular-archaeology.com/issue/03012014/article/archaeologists-explore-ancient-roman-forum-of-philippopolis this] which does say &quot; is among the oldest cities in Europe, with evidence of human settlement going back 6,000 years. Established first as the Thracian settlement of Eumolpia, today its ancient remains near the city center are most often identified with the name Philippopolis by archaeologists. That was the name given to the city after it was Hellenized within the Macedonian Empire under Philip II during the 4th century, B.C.E. But its most visible ancient remains took shape when the city was absorbed into the orbit of ancient Rome during the 1st century B.C.E. - 1st century C.E.,&quot;. That conflicts slightly with the source above, but doesn't claim it was a city 6000 years ago or that it has been continuously inhabited. Real life calls and I'll stop now, removing the obsolete sources before I go. [[User:Doug Weller|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#070&quot;&gt;Doug Weller&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Doug Weller|talk]] 16:59, 7 October 2016 (UTC)

:It doesn't appear that the sources even claim it's one of the world's continuously inhabited cities, just one of the world's oldest cities. The official website only says &quot;It is claimed that the city is a contemporary of Troy and Mycenae, but it is more ancient than Rome, Athens and Constantinople.&quot; [[User:Doug Weller|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#070&quot;&gt;Doug Weller&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Doug Weller|talk]] 18:20, 7 October 2016 (UTC)

::1.[[User:Doug Weller]], why have you removed the source of P.Detev's publication from 1965? Saying its &quot;far too old to use for this&quot; is ridiculous. In this publication the archeologist confirms that there was a settlement established around 4000 BC. Please do not remove references randomly.

::2.What about Philippopolis Album of Kesyakova? It is easy to find. I can show you scanned imagees if you want. 

::3.What is dubious about 4000 BC. Here is a quote from arch. Matey Mateev's Ancient Philippopolis publication (from 1999 ISBN: 978-954-491-821-7)
&quot;Безспорно е времето на укрепяване на Небет тепе - то е научно изследвано и намерените материали имат давност от 3600 - 3800 година пр.Хр.&quot;
In English: The time of the establishment of a fortified town on Nebet tepe is scientifically proven - between 3800 - 3600 BC.--[[User:Realsteel007|Realsteel007]] ([[User talk:Realsteel007|talk]]) 16:42, 10 October 2016 (UTC)


:::((yo|Realsteel007}} Detev? It would help if English translations were given, but you mean the 1963 source I removed, not 1965. It was being used to source &quot;ranking it among world's [[List of oldest continuously inhabited cities|oldest continuously inhabited cities]].&quot; Obviously a 53 year old source can't be used for that - but in fact it wasn't, the text it was used for was originally &quot;n the end of the 4th millennium BC, there already was an established settlement there,&lt;ref&gt;Детев, П. ''Разкопки на Небет тепе в Пловдив'', ГПАМ, 5, 1963, pp. 27–30.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ботушарова, Л. ''Стратиграфски проучвания на Небет тепе'', ГПАМ, 5, 1963, pp. 66–70.&lt;/ref&gt;&quot;. Someone decided that wasn't good enough, someone 'improved it' by changing the text. It's also a bit questionable - many dates that old (1960s) have been radically revised, radiocarbon dating was in its infancy, etc.  
:::I used another source by the same authors of the Philippopolis Album. Do they say something different there? But you seem to be missing the point. The claim that &quot;The city is continuously inhabited since 4000 BC ranking it among world's [[List of oldest continuously inhabited cities|oldest continuously inhabited cities]].&quot; is just wrong. There was no city there 6000 years ago, not even 3000 years ago. And so far as I can see the archaeological sources don't make that specific claim. I don't know how much you know about archaeology, but &quot;continuous habitation&quot; is sometimes very hard to prove. We also have a policy called [[WP:UNDUE]]. What other reliable sources make these claims? Your source says &quot;The time of the establishment of a fortified town on Nebet tepe is scientifically proven - between 3800 - 3600 BC.&quot; - but we can't say that when other sources dispute it.  Another source says that:

:::&quot;In connection with the topic under discussion, some results deserve attention. A wall surrounds the highest part of the hill, and its chronology has been much debated. Some scholars date it to the Late Iron Age and more precisely to the time after the conquest of Thrace by Alexander the Great (Botousharova 1963b, 110-115), while others are of the opinion that the wall dates to the Early Iron Age or to an even earlier period (Peikov 1986, 32-34). It has already been proved that the wall- building technique - unworked stones of different size without mortar between them - does not allow an exact dating of the site to the Early Iron Age (Domaradski 1982, 44-50). Therefore the existence of an enclosing wall of this type on Nebet Tepe is not an adequate reason to call this an Early Iron Age fortress or citadel. There has been much discussion in the archaeological literature of the problem of fortresses in the Early Iron Age settlement system. From all available data it has become evident that we cannot speak of purely military fortresses or chieftain citadels in Ancient Thrace in the second phase of the Early Iron Age (Gotzev 1994b). In the preliminary publication of the latest and most extensive archaeological excavations Dr. A. Peikov reports a temple complex, the residence of a ruler defended by a stone wall, and speaks of their role in the urbanization process (Peikov 1986, 35-38). For the time being there is no additional information to support his hypothesis and the question of the functions of the buildings on the hill of Nebet Tepe remains open.&quot; '''Urbanization in the Mediterranean in the 9th to 6th Centuries BC'''.[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=KdQhYldTIC4C&amp;pg=PA413&amp;dq=Nebet+tepe&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwisusWh6tDPAhWBtBoKHd7pDY8Q6AEIITAB#v=onepage&amp;q=Nebet%20tepe&amp;f=false] [[User:Doug Weller|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#070&quot;&gt;Doug Weller&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Doug Weller|talk]] 18:17, 10 October 2016 (UTC)
::::[[User:Realsteel007]] pinging again, typo in first one. [[User:Doug Weller|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#070&quot;&gt;Doug Weller&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Doug Weller|talk]] 18:19, 10 October 2016 (UTC)

::::[[User:Doug Weller]], I think we are speaking for different issues. I agree that claims such as &quot;continuosly-inhabited&quot; are debatable and not suitable for wiki. What I meant was that the earliest signs of habitation on Nebet tepe are dated as far back as ~4000 BC as P.Detev stated in his publication from 1963. Perhaps I misunderstood your edits and comments. So, it would be better to remove the &quot;continously inhabited&quot; part.--[[User:Realsteel007|Realsteel007]] ([[User talk:Realsteel007|talk]]) 22:00, 10 October 2016 (UTC)

:::::Sorry, [[User:Realsteel007]], I obviously misunderstood you. I still distrust using archaeological material that old for dating. But until we can find something better, ok. It seems likely that there was something there then, most areas have had some occupation in the last 10,000 years! I'll say now and later that we should not use official city or regional sites for history or archaeology, they can't help being political and used for political purposes, that's their nature. [[User:Doug Weller|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#070&quot;&gt;Doug Weller&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Doug Weller|talk]] 16:14, 11 October 2016 (UTC)

== Adding the Turkish name ==
I was in Plovdiv few months back. It has a significant Turkish population and demographical data prove that although not fully accurate. I think the Turkish name of the city, which is Filibe, should be added into the first part of the introduction. [[User:Berkaysnklf|Berkaysnklf]] ([[User talk:Berkaysnklf|talk]]) 22:03, 8 September 2016 (UTC)

:It's already in the name section, and your subjective experience means nothing as far as wikipedia is concerned. [[User:Athenean|Athenean]] ([[User talk:Athenean|talk]]) 05:51, 9 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>gg6rwt8hk61swcxk44mc2thq674v90s</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
