<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Bushido</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1227361</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748927722</id>
      <parentid>739993806</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-11T06:38:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot (v1.2.7.1)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21023">{{Talk header|search=yes}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Japan|class=c |importance=top| b1 &lt;!--Referencing &amp; citations--&gt; = n
| b2 &lt;!--Coverage &amp; accuracy    --&gt; =y
| b3 &lt;!--Structure              --&gt; = y
| b4 &lt;!--Grammar &amp; style        --&gt; = y
| b5 &lt;!--Supporting materials   --&gt; = y
| b6 &lt;!--Accessibility          --&gt; = yes|history=y|milhist=y|culture=y}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=Start
|B-Class-1=no
|B-Class-2=yes
|B-Class-3=yes
|B-Class-4=yes
|B-Class-5=yes
|importance=High|Japanese-task-force=yes}}
{{WikiProject Martial arts|class=C}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=C|importance=Top}}
}}

==Translations==
Can someone please check the translations of the virtues? &quot;Chugi&quot; apparently has a very different meaning than what is listed, for example. [[Special:Contributions/86.136.74.161|86.136.74.161]] ([[User talk:86.136.74.161|talk]]) 19:41, 28 December 2015 (UTC)

==Code of honor==
I simply cannot believe this doesn't fall under a Code of Honor WikiProject...  [[User:Trekphiler|&lt;font color=&quot;#1034A6&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;TREKphiler&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 15:01, 3 July 2008 (UTC)

==Historicize Bushido==
This article is improving gradually, but is still a pretty painful read.  We have to remember that ¨Bushido¨ is essentially a modern term.  Tokugawa period or medieval warriors simply did not conceive of themselves as following something called ¨Bushido.¨  Yes there are instances of this term in the literature, but they are a conspicuous minority.

Really, this would benefit most by being renamed ¨samurai ethics&quot; or something.  The article talks about EVERY reference to warrior ideals or codes of conduct as ¨bushido literature¨ or ¨reference to bushido ideals¨&quot;-- this implies that Japanese warriors had ONE ideal that remained unchanged throughout 1500 years of history.  Warriors changed over time as did their ideals.  If you want to talk about Bushido, you have to talk about it historically, not as something that has always existed as part of the Japanese genetic makeup.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/71.56.227.52|71.56.227.52]] ([[User talk:71.56.227.52|talk]]) 11:10, 6 June 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Piecemeal editing can't save this abomination of an article.  However I removed a statement that was patently untrue.  Something to the effect of &quot;bushido was widely practiced and didn't vary.&quot;  Since nothing called &quot;bushido&quot; existed in the Edo period, it's impossible that it was widely practiced.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/67.194.201.74|67.194.201.74]] ([[User talk:67.194.201.74|talk]]) 20:20, 25 October 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

I have to agree this article is weak and misleading in establishing the historical context of the evolution of Samurai culture and ethics, and would like to add two points for consideration.

Virtually no mention is made of the influance of Sun Wu (孙武) and his classic 孫子兵法 (commonly know as &quot;The Art of War&quot; in English). That this work significantly influanced Samurai culture is well established and failing to mention it is a major difficency. As close as we come is the passing mention of &quot;Taoist&quot; influance, but how, I must ask, did Samurai recieve this? From 孫子兵法.

Second, I must amplify the point made above that Bushido was a late 19th century work written to distill the essence of Samurai culture and ethics for (then) contemporary readers; there was no single source of a Samurai code before then and suggesting so is misleading. The content of this article appears to walk backward from there to create a frame for the picture. Certianly Samurai culture was the product of Japan, but it is not as esentially uniquely Japanese as the article states, and anyone with at least a general knowledge of Japanese history of the period must be aware of the great influance Chinese culture had on Japan and certianly this applies to Samurai culture as well.

One might question if this article was intended to be a Japanese secondary school textbook - the historical accuracy and perspective meets the requirements of the form.

Politely suggest to mention Sun Wu. Samurai such as Oda Nobunaga, Toyotomi Hideyoshi and Tokugawa Ieyasu were his readers and followers.

Suggested citation if needed:

McNeilly, Mark R. (2001), Sun Tzu and the Art of Modern Warfare, Oxford University Press, ISBN 0195133404 ; pp. 6–7.

[[User:Xiao-zi|Xiao-zi]] ([[User talk:Xiao-zi|talk]]) 16:59, 27 August 2010 (UTC)

:By all means, be [[WP:BOLD|bold]] and make the changes, as long as you have decent sources! &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#DDDDDD 0.2em 0.2em 0.1em; class=texthtml&quot;&gt;[[User:Nuujinn|Nuujinn]]&lt;/span&gt; 00:34, 28 August 2010 (UTC)

==Article Rewrite (December 29, 2009)==

'''This article is completely lacking in (accurate) historical context''', so I am rewriting it. I don't feel much need to go into extreme detail as to why this article needs to be rewritten. Criticism of its numerous flaws are enumerated in detail below and in the archive page, and have sat around for ages, but nobody has done anything about it. I rewrote the entire introduction to the article. As for the rest, I tried to keep as much of it as possible (all the lists of sources, etc), but I felt forced to omit numerous sections which were off topic, not relevant, or otherwise useless. I realize that Wikipedia fetishizes length above all other things, but honestly, nothing of worth is being lost here. Most of what was omitted were facile attempts to show how Bushido is a timeless and ahistorical concept and therefore no attempts at providing historical context are necessary. [[User:Nick Kapur|Nick Kapur]] ([[User talk:Nick Kapur|talk]]) 09:48, 30 December 2009 (UTC)

UPDATE (December 30, 2009) - My rewrite was completely reverted in less than 24 hours with no attempt made to integrate my new contributions or even read the talk page and consider why I rewrote the article. I will try restoring my edit one time. After that, I wash my hands of this whole business. If Wikipedia is content to have an extremely lenghty, convoluted, and entirely unhelpful article stand as is with no historicization whatsoever, despite countless criticisms of the article on the talk page and talk page archive, than there's not much I can do about it as a single individual. But I'll ask, just one time - if my rewritten article is inadequate, add to it or improve it. Don't just revert to the old one - that one is far, far worse. It's not just about length people, it has to be about quality in the end. [[User:Nick Kapur|Nick Kapur]] ([[User talk:Nick Kapur|talk]]) 09:48, 30 December 2009 (UTC)
:&quot;I don't feel much need to go into extreme detail as to why this article needs to be rewritten.&quot; Well, you should. An editor with less than 50 edits over the course of four years should be much less ham-handed especially when there are numerous objections to your clunky edits. Please, wash your hands as you say, and be constructive. [[User:Kintetsubuffalo|Chris (クリス • フィッチュ)]] ([[User talk:Kintetsubuffalo|talk]]) 10:24, 30 December 2009 (UTC)

== Requested move ==

&lt;div class=&quot;boilerplate&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #efe; margin: 2em 0 0 0; padding: 0 10px 0 10px; border: 1px dotted #aaa;&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Template:RM top --&gt;
:''The following discussion is an archived discussion of a [[WP:RM|requested move]]. &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on the talk page. No further edits should be made to this section. ''

The result of the move request was: '''Page moved'''. [[User talk:Ucucha|Ucucha]] 18:10, 20 January 2010 (UTC)

----


[[:Bushidō]] → [[Bushido]] —

Per [[WP:COMMONNAME]] and [[WP:USEENGLISH]] - the '''English''' form of this word is ''Bushido'', without the macron. 

[[Special:Contributions/76.66.197.17|76.66.197.17]] ([[User talk:76.66.197.17|talk]]) 07:07, 12 January 2010 (UTC)

*'''Comment''': Britannica[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/86168/Bushido] has it with the macro; the Columbia Encyclopedia[http://encyclopedia2.tfd.com/Bushido] doesn't.  Both sources use diacritics in some cases but not others (cf. &quot;Mexico&quot; in Britannica[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/379167/Mexico] and &quot;Bogotá&quot; in Columbia[http://encyclopedia.tfd.com/Bogot%C3%A1]), and so are useful for adjudicating the matter at hand.  Sources linked to in the references section, as far as I can tell, either strip diacritics indiscriminately or keep them for all Japanese words, and so are of no help.--[[User:Atemperman|Atemperman]] ([[User talk:Atemperman|talk]]) 19:49, 12 January 2010 (UTC)
**Except that this word is commonly used in fiction, where it is almost invariably written without a macron, such as in WWII fiction. A [http://books.google.com/books?as_q=bushido&amp;num=100&amp;btnG=Google+Search&amp;as_epq=&amp;as_oq=&amp;as_eq=&amp;as_brr=0&amp;as_pt=ALLTYPES&amp;lr=&amp;as_vt=&amp;as_auth=&amp;as_pub=&amp;as_sub=&amp;as_drrb_is=q&amp;as_minm_is=0&amp;as_miny_is=&amp;as_maxm_is=0&amp;as_maxy_is=&amp;as_isbn=&amp;as_issn= google book search] shows the predominance of the macronless form. [[Special:Contributions/76.66.197.17|76.66.197.17]] ([[User talk:76.66.197.17|talk]]) 21:10, 12 January 2010 (UTC)
*'''Comment''': You should also move the archive of this page.--[[User:Oneiros|Oneiros]] ([[User talk:Oneiros|talk]]) 01:51, 13 January 2010 (UTC)
*'''Comment''': Merriam-Webster [http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/bushido] and both the Random House and American Heritage dictionaries [http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/bushido] have the term coming from the Japanese &quot;bushidō&quot; with the macron. [[User:Armagebedar|armagebedar]] ([[User talk:Armagebedar|talk]]) 05:41, 13 January 2010 (UTC)
::Yes, but the entry in both M-W and AH is for the macronless spelling.  Both dictionaries also have &quot;Bogotá&quot; rather than &quot;Bogota&quot;, so it seems that so far for sources that recognize the use of diacritics in English in some cases but not others, it's 3-to-1 in favor of &quot;bushido&quot;. --[[User:Atemperman|Atemperman]] ([[User talk:Atemperman|talk]]) 20:48, 13 January 2010 (UTC)
*'''Support''' - this word has been &quot;absorbed&quot; into English usage, and most frequently appears without the macron.  [[Special:Contributions/81.111.114.131|81.111.114.131]] ([[User talk:81.111.114.131|talk]]) 22:52, 13 January 2010 (UTC)
:''The above discussion is preserved as an archive of a [[WP:RM|requested move]].  &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on this talk page. No further edits should be made to this section.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- Template:RM bottom --&gt;

== Format edits, minor wording changes ==
* Removed some self-important verbage used in quoting some of the sources (&quot;a lifetime of research&quot;). 
* Added an &quot;origins&quot; section, and re-structured the information to not give the appearance that Wikipedia editors are having a public battle about how far back in history the term &quot;bushido&quot; can be traced. The evidence is presented, and a disclaimer is added at the bottom of the section, keeping the sources intact.
* Fleshed out the &quot;Wilson, 1982&quot; reference, by researching an edition on Google scholar.
* Added a source for the [[Nitobe Inazō]] quotes. 
* Found 2 additional pictures on Wikimedia commons to use in the article. 
* Removed the &quot;all caps&quot; table with excessive space.
* Removed some excess verbage in the &quot;see also&quot; section, to create a 2 column table.
* Added &quot;main article&quot; links to [[Bushido literature]] and [[Virtue]]. --[[User:OliverTwisted|&lt;font color=&quot;006699&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;big&gt;O&lt;/big&gt;liver&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;[[User:OliverTwisted|&lt;font color=&quot;33CC99&quot;&gt;&lt;big&gt;T&lt;/big&gt;wisted &lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:OliverTwisted|&lt;font color=&quot;006699&quot; size=&quot;1px&quot;&gt; (Talk) &lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;[[Special:Contributions/OliverTwisted|&lt;font color=&quot;33CC99&quot; size=&quot;1px&quot;&gt;(Stuff)]] 03:54, 17 January 2010 (UTC)

== Minor Add ==
Added link in the See More section. I added [[Scout Law]] as it contains many common themes, not a lot really, but some. it gives another culture's perspective to the aricle and is a small link. Thought it might be good to have. Take it out as you wish. Thanks for the article! I really enjoyed it.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/192.91.172.42|192.91.172.42]] ([[User talk:192.91.172.42|talk]]) 18:46, 4 February 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:The Scout Law has nothing to do with Bushido. I've reverted your addition. [[User:Mark Shaw|Mark Shaw]] ([[User talk:Mark Shaw|talk]]) 18:49, 4 February 2010 (UTC)

== Chivalry? ==

The article now has this anti-historical tidbit:

&quot;Nitobe was not the first person to document Japanese chivalry in this way. In his text Feudal and Modern Japan, historian  Arthur May Knapp wrote:

    &quot;The samurai of thirty years ago had behind him a thousand years of training in the law of honor, obedience, duty, and self-sacrifice..... It was not needed to create or establish them. As a child he had but to be instructed, as indeed he was from his earliest years, in the etiquette of self-immolation. The fine instinct of honor demanding it was in the very blood...&quot;[3] &quot;

Which is to say, May noted that the warrior class were brought up to be filial and obedient.  How does this constitute 'Japanese chivalry,' rather than Confucianism?  Especially if the warriors themselves conceived of their loyalty, self-sacrifice etc in Confucian terms?  If the the entire language of loyalty is drawn from the Chinese classics?  The most this excerpt shows is that other people besides Nitobe were inventing fictitious pasts and &quot;essences of the Japanese spirit.&quot;  The point remains that &quot;Bushido&quot; (as presented in this article) is a product of late 19th and early 20th century historical imagination.

This article is even spinning off further innacurate articles.  If a text depicts warriors, it is now automatically part of the imaginary corpus of &quot;Bushido literature.&quot;  Talking about it in the Tokugawa period is highly questionable, and downright ridiculous when it starts being ascribed to the Kojiki.  Now we have &quot;Japanese chivalry&quot; existing even before the emergence of a warrior class!

Nick Kapur's revision was excellent.  I don't see any compelling reason why it has not been adopted.  Presumably the page should reflect scholarly consensus, and not the mistaken beliefs of martial arts enthusiasts.

So, why are these changes blocked?

== Missing Talk section ==

It seems that when this Talk page was last archived, a several-page chunk of it was inadvertedly deleted. Would someone be able to recover it and properly archive it? Cool. --[[User:DrHacky|DrHacky]] ([[User talk:DrHacky|talk]]) 16:28, 8 August 2010 (UTC)


== SPANISH Legion ==

The article don´t say taht the spanish legion was founded by Millán Astray and their &quot;Credo&quot; was based in the Samurai's Bushido  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/62.42.148.27|62.42.148.27]] ([[User talk:62.42.148.27|talk]]) 15:21, 1 May 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;


== Broken link ==

reference 25 &quot;excerpt from Samurai: The World of the Warrior by Stephen Turnbull&quot; links to a junk site  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Qube0|Qube0]] ([[User talk:Qube0|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Qube0|contribs]]) 12:00, 7 May 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Alexandre Pernikoff ==

There appears to be no WikiPedia article on the book &quot;Bushido&quot; written by Alexandre Pernikoff (1943, Liveright Publishing Company, New York, NY, USA). [[User:Desertphile|Desertphile]] ([[User talk:Desertphile|talk]]) 18:04, 22 September 2012 (UTC)

== Etymology ==

I removed the etymology added by a user [[Special:Contributions/ Parkmcgraw | Parkmcgraw]] last September.[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Bushido&amp;diff=513904177&amp;oldid=510372293] The edit only explain how the Chinese words 武, 士 and 道 was respectively derived from in China without any relation to the bushido. All the sources appended describe nothing about the bushido. Furthermore an irrelevant word 周髀 ([[Gnomon]]) is written as if it has anything to do with the bushido. ―― [[User:Phoenix7777|Phoenix7777]] ([[User talk:Phoenix7777|talk]]) 04:08, 11 January 2013 (UTC)

== &quot;Charity&quot; Principle ==

It seems to me that the best english translation to 仁　would be to Benevolence, and not charity, which is very different concept, but I am not an expert. Then it should point to http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ren_(Confucianism)  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/179.219.15.167|179.219.15.167]] ([[User talk:179.219.15.167|talk]]) 03:00, 25 October 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Grammar ==

First sentence: &quot;is a Japanese a phrase&quot;. Wtf?

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Bushido]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=739269815 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20121021003115/http://www2.uni-erfurt.de:80/ostasiatische_geschichte/texte/japan/dokumente/17/tokugawa_legislation/index.htm to http://www.uni-erfurt.de/ostasiatische_geschichte/texte/japan/dokumente/17/tokugawa_legislation/index.htm

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 18:50, 13 September 2016 (UTC)

It's remarkable how totally uncritical this article is of the near complete fiction that is the concept of &quot;bushidō&quot;.  This article should be rewritten from scratch, taking into account sources such as the following:

* Benesch, Oleg (2011) [https://open.library.ubc.ca/cIRcle/collections/ubctheses/24/items/1.0071589 &quot;Bushido: the creation of a martial ethic in late Meiji Japan&quot;]
* Benesch, Oleg (2014) ''Inventing the Way of the Samurai Nationalism, Internationalism, and Bushidō in Modern Japan''
* Hurst, G. Cameron III (1990) [http://enlight.lib.ntu.edu.tw/FULLTEXT/JR-PHIL/ew26464.htm &quot;Death, Honor, and Loyalty: The Bushido Ideal&quot;] 

[[User:Curly Turkey|Curly&amp;nbsp;Turkey]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;🍁&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Curly Turkey|''¡gobble!'']] 11:29, 18 September 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:3|one external link|3 external links}} on [[Bushido]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=748927715 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20090306180335/http://www.kodansha-intl.com:80/books/html/en/9784770029423.html to http://www.kodansha-intl.com/books/html/en/9784770029423.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20060220004601/http://www.nhk.or.jp/kumamoto/musashi/images/musashi_poster.jpg to http://www.nhk.or.jp/kumamoto/musashi/images/musashi_poster.jpg
*Added {{tlx|dead link}} tag to http://www.angelfire.com/extreme4/kendo/TheUnfetteredMind.pdf
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20031231014646/http://www.japantimes.com:80/cgi-bin/getarticle.pl5?fl20021215a1.htm to http://www.japantimes.com/cgi-bin/getarticle.pl5?fl20021215a1.htm

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 06:38, 11 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>iex7zq4vy8ppmc0zrz86vyfvg2q18zq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
