<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Capitalism</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>5417</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749749156</id>
      <parentid>749502615</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-16T00:02:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lowercase sigmabot III</username>
        <id>17518500</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Archiving 2 discussion(s) to [[Talk:Capitalism/Archive 29]]) (bot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15115">{{Skip to talk}}
{{Talk header}}
{{Vital article|level=3|topic=Society|class=C}}
{{Round in circles|search=yes}}
{{Not a forum}}
{{Article history
|action1=GAR
|action1date=8 August 2006
|action1result=delisted
|action1oldid=68336981

|action2=PR
|action2date=11:37, 28 August 2006
|action2link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Capitalism/archive1
|action2result=reviewed
|action2oldid=71471185

|action3=GAN
|action3date=01:45, 2 March 2008 (UTC)
|action3result=not listed
|action3oldid=194650880

|currentstatus=DGA
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|collapsed=yes|1=
{{WikiProject Capitalism|class=C|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Business|class=C|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Sociology|class=C|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Economics|class=C|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Politics|class=C|importance=high|liberalism=yes|liberalism-importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Philosophy|social=yes|importance=high|class=C}}
{{WikiProject Conservatism|class=C|importance=top}}
{{WP1.0|v0.5=pass|class=C|category=Socsci|VA=yes|WPCD=yes|importance=High}}
}}
{{US English}}

{{Auto archiving notice|bot=MiszaBot I |age=2 |units=months}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 29
|minthreadsleft = 5
|algo = old(60d)
|archive = Talk:Capitalism/Archive %(counter)d
}}
__TOC__
== referenced information deleted ==

&quot;According to economist [[Joseph Schumpeter]], capitalism is the most successful economic system that has existed thus far. Capitalism, he observed, creates wealth through advancing continuously to ever higher levels of productivity and technological sophistication; this process, known as [[creative destruction]], requires that the &quot;old&quot; be destroyed before the &quot;new&quot; can take over.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Challenge of Global Capitalism: The World Economy in the 21st Century |last=Gilpin |first=Robert |publisher=Princeton University Press |year=2000 |isbn=978-0-691-09279-9 |location=Princeton University |at=Introduction}}&lt;/ref&gt;&quot;

I'm not sure what the objection is to this statement, which can be confirmed by many other references.  The reasons for its deletion also seem strange: &quot;too specific&quot; and &quot;according to Marxism capitalism will be replaced.&quot;  Please note that it doesn't say that capitalism is &quot;good&quot;, just that it is the &quot;most successful&quot;, which it clearly is.  Comments? [[User:Rick Norwood|Rick Norwood]] ([[User talk:Rick Norwood|talk]]) 13:05, 19 May 2016 (UTC)

:No, it isn't clear that capitalism is the most successful. There are a lot of criticism about capitalism from thousands of economists. Picking just Schumpeter's opinion and adding it to the lead isn't neutral. His opinion can be added to subsections. [[User:Emijrp|emijrp]] ([[User talk:Emijrp|talk]]) 19:32, 19 May 2016 (UTC)

::I agree the information in the paragraph can be in the article, just not in the lead as it doesn't really summarize the article. Perhaps in &quot;Characteristics&quot; just after the first paragraph and before or in &quot;Summary&quot; or at the bottom of the article in &quot;Economic freedom&quot; (as that is sort of a &quot;Praise&quot; section to offset &quot;Criticism&quot;. I also [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Capitalism&amp;diff=721101138&amp;oldid=721040426 removed] the quote by Cassidy. It just restates the first sentence. We should probably avoid any quotes in the lead. [[User:Richard-of-Earth|Richard-of-Earth]] ([[User talk:Richard-of-Earth|talk]]) 19:57, 19 May 2016 (UTC)

Hi everyone! I'm the person who originally removed it. I took it out of the intro because it didn't seem like an introductory statement - &quot;creative destruction&quot; is not a general description of capitalism, just one popular theory about capitalism's tendency to create change. I called it &quot;too specific,&quot; which was maybe awkward wording, because it would clearly belong better in a body section of the text. It probably wouldn't have looked as out of place as it did if it hadn't been introduced by a subjective statement like &quot;capitalism is the most successful economic system that has ever existed,&quot; which did very much read like an attempt to put &quot;capitalism is good&quot; into the introduction of an article that is supposed to be neutral. [[Special:Contributions/74.96.155.160|74.96.155.160]] ([[User talk:74.96.155.160|talk]]) 22:39, 19 May 2016 (UTC)
 
:Wow, then we seem to have a consensus that it is OK to put in the article, but not in the lead . . . . . . now all we need is someone who cares enough about Schumpeter to do it. [[User:Richard-of-Earth|Richard-of-Earth]] ([[User talk:Richard-of-Earth|talk]]) 08:24, 20 May 2016 (UTC)
I think almost any modern economist would agree that capitalism is the most successful economic system that ever existed, not as a subjective opinion but as a statement of fact.  It is no more subjective than any other statement about the world as it is today.  And certainly the success or failure of capitalism is an important property of capitalism.  On the other hand, I agree that the &quot;creative destruction&quot; idea does not belong in the lead.  I'll look around for a better statement by a major economist of the idea that capitalism, in its various forms, is now pretty much universal. [[User:Rick Norwood|Rick Norwood]] ([[User talk:Rick Norwood|talk]]) 12:04, 20 May 2016 (UTC)

{{reflist-talk}}

== Could we not have a page for &quot;a capitalist&quot;? ==

My suggestion is that the definition of &quot;a capitalist&quot; should be indentified as &quot;a benefactor of capital&quot;. I think this is an objective, widely used and to use common language &quot;nonpolitical&quot; description. 

It also neither necessitates, nor does it in any way rule out supporters of &quot;capitalism&quot;, as such would defend it in terms of their own direct or indirect benefit; Wether through morality, theism, emotion etc.

Do we currently have any way of sourcing this definition, considering both the material referred to on the &quot;Capitalism&quot; page and other potential sources? If so, the original article could also possibly be shortened and cleared up even further.

[[Special:Contributions/78.69.217.113|78.69.217.113]] ([[User talk:78.69.217.113|talk]]) 09:10, 23 July 2016 (UTC)

:By new page I assume you mean a new article. There was an article in 2009: https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Capitalist&amp;oldid=323522168 It has since been [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Capitalist&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=329440336 linked] to here with the justification of &quot;All explained in Capitalism article. What is here is a weird hodgepodge&quot;. [[Wikipedia:Wikipedia is not a dictionary]] is policy that explains why we do not have articles about words. Like anything else if there is enough written about the word, the word can get an article, but I feel an article about &quot;Capitalist&quot; as a word itself lacks content. [[User:Richard-of-Earth|Richard-of-Earth]] ([[User talk:Richard-of-Earth|talk]]) 20:09, 24 July 2016 (UTC)

&quot;Benefactor&quot;?  What's a &quot;benefactor&quot;?  A &quot;capitalist&quot; is just an owner of capital, i.e. production equipment and raw materials, whether directly or via shares. Just like a &quot;Laborer&quot; is an owner of labor, and a &quot;Landlord&quot; is an owner of land. [[User:Walrasiad|Walrasiad]] ([[User talk:Walrasiad|talk]]) 08:21, 27 July 2016 (UTC)

== &quot;authocratic China&quot; ==

The characterization &quot;autocratic China&quot; under the image contradicts the article [[autocracy]] where autocracy is defined as the system of government where all the power is concentrated  in the hands of one person. I highly doubt that all power concentrated in one person in China.--[[User:Reciprocist|Reciprocist]] ([[User talk:Reciprocist|talk]]) 09:08, 31 July 2016 (UTC)
:Oddly the term was linked to the [[Authoritarianism]] article, which is a more apt description.  I removed the description.  [[User:The Four Deuces|TFD]] ([[User talk:The Four Deuces|talk]]) 16:08, 31 July 2016 (UTC)

== Economist Allan H. Meltzer has argued that all of these on anything more than a small scale have ended in authoritarianism. ==

What an absurd lie. What about Spain 1936? It was on a mass scale, and was later crushed by fascists. Please rewrite this phrase.--[[Special:Contributions/85.181.195.27|85.181.195.27]] ([[User talk:85.181.195.27|talk]]) 23:45, 28 October 2016 (UTC)

:It is a quote. It is what he said. It is cited. We are not going to alter a quote. The next section is Marx talking about how capitalism is just a phase. Shall we alter that to satisfy people who do not agree? [[User:Richard-of-Earth|Richard-of-Earth]] ([[User talk:Richard-of-Earth|talk]]) 06:41, 29 October 2016 (UTC)
::What about a more fair perspective? Or wait, I'll just put a quote in from some political scientists who says that everything Marx said was wrong, I mean, can't change it, it's a QUOTE....--[[Special:Contributions/85.180.181.221|85.180.181.221]] ([[User talk:85.180.181.221|talk]]) 16:07, 29 October 2016 (UTC)
:::It is balanced in that Marx is talking about capitalism is doomed in the next section. That said, if you can find some some political scientists saying alternative systems have worked, you are welcome to suggest them. You need to keep in mind [[WP:FRINGE]]. That is why we have Marx presenting the opposing opinion, because nobody can claim he is fringe. However, the place for how some other system works belong on that article for that system. So I do not see what we could put in there.  [[User:Richard-of-Earth|Richard-of-Earth]] ([[User talk:Richard-of-Earth|talk]]) 23:07, 29 October 2016 (UTC)
::::We have articles like Anarchism in Spain, or similar things. There are enough sources I think. I also think that this Quote I'm talking about should be removed, it should be just stating what other systems exist, not judging them. It's absurd, you read thins whole article about how capitalism is the worst thing, and at the end &quot;every alternative system has led to authoritarianism&quot; with just one guy saying it, so humanity is doomed forever or what? THAT'S RIDICULOUS. Also this doesn't make any sense, why should an alternative organisation of the workplace lead to authoritarianism? As if a change in the workplace would result in a state dicatorship when in the old system you already have an authority. So don't want fringe scientists in this article? Then remove the one you quoted there. Makes no sense. --[[Special:Contributions/85.180.180.79|85.180.180.79]] ([[User talk:85.180.180.79|talk]]) 21:36, 30 October 2016 (UTC)
:::::If what you say is true then the article is unbalanced and the quote needs to stay there to keep the balance. It seems you want to remove it solely because you do not like it. (See [[WP:Arguments to avoid on discussion pages#Personal point of view]]) Readers can judge for themselves the validity of that quote. Do you want to remove it as a favor to them so they do not have to make that decision? [[User:Richard-of-Earth|Richard-of-Earth]] ([[User talk:Richard-of-Earth|talk]]) 20:00, 31 October 2016 (UTC)

:He didn't say that.  He said that it has only been tried under authoritarian governments.  It would probably be better to use an article he wrote about the issue than a passing comment to a right-wing think tank.  [[User:The Four Deuces|TFD]] ([[User talk:The Four Deuces|talk]]) 07:42, 1 November 2016 (UTC)
::And that's also not true, there are many historical examples where this was tried not under authoritarian governments. Can't you use your brain? By the way, a single quote like this seems VERY biased, it's on top of the examples, and it seems like someone put it on purpose there because he/she didn't like alternative systems to capitalism, what about that point of view?? It's like puting a quote on top of an article about electrodynamics which says &quot;This author came to the conclusion that electrodynamics is a wrong theory&quot; --[[Special:Contributions/85.181.196.15|85.181.196.15]] ([[User talk:85.181.196.15|talk]]) 20:09, 1 November 2016 (UTC)
:::Meltzer said, &quot;The alternatives that have been tried are types of Socialism or Communism or other types of authoritarian rule.&quot;[https://hiram7.wordpress.com/2009/03/12/there-is-no-better-alternative-than-capitalism/]  Please distinguish between someone reporting what he said and someone endorsing what he said.  Also, please not this is not a blog.  Your are expected to maintain politeness in your postings.  [[User:The Four Deuces|TFD]] ([[User talk:The Four Deuces|talk]]) 16:04, 2 November 2016 (UTC)

:I am actually not liking the whole section now. The article is about Capitalism. Why have a section about alternative systems anyways? If we had an article about yellow cats, would we have a section listing the other colors cats can be? This section was perhaps added to say: &quot;See how much Capitalism sucks? Here what we could be doing instead.&quot; Then somebody came along and add this quote to try to throw a wrench in that plan. But that is just what I think. I do not care enough to go through the history to find out the truth of it. How about we just remove the whole section? [[User:Richard-of-Earth|Richard-of-Earth]] ([[User talk:Richard-of-Earth|talk]]) 08:44, 2 November 2016 (UTC)

::It is poorly written.  It is just a collection of comments.  [[User:The Four Deuces|TFD]] ([[User talk:The Four Deuces|talk]]) 16:04, 2 November 2016 (UTC)

I went ahead and removed it. If people object, we can discuss it more here. [[User:Richard-of-Earth|Richard-of-Earth]] ([[User talk:Richard-of-Earth|talk]]) 19:01, 10 November 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:5|one external link|5 external links}} on [[Capitalism]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=749502613 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20081202050426/http://www.bartleby.com:80/65/la/laissezf.html to http://www.bartleby.com/65/la/laissezf.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20071217185826/http://www.historycooperative.org:80/journals/llt/52/linden.html to http://www.historycooperative.org/journals/llt/52/linden.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20080219151222/http://www.vatican.va:80/archive/ENG0015/__P8C.HTM to http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P8C.HTM#-2FX
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20071127032512/http://minneapolisfed.org:80/pubs/region/04-05/essay.cfm to https://www.minneapolisfed.org/pubs/region/04-05/essay.cfm
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20120603131601/http://homepage.newschool.edu/%7eAShaikh/pal2.pdf to http://homepage.newschool.edu/~AShaikh/pal2.pdf

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 17:56, 14 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>diy8b6nrxroviujzwb54oqdl5pkcmjq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
