<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Baal</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>275425</id>
    <revision>
      <id>679953704</id>
      <parentid>679949520</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-09-07T20:37:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Johnmcintyre1959</username>
        <id>25923861</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Baal as an Israelite and Judahite God */ Suggest to remove RS</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="103387">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Assyria|class=start|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Mythology|importance=top|class=C}}
{{WikiProject Ancient Near East|class=c|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Judaism|class=C|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=C|importance=Top}}
}}
{{archivebox|
*[[/Archive1]]
}}
==References to Religious Texts==

This article is heavy on references to the Bible and Qur'an without scholarly interpretation of those references, particularly in the section on Ba'al of Tyre. The facts reported in this topic should be supported by scholarship based on something other than religious texts, which have an agenda of pushing their own deity to the exclusion of others. It is entirely appropriate to cite religious texts when discussing mention of Baal in those texts. However, if only religious texts are cited to support facts, it would appear that the person stating these facts is promoting his original research, not to mention his dogma. [[User:Aramink|Aramink]] ([[User talk:Aramink|talk]]) 23:12, 26 July 2012 (UTC)

==Baal of Ugarit==

I'm surprised to see that the article lacks to mention Ugaritic Baal, whose cult played a very significant role in the religious life of ancient Ugarit and who is one of the main characters in Ugaritic poetic narratives such as KTU, 1.1; 1.3; 1.5; 1.10; 1.12; 1.82. To all editors who have enough free time (which is something I lack at the moment), I recommend to correct this omission. [[User:Asharidu|Asharidu]] ([[User talk:Asharidu|talk]]) 06:43, 19 April 2010 (UTC)

== Dios &lt;-&gt; God analogy ==


Just a quick scribble: The analogy

&gt; A contemporary example of this would be God in English and Dios in Spanish.

is a bit off if I understood the article corrrectly, since the _name_ of god is different amongst languages, not his title. So Ba'al stands to God and &quot;Hadad vs Melqart&quot; is more comparable to Jehova, and maybe different transliterations lke Jahwee.

[[Special:Contributions/88.159.74.100|88.159.74.100]] ([[User talk:88.159.74.100|talk]]) 15:29, 22 May 2009 (UTC)



Baal or Bal is an indoeuropean word for Dragon or Snake.for example the name of the dacian king Decebal (dece ten, bal . dragon,snake)it could mean tensnakes or tendragons. in southern romania Bal is an archaic word meaning &quot;large snake&quot;.in romanian mythology we have the Balaur meaning dragon . also in contemporary romanian bal  is a word to depict  saliva dangling from the mouth.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/94.52.225.123|94.52.225.123]] ([[User talk:94.52.225.123|talk]]) 19:14, 25 January 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Ba'al Zeb没b ==

I'm not sure about this section. The Oxford guide to people &amp; places of the Bible  By Bruce M. Metzger, Michael D. Coogan says &quot;BAAL-ZEBUB. The 'Phoenician god at Ekron consulted by King Al The name in Hebrew means &quot;L Flies&quot; but no evidence exists for a Philistine god who either drove off flies or gave oracles through their buzzing. The Hebrew form is probably a derogatory transformation of Baal-zebul, which appears in Ugaritic texts meaning &quot;Lord *Baal,&quot; but could also be understood as &quot;Master of the Heavenly House&quot; (cf. Matt 10.25).&quot;[http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=amlXOOaSuLMC&amp;pg=PA28&amp;dq=Ugarit+Baal+Zebul&amp;num=100&amp;as_brr=3&amp;ei=CsR-S6XJF4n2MYS41ekP&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;cd=14#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false]
Eerdmans Dictionary of the Bible says &quot;oIt is more likely that the name was originally ba'al-zibdl (cf. Beelzebul in the NT). Although ztbul alone can mean &quot;lofty, exalted place' (thus &quot;lord of heaven&quot;), the fixed phrase zbl b'l (&quot;prince Baal&quot;) at Ugarit supports taking Baal-zcbul as a local manifestation of the storm-god Baal. Baal-zebub would thus be a derogatory pun on the original name.&quot; [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=qRtUqxkB7wkC&amp;pg=PA137&amp;dq=Ugarit+Ba%27al+Zebul&amp;num=100&amp;as_brr=3&amp;ei=bsN-S6vSJ6HMMsm1jOsP&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;cd=5#v=onepage&amp;q=Ugarit%20Ba%27al%20Zebul&amp;f=false]

A comparative study of thirty city-state cultures: an investigation  By Mogens Herman Hansen &quot;From Ihc Bible we learn that the Philistines in Ekron in the middle of the 9lh century worshipped the Canaanite god Ba'al-Zebub, Lord of the Flies (2 Kings 1,2-17): although this name is very early, it is also attested in the Greek versions, and is probably a parody of a genuine Canaanite god's name. &quot;Ba'al Zebul&quot;, which means &quot;Prince Ba'al&quot; and is found already in the lexis from Ugarit. Il shows that the Philistines were prompt to acculturale thcmsclve religiously lo their Levantine surroundings (cf, Ura (19701463).&quot;

Zondervan says much the same- &quot;a deliberate change by followers of the Lord (Yahweh) to ridicule and protest the worship of Baal-Zebul (Baal the Prince).&quot; p.347

So, I think the section heading has the wrong name, and needs to be rewritten in the light of the above. Comments? [[User:Dougweller|Dougweller]] ([[User talk:Dougweller|talk]]) 17:15, 19 February 2010 (UTC)

the article is generally quite bad. I did a little bit of cleanup, but much work is still needed. --[[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|()]]&lt;/small&gt; 11:01, 28 July 2010 (UTC)

==Archive==
I put the actual archive content in the archive. [[User:Group29|Group29]] ([[User talk:Group29|talk]]) 13:56, 3 April 2010 (UTC)

==Hadad vs. other Baals==
The article makes a mess of diachrony. The fact that there were many Baals in biblical times (6th to 5th century BC) says nothing about Bronze Age Canaanite religion (Ugarit).
As far as I know, Hadad was the original god who came to be identified as Baal, and it is misleading to say that he was one among many gods so identified. The proper way of putting it would be that Hadad-Baal became so popular that 800 years later, at the time of the Hebrew Bible, he had fragmented into numerous regional deities called &quot;Baal&quot;. Gods and religions don't just stay the same over 1,000 years, and it is important to make clear which period is being discussed at any time. --[[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|()]]&lt;/small&gt; 11:19, 28 July 2010 (UTC)

== all usages of Baal in the Tanakh ==
Though not Translated, Abraham and Sarah are the first called Baal and Baallat, these words simply mean &quot;Boss and Owner,&quot; like in a Male and Female Relationship, translating them as Husband and Wife is not correct, before having a Mate Joseph is called Baal of the Dreams, and it foretells of a Baal of the Arrows that lays in wait for Joseph in the latter days, and it speaks of People who are Baal of Cattle and or Land and or Possessions. Even before the Law was written by Moses, under Phonetician  and Egyptian Oral Law, it was a death sentence for anyone to take and or trespass on the Property of a Baal or Baalat, which is why Yahweh said to the King he was a dead Man for taking the Baalet Sarah from the Baal Abraham, when he had taken Sarah, which was before written Law.

{{cot|title=Here are all the usages in the Tanakh;}}

Genesis 14:13  驻  专 注专  砖  专 专  砖  注专  注 专转志专

Genesis 20:3   志   专   转 注志砖 砖专志拽转  注转 注

Genesis 36:38 转 砖  转转 注  志注专

Genesis 36:39 转 注  志注专  转转 专 砖 注专 驻注 砖 砖转  转志专 转  

Genesis 37:19 专 砖 志  注 转  

Genesis 49:23 专专 专 砖 注 爪

Exodus 9:31 驻砖转 砖注专 转  砖注专  驻砖转 注

Exodus 14:2 专 志 砖专 砖  驻 驻 专转     驻 注 爪驻  转 注志

Exodus 14:9 专驻 爪专 专 砖 转  注志 志住住 专 驻专注 驻专砖  注志驻 专转 驻 注 爪驻

Exodus 21:3 志驻  驻 爪 志注 砖  爪 砖转 注

Exodus 21:22 志爪 砖 驻 砖 专 爪    住 注砖 注砖 砖专 砖转 注 注 砖 转 驻

Exodus 21:28 志 砖专 转志砖  转志砖 转 住拽 住拽 砖专   转志砖专 注 砖专 拽

Exodus 21:29  砖专   转 砖砖 注 注  砖专 转 砖  砖 砖专 住拽 志注 转

Exodus 21:34 注 专 砖 住祝 砖 注 转 志 住

Exodus 21:36  注  砖专   转 砖砖  砖专 注 砖 砖 砖专 转转 砖专 转 志 住

Exodus 22:7 志 爪  拽专 注志转 志 志 砖  转 专注

Exodus 22:10 砖注转  转  砖 志 砖  转 专注 拽 注  砖

Exodus 22:11 志  注 砖 注

Exodus 22:13 志砖 砖 注 专注 砖专 志转 注 志注 砖 砖

Exodus 22:14 志注 注  砖 志砖专   砖专 住

Exodus 24:14 志拽 专 砖志  注 砖专志砖   专 专 注 志注 专 砖 

Exodus 34:24 志专砖  驻 专转 转志 志 砖 转志专爪 注转 专转 转志驻   砖砖 驻注 砖

Leviticus 21:4   注 注 

Numbers 21:28 志砖 爪 砖  拽专转 住  注专  注 转 专

Numbers 22:41  拽专 拽 拽 转志注 注 转 注 专 砖 拽爪 注

Numbers 25:3 爪 砖专 注 驻注专 专志祝  砖专

Numbers 25:5 专 砖 志砖驻 砖专 专 砖 砖 爪 注 驻注专

Numbers 32:38 转志 转志注 注 住转 砖 转志砖 拽专 砖转 转志砖转 注专 砖专 

Numbers 33:7 住注 转 砖 注志驻 专转 砖专 注志驻 注 爪驻  驻 

Numbers 33:46 住注    注 转

Deuteronomy 4:3 注 专转 转 砖专志注砖  注 驻注专  志砖 砖专  专 注志驻注专 砖   拽专

Deuteronomy 9:9 注转 专 拽转 转  转 专转 砖专志专转  注 砖 专 专注  专注    转   砖转转

Deuteronomy 15:2  专 砖 砖 志注 砖  砖专 砖 专注 志砖 转志专注 转志 志拽专 砖 

Deuteronomy 21:3  注专 拽专 志 拽 拽 注专  注转 拽专 砖专 志注  砖专 志砖 注

Deuteronomy 21:13 住专 转志砖转 砖 注 砖 转 转 转志 转志 专  专  转  注转 转  砖

Deuteronomy 22:22 志爪 砖 砖 注志砖 注转志注 转 志砖 砖 砖 注志砖 砖 注专转 专注 砖专 住

Deuteronomy 24:1 志拽 砖 砖 注  志 转爪志 注 志爪  注专转 专 转  住驻专 专转转 转  砖 转

Deuteronomy 24:4 志 注 专砖 砖专志砖 砖 拽转 转  砖 专 砖专  志转注  驻   转 转志专抓 砖专   转   住

Joshua 4:18  = 注转 拽= 注转  砖 专 专转志 转 专 转拽 驻转 专   专 砖 志专 拽  转志砖砖 注志志转

Joshua 11:17 志专 拽 注 砖注专 注志注  拽注转  转转 专志专 转 志   转

Joshua 12:7   专抓 砖专  砖注  砖专 注专 专  注  拽注转  注志专 拽 注 砖注专 转 砖注 砖 砖专 专砖 拽转

Joshua 13:5 专抓  志 专 砖砖 注  转转 专志专 注  转

Joshua 13:17 砖 志注专 砖专 砖专  转 注 转 注 注

Joshua 15:9 转专  专砖 专 志注  驻转 爪 志注专 专志注驻专 转专  注  拽专转 注专

Joshua 15:10 住  注  志专 砖注专 注专 志转祝 专志注专 爪驻  住 专 转志砖砖 注专 转

Joshua 15:11 爪  志转祝 注拽专 爪驻 转专  砖专 注专 专志注 爪   转爪转  

Joshua 15:24 祝  注转

Joshua 15:29 注 注 注爪

Joshua 15:60 拽专转志注  拽专转 注专 专 注专 砖转 爪专 住

Joshua 18:14 转专  住 驻转志  志专 砖专 注志驻 转志专  =  拽=  转爪转 志拽专转志注  拽专转 注专 注专   转 驻转志

Joshua 19:8 志爪专 砖专 住转 注专  注志注转 专 专转  转 转  志砖注 砖驻转

Joshua 19:44 转拽 转 注转

Joshua 22:27  注     专转 专 注 转志注转  驻 注转  砖 志专  专  志 拽 

Joshua 24:11 转注专 转志专 转 志专   注志专 专 驻专 注 转 专砖  住 转 转 

Judges 2:11 注砖 志砖专 转志专注 注  注 转志注

Judges 2:13 注 转志 注 注 注砖转专转

Judges 3:3 砖转 住专 驻砖转 志注 爪  砖 专  专 注 专 注  转

Judges 3:7 注砖 志砖专 转志专注 注  砖 转志  注 转志注 转志砖专转

Judges 3:20    志砖 注转 拽专 砖专志  专  专志   拽 注 住

Judges 6:25    专   拽 转志驻专志砖专 砖专  驻专 砖 砖注 砖 专住转 转志 注 砖专  转志砖专 砖专志注 转专转

Judges 6:28 砖 砖 注专 拽专  转抓  注 砖专 砖专志注 专转 转 驻专 砖 注 注志 

Judges 6:30 专 砖 注专 志砖 爪 转志 转  转抓 转志 注  专转 砖专 砖专志注

Judges 6:31 专 砖  砖专志注 注 转 转专 注 志转 转砖注 转 砖专 专  转 注志拽专 志  专   转抓 转志

Judges 6:32 拽专志 志 专注 专 专  注  转抓 转志 祝

Judges 7:1 砖 专注  注 志注 砖专 转  注志注 专   志 爪驻 注转 专 注拽

Judges 8:29  专注 志砖 砖 转

Judges 8:33  砖专 转 注 砖  砖专  专 注 砖  注 专转 

Judges 8:35 志注砖 住 注志转 专注 注 志 砖专 注砖 注志砖专 祝

Judges 9:1   志专注 砖 志  专  志志砖驻转 转志  专

Judges 9:2 专志  志注 砖 志  砖  砖注 砖   专注 志砖  砖  专转 志注爪 砖专 

Judges 9:3 专 志 注  志注 砖 转 志专    专   专  

Judges 9:4 转志 砖注 住祝 转 注 专转 砖专   砖 专拽 驻  专

Judges 9:5  转志 注驻专转 专 转志 志专注 砖注 砖 注志 转 转专 转 志专注 拽   住

Judges 9:6 住驻 志注 砖 志转    转志  注志 爪 砖专 砖

Judges 9:7  转  注 专砖 专志专 砖 拽 拽专 专  砖注  注 砖 砖注  

Judges 9:16 注转 志转 转 注砖转 转 转志 志 注砖转 注志专注 注志转 志  注砖转 

Judges 9:18 转 拽转 注志转   转专 转志 砖注 砖 注志 转 转 转志 志转 注志注 砖   

Judges 9:19 志转 转 注砖转 注志专注 注志转   砖  砖 志 

Judges 9:20 志 转爪 砖  转 转志注 砖 转志转  转爪 砖 注 砖 转  转 转志

Judges 9:23 砖  专 专注    注 砖  注志砖 

Judges 9:24  住 砖注 志专注  砖 注志  砖专 专 转 注 注 砖 砖专志拽 转志 专 转志

Judges 9:25 砖  注 砖 专 注 专砖 专  转 志砖专志注专 注 专   祝

Judges 9:26  注 志注  注专 砖 志 注 砖

Judges 9:28 专 注 志注 志 志砖  注  志专注  驻拽 注 转志砖 专  砖 注 注 

Judges 9:39 爪 注 驻 注 砖  

Judges 9:46 砖注 志注 志砖  志爪专 转  专转

Judges 9:47    转拽爪 志注 志砖

Judges 9:51 志注  转志注专 住 砖 志砖 砖  注 注专 住专 注 注 注志 

Judges 9:57 转 志专注转 砖 砖 砖  专砖 转  拽转 转 志专注 祝

Judges 10:6 住驻  砖专 注砖转 专注 注  注 转志注 转志注砖转专转 转志 专 转志 爪 转   转  志注 转  驻砖转 注 转志  注

Judges 10:10 注拽  砖专 志 专    注 转志 注 转志注 祝

Judges 11:13 专  志注 志 驻转 志拽 砖专 转志专爪 注转 爪专 专 注志拽 注志专 注转 砖 转 砖

Judges 11:16  注转 爪专  砖专 专 注志志住祝  拽砖

Judges 13:20  注转  注  砖 注 志    砖转 专 驻 注志驻 专爪

Judges 19:22   转志  砖 注专 砖 志注 住 转志转 转驻拽 注志转 专 志砖 注 转 拽 专 爪 转志砖 砖专志 志转 注

Judges 19:23 爪  砖 注 转 专  志 志转专注  专 砖专志 砖  志转 志转注砖 转志 转

Judges 19:25 志 砖 砖注  拽 砖 驻砖 爪  抓 注 转 转注志 志 注志拽专 砖 = 注转 拽= 注转 砖专

Judges 20:5 拽 注 注 注 住 注 转志转  转  专 转志驻砖 注 转转

Judges 20:33  砖 砖专 拽 拽 注专 注 转专 专 砖专  拽 注专志注

1 Samuel 2:19 注 拽 转注砖志  注转    注转 转志砖  转志 

1 Samuel 7:4 住专  砖专 转志注 转志注砖转专转 注 转志  祝

1 Samuel 12:10 注拽 志 = 专 拽= 专   注 转志 注 转志注 转志注砖转专转 注转 爪   注

1 Samuel 12:11 砖  转志专注 转志 转志驻转 转志砖 爪 转   住 转砖 

1 Samuel 15:2  专  爪转 驻拽转 转 砖专志注砖 注拽 砖专 砖专志砖  专 注转 爪专

1 Samuel 15:6 专 砖 志拽  住专* 专 转 注拽 驻志住驻 注 转 注砖转 住 注志志 砖专 注转 爪专 住专 拽 转 注拽

1 Samuel 15:22 专 砖 驻抓  注转  砖注 拽   砖注   拽砖  

1 Samuel 23:11 住专 注 拽注  专 砖 砖专 砖注 注   砖专 志 注 住 专  专

1 Samuel 23:12 专  住专 注 拽注 转 转志砖 志砖 专  住专 住

1 Samuel 28:7 专 砖 注 拽砖志 砖转 注转志 *  专砖志 专 注   砖转 注转志 注 专

2 Samuel 1:6 专 注专   拽专 拽专转 专 注  砖 砖注 注志转  专 注 驻专砖 拽

2 Samuel 5:20   注志驻专爪  砖  专 驻专抓  转志 驻 驻专抓  注志 拽专 砖志拽  注 驻专爪

2 Samuel 6:2 拽   志注 砖专 转 注  注转 砖 转 专  砖专志拽专 砖 砖  爪转 砖 专 注

2 Samuel 11:26 转砖注 砖转 专 志转 专 砖 转住驻 注志注

2 Samuel 13:23  砖转    砖 注 爪专 砖专 注志驻专 拽专 砖 志 

2 Samuel 21:12   拽 转志注爪转 砖 转志注爪转 转  转 注 砖 注 砖专  转 专 转志砖 砖专 = 转 拽= 转 = 砖 拽= 砖 = 驻砖转 拽= 驻砖转  转 驻砖转 转志砖 注

1 Kings 4:16 注 志砖 砖专 注转 住

1 Kings 9:18 转志注转 转志= 转专 拽= 转专 专 专抓

1 Kings 11:15  转  转志 注转  砖专 爪 拽专 转志  志专 

1 Kings 16:31  拽 转 转 专注 志 拽 砖 转志 转志转注  爪  注 转志注 砖转 

1 Kings 16:32 拽  注 转 注 砖专  砖专

1 Kings 17:17  专 专   志砖 注转 转   拽  注 砖专 志转专志 砖

1 Kings 18:18 专  注专转 转志砖专  志转 转  注 转志爪转  转 专 注

1 Kings 18:19 注转 砖 拽抓  转志志砖专 志专 专 转志 注 专注 转 砖  砖专 专注 转  砖 

1 Kings 18:21 砖  志志注 专 注志转 转 驻住 注志砖转 住注驻 志   专 志注  专 志注 注 转 专

1 Kings 18:22 专  志注  转专转     注 专注志转 砖 砖

1 Kings 18:25 专   注 专  驻专  注砖 专砖  转 专 拽专 砖  砖  转砖

1 Kings 18:26 拽 转志驻专 砖专志转  注砖 拽专 砖志注 拽专 注志爪专 专 注 注  拽  注 驻住 注志 砖专 注砖

1 Kings 18:36  注转  砖   专   专 爪拽 砖专  注 志转  砖专  注 = 专 拽= 专 注砖转 转 志专 

1 Kings 18:40 专   转驻砖 转志 注 砖 志  转驻砖 专  志 拽砖 砖 砖

1 Kings 19:18 砖专转 砖专 砖注转 驻 志专 砖专 志专注 注 志驻 砖专 志砖拽 

1 Kings 22:54 注 转志注 砖转  注住 转志  砖专  砖专志注砖 

2 Kings 1:2 驻  注 砖 注转 砖专 砖专  砖  专   专砖 注   注拽专 志   住

2 Kings 1:3   专 志 转砖 拽 注 拽专转  志砖专 专   志 砖专 转  专砖 注   注拽专

2 Kings 1:6 专  砖 注 拽专转 专   砖 志 砖专志砖 转 专转   专   志 砖专 转 砖 专砖 注   注拽专   砖专志注转 砖 志转专  志转 转转

2 Kings 1:8 专  砖 注 砖注专 专 注专 专 转 专  转砖 

2 Kings 1:16 专  志专  注 砖专志砖转  专砖 注   注拽专  志 砖专 专砖 专   砖专志注转 砖 志转专  志转 转转

2 Kings 3:2 注砖 专注 注  专拽    住专 转志爪转 注 砖专 注砖 

2 Kings 4:42 砖  注 砖砖  砖   专 注砖专志 砖注专 专 爪拽 专 转 注 

2 Kings 10:18 拽抓  转志志注 专   注 转志注 注  注 专

2 Kings 10:19 注转 志 注 志注 志 拽专  砖 志驻拽     注  砖专志驻拽    注砖 注拽 注  转志注 注

2 Kings 10:20 专  拽砖 注爪专 注 拽专

2 Kings 10:21 砖  志砖专  志注 注 志砖专 砖 砖专 志  转 注  转志注 驻 驻

2 Kings 10:22 专 砖专 注志转 爪 砖  注 注 爪  砖

2 Kings 10:23    志专 转 注 专 注 注 驻砖 专 驻志砖志驻 注 注   志注 注 

2 Kings 10:25  转 注砖转 注 专  专爪 砖砖   砖 志爪  驻志专 砖 专爪 砖砖  注志注专 转志注

2 Kings 10:26 爪 转志爪转 转志注 砖专驻

2 Kings 10:27 转爪 转 爪转 注 转爪 转志转 注 砖 = 专转 拽= 爪转 注志

2 Kings 10:28 砖  转志注 砖专

2 Kings 11:18  志注 专抓 转志注 转爪 转志= 转 拽= 转 转志爪 砖专  转 转  注 专 驻 转 砖  驻拽转 注志转 

2 Kings 17:16 注 转志志爪转   注砖  住 = 砖 拽= 砖 注 注砖 砖专 砖转 志爪 砖 注 转志注

2 Kings 21:3 砖  转志转 砖专  拽  拽 转 注 注砖 砖专 砖专 注砖   砖专 砖转 志爪 砖 注 转

2 Kings 23:4 爪  转志拽   转志 砖 转志砖专 住祝 爪   转 志 注砖 注 砖专  爪 砖 砖专驻 抓 专砖 砖转 拽专 砖 转志注驻专 转志

2 Kings 23:5 砖转 转志专 砖专 转   拽专 转 注专  住 专砖 转志拽专 注 砖砖 专 转  爪 砖

1 Chronicles 1:49 转 砖  转转 注  志注专

1 Chronicles 1:50 转 注   转转  砖 注专 驻注 砖 砖转  转志专 转  

1 Chronicles 4:22 拽 砖  砖 砖专祝 砖专志注  砖  专 注转拽

1 Chronicles 4:33 志爪专 砖专 住转 注专  注志注 转 砖转 转砖 

1 Chronicles 5:5   专  注 

1 Chronicles 5:8 注 志注 志砖注 志  砖 注专注专 注志 注 注

1 Chronicles 5:23  爪 砖 砖 砖 专抓 砖 注志注 专 砖专 专志专  专

1 Chronicles 8:30  专 注 爪专 拽砖 注 

1 Chronicles 8:33 专  转志拽砖 拽砖  转志砖 砖  转志转 转志志砖注 转志 转志砖注

1 Chronicles 8:34 志转 专 注 专 注  转志 住

1 Chronicles 9:36  专 注 爪专 拽砖 注 专 

1 Chronicles 9:39 专  转志拽砖 拽砖  转志砖 砖  转志转 转志志砖注 转志 转志砖注

1 Chronicles 9:40 志转 专 注 专志注  转志

1 Chronicles 12:6 注 专转 注 砖专 砖驻 = 专驻 拽= 专驻

1 Chronicles 13:6 注  志砖专 注转 志拽专转 注专 砖专  注转 砖 转 专   砖 专 砖专志拽专 砖

1 Chronicles 14:7 砖注 注注 驻

1 Chronicles 14:11 注 注志驻专爪  砖  专  驻专抓  转志  驻专抓  注志 拽专 砖志拽  注 驻专爪

1 Chronicles 27:28 注志转 砖拽 砖专 砖驻 注  专 住 注志爪专转 砖 注砖 住

2 Chronicles 8:6 转志注转 转 志注专 住转 砖专  砖 转 志注专 专 转 注专 驻专砖 转 志砖拽 砖 砖专 砖拽 转 专砖   专抓 砖转

2 Chronicles 17:3   注志砖驻   专   专砖  专砖 注

2 Chronicles 23:17  志注 转志注 转爪 转志转 转志爪 砖专 转 转  注 专 驻 转

2 Chronicles 24:7  注转 专砖注转  驻专爪 转志转   志拽砖 转志 注砖 注

2 Chronicles 26:7 注专  注志驻砖转 注志= 注专 拽= 注专 砖 专志注 注

2 Chronicles 28:2  专  砖专  住转 注砖 注

2 Chronicles 33:3 砖  转志转 砖专 转抓 拽  拽 转 注 注砖 砖专转 砖转 志爪 砖 注 转

2 Chronicles 34:4 转爪 驻 转 转 注  砖专志注 注 注 砖专 驻住 住转 砖专 拽 专拽 注志驻 拽专  

Ezra 4:8 专 注志注 砖砖 住驻专 转 专  注志专砖 专转砖砖转  

Ezra 4:9  专 注志注 砖砖 住驻专 砖专 转  驻专住转 专驻 驻专住 = 专 拽= 专  砖砖 =  拽=  注

Ezra 4:17 驻转 砖  注志专 注志注 砖砖 住驻专 砖专 转  转 砖专 砖专 注专志专 砖 注转 住

Nehemiah 6:18 志专  注 砖注  志转  砖 志专   拽 转志转志砖  专

Esther 1:17 志爪 专志 注志志砖 转 注 注 专  砖专砖 专  转志砖转  驻 志

Esther 1:20 砖注 驻转  砖专志注砖 志转  专  志砖 转 拽专 注  注志拽

Job 31:39 志 转 志住祝 驻砖 注 驻转

Psalms 12:7 专转  专转 专转 住祝 爪专祝 注 专抓 拽拽 砖注转

Psalms 73:11 专  注志 砖 注 注

Psalms 77:13 转 志驻注 注转 砖

Psalms 106:28 爪 注 驻注专   转

Proverbs 1:17 志 专 专砖转 注 志注 祝

Proverbs 1:19  专转 志爪注 爪注 转志驻砖 注 拽 祝

Proverbs 3:27 志转注志 注 转  =  拽=  注砖转

Proverbs 12:4 砖转志 注专转 注 专拽 注爪转 砖

Proverbs 16:22 拽专  砖 注 住专  转

Proverbs 17:8 志 砖 注 注 志志砖专 驻 砖

Proverbs 18:9  转专驻 转   注 砖转

Proverbs 22:24 志转转专注 转志注 祝 转志砖 转  转

Proverbs 23:2 砖转 砖 注 志注 驻砖 转

Proverbs 24:8 砖 专注  注志转 拽专

Proverbs 27:22  转转砖志转志 转砖 转 专驻转 注 志转住专 注 转 祝

Proverbs 28:12 注抓 爪拽 专 转驻专转 拽 专砖注 驻砖 

Proverbs 29:22 砖志祝 专  注  专志驻砖注

Proverbs 30:19 专 砖专 砖 专 砖 注 爪专 专志 志 专 专 注

Proverbs 30:23 转转 砖  转注 砖驻 志转专砖 专转 祝

Proverbs 31:11    注 砖  住专

Proverbs 31:23 注 砖注专 注 砖转 注志拽志专抓

Proverbs 31:28 拽  砖专 注 

Ecclesiastes 5:10 专转  专  志砖专 注  志= 专转 拽= 专转 注

Ecclesiastes 5:12 砖 专注  专转 转转 砖砖 注砖专 砖专 注 专注转

Ecclesiastes 7:12  爪  爪 住祝 转专 注转  转 注

Ecclesiastes 8:8   砖 专  转志专  砖  转  砖转  志 专砖注 转志注

Ecclesiastes 10:11 志砖 砖 志砖  转专 注 砖

Ecclesiastes 10:20  注  志转拽 专 砖 志转拽 注砖专  注祝 砖  转志拽 注 = 驻 拽= 驻  专

Ecclesiastes 12:11 专  专转 砖专转 注 注 住驻转 转 专注 

Song of Songs 8:11 专  砖 注  转 转志专 专 砖  驻专 祝 住祝

Isaiah 1:3 注 砖专 拽 专 住 注 砖专  注 注  转

Isaiah 16:8  砖转 砖  驻 砖 注   砖专拽 注志注专 注 转注 专 砖转 砖 注专 

Isaiah 26:13   注  转 志 专 砖

Isaiah 41:15  砖转 专 专抓 砖 注 驻驻转 转砖 专 转拽 注转 抓 转砖

Isaiah 50:8 拽专 爪拽 志专 转 注  志注 砖驻 砖 

Isaiah 54:5  注 注砖  爪转 砖  拽砖 砖专  志专抓 拽专

Isaiah 62:4 志专  注 注 专爪 志专 注 砖   拽专 驻爪志 专爪 注 志驻抓   专爪 转注

Isaiah 62:5 志注 专 转 注  砖砖 转 注志 砖砖 注 

Jeremiah 2:8   专   转驻砖 转专  注 专注 驻砖注    注 专 志注 

Jeremiah 2:23  转专  转 专 注  转 专 专  注  注砖转 专 拽 砖专转 专

Jeremiah 3:14 砖  砖 志   注转  拽转 转  注专 砖 砖驻 转 转 爪

Jeremiah 7:9  专爪 祝 砖注 砖拽专 拽专 注  专  专 砖专 志注转

Jeremiah 9:13  专 砖专专转  专 注 砖专  转 住

Jeremiah 11:13  住驻专 注专    住驻专 爪转 专砖 砖转 转 砖转 转 拽专 注 住

Jeremiah 11:17  爪转 注 转 专 注 专注  专注转 转志砖专 转  砖专 注砖  注住 拽专 注 住

Jeremiah 12:16  志  转志专 注 砖注 砖 志 砖专  转志注 砖注 注  转 注

Jeremiah 19:5  转志转 注 砖专祝 转志 砖 注转 注 砖专 志爪转  专转  注转 注志 祝

Jeremiah 23:13  砖专 专转 转驻  注 转注 转志注 转志砖专 住

Jeremiah 23:27 砖 砖 转志注 砖 转 砖专 住驻专 砖 专注 砖专 砖 转 转志砖 注

Jeremiah 27:8    砖专 志注 转 转志爪专 志 转 砖专 志转 转志爪专 注   专 专注 专 驻拽 注志  志 注志转 转 

Jeremiah 27:11  砖专  转志爪专 注 志 注 转 注志转 志 注 砖 

Jeremiah 27:12 志爪拽 志 专转 志专  专  转志爪专 注 志 注 转 注 

Jeremiah 31:32  专转 砖专 专转 转志转  拽  爪 专抓 爪专 砖专志 驻专 转志专转  注转  志

Jeremiah 32:29  砖  注志注专 转 爪转 转志注专 转 砖 砖专驻 转 转 砖专 拽专 注志转 注 住 住  专 注 注住

Jeremiah 32:35  转志转 注 砖专  志 注专 转志 转志转  砖专 志爪转  注转 注志 注砖转 转注 转 注 =  拽=  转志 住

Jeremiah 35:11  注转 专爪专 志 志专抓 专   专砖 驻  砖 驻  专 砖 专砖 祝

Jeremiah 37:13 志 砖注专  砖 注 驻拽转 砖 专 志砖 志 转驻砖 转志专  专 志砖 转 驻

Jeremiah 40:14 专  注* 转注  注住  志注 砖 转志砖注 志转 转 驻砖 志   志拽

Ezekiel 12:6 注 注志转祝 转砖 注 转爪 驻 转住  转专 转志专抓 志驻转 转转 转 砖专

Ezekiel 12:7 注砖  砖专 爪转  爪转    注专 转专转志 拽专  注 爪转 注志转祝 砖转 注 祝

Ezekiel 12:12 砖 砖专志转 志转祝 砖 注 爪 拽专 转专 爪  驻 住 注 砖专 志专 注  转志专抓

Ezekiel 25:9   驻转 转志转祝  注专 注专 拽爪 爪 专抓 转 砖转 注 注 = 拽专转 拽= 拽专转

Ezekiel 36:17 志 转 砖专 砖 注志转  转 专 注转 转  转 专 驻

Daniel 6:11   注 志专砖 转 注 转  驻转  注转  专砖  转转   专 注志专 爪  拽  志拽 志 注 志拽转  住

Daniel 8:6  注志 注 拽专 砖专 专转 注 驻  专抓  转 

Daniel 8:20  砖专志专转 注 拽专   驻专住

Hosea 2:10   注   转转   转专砖 爪专 住祝 专转   注砖 注

Hosea 2:15 驻拽转 注 转志 注 砖专 转拽专  转注  转 转 专  转 砖 志 祝

Hosea 2:18  志 志 转拽专 砖 志转拽专志 注 注

Hosea 2:19 住专转 转志砖转 注 驻 志专 注 砖

Hosea 9:10 注 专 爪转 砖专 专 转 专砖转 专转 转   注志驻注专 专 砖转  砖拽爪 

Hosea 11:2 拽专    驻 注  驻住 拽专

Hosea 13:1 专 驻专 专转转 砖  砖专 砖 注 转

Joel 1:8  转 专转志砖拽 注志注 注专

Jonah 4:7   转注转 注转 砖专 专转 转 转志拽拽 砖

Nahum 1:2  拽 拽  拽  注  拽  爪专 专  

Nahum 3:4 专   转  注转 砖驻 专转   砖驻转 砖驻

Zephaniah 1:4 转  注志 注 志砖 专砖 专转 志拽  转志砖专 注 转志砖 专 注志

Malachi 2:11   转注 注砖转 砖专 专砖    拽砖  砖专  注 转志 专
{{cob}}
--[[User:JosephLoegering]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:JosephLoegering]]&lt;/small&gt; 2:53, 16 July 2011

:Nice. And now go on and filter it into the various usages of the word. Especially where Baal indeed refers to the deity. [[User:Cush|&lt;span style=&quot;padding:0px 8px 0px 8px;background-color:#eeeedd;border:1px solid #ddddcc;color:#880000;font-family:'Trebuchet MS',Arial;font-weight:bold;text-shadow:0 0 7px #666666;&quot;&gt;&amp;#9798;&amp;nbsp;CUSH&amp;nbsp;&amp;#9798;&lt;/span&gt;]] 09:10, 16 July 2011 (UTC)

:Great, I thought this was the English Wikipedia... If you're going to give us the Hebrew, perhaps a translation might be useful?[[User:1812ahill|1812ahill]] ([[User talk:1812ahill|talk]]) 00:37, 29 April 2012 (UTC)

==Semitic cognates ==
In Ge'ez and Amharic the form ''bal'' means husband or owner and has no negative connotation.  But the name for the pagan idol cursed in the Bible is Be'al, a lexically distinct phoneme. Another very similar word is be`al (note the different apostrophe) meaning 'holiday', also a distinct phoneme with no negative connotation. [[User:Til Eulenspiegel|Til Eulenspiegel]] ([[User talk:Til Eulenspiegel|talk]]) 13:13, 30 July 2011 (UTC)

== Arabic transliteration ==

Why the transliteration &quot;ba士alah)&quot;? The final letter is ta marbuta so surely ba士alat is correct? [[User:Northutsire|Northutsire]] ([[User talk:Northutsire|talk]]) 15:08, 12 June 2012 (UTC)
:In Arabic, ta marbuta is pronounced &quot;h&quot; when it's at the end of the sentence (i.e. without [[Arabic diacritics|diacritics]]). [[User:Zozo2kx|Yazan]] ([[User talk:Zozo2kx|talk]]) 17:37, 6 November 2012 (UTC)

== Requested move ==
&lt;div class=&quot;boilerplate&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #efe; margin: 2em 0 0 0; padding: 0 10px 0 10px; border: 1px dotted #aaa;&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Template:RM top --&gt;
:''The following discussion is an archived discussion of a [[WP:requested moves|requested move]]. &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on the talk page. Editors desiring to contest the closing decision should consider a [[Wikipedia:move review|move review]]. No further edits should be made to this section. ''

The result of the move request was: '''Move'''. [[User:Cuchullain|C煤chullain]] [[User talk:Cuchullain|&lt;sup&gt;t&lt;/sup&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/Cuchullain|&lt;small&gt;c&lt;/small&gt;]] 18:44, 28 November 2012 (UTC)

----

----

[[Ba士al]]  {{no redirect|Baal}}  According to the Lead, &quot;Ba士al&quot; is &quot;usually spelled Baal in English&quot;.

As such, per [[WP:COMMONNAME]], this article should be moved to [[Baal]] over the redirect. --[[User:Dweller|Dweller]] ([[User talk:Dweller|talk]]) 14:11, 6 November 2012 (UTC)

:*'''Strong Support''', all the sources I came across refer to him as Baal. (Which is why I chose to ignore this title in the article on [[Baal with Thunderbolt]]). [[User:Zozo2kx|Yazan]] ([[User talk:Zozo2kx|talk]]) 15:57, 6 November 2012 (UTC)

:*'''Oppose''' - the ` is correct because it represents an audible glottal stop in the correct pronunciation used in the Ancient Near East, and still today in Semitic languages with cognates.  Yes, I know, because of the [[Great Vowel Shift]] etc., a number of Biblical names have completely unique new pronunciations in English only, when the pronunciation in other languages might be closer to the original correct one. But people who pronounce this &quot;BAYyul&quot; tend to come across as completely ignorant of the sounds of the culture this actually came from, and showing there was really a glottal consonant between the two A's helps in part not to perpetuate this ignorance, but rather to dispel it. [[User:Til Eulenspiegel|Til Eulenspiegel]] /[[User talk:Til Eulenspiegel|talk]]/ 16:29, 6 November 2012 (UTC)
::*I understand that (I speak Arabic, so it makes perfect sense to me) but we do have a policy on common names in English, or else [[Averroes]] would've been Ibn Rushd. [[User:Zozo2kx|Yazan]] ([[User talk:Zozo2kx|talk]]) 16:34, 6 November 2012 (UTC)
::*&lt;edit conflict&gt;Hi. I appreciate your scholarly erudition, but Wikipedia does not name articles in a ''scholarly manner'' but does so ''according to Wikipedia policy''. The policy is to name articles as they are most commonly referred to in English language reliable sources. Hence we have our articles on Federal Republic of Germany and Edison Arantes do Nascimento at [[Germany]], and [[Pel茅]]. Taking your proposal to its logical extension, we would have [[Alexander the Great]] not even at Alexander III of Macedon, but presumably at 峒位苇尉伪谓未慰 峤 苇纬伪. The point is to have the article at the place where the user of an encyclopedia would expect to find it, not an expert in the field. --[[User:Dweller|Dweller]] ([[User talk:Dweller|talk]]) 16:46, 6 November 2012 (UTC)

:*'''Oppose''' - We should try to use proper naming whenever possible.
::#Using ''Ba士al'' over ''Baal'' doesn't violate '''recognizability''', one of the [[WP:CRITERIA|reasons]] we would use a common name over a proper name.
::#Anyone searching for 'Baal' is redirected to 'Ba士al'.
::#From an English speaker's perspective, the difference would look more like one of punctuation than spelling.
::#I doubt 'Baal' is even common enough in English to warrant a common spelling exception.
::&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 18:09, 6 November 2012 (UTC)
:::* You may have a point in (1), (2,3) are irrelevant and subjective. (4) is patently wrong though, &quot;Ba'al&quot; gets [https://www.google.com/search?q=%22Baal%22&amp;btnG=Search+Books&amp;tbm=bks&amp;tbo=1#hl=en&amp;safe=off&amp;tbo=1&amp;tbm=bks&amp;sclient=psy-ab&amp;q=%22Ba'al%22&amp;oq=%22Ba'al%22&amp;gs_l=serp.3...2533.2533.0.2837.1.1.0.0.0.0.80.80.1.1.0...0.0...1c.1.vgC5bB8huhk&amp;pbx=1&amp;bav=on.2,or.r_gc.r_pw.r_cp.r_qf.&amp;fp=c6f6626efc54c437&amp;bpcl=37643589&amp;biw=1280&amp;bih=702 327,000] results on GBooks, while &quot;Baal&quot; gets [https://www.google.com/search?q=%22Baal%22&amp;btnG=Search+Books&amp;tbm=bks&amp;tbo=1#hl=en&amp;safe=off&amp;tbo=1&amp;tbm=bks&amp;sclient=psy-ab&amp;q=%22Baal%22&amp;oq=%22Baal%22&amp;gs_l=serp.3..0l2.213253.213253.2.213661.1.1.0.0.0.0.95.95.1.1.0...0.0...1c.1.YJgQ8Ig4u6w&amp;pbx=1&amp;bav=on.2,or.r_gc.r_pw.r_cp.r_qf.&amp;fp=c6f6626efc54c437&amp;bpcl=37643589&amp;biw=1280&amp;bih=702 3,570,000] (almost 10x) including important book titles and publications. [[User:Zozo2kx|Yazan]] ([[User talk:Zozo2kx|talk]]) 18:39, 6 November 2012 (UTC)
:::::On ''4'', I have reservations using Google hits as a metric, even when limited to books.&lt;br/&gt;On ''2'' &amp; ''3'', these points are very much relevant and tied with ''1''. If an English reader types 'Baal' and finds themself on 'Ba士al', they are not likely to be confused. I put forth that English readers are likely to interpret that sort of difference as one of grammar and not quite one of spelling. Wikipedia has a tradition of using redirects to correct common grammatical errors, rather than conforming article titles to them.&lt;br/&gt;I am not sure the common name exception is completely applicable hear. It is meant to deal with the issues of ''Alexander the Great'' vs ''Alexander III of Macedon'' vs ''峒位苇尉伪谓未慰 峤 苇纬伪'' or ''Confucius'' vs ''Kong Qiu'' vs ''Kong Fuzi'' vs ''K'ung Fu-tzu'' or ''Caffeine'' vs ''1,3,7-trimethyl-1H-purine-2,6(3H,7H)-dione''. What we are dealing with is more nuanced and not nearly as noticeable, confusing, or problematic as the aforementioned differences in spelling and title.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 10:18, 7 November 2012 (UTC)
::::::I'm afraid it isn't just Google. JSTOR returns [http://www.jstor.org/action/doAdvancedSearch?q0=%22Baal%22&amp;f0=all&amp;c1=AND&amp;q1=&amp;f1=all&amp;wc=on&amp;Search=Search&amp;sd=&amp;ed=&amp;la=&amp;jo= 10031] results for Baal, while only [http://www.jstor.org/action/doBasicResults?hp=25&amp;la=&amp;wc=on&amp;gw=jtx&amp;Query=%28%22Ba%27al%22%29&amp;sbq=%28%22Ba%27al%22%29&amp;prq=%28%22Baal%22%29&amp;acc=off 1741] for &quot;Ba'al&quot;. As for the rest of your points: you can see from the more prominent example of [[Ali]] (which has the same glottal sound as Baal, and should thus be at [[士Ali]]), whereby a common, recognizable and standard transliteration of the name in Latin alphabet, is used instead of the (perhaps) more accurate one phonetically. Furthermore, there seems to be agreement across other Wikipedias (French, Spanish, German....) that this is the most recognizable and common spelling in Latin alphabets; I don't see why English should be any different. [[User:Zozo2kx|Yazan]] ([[User talk:Zozo2kx|talk]]) 04:08, 8 November 2012 (UTC)
:::::::This isn't an issue I'll [[Consensus#Agreement vs. consent|obstruct a clear majority]] over. If no other positions of objection are lodged by the weekend, you'll have at least a [[Consensus#Near-Unanimous Consensus|consensus-1]].&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 09:09, 8 November 2012 (UTC)
::::::::Same here, and I can't help but point out that it can be expressed in Latin with just a 4 word phrase: &quot;Nec Hercules contra plures!&quot; [[User:Til Eulenspiegel|Til Eulenspiegel]] /[[User talk:Til Eulenspiegel|talk]]/ 15:40, 8 November 2012 (UTC)

*'''Support''' as &quot;Baal&quot; is much more commonly used. We can leave a redirect at &quot;Ba'al&quot;. 路路路[[User:Nihonjoe|&lt;font color=&quot;darkgreen&quot;&gt;ユ绌&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[WP:HIJCS|?]]&lt;/sup&gt; 路 &lt;small&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Nihonjoe|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;绋&lt;/font&gt;]] 路 [[User talk:Nihonjoe|Talk to Nihonjoe]] 路 [[WP:JA|&lt;font color=&quot;maroon&quot;&gt;Join WP Japan&lt;/font&gt;]]!&lt;/small&gt; 21:02, 6 November 2012 (UTC)

*'''Support''', per ''[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/47227/Baal Britannica]'', ''[http://www.infoplease.com/encyclopedia/society/baal.html Columbia]'', [http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/baal Merriam-Webster], and [http://oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/Baal?q=Baal Oxford]. The title should inform the reader by giving the correct English-language name of the subject. I say, down with Ba士al worship. [[User:Kauffner|Kauffner]] ([[User talk:Kauffner|talk]]) 21:16, 6 November 2012 (UTC)

*'''Support''' I always wondered why the apostrophe was there. Ties in nice with my [[Baal Hermon]] page which should get merged with [[Ba'al Hermon]] now. &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:grey 0.1em 0.1em 0.1em; class=texhtml; font-family: Verdana;&quot;&gt;[[User:Paul Bedson|&lt;span style=&quot;color:Indigo&quot;&gt;Paul Bedson&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Paul Bedson|&lt;span style=&quot;color:FireBrick&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 00:50, 7 November 2012 (UTC)
:''The above discussion is preserved as an archive of a [[WP:RM|requested move]].  &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on this talk page or in a [[WP:move review|move review]]. No further edits should be made to this section.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- Template:RM bottom --&gt;

== Material that should be removed ==
This should be removed.  'In any case, King Ahab, despite supporting the cult of this Ba士al, had a semblance of worship to [[Yahweh (Canaanite deity)|Yahweh]] (1 Kings 16-22). Ahab still consulted Yahweh's prophets and cherished Yahweh's protection when he named his sons [[Ahaziah of Israel|Ahaziah]] (&quot;Yahweh holds&quot;) and Jehoram (&quot;Yahweh is high.&quot;)'  It is not relevant to this article.  This article is about Baal, and not about King Ahab, or Yahweh.  I propose to remove this material.  [[User:Cocoamelia|Cocoamelia]] ([[User talk:Cocoamelia|talk]]) 01:42, 28 September 2013 (UTC)
:What a poorly-taken point. The relation of the Hebrew kingdoms to the worship of Ba'al is possibly the single ''most'' relevant aspect of the entire article, given its continuing importance to Jews and Christians. We should be using footnote references, not citations in the running text, but otherwise there's no problem with that passage at all.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:LlywelynII|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#BBBBBB 0.1em 0.1em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;Llywelyn&lt;font color=&quot;Gold&quot;&gt;II&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 21:50, 12 August 2015 (UTC)

== 9th century? ==

It was the program of Jezebel, in the 9th century, to introduce into Israel's capital city of Samaria her Phoenician cult of Baal as opposed to the worship of Yahweh that made the name anathema to the Israelites.[16] The competition between the priestly forces of Yahweh and of Baal in the ninth century is attested in 1Kings 18. Elijah the prophet challenged Baal's prophets to settle the question whether it was Ba'al or Yahweh who supplied the rain. Elijah offered a sacrifice to Yahweh; Baal's followers did the same. According to the Hebrew Bible, Baal did not light his followers' sacrifice, but Yahweh sent heavenly fire to burn Elijah's sacrifice and altar to ashes, even after it had been soaked with water. Directly after that event, Elijah had the prophets of Ba'al slain and soon it begins to rain.

Clearly there are some mistakes in this paragraph. 1 Kings is part of the Hebrew Bible which stopped adding books before 1st century BCE. Is this &quot;9th century&quot; a mistake from &quot;9th century BCE&quot;?
:It's common in scholarly contexts to omit &quot;BCE&quot; when it's obvious (to experts) that the timeframe is before the Common Era. But as this can be confusing to readers not familiar with this convention or with the subject, I'll add it. -[[User:Snarkibartfast|Snarkibartfast]] ([[User talk:Snarkibartfast|talk]]) 14:52, 10 February 2015 (UTC)

== El, Dagon, Molok Baal Hadad-Hammon &amp; YHWH ==

Established interpretations about Canaanite and Phoenician deities are affected by Jewish-Christian biased interpretations, and thus they are categorically wrong.
Canaan is etymologized from &quot;Can&quot; (&quot;Serpent&quot;) &quot;An&quot; (&quot;Lord&quot;). Assyrian god Enki (Lord-Earth) proves that &quot;En&quot; and &quot;An&quot; variants mean &quot;Lord&quot;. Thus &quot;Can-An&quot; means &quot;Serpent-Lord&quot;, referring to Canaanite pantheon headed by Serpent Lord Dagon (i.e. El).
El is both noun (God) and subjective (god). To Phoenicians Baal was not El, because El fathered Baal Hadad-Hammon as well as all other deities of Phoenician pantheon.
Canaanites knew El with name Dagon: Dagon was El. Irish father god Dagda is form of Dagon-El i.e. Daniel: Canaanites introduced Dagon-Dagda to Ireland.
Canaanites were not descendants of Noah as Jewish propaganda claims but descendants of Danube urn-field cultures, who migrated through Epirus to Peloponnessos, Crete, and Aegean Sea islands, and eventually to Palestine. Also Celts descended from urn-field cultures of Rhein and Rh么ne, so Canaanites and Celts were at least cousins if not brothers. 
Dra-Gon comes from Greek meaning Huge-Snake: Lingual Dagon-Dragon connection is obvious, but they have symbolic link too. 
Snakes were symbols of healing gods fathered by Sun gods: Greek Apollo fathered Asclepius, Phoenician Toru-El fathered Eshmun, etc. Healer gods Asclepius and Eshmun both were depicted in dozens of reliefs, mosaics, and murals with snakes; ever since snakes were depicted as symbol animals of medicine sciences. Dragon (huge snake) was king of serpents, the healer god.
Eshmun was called &quot;Prince&quot; as Eshmun was son of Sun god El: in Phoenician language &quot;Prince&quot; was &quot;Ecooc&quot;: At Tartessos Carthaginians introduced Eshmun-Ecooc to Celts, and druids adopted Ecooc into druidic pantheon as Esus. Also Jesus Christ of Christianity based on Phoenician Eshmun. Roman Mercury, Greek Hermes-Asclepius, Egyptian Thoth, Phoenician Eshmun, Celtic Esus, and Canaanite Yeshu (i.e. Jesus Christ) were same jack-of-all-trades and healer deity.

In Phoenician pantheon Mary Magdala and Virgin Mary both belong to Kotharat-goddesses who were wives of El and mothers of all other deities in Phoenician pantheon. Jews denigrated Kotharat goddesses as whores.

El was Sun god, similar to Assyrian Shamash, Greek Apollo, Egyptian Ra, Celtic Bel etc. El was also known as Toru-El i.e. Bull God, what furthermore proves that El was Sun god, because Bull was symbol animal of Sun gods. Also in astrology Sun is exalted in Taurus.

Phoenicians knew planet Saturn with name Elus, what might have been equivalent to El. Saturn was also known as Black Sun, because it was outermost of bare-eyed visible planets. Saturn symbols were black cube (such Kaaba in Mecca) and six-pointed star i.e. Star of David i.e. Seal of Solomon.

Molok (&quot;Molok&quot; means &quot;King&quot;) Baal Hammon was chief god of Carthaginians who were Phoenicians. Molok Baal Hammon i.e. Hadad was thunder god. Canaanites knew Hammon-Hadad as Yahweh i.e. YHWH.
In Hebrew &quot;Yahweh&quot; i.e. &quot;YHWH&quot; is not noun per se but subjective meaning &quot;Outburst of Force&quot; which most obvious natural expression is thunder and thunderbolts. Thus Yahweh-YHWH belongs into group of thunder gods with Baal Hammon-Hadad, Indra, Jupiter, Taranis, Zeus etc. In astrology planet Jupiter was dedicated to thunder gods.&lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:91.158.238.162|91.158.238.162]] ([[User talk:91.158.238.162|talk]]  [[Special:Contributions/91.158.238.162|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;
:New material goes at the bottom, please sign your posts with four tildes (&lt;nowiki&gt;~~~~&lt;/nowiki&gt;).  Wikipedia does [[WP:NOR|not engage in original research]], please [[WP:CITE|cite]] and summarize [[WP:RS|reliable and mainstream academic sources (as defined at this link)]].  Also, familiarize yourself with [[False cognate]]s, [[Parallelomania]], and [[Theories_about_religions#Edward_Burnett_Tylor_and_James_George_Frazer|academia's rejection of reductionism in the study of the history and anthropology of religion]]; which are why all we go with books instead of random posts on this page.  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 21:40, 8 October 2014 (UTC)

== Unclear Meaning ==

There is a sentence in the text that says: It is difficult to determine to what extent the 'false worship' which the prophets stigmatize is the worship of Yahweh under a conception and with rites that treated him as a local nature god, or whether particular features of gods more often given the title Baal were consciously recognized to be distinct from Yahwism from the first. --- I sense that there is something wrong in the phrase &quot;to be distinct from Yahwism from the first&quot; but since I do not understand the meaning, I cannot correct it.[[Special:Contributions/190.81.202.250|190.81.202.250]] ([[User talk:190.81.202.250|talk]]) 18:13, 19 February 2015 (UTC)


==Introduction==
The introduction gives a false view of the generally accepted meaning of the word Baal when used as a proper noun.  Prior to the discovery of the Ugaritic texts it was sometimes thought that there were various and quite-separate gods called Baal. However, since the discovery of the Ugaritic texts it is generally accepted clear that there was one great Canaanite storm-and-fertility deity Baal-Hadad, and local manifestations of this one god.   Day, J. (1992). Baal (Deity). In D. N. Freedman (Ed.), The Anchor Yale Bible Dictionary (Vol. 1, p. 547). New York: Doubleday.  See also Encyclopaedia Judiaca     despite the biblical tendency to avoid the use of the word as a proper name, it is now quite clear that by pre-Israelite times the term had become the usual name of the weather-god of Syria-Palestine. vol 3 pg 10.

In particular this sentence should be replaced by something based on the above.       Nevertheless, few if any biblical uses of &quot;Baal&quot; refer to Hadad, the lord over the assembly of gods on the holy mount of Heaven; most refer to a variety of local spirit-deities worshiped as cult images, each called baal and regarded in the Hebrew Bible in that context as a false god.[[User:Theredheifer|Theredheifer]] ([[User talk:Theredheifer|talk]]) 18:53, 21 February 2015 (UTC)

==Dead links==
These guys are dead
* [http://www.bartleby.com/61/roots/S41.html Bartleby: ''American Heritage Dictionary'': Semitic roots: b{{sup|c}}l].
* [http://www.barca.fsnet.co.uk/baal-hammon.htm Punic images of Baal Hammon described.]
I don't even see what the point of the first one is but the second might be useful to find a cached version of. Better still, pull the PD-Art-compliant images and upload them to Commons for use in the article.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:LlywelynII|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#BBBBBB 0.1em 0.1em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;Llywelyn&lt;font color=&quot;Gold&quot;&gt;II&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 22:02, 12 August 2015 (UTC)

==WP:ERA==
Per {{sc|[[wp:era]]}}, [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Baal&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=1468387 this edit] established the use of the page as {{sc|bce/ce}}. Kindly maintain it consistently, pending a new consensus.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:LlywelynII|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#BBBBBB 0.1em 0.1em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;Llywelyn&lt;font color=&quot;Gold&quot;&gt;II&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 14:10, 13 August 2015 (UTC)

==Hebrew idiom==
:''A reminiscence of Baal as a title of a local fertility god (or referring to a particular god of subterraneous water) may occur in the [[Talmud]]ic Hebrew phrases ''field of the Baal'' and ''place of the Baal''.''
Well... ok... but {{sc|(a)}} needs a cite and {{sc|(b)}} needs an explanation as to what those &quot;Talmudic phrases&quot; are supposed to refer to and how that ties in with Baal's fertility status.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:LlywelynII|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#BBBBBB 0.1em 0.1em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;Llywelyn&lt;font color=&quot;Gold&quot;&gt;II&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 18:39, 13 August 2015 (UTC)

==Ugaritic form==
Removed this bit
:''&lt;nowiki&gt;An exception was in late Ugaritic, [[Ugaritic alphabet|whose alphabet]] marked vowels following a glottal stop:{{sfnp|Schniedewind &amp; al.|2007|p=[http://books.google.com.eg/books?id=L2T_4KVwpTQC&amp;pg=PA149 149]}} B士aL ({{unicode|}}).&lt;/nowiki&gt;''
that I added per [[Ugaritic language]], since it seems that my edit was the first appearance of  on the internet, whereas there are sources for . Not sure why the ''a'' is omitted though. Was the Ugaritic form actually closer to Arabic ''ba士l'' and just gets written ''Ba士al'' by analogy with Hebrew? or is it just that  is a variant from later inscriptions?&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:LlywelynII|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#BBBBBB 0.1em 0.1em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;Llywelyn&lt;font color=&quot;Gold&quot;&gt;II&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 02:13, 14 August 2015 (UTC)

{{anchor|Dubious}}
==Plural form==
I left this
:''The plural form is ba士alim, which appears in the Hebrew Scriptures but not other Phoenician, Canaanite, or Aramaic sources.''
as there's probably some underlying source or point but it's certainly belied by the ''DULAT'' entry for &quot;bl (II)&quot; which has copious examples of ''blm'' in Ugaritic both as a proper plural and as [[pluralis majestatis|an emphatic one]].&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:LlywelynII|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#BBBBBB 0.1em 0.1em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;Llywelyn&lt;font color=&quot;Gold&quot;&gt;II&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 23:00, 30 August 2015 (UTC)

== presumably in reference to Yahweh ==
Names including the element Ba士al presumably in reference to Yahweh include the judge Gideon (also known as Jeruba士al, lit. &quot;The Lord Strives&quot;), Saul's son Eshba士al (&quot;The Lord is Great&quot;), and David's son Beeliada (&quot;The Lord Knows&quot;).  The phrase presumably in reference to Yahweh sound sounds very much like OR.  I cannot find it in either of the RS given.  Therefore I suggest that we remove it.[[User:Johnmcintyre1959|Johnmcintyre1959]] ([[User talk:Johnmcintyre1959|talk]]) 07:21, 31 August 2015 (UTC)
:I get that some of the trouble here is that you'd like to change the {{sc|scope}} of this article so that it focuses exclusively on Ba'al Haddu (even though he has [[Hadad|his own article]] and this one has always been about the general term: I'm opposed but am fine with a Request for Comment to get other people's ideas). It'd be helpful if you stopped pretending that the RS discussing the &quot;Lord of Israel&quot; means that making reference to [[Yahweh]] is &quot;OR&quot;. The &quot;presumably&quot; leaves open the chance that it does reflect actual Ba'al worship among the Israelites, which the ''DDD'' at the very least leaves open as a possibility.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:LlywelynII|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#BBBBBB 0.1em 0.1em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;Llywelyn&lt;font color=&quot;Gold&quot;&gt;II&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 23:57, 31 August 2015 (UTC)
::All I am asking for is an RS where &quot;the Lord of Israel&quot; is referred to as YHWH.  Until an RS is provided that covers that then I am correct in asking for one.  The presumably is clearly OR, and you do not seem to be disputing that.  If it is not in there, then it gets removed, there is no need for any discussion.  See my other post covering your misunderstanding of the scope of this article.[[User:Johnmcintyre1959|Johnmcintyre1959]] ([[User talk:Johnmcintyre1959|talk]]) 17:02, 1 September 2015 (UTC)
:::This really falls under {{sc|[[wp:blue]]}} but I have no problem with {{sc|[[wp:agf]]}} so {{done}}. See also [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?search=lord+of+israel&amp;title=Special%3ASearch&amp;go=Go here], [https://scholar.google.com.hk/scholar?hl=en&amp;q=%22lord+of+israel%22&amp;btnG=&amp;as_sdt=1%2C5&amp;as_sdtp= here], and [http://www.google.com/search?q=%22lord+of+israel%22&amp;tbm=bks here] if this really is an expression with which you're unfamiliar.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:LlywelynII|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#BBBBBB 0.1em 0.1em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;Llywelyn&lt;font color=&quot;Gold&quot;&gt;II&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 01:24, 5 September 2015 (UTC)

Your reply reveals s complete misunderstanding of what I am stating.  I am not disputing that Lord of Israel can refer to YHVH.  I am pointing out that stating that the name Baal presumably refers to YHVH is simply  OR without an RS  the name Baal could simply refer to Israelite worship of Baal  refusal to provide an RS means I will take this to dispute   [[User:Johnmcintyre1959|Johnmcintyre1959]] ([[User talk:Johnmcintyre1959|talk]]) 16:45, 5 September 2015 (UTC)

== Baal as an Israelite and Judahite God ==
There is a need for a section that specifically refers to Baal worship among Israelites and Judahites, whether in opposition to, or alongside the cult of YHWY.  What is the best way of introducing this material. The article should not have Baal under the heading of Judaism.  Judaism is OR, and does not refer to anything before the Babylonian exile.[[User:Johnmcintyre1959|Johnmcintyre1959]] ([[User talk:Johnmcintyre1959|talk]]) 07:25, 31 August 2015 (UTC)
:There is a section on the worship of the Canaanite Ba'al. It's under the Canaanite area. Feel free to add RS about his worship among the Israelites under Jezebel &amp;c. There's no need for a separate ''section'' about his worship among the Israelites until it's well-referenced and long enough that it's helpful to the article's structure. Otherwise, it can be a paragraph or two within the existing section.

: #Ba'al as a divine title in Israel and Judah, besides being unpleasant to look at, needlessly un{{sc|terse}}, and out of line with the other section heads... is obviously confusing enough to you that you didn't realize it's ''not'' talking about the Canaanite Ba'al at all: it deals with Ba'al as a title of the Israelite god Yahweh, always has, and has just been reworded into a terser form to make that clear. 

:It's fine if you think the way forward is to {{sc|fork}} the content (the Yahweh bit is already dealt with at [[Names of God in Judaism]], e.g.) or turn this page into a {{sc|dab}}, but as it's stood for years it's not about a single entitygiven that it obviously changed over time and with contextbut about the term. Early on, it may have been limited to Ba'al Haddu; by the 1st millennium, he was a separate god from Ba'al; similarly, the Israelites' use of the name for Yahweh is a separate use of the term, which is within the current {{sc|scope}} of this article but needs a separate section.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:LlywelynII|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#BBBBBB 0.1em 0.1em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;Llywelyn&lt;font color=&quot;Gold&quot;&gt;II&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 23:53, 31 August 2015 (UTC)

:::There appears to have been no consensus for the change from the title Ba'al as a divine title in Israel and Judah.  That title was used for a long time. It is you who is confused, the section has not been about Baal as a title for YHWH, that is simply your OR.  The section has been about Israelite and Judahite worship of Baal.  No one is claiming that this article is solely about a single entity. It has always been about the use of the term Baal in all its meanings.  You seem to want to change the scope of the article to match opinions which are not backed up by the RS[[User:Johnmcintyre1959|Johnmcintyre1959]] ([[User talk:Johnmcintyre1959|talk]]) 17:32, 1 September 2015 (UTC)
::::It is not about that at all and you are completely misreading both the section and the source, which are talking about the ''name'' Ba'al being applied to the Lord of Israel [[Yahweh]], not the Canaanite god. You're about to hit {{sc|[[wp:3rr]]}} so kindly restrict yourself to the talk page before building some consensus for your scope and definitional change.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:LlywelynII|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#BBBBBB 0.1em 0.1em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;Llywelyn&lt;font color=&quot;Gold&quot;&gt;II&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 00:24, 5 September 2015 (UTC)
:::::As for Baal being applied to the LoI, we should remove this RS.  Ayles (1904), p. 103.  Nowhere in the text do the names Jeruba士al, Eshba士al or Beeliada occur, so I suggest that it should be removed.[[User:Johnmcintyre1959|Johnmcintyre1959]] ([[User talk:Johnmcintyre1959|talk]]) 20:37, 7 September 2015 (UTC)

== Baal Hadad ==
This claim
:''Most modern scholarship asserts that this Ba士alusually distinguished as &quot;The Lord&quot; (注, Ha Ba士al)was identical with the storm and fertility god Hadad;''[9][18][12]
is too strong based on the RS.  Of the RS given Pope states that despite the biblical tendency to avoid the use of the word as a proper name, it is now quite clear that by pre-Israelite times the term had become the usual name of the weather-god of Syria-Palestine. In the El- Amarna letters the logogram for the weather-god is conventionally read Addu, but that it is sometimes to be read Ba士lu is indicated by the addition of the phonetic complement-lu, as well as by the names like Mut dIm written syllabically ....... In the El-Amarna letters Canaanite clients addressed the Egyptian king as My Baal, my Addu. '''In the Ugaritic mythological texts Ba士lu (b士l) is the name of the god which is used more than twice as often as his next most frequent  name, Haddu (hd).''' The latter name (Amarna, Addu) is to be related to Arabic hadda (break, crash) with reference to thunder. The variant form Hadad (hdd) is attested to  only once in Ugaritic.  My emphasis.

From the other RS, Pettinato  1980 argues for Baal as an original Cannanite God distinct from Hadad.  and Kapelrud  1952 50:52 that the name Hadad was secondarily applied to Baal.  Only Day states that Baal was the personal name of Hadad.

That renders this  A ''minority propose that Ba士al was a native Canaanite deity whose cult was identified with or absorbed aspects of Adad's.[9]''  my italics   too weak.

Can we agree to replace the terms 'most modern scholarship' and 'a minority' with something less numerical? Suggestions welcome.  [[User:Johnmcintyre1959|Johnmcintyre1959]] ([[User talk:Johnmcintyre1959|talk]]) 11:11, 31 August 2015 (UTC)

Mercer's Dictionary of the Bible pg 79, also has it that Baal and Hadad are usually regarded as separate deities.[[User:Johnmcintyre1959|Johnmcintyre1959]] ([[User talk:Johnmcintyre1959|talk]]) 12:38, 31 August 2015 (UTC)

Kingdom of Priests: A History of Old Testament Israel  By Eugene H. Merrill pg 179 states that according to many scholars Baal was an epithet of Hadad. That coud be useful.[[User:Johnmcintyre1959|Johnmcintyre1959]] ([[User talk:Johnmcintyre1959|talk]]) 12:49, 31 August 2015 (UTC)
:Go reread the Hermann source, which you apparently haven't. Section II makes it quite clear that the understanding of the deity &quot;Ba'al&quot; has evolved from (early 19th century) a unified solar god to (later 19th-early 20th c.) disparate local gods to (post-Ugarit) a unified weather god Hadad spread across many local cults, with a minority of dissenting scholars. It precisely backs up that point:
::''Their identity is nevertheless often emphasized in modern studies. Many scholars hold that Hadad was the real name of the West Semitic weather god...''
:followed by a laundry list of sources to that effectthe named ones are Eissfeldt, Dahood, Gese, De Moor &amp; Mulder, Caquot, Sznycerand only a few minority voices saying otherwise. It's important to note the disagreement (particularly in light of your desire to treat this article as dealing with a single god rather than a term that was used for several different ones) but it's also important to note which is the majority and which is the minority view. 

:Now, of course, the ''DDD'' article looks like very solid scholarship to me. If it actually is {{sc|fringe}} or just ''wrong''... well, then, let's fix that. You're welcome to find other RS to dissent but I don't think that it's inaccurate. Most of the scholarship I saw while patching up this article ''does'' assume an identity between the Ba'als and Hadad, despite the ''DDD''&amp;rsquo;s review of the material stating they'd diverged by at least the 1st millennium BC.

:Based on this passage, in addition to changing the article's {{sc|scope}} to focus solely on Hadad, are you proposing to merge [[Hadad]]'s article ''here''? I think it's still better the way we had it: treating Ba'al in all its different forms here while leaving Hadad at his article. (Whether [[Hadad]] and [[Adad]] really need separate treatment is another issue. I understand why they're separate but it'd probably be more helpful to just treat them as sections of a single page.)&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:LlywelynII|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#BBBBBB 0.1em 0.1em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;Llywelyn&lt;font color=&quot;Gold&quot;&gt;II&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 00:47, 1 September 2015 (UTC)2

::You should be much more careful about throwing around claims as to who has read what.  I have pg 132 of Hermann in front of me, and it uses the word Many.  You can't simply count up the number of references in a SINGLE source, as an RS for the use of the terms most, and a minority.  If you can find an RS that states the terms most and a minority then use it here. Until then I suggest that we change the text to state, (as per the RS)  Many modern scholars assert that etc etc, and Other scholars  propose that Ba士al was a native  Cannanite deity, with whom the name Hadad was later associated.  I can then list the references that back this claim that.  There is no need to discuss the separate article of Baal Hadad.[[User:Johnmcintyre1959|Johnmcintyre1959]] ([[User talk:Johnmcintyre1959|talk]]) 17:53, 1 September 2015 (UTC)
:::Fair enough. The important thing is to communicate which one is the minority view and which the majority. If you prefer to replace the word majority by including every source in the ''DDD'' so that the reader can see a dozen odd cites against a single opposing voice, that's fine with me. You're banged up against your {{sc|[[wp:3rr]]}} though, so refrain from editing the page in any other way [such as removing those terms and ''not'' replacing them with such an equivalent cite disparity] without building more support here on the talk page.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:LlywelynII|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#BBBBBB 0.1em 0.1em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;Llywelyn&lt;font color=&quot;Gold&quot;&gt;II&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 00:23, 5 September 2015 (UTC)

No that is not the answer the answer is to use the word many and the words other scholars  the present wording is OR based on as single source so
I am perfectly entitled to change it   You clearly have not read widely enough  there Is more than one other source  also note that I am not reverting I am making a new change which is as per RS so the 3 rule starts again   [[User:Johnmcintyre1959|Johnmcintyre1959]] ([[User talk:Johnmcintyre1959|talk]]) 17:01, 5 September 2015 (UTC)

== Scope of the article ==
It has been suggested (on my talk page, rather than here, I do not know why) that
:''Glad you finally went to the [[Talk:Baal|talk page]] there. Kindly keep it there since you're about to bang up against {{sc|[[wp:3rr]]}} and I'm sure you're well-meaning: it just seems like you just haven't read through the ''DDD'' article and are misunderstanding the article's {{sc|[[wp:scope]]}}. [[Hadad]] deals with Hadad; [[Baal]] has always been about the general term, in reference to Hadad, to Yahweh, and to other local gods. If you'd like to ''change'' that scope, I understand the idea but think it's a mistake since it would involve {{sc|[[wp:merge|wp:merging]]}} it with the [[Hadad]] article and I don't think the scholarship is really settled on that point. Anyway, let's talk about it over there and, if you don't like my take on it, present your thoughts and let's do a {{sc|[[wp:rfc]]}} or something to get some more opinions.''  Also see this from a recent reversion.  ''Undid revision 678739348 by Johnmcintyre1959 (talk) This article is not about a single god Ba'al. Read its history and reread the article''
My italics.

This reveals a fundamental misunderstanding about the scope pf this article. I am not claiming that this article should only be about the multilple references to a single God known as Baal, or to multiple local Baals.  However lets look at the history, as invited.

Here is the present lede.
:Baal (/be瑟l/),[1][n 1] properly Ba士al (Ugaritic: ;[5] Phoenician: ; Biblical Hebrew: 注, pronounced [baal]),[6] was a title and honorific meaning &quot;lord&quot; in the Northwest Semitic languages spoken in the Levant during antiquity. From its use among people, it came to be applied to gods. Scholars previously associated the theonym with solar cults and with a variety of unrelated patron deities, but inscriptions have shown that the name Ba士al was particularly associated with the storm and fertility god Hadad and his local manifestations.[7] The Hebrew Scriptures, compiled and curated over a span of centuries, include early use of the term in reference to their God Yahweh, generic use in reference to various Levantine deities, and finally pointed application towards Hadad, who was decried as a false god. This use was taken over into Christianity and Islam, sometimes under the opprobrious form Beelzebub.

Here it is with my change.
:&lt;nowiki&gt;''Baal''' ({{IPAc-en||b|e瑟||l}}),&lt;ref name=oed&gt;''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'' (1885), &quot;[http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/14174 Baal, ''n.'']&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|group=n|The [[American English|American pronunciation]] is usually the same&lt;ref&gt;''Oxford Dictionaries'' (2015), &quot;[http://www.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/american_english/Baal Baal]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=mwo/&gt; but some speakers prefer variants closer to the original sound, such as {{IPAc-en|b||||l}} or {{IPAc-en||b||l}}.&lt;ref name=mwo&gt;''Merriam-Webster Online'' (2015), &quot;[http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/baal baal]&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Webb's Easy Bible Names Pronunciation Guide'' (2012), &quot;[https://books.google.com.hk/books?id=IrrtAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT36 Baal]&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;}} properly '''Ba士al''' ({{lang-uga|{{linktext|}}}};{{sfnp|De Moor &amp; al.|1987|p=[https://books.google.com.hk/books?id=fu_Y5qnoCpAC&amp;pg=PA1 1]}} {{lang-phn|{{linktext|}}}};&lt;!--right-to-left--&gt; {{lang-hbo|{{linktext|注}}}}, {{IPA-he|baal|pron}}),{{sfnp|Strong|1890|loc=[http://www.blueletterbible.org/lang/lexicon/lexicon.cfm?strongs=H1166 H1166]}} was a god worshiped in many ancient Middle Eastern communities, especially among the [[Canaanites]], who considered him a fertility deity and one of the most important of the gods.&lt;/nowiki&gt;
Followed by the above.

Now this version of the lede is from 21 May 2012 !!!!!
:Ba士al (Biblical Hebrew 注, pronounced [baal], usually spelled Baal in English) is a Northwest Semitic title and honorific meaning &quot;master&quot; or &quot;lord&quot;[1] that is used for various gods who were patrons of cities in the Levant and Asia Minor, cognate to Akkadian Blu. A Baalist or Baalite means a worshipper of Baal.

:&quot;Ba士al&quot; can refer to any god and even to human officials; in some texts it is used as a substitute for Hadad, a god of the rain, thunder, fertility and agriculture, and the lord of Heaven. Since only priests were allowed to utter his divine name, Hadad, Baal was commonly used. Nevertheless, few if any Biblical uses of &quot;Ba士al&quot; refer to Hadad, the lord over the assembly of gods on the holy mount of Heaven, but rather refer to any number of local spirit-deities worshipped as cult images, each called ba士al and regarded in the Hebrew Bible in that context as a &quot;false god&quot;.

Note that it also contains the sub section  Ba士al as a divine title in Israel and Judah

This article has for a long time been about Baal as a God or Gods.  The use of the article to discuss the meaning of the word lord, master, etc is not the primary purpose of the article.

I am not changing the article, I am restoring it to what has always been its primary purpose.[[User:Johnmcintyre1959|Johnmcintyre1959]] ([[User talk:Johnmcintyre1959|talk]]) 17:16, 1 September 2015 (UTC)

Encyclopaedia Judaica vol EJ vol III pg 12 article Baal worship   Nevertheless, despite the biblical tendency to avoid the use of the word as a proper name, it is now quite
clear that by pre-Israelite times the term had become the usual name of the weather-god of Syria-Palestine.  is an RS for the use of the term in reference to God/Gods.  Also https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=n7i7k06rq7IC&amp;pg=PA55&amp;dq=baal&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0CCMQ6AEwAThQahUKEwi79rWowNbHAhX0K9sKHfgpDR4#v=onepage&amp;q=baal&amp;f=false The Dictionary of Demons Baal the Cannanite name for God or Lord.  Also  Zondervan Illustrated Bible Dictionary  By J. D. Douglas, Merrill C. Tenney  the word Baal in the OT (sic) most often refers to a Semitic deity.  in early years used for the God of Israel - Yahweh.[[User:Johnmcintyre1959|Johnmcintyre1959]] ([[User talk:Johnmcintyre1959|talk]]) 19:03, 1 September 2015 (UTC)
:I really don't know what to say to [[User:Johnmcintyre1959|you]] if you think that &quot;Baal... is a Northwest Semitic title and honorific meaning &quot;master&quot; or &quot;lord&quot;&quot; [the scope which has actually been upheld by myself and other editors] being turned into &quot;Baal was a god&quot; isn't a scope change. It's so obviously incorrect that there's really nothing more to say except for you're up against your {{sc|[[wp:3rr]]}} and should refrain from editing this page until you've gathered support for your changes on the talk page. This article has started the way it has and focused the way it has since the [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Baal&amp;oldid=100771 very first copy-and-paste from the ''Britannica'' in 2002]. I'm not even saying that's the best way to handle it: it's just how it's always been. As I told you on your talk page [because it was an issue for you rather than the page itself], I suggest launching a {{sc|rfc}} and getting some other voices involved so you don't feel you're being stymied by a single other editor and can make some peace with the magnitude of your error and/or build a consensus to change the article to reflect the {{sc|scope}} you think it should have instead of the one it always has.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:LlywelynII|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#BBBBBB 0.1em 0.1em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;Llywelyn&lt;font color=&quot;Gold&quot;&gt;II&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 00:19, 5 September 2015 (UTC)
::I really don't know what to say to you if you think that a single sentence from a cut and paste from Britannica justifies your claim that this article is only about Baal as a term for lord or master.  The original article refers to the God Baal, and to the various Baals known by their local names.  The article overwhelming supports this longstanding text which I wish to restore so that we can get back to the original purpose of the article.

Ba士al (Biblical Hebrew 注, pronounced [baal], usually spelled Baal in English) is a Northwest Semitic title and honorific meaning &quot;master&quot; or &quot;lord&quot;[1] that is used for various gods who were patrons of cities in the Levant and Asia Minor, cognate to Akkadian Blu. A Baalist or Baalite means a worshipper of Baal.
&quot;Ba士al&quot; can refer to any god and even to human officials; in some texts it is used as a substitute for Hadad, a god of the rain, thunder, fertility and agriculture, and the lord of Heaven. Since only priests were allowed to utter his divine name, Hadad, Baal was commonly used. Nevertheless, few if any Biblical uses of &quot;Ba士al&quot; refer to Hadad, the lord over the assembly of gods on the holy mount of Heaven, but rather refer to any number of local spirit-deities worshipped as cult images, each called ba士al and regarded in the Hebrew Bible in that context as a &quot;false god&quot;.

How you can claim that it is a scope change to say that Baal is a God is beyond me.  The article has always said that Baal is both a title meaning lord etc, and a God/Gods.  Will you accept that something close to this text above be restored to the lede, or shall we take it to dispute?[[User:Johnmcintyre1959|Johnmcintyre1959]] ([[User talk:Johnmcintyre1959|talk]]) 21:34, 5 September 2015 (UTC)

:Whilst the article may have started with a cut and paste from the 1911 Encyclopedia Britannica, the current EB article on Baal makes it very clear as to the current scope and meaning of the word.  '''Baal, god worshiped in many ancient Middle Eastern communities, especially among the Canaanites, who apparently considered him a fertility deity and one of the most important gods in the pantheon. As a Semitic common noun baal (Hebrew ba士al) meant owner or lord, although it could be used more generally; for example, a baal of wings was a winged creature, and, in the plural, baalim of arrows indicated archers'''  My bold.  If we want to restrict ourselves then we could change the title to more meaningfully reflect the limited relevance of the article to what is now understood to be the meaning of the word Baal.[[User:Johnmcintyre1959|Johnmcintyre1959]] ([[User talk:Johnmcintyre1959|talk]]) 20:04, 7 September 2015 (UTC)

== Early use of Baal to refer to YHWH ==
This claim in the lede
:The Hebrew Scriptures, compiled and curated over a span of centuries, include early use of the term in reference to their God Yahweh
should also include the  RS Hermann DDD pg 136 which states that there was an Israelite cult of Baal. Where should this go?[[User:Johnmcintyre1959|Johnmcintyre1959]] ([[User talk:Johnmcintyre1959|talk]]) 19:06, 1 September 2015 (UTC)
:In the section on the Canaanite Ba'al, obviously.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:LlywelynII|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#BBBBBB 0.1em 0.1em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;Llywelyn&lt;font color=&quot;Gold&quot;&gt;II&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 00:14, 5 September 2015 (UTC)

==Returning to attempts to improve the page==
[https://books.google.com.hk/books?id=S4geAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA15 this source] says that tablets (now called the &quot;Ugaritic Pantheon&quot;) were discovered in the 1920s and '50s. Discussing the Ugaritic Ba'al, they place him in 3rd position after El and Dagan and describe ''7'' Ba'als: Ba'al Sapuna and 6 others who are distinguished simply by numbering them. (a) That should be included but (b) it could use some context for how scholars square that with their present idea that the Canaanite Ba'al was usually simply a manifestation of Hadad and (c) for what the differences are between those numbered Ba'als. The source offers that there are references to &quot;Ba'al's brothers&quot; in some other texts but hopefully something has been discovered since then. Also note (d) that [[Jebel Aqra]] was worshipped in its own right separate from the cult of Ba'al of Zaphon.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:LlywelynII|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#BBBBBB 0.1em 0.1em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;Llywelyn&lt;font color=&quot;Gold&quot;&gt;II&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 01:09, 5 September 2015 (UTC)

Not all scholars agree that Baal was Hadad.  Baal was an Israelite and Judahite God as well.  This material has nothing to do with what you claim is the sole purpose of the article which is to refer to the use of Basl as a reference to YAHWEH.   [[User:Johnmcintyre1959|Johnmcintyre1959]] ([[User talk:Johnmcintyre1959|talk]]) 16:49, 5 September 2015 (UTC)

==Sources for future article expansion==
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20070607040504/http://www.geocities.com/SoHo/Lofts/2938/majdei.html this archived web page] and
* [http://www.ancient.eu/baal/ this ''AE'' entry]
probably aren't {{sc|rs}} on their own but have a wealth of information on the Ugaritic Ba'al's stories and epithets in translation that could be used while searching for true {{sc|rs}}.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:LlywelynII|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#BBBBBB 0.1em 0.1em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;Llywelyn&lt;font color=&quot;Gold&quot;&gt;II&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 01:50, 5 September 2015 (UTC)

== Request for RS ==
I cannot find an RS that backs up this claim;   From its use among people, it came to be applied to gods.   If no one can find one I propose to remove it. [[User:Johnmcintyre1959|Johnmcintyre1959]] ([[User talk:Johnmcintyre1959|talk]]) 21:36, 5 September 2015 (UTC)
:It's good that you come here and talk about it but you're making it very hard to {{sc|[[wp:agf|assume]]}} your good faith with such tendentious requests. The {{sc|primary}} and continuing meaning of the word is &quot;owner&quot;, &quot;lord&quot;, and &quot;husband&quot;, as backed up by numerous cites in the text; the Semitic languages don't use the word for leaseholders and husbands because it was originally applied to gods; it went the other way around and {{sc|[[wp:blue]]}} covers this point entirely. {{sc|[[wp:leadcite]]}} suggests we not use citations in the lead for things that are well established in the text. (Here, in the #Word section.)

:So... it'd be better if you just withdrew the tendentious request. That said, {{sc|[[wp:leadcite]]}} does permit citations in the lead for challenged points and if you ''really'' were doubting that it's correct, we can add the cite. ''I'' really feel that it's needless and bad form, but it's not something we'll have to remove until this article goes up for {{sc|[[wp:ga]]}} status and that seems like it's aways off.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:LlywelynII|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#BBBBBB 0.1em 0.1em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;Llywelyn&lt;font color=&quot;Gold&quot;&gt;II&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 01:39, 7 September 2015 (UTC)

::The argument that it can be derived from the text in the article just makes me more certain that the cite is required. I see that you have added EB 1878. The latest online version of EB does not contain that text, so I suggest that we need another RS, as that one is so out of date.[[User:Johnmcintyre1959|Johnmcintyre1959]] ([[User talk:Johnmcintyre1959|talk]]) 17:39, 7 September 2015 (UTC)

==Jezebel's god==
It's good that we're adding more scholarship about who it might have been. On the other hand, do be careful not to violate {{sc|[[wp:undue]]}}: if Day's book (and don't introduce needless new versions: just use the existing citation we already have) is the only one working the angle that it's Ba士al Shamem (and try to use the proper form of his name consistently in the running text) then we shouldn't go into excessive detail on his arguments, giving it an undue weight in our own presentation. His reasoning is available at the provided source.

The alternative would be to follow the other source and just go into more detail as to why the scholars feel it's the Tyrian Ba士al: certainly Day's argument as presentedthey wouldn't accept Melqart because they could only have one Ba士al at a time and they've already got one and 'e'z verr' niceis unconvincing to the point of dubiousness. The Canaanites had so little problem with the idea of more than one Ba士al that Ugarit just laundry lists them with numbers: Ba士al Zaphon, Ba士al 1, Ba士al 2, Ba士al 3... In fact, the snippet I can see on Google Books shows that Day's argument was ''better'' than that: he didn't argue that Melqart couldn't've been accepted by the Israelites because they had a Ba士al who was Ba士al Shamem. He argues that the Tyrian Ba士al himself was Ba士al Shamem during this period.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:LlywelynII|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#BBBBBB 0.1em 0.1em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;Llywelyn&lt;font color=&quot;Gold&quot;&gt;II&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 01:39, 7 September 2015 (UTC)

:One of the problems is that the single source Josephus for the claim that this is Melqart is so weak, as he is unreliable on so much else.  I can replace the Josephus RS with Day who admits that 'Many standard work on this narrative' take the opposite view to him. Of course at present there is no RS for this claim, who is ridiculous for an article of this long standing, and reveals how much work is needed (and how much is 'assumed' or actually OR in the article). BEWR only provides an RS for the word Cannanite, although the pg number is not given, it is pg 24.  There is no discussion in BEWR for Melqart v Baal that I can find. I can add in Day's summary  for and against, and list major scholars on both sides.  As I thought I wrote earlier I am not claiming that Day is alone in this view. Your view on the unconvincing nature of Day's argument is not relevant, and just OR, as with respect, you are not competent to judge such a world renowned scholar. I only picked one of his arguments, I can certainly summarise them all.[[User:Johnmcintyre1959|Johnmcintyre1959]] ([[User talk:Johnmcintyre1959|talk]]) 16:45, 7 September 2015 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>5csd5xlrfmxtcmyk2zff5c5junbrdvs</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
