<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Alexander technique</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>177292</id>
    <revision>
      <id>740255429</id>
      <parentid>740248266</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-20T00:25:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lowercase sigmabot III</username>
        <id>17518500</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Archiving 2 discussion(s) to [[Talk:Alexander technique/Archive 3]]) (bot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24117">{{Talk header}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Dance|class=Start|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Alternative medicine|class=Start}}
{{WikiProject Skepticism|class=|importance=}}
}}
{{Old AfD multi|page=Alexander technique|date=28 September 2010|result='''keep'''}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 3
|minthreadsleft = 4
|algo = old(30d)
|archive = Talk:Alexander technique/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Auto archiving notice|bot=MiszaBot I |age= |units= 30 days}}
{{Backwardscopy|title=ARO HEALING Touching Lives THEORIES, TECHNIQUES and THERAPIES: The Techniques and Therapies of Aro-Healing|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=brZNBAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT230|author=Lynette Barnard|year=2014|org=Xlibris Corporation|comments=a lot of the book seems to be copied from this and other WP articles}}

== Verifiable? ==

This was removed as not verifiable.

''...a systematic review by Woodman and Moore (2012)[&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |author1=J. P. Woodman |author2=N. R. Moore | title = Evidence for the effectiveness of Alexander Technique lessons in medical and health-related conditions: a systematic review | journal = International Journal of Clinical Practice | volume = 66 | issue = 1 | pages = 98–112 |date=January 2012  | doi = 10.1111/j.1742-1241.2011.02817.x | pmid = 22171910}}&lt;/ref&gt;]. 
''

The Australian review cites this review as moderate in quality, and possibly the only review that dealt with studies before 2008 a more comprehensive view. With a change in wording I see no reason to not add this review.

Why is this review not verifiable? Thanks.([[User:Littleolive oil|Littleolive oil]] ([[User talk:Littleolive oil|talk]]) 17:23, 9 September 2016 (UTC))
{{reflist-talk}}
:How does it verify the text &quot;The most comprehensive guide to the scientific evidence for the efficacy of Alexander Technique lessons is a systematic review by Woodman and Moore&quot;? The review (which we already cite) has been superseded by some later work in most respects too. [[User:Alexbrn|Alexbrn]] ([[User talk:Alexbrn|talk]]) 17:29, 9 September 2016 (UTC)

Ok. Good. I see the review is used elsewhere, and I did suggest changing the text to reflect the review. However, its used elsewhere so end of discussion.Thanks.([[User:Littleolive oil|Littleolive oil]] ([[User talk:Littleolive oil|talk]]) 17:34, 9 September 2016 (UTC))
:Note, content was originally added by STATRG  [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Alexander_technique&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=738538859&amp;oldid=736150405 here], reverted by Alxbrn  [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Alexander_technique&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=738538859 here], added back by STATRG [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Alexander_technique&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=738590040&amp;oldid=738559077 this edit], removed by me [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Alexander_technique&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=738590040 here], added back by STATRG [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Alexander_technique&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=738590273 here]  and removed again by me [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Alexander_technique&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=738592302&amp;oldid=738591758 here].  On STATRG's Talk page, I left a [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=User_talk:STATRG&amp;oldid=738590916 welcome message] and a note about OR for STATRG [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=User_talk:STATRG&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=738590916 here]. [[User:Jytdog|Jytdog]] ([[User talk:Jytdog|talk]]) 00:14, 10 September 2016 (UTC)

==Attempt to change wording== 
Who is edit warring who? Seems disingenuous to cite me for edit warring when I made a change and was reverted. I cited the review conclusions specific to the technique, that's how we best serve science, the review, and the encyclopedia. I can't fight tag teaming nor do I want to.([[User:Littleolive oil|Littleolive oil]] ([[User talk:Littleolive oil|talk]]) 18:12, 9 September 2016 (UTC))
::LittleOliveOil we negotiated the heck out of this above - a long and unpleasant negotiation - but we finally reached a point where everyone was happy enough and not too unhappy.  Unilaterally reopening that, especially with no prior discussion, is a prime example of [[WP:TENDENTIOUS]] editing and is just disruptive.  If - and I hope you think long and hard about it - you ''really'' want to re-open this negotiation again, please start a discussion here, taking into account the work we already did.  Again I find it remarkable that you have said over and over that the key aspects of Alexander are about theater/dance and not about health ([https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=715127169 dif, first comment here], [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:Alexander_technique&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=715154319 here], [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=715156263 here], [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=716082574 here], but every single edit you have made to the article has been to this stuff about health benefits or the lack thereof.  [https://tools.wmflabs.org/sigma/usersearch.py?name=Littleolive+oil&amp;page=Alexander_technique&amp;server=enwiki&amp;max= Every one  of the 27]. 
:: but please do really consider if you want to re-open the discussion.  Thanks.  [[User:Jytdog|Jytdog]] ([[User talk:Jytdog|talk]]) 18:18, 9 September 2016 (UTC)

:::We did not discuss this section and the specific wording which reflects the conclusions reviewers reached on the technique. We were discussing the lead.

:::What I said is that the technique is a long-used technique in theater and that the research is less dominant than is AT use in a practical setting in theater ( summarizing myself). I am working on an article as a whole , so in that light, whatever my views are I am attempting to deal with the research in a forthright and accurate way. The information I added was specific and very specific to the reviewers own words. The words edit warred  in place were  not and were as far as I can see sourced to a blog. Jytdog do not threaten me,  and do not mischaracterize my actions or try to make them what they are not. You reverted a good faith edit as did Alexbrn. As I said above but I'll repeat it, I have no interest in a discussion in which my actions are mischaracterized, and where there is tag teaming. What is tendentious are the efforts to mischaracterize this technique, one that is so mainstream in the theater world as to be blatantly obvious to anyone who has any kind of experience in theater /dance. I understand some editors here do not have this kind of experience, but what is not acceptable is to paint pictures that are false both of the topic area and the editors editing here.([[User:Littleolive oil|Littleolive oil]] ([[User talk:Littleolive oil|talk]]) 18:55, 9 September 2016 (UTC))

::::I'd add. I have no interest in this technique's health benefits outside of the  posture that is necessary for healthy and effective movement in a performance format. I had no interest in the research, did not even know there was any, and had no idea the technique was being touted for its other health benefits. Its use, lets call it clinical, is clear. So no I didn't come to this article trying to skew the research as is implied by some editors and Jytdog above, and could care less personally; it doesn't impact me in a personal way. However, the bias exhibited here in terms of wanting to make sure the technique is characterized as a pseudoscience when its not a science, its a movement technique, and when it looks like there is legitimate research connected to the technique is mind boggling. I can only wonder with real amazement as to how a movement technique has come under the thumb of  the pseudoscience fighters.([[User:Littleolive oil|Littleolive oil]] ([[User talk:Littleolive oil|talk]]) 19:24, 9 September 2016 (UTC))
:::::Is it a pseudoscience? Awaiting comment in the thread above! [[User:Alexbrn|Alexbrn]] ([[User talk:Alexbrn|talk]]) 19:35, 9 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::No interest in getting into a discussion when editors start mischaracterizing. I've said what I have to say, but I will ask you a question. Is an apple pseudoscience or is it that there is a possibility that research on that apple, just a fruit and a food, could be pseudoscientific? Science is the tool and the servant not the master. I was shocked to hear a physician here say medicine is science. I find that broad brush  approach surprising. Medicine, I hope, is a healing modality; its servant along with the physician is science.  Pseudoscience theories according to Wikipedia,  &quot;...characteristically fail to adhere to scientific standards and methods.&quot; Few people eating apples or teaching a movement technique as is taught all over the world with AT are carrying on scientific research. As with apple eating there may be good research on AT and there may be research which does not comply with scientific standards and methods. Pseudoscience is possible with both. Neither the apple nor the AT technique are pseudoscientific in and of themselves, and the while science behind eating the apple serves the apple and its benefits, the apple is not in and of itself science. Since you and others have allowed reviews on the study of the AT into this article I have to assume that per our RS you consider these reviews to be science not pseudoscience. Perhaps you have discarded other research as not compliant with good scientific standards-pseudoscience.([[User:Littleolive oil|Littleolive oil]] ([[User talk:Littleolive oil|talk]]) 22:10, 9 September 2016 (UTC))
:::::::Following the analogy, this article isn't about apples, but a concoction made from apples that's notable for health claims about it. --[[User:Ronz|Ronz]] ([[User talk:Ronz|talk]]) 22:37, 9 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::In my view AT is notable for its use by people in the performing arts to help them be more aware of their bodies so they can perform better.  The claims about &quot;health benefits&quot; are fringey and are not a big deal overall, and are appropriately WEIGHTed in the article.   The fuss over the lack of evidence that it is good for much healthwise (treating any actual disease or condition) is hard for me to understand.  This is not like acupuncture or something. [[User:Jytdog|Jytdog]] ([[User talk:Jytdog|talk]]) 22:44, 9 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::Yes and its notable because of its world wide use not because of the research on it. I agree. I wouldn't expect to find health benefits from what is basically a posture technique beyond the kinds of effects good posture and good balance bring. Fringe  may be a better word to describe its research at this point in time.([[User:Littleolive oil|Littleolive oil]] ([[User talk:Littleolive oil|talk]]) 23:00, 9 September 2016 (UTC))

===section header sidebar===
{{collapse top|section header sidebar}}
:::::::::::LittleOlive Oil. The edit that was reverted, after which you opened this section, was [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Alexander_technique&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=738552225&amp;oldid=738544358 this], shown via redaction marks: An Australian review concluded that the Alexander Technique might help alleviate [[lower back pain]] in the short-term (up to 3 months) but that the safety and cost-effectiveness of the treatment was not established. &lt;s&gt;It considered the&lt;/s&gt; &lt;u&gt;The Australian review concluded there is insufficient&lt;/u&gt;  evidence &lt;u&gt;for conclusions&lt;/u&gt;  to be &lt;s&gt;poor&lt;/s&gt; &lt;u&gt;drawn in regards to other clinical conditions&lt;/u&gt;.   	
:::::::::::When you opened this section, [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:Alexander_technique&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=738555579 here], you named it &quot;Edit warring, tag teaming?&quot;
:::::::::::I changed the header [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3AAlexander_technique&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=738596398&amp;oldid=738596340 here] with edit note: &quot;More neutral header&quot; to &quot;Health claims redux&quot;	
:::::::::::In [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:Alexander_technique&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=738596398 this edit], you changed the header to &quot;Attempt to change wording per source&quot; and your edit note read: &quot;Mischaracterization. Again.This was never about health effects, but simply about closer wording to source&quot;
:::::::::::The content you edited was about health.  Again, every single edit you have made to the article has been to this stuff about health benefits or the lack thereof.  [https://tools.wmflabs.org/sigma/usersearch.py?name=Littleolive+oil&amp;page=Alexander_technique&amp;server=enwiki&amp;max= Every one  of the 27].   I have recorded the diffs here.  [[User:Jytdog|Jytdog]] ([[User talk:Jytdog|talk]]) 23:25, 9 September 2016 (UTC)

{{od}}I edited content to reword the review conclusions to be closer to what the source says. To say the edit was about health is  a broad generalization which could be used almost anywhere and for anyone on this article, and ultimately mischaracterizes  my edit. Are syntax changes about health? What are you trying to do Jytdog?([[User:Littleolive oil|Littleolive oil]] ([[User talk:Littleolive oil|talk]]) 23:34, 9 September 2016 (UTC))
: Every edit you have made to this article to date has been exactly this - contesting the description of how the lack of evidence for health effects to treat diseases/conditions is described. Every one.  Protest all you want. If I need to use these diffs to stop your disruption, your misrepresentations, including [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3AAlexander_technique&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=738601865&amp;oldid=738600697 the one] you just made again (you changed far more than &quot;syntax&quot;), will be obvious to everyone.  [[User:Jytdog|Jytdog]] ([[User talk:Jytdog|talk]]) 23:41, 9 September 2016 (UTC)
{{collapse bottom}}

The wording &quot;poor&quot; was not agreed to and it is not what the source says.  the source says &quot;insufficient.&quot;  So let's stay with the source.  Very few words. Please also maintain civility and do not threaten other editors. [[User:Montanabw|&lt;font color=&quot;006600&quot;&gt;Montanabw&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Montanabw|(talk)]]&lt;/sup&gt; 07:19, 17 September 2016 (UTC)

:Not interested in stirring up old stuff, just think the content &quot;poor&quot; exceeds what the source says.  It's [[WP:SYNTH]].  The evidence might be poor, it might be great, but we can't make that assessment; we need to stay within the parameters of the source, which said &quot;insufficient.&quot;  Perhaps rather than the old phrasing, we can just agree to replace the word &quot;poor&quot; with the word &quot;insufficient&quot; (and any minor adjustments of surrounding words to make grammatical sense).  [[User:Montanabw|&lt;font color=&quot;006600&quot;&gt;Montanabw&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Montanabw|(talk)]]&lt;/sup&gt; 22:00, 17 September 2016 (UTC)
::If you are not interested in stirring up old stuff, then this conversation would not have been restarted for the second time, by you. [[User:Jytdog|Jytdog]] ([[User talk:Jytdog|talk]]) 22:13, 17 September 2016 (UTC)
:::Please focus on content, not personalities.  There were some active edits by some drive-bys, I looked back at older edits and saw that we did have a synth problem in that sentence.  I suggest it be changed to better match the source.  [[User:Montanabw|&lt;font color=&quot;006600&quot;&gt;Montanabw&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Montanabw|(talk)]]&lt;/sup&gt; 09:41, 18 September 2016 (UTC)
::::Am discussing behavior, not personalities. See my [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3AAlexander_technique&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=738562002&amp;oldid=738560532 initial note] in this section above.  [[User:Jytdog|Jytdog]] ([[User talk:Jytdog|talk]]) 19:05, 18 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::Behavior is indistinguishable from &quot;personalities&quot; in this situation.  Please focus on CONTENT.  [[User:Montanabw|&lt;font color=&quot;006600&quot;&gt;Montanabw&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Montanabw|(talk)]]&lt;/sup&gt; 22:20, 18 September 2016 (UTC)
You have to stop insisting the section and content was discussed; it wasn't. The lead was discussed; this content was not. Furthermore, mischaracterizing what an editor says and does as you did with me is the worst kind of personal attack. And you did personalize this conversation above when you said to Montana, &quot;If you are not interested in stirring up old stuff, then this conversation would not have been restarted for the second time, by you.&quot;  Deal with the edit and the legitimate question of why wording for the conclusion which accurately summarizes the conclusions in the review   has been superseded by another version which is further from the wording of the review and possibly OR. This is such a simple thing why the big fuss. What do you gain by representing the review this way? And no I have no interest in reverting you, but I am concerned about accuracy in what is going on here.([[User:Littleolive oil|Littleolive oil]] ([[User talk:Littleolive oil|talk]]) 20:20, 18 September 2016 (UTC))
:if there is something that has changed in the literature that make this actually worth revisiting, that would make sense.  This is indeed a very minor thing and I have no desire to repeat what we went through earlier, especially for no good reason.,  &quot;i happened to look at this again and gee i really don't like where we ended up&quot; is not a great reason. [[User:Jytdog|Jytdog]] ([[User talk:Jytdog|talk]]) 21:11, 18 September 2016 (UTC)
::You're mischaracterizing. Please don't.([[User:Littleolive oil|Littleolive oil]] ([[User talk:Littleolive oil|talk]]) 21:33, 18 September 2016 (UTC))
:::please reread Montanabw's comment [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3AAlexander_technique&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=739983349&amp;oldid=739916813 here]; yes i paraphrased that. [[User:Jytdog|Jytdog]] ([[User talk:Jytdog|talk]]) 22:12, 18 September 2016 (UTC)
::::Your &quot;paraphrase&quot;, Jytdog, was overbroad and exceeded what the source stated.  Returning to the CONTENT discussion, I suggest we change the section &quot;It considered the evidence to be poor&quot; to either read,  &quot;It concluded there was insufficient evidence for conclusions to be drawn in regards to other clinical conditions,&quot; or &quot;It considered the evidence insufficient.&quot;  Take your pick, but the study did not say the evidence was &quot;poor&quot; -- it said there wasn't enough of it to draw a conclusion one way or the other.

* as i said if some new sources were being introduced that drove a change i would be happy to discuss new content based on them. I don't see any point in re-opening the very ugly discussion we had above.  &quot;i see SYN now&quot; is not real convincing when we ''together'' beat all of this to death not too long ago.  it was good enough for all of us then, and nothing has changed.  please respect the work we already did.  
: On the other hand if you really want to renegotiate this, we can do that.  I have some more sources I can bring that will allow even stronger language about the the lack of evidence for  AT for various diseases/conditions.  It hasn't been worth my time to generate that content but if you really want to re-open this,  then I'll just do a rewrite with the additional sources.  I would rather spend my time elsewhere. but what would you like to have happen here?  [[User:Jytdog|Jytdog]] ([[User talk:Jytdog|talk]]) 22:29, 18 September 2016 (UTC)

:: I guess this is a threat - keep on discussing this and I will bring in more sources which indicate a lack of evidence for the effectiveness of AT.  Unfortunately, what this indicates is that you are determined to see a simple sentence which accurately summarizes the conclusions of the review as positive rather than just the clear and neutral edit that references a source correctly- a non-neutral  position on your part. Further have you forgotten that  I indicated above,  &quot;I wouldn't expect to find health benefits from what is basically a posture technique beyond the kinds of effects good posture and good balance bring.&quot; Why would I care if you have more evidence about AT's lack of evidence unless that content and also any other content entered into the article violates weight. I don't like to be threatened Jytdog. You are skirting an issue here by attempting to intimidate and mischaracterize the editors and the discussion. That's not great!([[User:Littleolive oil|Littleolive oil]] ([[User talk:Littleolive oil|talk]]) 23:13, 18 September 2016 (UTC))
:::We are not &quot;renegotiating&quot; anything.  In my case, in the prior rounds of dispute over this article, I either missed that one, or it simply was lost in the walls and walls of text that were spent here.  To me, this is almost like a discussion over whether to fix a typo — We are looking at a single source and a single sentence with an eye to making our phrasing line up with the content.  In a normal situation, this would be a small wikignoming edit.  I believe that within the article space, [[WP:POINT]] is applicable.  There already is an accepted general agreement —even if reached through a combination of compromise and fatigue rather than consensus—that the article is stable.  We have an error that I believe constitutes SYNTH.  I think that error should be corrected.  Now, shall we return to the discussion of the word &quot;poor&quot; versus the word &quot;insufficient&quot;?  I see no reason to disrupt the entire article over this small issue.  [[User:Montanabw|&lt;font color=&quot;006600&quot;&gt;Montanabw&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Montanabw|(talk)]]&lt;/sup&gt;

:::adding sourced content is a threat?  strange.  OK it seems there is a strong desire to renegotiate.  I will go ahead and work on the new sourced content and we can revisit then, when there is some new basis for discussion.  will take a bit of time. [[User:Jytdog|Jytdog]] ([[User talk:Jytdog|talk]]) 00:32, 19 September 2016 (UTC)

::::Do not make assumptions about other people's motives. A desire to change one sentence or even word was not a request to &quot;renegotiate&quot; an entire section.  Your changes were pretty [[WP:POINT]]y, and normally you can write better than this, but if you are content with the new phrasing and it calms you down, then we only need to do minor text cleanup.  [[User:Montanabw|&lt;font color=&quot;006600&quot;&gt;Montanabw&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Montanabw|(talk)]]&lt;/sup&gt; 21:16, 19 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::No discussion of motives.  You were explicit in wanting to re-open discussion about this section, which we did beat to death not long ago.  You wanted to renegotiate it.  So here we are. [[User:Jytdog|Jytdog]] ([[User talk:Jytdog|talk]]) 23:23, 19 September 2016 (UTC)

== Update done ==

[https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Alexander_technique&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=740097580&amp;oldid=739891828 in this dif].  I used quotes extensively since we seem unable to agree on paraphrasing.  This approach usually resolves differences on that front. [[User:Jytdog|Jytdog]] ([[User talk:Jytdog|talk]]) 01:47, 19 September 2016 (UTC)
:Pretty sad that this was necessary. [[User:Alexbrn|Alexbrn]] ([[User talk:Alexbrn|talk]]) 05:59, 19 September 2016 (UTC)
::This change, at least, reflects the source accurately which is what I was requesting. While there may be an overabundance of quoted text at least we now have accuracy. I am fine with this change.([[User:Littleolive oil|Littleolive oil]] ([[User talk:Littleolive oil|talk]]) 14:06, 19 September 2016 (UTC))

:::There was a bit of overuse of the word &quot;claim,&quot; I did a bit of wikignoming on that.  Yeah, we won't be a featured article any time soon, but that works well enough for now to settle the immediate issue.  [[User:Montanabw|&lt;font color=&quot;006600&quot;&gt;Montanabw&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Montanabw|(talk)]]&lt;/sup&gt; 21:11, 19 September 2016 (UTC)

== Note ==

big bolus of unsourced content was added back in 2009 in [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Alexander_technique&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=291335709 this dif].  Need to see where that come from... [[User:Jytdog|Jytdog]] ([[User talk:Jytdog|talk]]) 09:40, 19 September 2016 (UTC)

:That section has a few sources now.  Looks like it is mostly descriptive.  Probably no rush there, as it describes concepts, makes no scientific claims.  [[User:Montanabw|&lt;font color=&quot;006600&quot;&gt;Montanabw&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Montanabw|(talk)]]&lt;/sup&gt; 21:13, 19 September 2016 (UTC)
::there is never a rush. [[User:Jytdog|Jytdog]] ([[User talk:Jytdog|talk]]) 21:16, 19 September 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>nvf0zsk251x525euksqivxpjxknp4vp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
