<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:MorphOS</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1638700</id>
    <revision>
      <id>735982377</id>
      <parentid>584795803</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-24T10:44:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pavlor</username>
        <id>8522287</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Doubled informations about MorphOS versions</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15075">{{WikiProject Computing|class=start|importance=|amiga=yes|amiga-importance=High}}

=== Kernel Type Source Needed!! ===

I think they ALL Amiga OS &amp; Amiga OS-Like operating systems are microkernel, and always were to begin with...unless there is recent development to add memory protection and that function caused it to be another type of kernel. MorphOS is based on the Quark Microkernel, and AmigaOS is based on Exec. That is very confusing...and also the source given is now a dead link. I will contact MorphOS Team to verify this. [[User:In-Correct|In-Correct]] ([[User talk:In-Correct|talk]]) 00:45, 15 November 2011 (UTC)
:You think? I dont think so :) I read kernel pages in wikipedia and could not categorize AmigaOS (or Exec) to any of those. Link to MorphOS site is dead but I found it via web archive: http://web.archive.org/web/20070709170837/http://www.morphos.org/kernelinfo.php3 but there is Exec subkernel and I dont know if micro/picokernel is really true. [[User:Xorxos|Xorxos]] ([[User talk:Xorxos|talk]]) 23:29, 16 November 2011 (UTC)
::WHAT?! It has all those features, including Memory protection, and Symmetrical multi processing???? and optional Virtual Memory?  Really??

:::MorphOS/Quark has the following basic design goals
:::*High Super/Usermode switch speed
:::*Low interrupt latency
:::*IntThreads and Int PCode abstraction
:::*Memory protection
:::*Symmetrical multi processing (SMP)
:::*Task/Thread and Clan/Chief model
:::*Resource tracking
:::*Asynchronous message system
:::*Virtual memory (optional)
:::*Recursive Memory Management
:::*Distributed computing
:::*No access to Kernel structures
:::*Clean design with an elegant API
:::*Micro/pico kernel mixture

:::[[User:In Correct|In Correct]] ([[User talk:In Correct|talk]]) 23:45, 24 March 2013 (UTC)
::::The source only states those are the basic design goals for Quark kernel. It does not say what features are implemented nor available but what I know memory protection or SMP is not used inside Exec kernel. There is this sandbox approach where Exec kernel is running in abox thread. [[User:Xorxos|Xorxos]] ([[User talk:Xorxos|talk]]) 03:47, 6 December 2013 (UTC)

===mixed proprietary and open source?===

There need to be more clarification about this in the article.
Which elements of MorphOS are open source? Or which elements of MorphOS are proprietary.
This article is somewhat confusing. Very sad that there aren't many pieces of information about this Amiga-like operating system.

[[User:Komitsuki|Komitsuki]] ([[User talk:Komitsuki|talk]]) 01:11, 22 May 2009 (UTC)

===Information lack===
Just asking for someone to definetely place any coerent info related to the notice in the official home page

===Wikipedia ain't a battleground===
It's sad to see that [[MorphOS]] has turned into a battle ground where pages not directly related to MorphOS is promoted at and the content of the page is altered to contain one persons wishes about the death of MorphOS. The whole campaign is childish, and the claim seems to be quite false, for if they had, then a normal person would have taken the matter to a court instead of vandalise the wikipedia. [[User:Trizt|Trizt]]

== May2005-Error in the image of root-tree of Amiga OSes==

Please correct the image.

AmigaOS 4 is not related with AmigaOS 3.9 by Haage&amp;Partner. AOS4 is developed by Hyperion from scratch, descending directly from 3.1 and 3.5.

==Protected==
I protected this page due to the edit war. Please try to sort out this dispute using this talk page, and be sure to cite sources. [[User:Rhobite|Rhobite]] 19:56, Mar 23, 2005 (UTC)

== Thanks ==

Thanks Rhobite, for locking the [[MorphOS]] page. 
As I see it will be really difficult to get to an agreement with Mr Gerber, as he feels quite pissed on the remaining MorphOS development Team and Genesi. Even letting him have a link to his homepage hasn't changed his vandalism on the wikipedia entry. [[User:Trizt|Trizt]]
:Protecting the article isn't an endorsement of the current version. Please try to come to a compromise over the content of the article. [[User:Rhobite|Rhobite]] 20:13, Mar 23, 2005 (UTC)
:I wish I knew how, I think I have compromised quite a lot, by letting the link to the claim page made by Mr Gerber, added link to his page about Ambient, included a text that there has been troubles (both sides have quite different opinions about matters, I have seen it's best none of the sides should have their opinion influence the page). I hope that Mr Gerber can managa to discusse this, but I think there is a big need of help from the outside that can be more objective than we who has some kind of connection to MorphOS (end user, developer or former developer). [[User:Trizt|Trizt]]

I was directly involved in the creation and development of MorphOS and it is quite insulting to see wrong information here. MorphOS is owned by its contributors which includes various people and it is not owned by Genesi. It doesn't matter that Genesi claims they own it, they don't. Trizt, you have a MorphOS installation yourself, why don't you check the about window and read the names here? Those are the copyright holders. [http://www.morphos.org/] was created by the MorphOS authors and [http://www.morphos.net/] is a protest against Genesi. Why don't your try mailing Oliver Wagner, Stefan Stuntz and Treveur Bretaudiere if you think this page is done by an individual they would surely deny being involved right? Also I suppose [http://www.openbsd.org/pegasos.html] is untrue as well?

Sure, it is sad what happened, but there's no need to lie. More sources? See 
[http://www.morphzone.org/modules/newbb_plus/viewtopic.php?forum=14&amp;topic_id=3234&amp;post_id=28772&amp;viewmode=thread&amp;order=0#28772]
to have Genesi themselves recognize they owe money to Stefan Stuntz and that they won't pay him. Quote:

&quot;For the record, we were agreeable to the terms we worked out with you. We do acknowledge the value of your work and saw your future involvement as essential.

Unfortunately, we no longer felt comfortable with the development in general thus it made little sense to invest further into the effort. If we had we would have paid you.&quot;

What else do you need?

Oh, and if you think I'm trying to destroy MorphOS. Perhaps you could check the Ambient archive I released, look at all the work done there and consider I released it for free for anyone to use, [http://zapek.com/software/ambient/].

:The issue isn't if or what Genesi may own you or anyone else for that matter, this is a wikipedia and an entry about [[MorphOS]]. If you feel that Genesi may own you money, there is a court system that you can use for that. If you take a close look, you see that there is a link to your page about the payment, but your page do not hold any information about MorphOS.

:The problem is that you rewite the content of the text, either in a past tempus or throwing in negative formulations, the development may not be fast, but thats was the case when you too was working. We shouldn't forget your constant changes of the MorphOS homepage link or claim that a page is hijacked, you should take a look at [http://www.morphosppc.com] and see what it says in the foot, and compare that what it sade on the foot of the pages that once was on your computer and you see that it's not a question about hijack or any faul play, the owner of the pages has it's right to use it and the material in question you yourself have called to be the official one.

:It's really nice of you to release the Ambient source as GPL, but you still are trying to kill off the MorphOS in the way that your writing here at wikipedia, past tempus. [[User:Trizt|Trizt]]

So basically you're saying that you're writing optimistic and wrong information in order to &quot;not kill MorphOS&quot;.

Optimistic, because Ralph Schmidt (laire) himself, one of the leading MorphOS developer,  told about the development state here, [http://dcs.suomiscene.org/temp/18_01_05_when_morphos_finally_died.log]. Notice how Sigbjoern Skjaeret (CISC) and Jacek Piszeck (jacaDcaps) have issues with him when he tries to blame developers.

Wrong information because the licensing was done with Thendic France and is not transferable, hence, Genesi cannot own MorphOS parts. What they did was making promises but it seems no one reads [http://www.morphos.net/].

Stefan Stuntz also confirms it at [http://www.sasg.com/mui/mui-mos-statement.txt] which is his own website.

So far all of this isn't nice. But I thought wikipedia was about correct information and not about fantasy and wishfull thinking for Amiga users.

:As MorphOS is still developed, regadles of the speed, you can't talk about it in past tempus. The text I have written have in no way been optimistic, far more objective, where my opinion do not shine like in your text.

:If you feel that the agreement you had with Thendic France isn't transferable to Genesi, it's still an issue between you and Genesi and not a reason why you should be removing links or change the link description in your taste, as you will that way remove links that are relavant for MorphOS. As far as I can see the page we are discussing about do not claim that Genesi do own MorphOS or parts, but that it has been part of the development (they still have paid money, even if it's not as much as you wished it to be). I do suggest you go to court if you feel that Genesi is doing something that they shouldn't.

:There has been no one who has denied that there has been troubles within the development team and between members of the development team and Genesi, but saying that MorphOS is dead and remove links to MorphOS homepage aren't the solution (even if it's not on your machine, it won't make it hijacked, as you never owned those pages) as the wikipedia do not include all information about MorphOS and your page does even less. The page you lately have been pointing at [http://www.morphos.org] is heavilly outdated and it hasn't been considered to be official for many years.
:If it feels better for you, do write a suggestion on text that will cover the difficulties, but be objective, I may or may not have objections, but when we agree on the form of that text, add it as an own paragraph into the page, we both agree on that the page will not be modified (no tempus changes untill the whole project is put on ice, no adding of personal opinions, no changes of the links as they are currently), can this be something you can agree on? [[User:Trizt|Trizt]]

==Note==

I've cleaned up [[MorphOS]]; the war did some damage to the page layout.  If I omitted anything or if any of the involved users need me to do something on the page, notify me on my user talk page.  --[[User:Merovingian|&lt;font color=&quot;FF0000&quot;&gt;M&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;CC9900&quot;&gt;e&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;FF9933&quot;&gt;r&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;FFFF00&quot;&gt;o&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;CCFF33&quot;&gt;v&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;66FF33&quot;&gt;i&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;00CC99&quot;&gt;n&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;3399FF&quot;&gt;g&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;0000FF&quot;&gt;i&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;330066&quot;&gt;a&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;330033&quot;&gt;n&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Merovingian|(t)]] [[Special:Contributions/Merovingian|(c)]] [[Special:Watchlist/Merovingian|(w)]] 12:32, Mar 24, 2005 (UTC)

== Amiga is not dead ==

I give up. Argueing with Amiga users is pointless. MorphOS is under very fast development. Genesi is a great company. Nothing happened and everything runs smoothly, it was all a bad dream. Just don't ask yourself why there is still no new release after 2 years. What makes you think I didn't go to court btw? And since when people have to go to court to correct wikipedia articles?

I gave enough sources to backup my claims. If this is how wikipedia disputes are sorted out, then one should be very careful with other content. My point was that Genesi doesn't own MorphOS, the current article tells otherwise by pointing &quot;The MorphOS Homepage&quot; to their website and flagging the homepage written by the developers of the OS itself as &quot;inofficial&quot;.

-------------------

Thank You who ever you are for bringing this very nice discussion to wikipedia :-(

/Gunne

:What I asked for was objectivity for the [MorphOS] page here on the wikipedia and relevant links and I can't call that has been the case when some have been editing the wikipedia entry.[[User:Trizt|Trizt]]

==Unprotected==
Be good. I've unprotected because there seem to be no ongoing discussions. --[[User:Tony Sidaway|Tony Sidaway]]|[[User talk:Tony Sidaway|Talk]] 06:03, 27 Mar 2005 (UTC)


I have edited to add that Efika will be supported in the next official release.  http://www.morphzone.org/modules/news/article.php?storyid=1305 -- anon.

==Contradition: Open Source or Closed Source?==
I was reading the beginning of this article, stating that MorphOS is an open source operating system.
However, the box on the side states that MorphOS is closed source.  Which one is it?
-mogchr 12:27 GMT -5:00

:Mixed. The kernel and many core OS functions are proprietary and closed source, but then the desktop Ambient and I think some other portions are open source. [[User:DanielM|DanielM]] 00:59, 20 July 2007 (UTC)

==Fair use rationale for Image:Lmm c.gif==
[[Image:Nuvola apps important.svg|70px|left]]
'''[[:Image:Lmm c.gif]]''' is being used on this article. I notice the image page specifies that the image is being used under [[Wikipedia:Fair use|fair use]] but there is no [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline|explanation or rationale]] as to why its use in '''this''' Wikipedia article constitutes fair use. In addition to the [[Wikipedia:Image copyright tags/Fair use|boilerplate fair use template]], you must also write out on the image description page a specific explanation or rationale for why using this image in each article is consistent with [[WP:FU|fair use]].

Please go to [[:Image:Lmm c.gif|the image description page]] and edit it to include a [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline |fair use rationale]]. Using one of the templates at [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline]] is an easy way to ensure that your image is in compliance with Wikipedia policy, but remember that you must complete the template. Do not simply insert a blank template on an image page.

If there is  other fair use media, consider checking that you have specified the fair use rationale on the other images used on this page.  Note that any fair use images lacking such an explanation can be deleted one week after being tagged, as described on [[Wikipedia:Criteria for speedy deletion#Images.2FMedia|criteria for speedy deletion]]. If you have any questions please ask them at the [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions|Media copyright questions page]]. Thank you.&lt;!-- Template:Missing rationale2 --&gt;

[[User:BetacommandBot|BetacommandBot]] ([[User talk:BetacommandBot|talk]]) 00:43, 14 February 2008 (UTC)

==Doubled informations about MorphOS versions==
Informations about MorphOS releases are both in simple table and text bellow (which contains mostly the same informations). I would like to join both groups in single table. Any objections? [[User:Pavlor|Pavlor]] ([[User talk:Pavlor|talk]]) 10:44, 24 August 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>o5fnjujq9xg1s34mfql1z0jgjgzahpw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
