<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.28.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2600" case="first-letter">Topic</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Black American Sign Language</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>46182131</id>
    <revision>
      <id>717296860</id>
      <parentid>708188419</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-04-26T21:27:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mr Stephen</username>
        <id>863017</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>clean up, ISBN format using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20392">{{featured article}}

{{Infobox language
|name = Black American Sign Language
|nativename = [[File:Sign language BASL.svg|250px|alt=A series of four hands fingerspelling &quot;B-A-S-L&quot;]] [[Fingerspelling]] of &quot;BASL&quot;
|region = North America
|speakers = ?
|date = 
|ref=
|familycolor = sign
|fam1 = [[French Sign Language family|French Sign]]–based (possibly a [[creole language|creole]])
|fam2 = [[American Sign Language]]
|isoexception=dialect
|glotto=none
}}

'''Black American Sign Language''' ('''BASL''') or '''Black Sign Variation''' ('''BSV''') is a [[dialect]] of [[American Sign Language]] (ASL)&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFEthnologue|Ethnologue 2015]], [http://www.ethnologue.com/language/ase American Sign Language]&lt;/ref&gt; spoken most commonly by deaf [[African American]]s in the United States. The divergence from ASL was influenced largely by the [[School segregation in the United States|segregation]] of schools in the American South. Like other schools at the time, schools for the deaf were segregated based upon race, creating two language communities among deaf signers: White deaf signers at White schools and Black deaf signers at Black schools. Today, BASL is still used by signers in the South despite schools having been legally desegregated since 1954.

Linguistically, BASL differs from other varieties of ASL in its [[American Sign Language phonology|phonology]], [[syntax]], and [[lexicon]]. BASL tends to have a larger [[signing space]] meaning that some signs are produced further away from the body than in other dialects. Signers of BASL also tend to prefer two-handed variants of signs while signers of ASL tend to prefer one-handed variants. Some signs are different in BASL as well, with some borrowings from [[African American English]].

==History==

Like many educational institutions for hearing children during the 1800s and early 1900s, schools for deaf children were [[School segregation in the United States|segregated]] based on race.&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFMcCaskill2011|McCaskill, et al. 2011]], p. 8&lt;/ref&gt; The first school for the deaf in the United States, [[American School for the Deaf|The American School for the Deaf]] (ASD), was founded in 1817 but did not admit any Black students until 1952. Of the schools for the deaf that began to be created, few admitted [[Person of color|students of color]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFMcCaskill2011|McCaskill, et al. 2011]], pp. 16–17&lt;/ref&gt; Seeing a lack of educational opportunities for the Black deaf, [[Platt Skinner]] founded the Skinner School for the Colored Deaf, Dumb, and Blind in 1856 in [[Niagara Falls, New York]]. Skinner described his school as &quot;the first effort of its kind in the country&amp;nbsp;... We receive and instruct those and only those who are refused admission to all other institutions and are despised on account of their color.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFSkinner1859|Skinner 1859]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFMcCaskill2011|McCaskill, et al. 2011]], p.17&lt;/ref&gt; The school moved to Trenton, New Jersey in 1860. After its closure in 1866,&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFMcCaskill2011|McCaskill, et al. 2011]], p.17&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#NFUndergroundRR|Niagara Falls Underground Railroad Heritage Area, n.d.]]&lt;/ref&gt; no Northern state created an institution for the Black deaf. Even after these states outlawed segregation by 1900, integration was sparse as some institutions allowed Black students and others did not.&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFMcCaskill2011|McCaskill, et al. 2011]], pp. 17–18&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFDouglas2005|Douglas 2005]], p. 83&lt;/ref&gt;

After the foundation and success of the American School for the Deaf, many other institutions for the deaf were founded throughout the country. Since schools, particularly in the South, were segregated, many Southern states created separate schools or departments for the Black deaf. The first school established for the Black deaf below the [[Mason–Dixon line]] opened in the [[Washington, D.C.|District of Columbia]] in 1857 and remained segregated until 1958. The last Southern state to create an institution for the Black deaf was Louisiana in 1938. Black Deaf children thus became a language community isolated from the White Deaf with different means of [[language socialization]], allowing for different dialects to develop. Because the education of White children was privileged over that of Black children, [[Oralism]]—the prominent pedagogical method of the time—was not as strictly applied to the Black deaf students. Oralist methods often forbade the use of sign language, so  Black deaf students had more opportunities to use ASL than their White peers. Despite the decision in ''[[Brown v. Board of Education]]'' in 1954 which declared racial segregation in schools unconstitutional, integration was slow to come, and schools for the deaf were no exception: the last desegregated in 1978, 24 years after the decision.&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFMcCaskill2011|McCaskill, et al. 2011]], pp. 19–20&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFDouglas2005|Douglas 2005]]&lt;/ref&gt;

As schools began to integrate, students and teachers noticed differences in the way Black students and White students signed. [[Carolyn McCaskill]], professor of ASL and Deaf Studies at [[Gallaudet University]], recalls the challenge of understanding the dialect of ASL spoken by her White principal and teachers after her segregated school integrated: &quot;When I began attending the school, I did not understand the teacher and she did not understand me because we used different signs.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFMcCaskill2014|McCaskill 2014]]&lt;/ref&gt; Carl Croneberg was the first to discuss differences between BASL and White ASL in his appendices of the 1965 version of the ''Dictionary of American Sign Language'', and work has continued on BASL since then.&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFMcCaskill2011|McCaskill, et al. 2011]], p. 11&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Dictionary /&gt;

As deaf education and sign language research continued to evolve, so did the perception of ASL. With the publication of the ''Dictionary of American Sign Language'', ASL began to be recognized as a legitimate language. The greater acceptance of ASL as a language led to standardization and the development of a [[Prestige (sociolinguistics)|prestige dialect]] which was based upon the signs used at Gallaudet University.&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFHill2015|Hill 2015]], pp. 153–155&lt;/ref&gt; Despite this standardization, there are still regional accents of ASL similar to spoken languages.&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFWalker1987|Walker 1987]], p. 31&lt;/ref&gt; Dialects that are different from the standard one, and especially those spoken by marginalized groups, are often stigmatized.&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFMcCaskill2011|McCaskill, et al. 2011]], p. 64&lt;/ref&gt; As a non-standard dialect, BASL is stigmatized by signers and seen as inferior to prestige dialects of ASL.&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFMcCaskill2011|McCaskill, et al. 2011]], p. 72&lt;/ref&gt; This difference in prestige has led BASL speakers to [[code switching|code switch]] to a prestige dialect when speaking with different groups of people, despite BASL being [[mutually intelligible]] with other dialects of ASL.&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFLewis1995|Lewis, et al. 1995]]&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|+ Table of states with black deaf schools&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFMcCaskill2011|McCaskill, et al. 2011]], p. 20&lt;/ref&gt;
!State
!White school
established
!Black school
or department
established
!Integration
|-
|[[Washington, DC]]
|1857
|1857 (dept.)
|1958
|-
|[[North Carolina]]
|1845
|1868–1869
|1967
|-
|[[Maryland]]
|1868
|1872
|1956
|-
|[[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]]
|1846
|1882
|1965
|-
|[[Tennessee]]
|1845
|1881 (dept.)
|1965
|-
|[[Mississippi]]
|1854
|1882 (dept.)
|1965
|-
|[[South Carolina]]
|1849
|1883 (dept.)
|1966
|-
|[[Kentucky]]
|1823
|1884 (dept.)
|1954–1960
|-
|[[Florida]]
|1885
|1885
|1965
|-
|[[Texas]]
|1857
|1887
|1965
|-
|[[Arkansas]]
|1850/1867
|1867
|1967
|-
|[[Alabama]]
|1858
|1868
|1968
|-
|[[Missouri]]
|1861
|1888 (dept.)
|1954
|-
|[[Virginia]]
|1839
|1909
|1965
|-
|[[Oklahoma]]
|1898
|1909 (dept.)
|1962
|-
|[[Kansas]]
|1861
|1888 (dept.)
|1954
|-
|[[Louisiana]]
|1852
|1938
|1978
|-
|[[West Virginia]]
|1870
|1926
|1956
|}

==Phonology==
[[File:Typical ASL Signing Space representation.svg|thumb|upright=0.5|alt=Silhouette of a man standing with a gray translucent box superimposed over his torso and face.|The gray box represents the typical signing space of ASL. Signers of BASL are more likely to produce signs outside of this area than other signers.&lt;ref name=&quot;McCaskill104to105&quot;&gt;[[#CITEREFMcCaskill2011|McCaskill, et al. 2011]], pp. 104–105&lt;/ref&gt;]]
When asked, many signers in the South gave anecdotal accounts of differences between the signing of Black and White signers. These differences turned out to be aspects of the differing [[American Sign Language phonology|phonology]] of BASL. Among these accounts were claims that Black signers had a larger signing space and used more two-handed signs. Investigation into these anecdotes has found correlations.&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFMcCaskill2011|McCaskill, et al. 2011]], p. 75&lt;/ref&gt;

When compared, Black signers were more likely to produce signs outside of the typical signing space and to use two-handed signs than were White signers.&lt;ref name=&quot;McCaskill104to105&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFMcCaskill2011|McCaskill, et al. 2011]], p. 86&lt;/ref&gt; Adverbs are most likely to utilize a larger signing space. Less [[Markedness|marked]] forms such as pronouns, determiners, plain verbs, and nouns tend to be less likely to be produced outside the typical signing space.&lt;ref name=&quot;McCaskill104to105&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFMcCaskill2011|McCaskill, et al. 2011]], p. 101&lt;/ref&gt; The selection of two-handed signs over one-handed signs was found to have [[Optimality theory|systematic constraints]] on their production. When the sign could be produced with one or two hands, Black signers often produced the variant that matched the handedness of the following sign; if the following sign was two-handed, they were more likely to produce a two-handed variant, while if the following sign was one-handed, they were more likely to produce the one-handed variant. The use of innovative one-handed forms though, even in environments which favored them, did not exceed 50 percent.&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFMcCaskill2011|McCaskill, et al. 2011]], pp. 82–86&lt;/ref&gt;

BASL signers further tend to favor lowered variants of side-of-forehead signs resulting in contact at the cheek. The sign {{sc|Know}} is usually produced by placing the fingers of a flat hand on the [[temple]], but when lowered the fingers make contact at the cheek.&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFMcCaskill2011|McCaskill, et al. 2011]], pp. 86–87&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFLifeprint|Lifeprint]], n.d. [http://www.lifeprint.com/asl101/pages-signs/k/know.htm KNOW]&lt;/ref&gt; Early research showed that BASL signers used these lowered forms at a rate of 53 percent with grammatical category being the strongest constraint.&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFLucas2002|Lucas, et al. 2002]]&lt;/ref&gt; Other conditioning environments for lowered signs depend on preceding location; for instance, signs produced in front of the body lead to lowered sign variants while signs produced at the head cause signers to favor non-lowered forms.&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFMcCaskill2011|McCaskill, et al. 2011]], pp. 92–97&lt;/ref&gt;

==Syntax==
Unlike ASL, BASL allows for the frequent use of [[syntactic repetition]]. In a study conducted by McCaskill, of 26 signers (13 Black and 13 White), there were 57 instances of repetition from Black signers compared to 19 from White signers, and of those 19 instances, 18 came from a single signer. The use of repetition by BASL signers is considered to be [[Pragmatics|pragmatic]] rather than as a way to clarify meaning.&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFMcCaskill2011|McCaskill, et al. 2011]], p. 116&lt;/ref&gt;

A study in 2004 by Melanie Metzger and Susan Mather found that Black male signers used [[constructed action]], with or without [[constructed dialogue]], more often than White signers, but never used constructed dialogue by itself.&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFMetzger2004|Metzger and Mathers 2004]]&lt;/ref&gt; These results were not reproduced in a later study into constructed action and constructed dialogue by McCaskill, which found that Black signers not only used constructed dialogue, but did so more frequently than white signers.&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFMcCaskill2011|McCaskill, et al. 2011]], p. 122&lt;/ref&gt;

==Lexical variation==
[[Lexical variation]] between BASL and other dialects of ASL was first noted in the ''Dictionary of American Sign Language.''&lt;ref name=Dictionary&gt;[[#CITEREFStokoe1965|Stokoe 1965]], pp. 313–19&lt;/ref&gt; In a later study of 34 lexical signs, Black signers had 28 signs that White signers did not know.&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFLucas2014|Lucas and McCaskill 2014]], p. 41&lt;/ref&gt; Older signers are more likely to use variant signs than younger signers, and most, having been developed in segregated schools for the Black Deaf, refer to everyday life. Younger signers of BASL are less likely to use these variants, but when asked about them are aware that older signers have and use these innovative signs.&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFMcCaskill2011|McCaskill, et al. 2011]], p. 150&lt;/ref&gt;

===Borrowing from African American English===
[[File:BentV@InForward.jpg|thumb|left|upright=0.5|alt=Person in orange shirt with hand in front of him with index and middle fingers crooked creating a &quot;bent - v&quot; shape|The bent-v handshape used in the sign {{sc|Stop tripping}}]]
A body of work has arisen looking at the similarities between Black American Sign Language and [[African American Vernacular English|African American English]] (AAE) since both are language varieties marked by their use in African American communities. In 1998 John Lewis investigated the incorporation of aspects of AAE into BASL. He reported that, during narrative storytelling by a Black signer, there were &quot;[[African American Vernacular English|Ebonic shifts]]&quot; marked by shifts in posture and rhythmicity and by incorporating side-to-side head movement. He concluded that this &quot;'songified' quality was related to the style of AAE.&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFLewis1998|Lewis, et al. 1998]]&lt;/ref&gt; This finding was not reproduced by McCaskill, which she attributes to the nature of the speech acts: Lewis analyzed a narrative event while McCaskill utilized natural or elicited data.&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFMcCaskill2011|McCaskill, et al. 2011]], p. 133&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lexical borrowing]] has been seen in BASL signers under age 35 which is likely due to the advances in mass media—younger signers would have more contact with AAE through movies, television, and the Internet.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lucas2015&quot;&gt;[[#CITEREFLucas2015|Lucas, et al. 2015]]&lt;/ref&gt;

When asked about distinctive features of their signing, Black Deaf signers tended to identify a number of idioms borrowed from AAE.&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFSolomon2010|Solomon 2010]], p. 10&lt;/ref&gt; Some were [[Calque|literal translations]] like {{sc|I feel you}} or {{sc|girl please}} which are signed the standard way but have meanings different from their literal interpretation.&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFSolomon2010|Solomon 2010]], p. 10&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFLucas2015|Lucas, et al. 2015]], Figure 3. p. 165&lt;/ref&gt; Other loan words modified existing signs like {{sc|stop tripping}} which took the bent-v handshape of {{sc|trip}} and moved it up to the head to indicate a new meaning of &quot;stop imagining things.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#CITEREFLucas2015|Lucas, et al. 2015]], p. 163&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Clear}}

==See also==
*[[Sociolinguistics of sign languages]]
*[[Varieties of American Sign Language]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|30em}}

==References==
{{refbegin|2}}
&lt;!--Should be kept in alphabetical order--&gt;
*{{cite LSA|last=Douglas|first=Davison|year=2005|title=Jim Crow Moves North: The Battle over Northern School Segregation, 1865–1954|publisher=Cambridge University Press|place=New York, NY}} ISBN 978-0-521-60783-4.
*{{Cite LSA|last=Hill|first=Joseph|year = 2015| chapter=Language attitudes in Deaf communities|title=Sociolinguistics and Deaf Communities|editorfirst=Adam|editorlast=Schembri|editorfirst2=Ceil|editorlast2=Lucas|publisher=Cambridge UP|place=Cambridge, UK|pages=146–174}} ISBN 978-1-107-66386-2.
*{{Cite LSA|last=Lewis|first=John|year=1998|chapter=Ebonics in American Sign Language: stylistic variation in African American signers|title=Deaf Studies V: Towards 2000: Unity and Diversity|editorfirst=C.|editorlast=Carroll|place=Washington, D.C.|publisher=College for Continuing Education, Gallaudet University}} ISBN 978-1-893891-09-8.
*{{Cite LSA|last=Lewis|first=John|first2=Carrie|last2=Palmer|first3=Leandra|last3=Williams|title=Existence of and attitudes towards Black variations of sign language|journal=Communication Forum|volume=4|year=1995|pages=17–48}}
*{{Cite LSA|last=Lucas| first=Ceil| last2=Bayley |first2=Robert |last3=McCaskill |first3=Carolyn |last4=Hill |first4=Joseph |year=2015 |title=The intersection of African American English and Black American Sign Language |journal=International Journal of Bilingualism |volume=19 |pages=156–168}}
*{{Cite LSA|last=Lucas|first=Ceil| first2=Robert| last2=Bayley| first3=Mary|last3=Rose|first4=Alyssa|last4=Wulf| year=2002| title=Location variation in American Sign Language|journal=Sign Language Studies|volume=2|publisher=Gallaudet UP|place=Washington, D.C.|pages=407–440}}
*{{Cite LSA|last=Lucas|first=Ceil|last2=Bayley|first2=Robert| first3=Clayton| last3=Valli| year=2001|title=Sociolinguistic Variation in American Sign Language| place=Washington, D.C.|publisher=Gallaudet University Press}} ISBN 978-1-56368-113-4.
*{{Cite LSA|last=Lucas|first=Ceil|last2=McCaskill|first2=Carolyn|year=2014|chapter=American Sign Language|title=The New Encyclopedia of Southern Culture|volume=5|publisher=UNC Press|place=Chapel Hill, NC|pages=40–42|editorlast=Montgomery|editorfirst=Michael|editorlast2=Johnson|editorfirst2=Ellen}} ISBN 978-0-8078-5806-6.
*{{cite LSA|last=McCaskill | first=Carolyn |year=2014 |title=Black ASL|url=http://www.sorensonvrs.com/february_2014_deaf_black_asl|accessdate=21 March 2015}} Video. ''In ASL with English captions''
*{{Cite LSA|last=McCaskill|first=Carolyn|first2=Ceil|last2=Lucas|first3=Robert|last3=Bayley|first4=Joseph|last4=Hill|title=The Hidden Treasure of Black Asl: Its History and Structure|place=Washington, D.C.|publisher=Gallaudet University Press| year=2011}} ISBN 978-1-56368-489-0.
*{{Cite LSA|last=Metzger|first=Melanie|first2=Susan|last2=Mather|title=Constructed Dialogue and Constructed Action in Conversational Narratives in ASL|year=2004}} cited in [[#CITEREFLucas2002|Lucas, et al. 2002]]
*{{Anchor|NFUndergroundRR}}{{Cite LSA|publisher=Niagara Falls Underground Railroad Heritage Area|year=n.d|title=Site of Dr. P.H. Skinner's and Jarusha Skinner's School for Colored Deaf, Dumb and Blind Children|url=http://www.niagarafallsundergroundrailroad.org/documents/22_Site%20of%20Dr%20Skinners%20School%20for%20Deaf%20or%20Blind%20African%20American%20Children.pdf |accessdate=21 November 2015}} Web.
*{{Anchor|CITEREFEthnologue}}{{cite LSA|year=2015|title=Ethnologue: Languages of the World|editorlast=Lewis|editorfirst=M. Paul|editorfirst2=Gary| editorlast2=Simons |editorfirst3=Charles |editorlast3=Fennig |edition=18 |place=Dallas, Texas|publisher=SIL International}} Web.
*{{Cite LSA|last = Skinner|title = The Mute and the Deaf|first = Platt|year = 1859|place = Niagara City, NY}}
*{{Cite LSA|last=Solomon|first=Andrea|title =Cultural and Sociolinguistic Features of the Black Deaf Community | year = 2010 |publisher=Carnegie Mellon|url=http://repository.cmu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1060&amp;context=hsshonors|accessdate=5 December 2015}} Honors Thesis.
*{{Cite LSA|last=Stokoe|first=William|first2=Dorothy|last2=Casterline|first3=Carl|last3=Croneberg|chapter=Appendix D: sign language and dialects|year=1965|title=A Dictionary of American Sign Language|place=Silver Spring, MD|publisher=Linstok}} ISBN 978-0-932130-01-3.
*{{Anchor|CITEREFLifeprint}}{{Cite LSA|last=Vicars|first=William|year=n.d|title=ASL University|url=http://www.lifeprint.com/index.htm|publisher=Lifeprint|accessdate=5 December 2015}}
*{{Cite LSA|last=Walker|first=Lou Ann|year=1987|title=A Loss for Words: The Story of Deafness in a Family|place=New York|publisher=Harper Perennial|page=31}} ISBN 978-0-06-091425-7.
{{refend}}

{{Languages of the United States}}

&lt;!-- Categories --&gt;
[[Category:American Sign Language]]
[[Category:Languages of the United States]]
[[Category:Deaf culture in the United States]]
[[Category:Languages of the African diaspora]]
[[Category:African-American culture]]
[[Category:American Sign Language family]]</text>
      <sha1>fefncrx4mo2xmte1p41gbloi4zm53fh</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
