<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Calabozos</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>30491347</id>
    <revision>
      <id>729743915</id>
      <parentid>729090279</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-07-14T07:30:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dcirovic</username>
        <id>11795905</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>refs</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23512">{{Infobox mountain
| name = Calabozos
| photo = 
| photo_caption = 
| elevation_m = 3508
| elevation_ref = &lt;ref name=syn/&gt;
| prominence_m = 
| prominence_ref = 
| range = [[Andes]]
| location = Central [[Chile]]
| map = Chile |relief=1
| region_code = CL-ML
| map_alt = Calabozos is located in East-central Chile, which lies on the southwestern coast of South America.
| map_caption = The South American country of Chile
| map_width = 200
| label_position = right
| lat_d = 35 | lat_m = 33 | lat_s = 30 | lat_NS = S
| long_d = 70 | long_m = 29 | long_s = 47 | long_EW = W
| coordinates_ref = &lt;ref name=SUM/&gt;
| type = [[Caldera]]
| age = [[Pleistocene]]
| volcanic_belt = [[Andean Volcanic Belt]]
| last_eruption = Unknown&lt;ref name=SUM/&gt;
}}

'''Calabozos''' is a [[Holocene]] [[caldera]] in central [[Chile]]'s [[Maule Region]] (7th Region). Part of the Chilean [[Andes]]' volcanic segment, it is considered a member of the [[Andean Volcanic Belt#Southern Volcanic Zone|Southern Volcanic Zone]] (SVZ), one of the three distinct volcanic belts of South America. This most active section of the Andes runs along central Chile's western edge, and includes more than 70 of Chile's [[stratovolcano]]es and volcanic fields. Calabozos lies in an extremely remote area of poorly glaciated mountains.

Calabozos and the majority of the Andean volcanoes formed from the [[subduction]] of the oceanic [[Nazca Plate]] under the continental [[South American Plate|South American continental lithosphere]]. The caldera is in a transitional region between thick and thin lithosphere, and is probably supplied by a pool of [[Andesite|andesitic]] and [[Rhyolite|rhyolitic]] magma. It sits on a historic bed of volcanic and [[plutonic]] [[sedimentary rock]] (rock formed within the Earth) that in turn sits on top of a layer of merged sedimentary and [[metamorphic rock]].

Calabozos is responsible for the huge Loma Seca [[Tuff]], a body of material {{convert|200|km3|cumi|0}} to {{convert|500|km3|cumi|0}} in volume. It accumulated over at least three eruptive periods, beginning 800,000 years ago (0.8 [[mya (unit)|mya]]) and lasting until 150,000 years ago (0.15 mya).

The caldera's dimensions are {{convert|26|km|mi|0}} by {{convert|14|km|mi}}, and it has an [[elevation]] of {{convert|3508|m|ft|0}}.&lt;ref name=SUM&gt;{{cite gvp |vnum=1507-042 |name=Calabozos |accessdate=January 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Activity from the caldera has produced many other stratovolcanoes to form a [[complex volcano]].&lt;ref name=SUM/&gt;

== Geography and structure ==
Calabozos lies in central Chile's [[Maule Region]], near [[Curicó, Chile|Curicó]] and [[Talca, Chile|Talca]], on the western Andes.&lt;ref name=HEA45&gt;Hildreth ''et al.'' (1984), p. 45.&lt;/ref&gt; This is an area of poorly [[glaciated]] mountains that is not permanently populated. There are no roads, and it is only accessible via horse or on foot.&lt;ref name=HEA47&gt;Hildreth ''et al.'' (1984), p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt;

Calabozos is part of the South Volcanic Zone, which runs along the western edge of central Chile and extends south, jumping the border to continue its course in Argentina. This range includes at least nine [[volcanic field|caldera complexes]], more than 70&amp;nbsp;of Chile's stratovolcanoes and volcanic fields that have been active in the [[Quaternary]], and hundreds of minor eruptive centers. The South Volcanic Zone is the most volcanically active region in Chile, and produces around one eruption per year. Its largest historical eruption was at Quizapu Crater, located {{convert|15|km|mi|0}} to {{convert|20|km|mi|0}} from the north side of Cerro Azul's summit,&lt;ref name=HEA51/&gt; and its most active volcanoes are [[Llaima]] and [[Villarrica (volcano)|Villarrica]].&lt;ref name=Stern154&gt;Stern ''et al.'' (2007), pp. 154–156.&lt;/ref&gt;

Calabozos is a ring-shaped [[caldera]] {{convert|26|km|mi|0}} by {{convert|14|km|mi|0}} wide,&lt;ref name=HEA45/&gt; with an elevation of {{convert|3508|m|ft|0}}.&lt;ref name=SUM/&gt; Volcanoes have been formed by eruptions in the crater. The largest, which is on the southern rim of the caldera, is the Holocene Cerro del Medio complex with an elevation of {{convert|3508|m|ft|0}}.&lt;ref name=syn&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.volcano.si.edu/world/volcano.cfm?vnum=1507-042&amp;volpage=synsub|title=Calabozos: Synonyms and Subfeatures|publisher=[[Smithsonian Institution]]|work=[[Global Volcanism Program]]|accessdate=January 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is made mainly of andesite and dacite, and has a volume of {{convert|20|km3|cumi|0}} to {{convert|25|km3|cumi|0}}. On the southwestern edge several eruptions have created the Descabezado Chico volcano (elevation: {{convert|3250|m|ft|0}})&lt;ref name=syn/&gt; which consists of four overlapping [[volcanic crater]]s.&lt;ref name=SUM/&gt; The last eruption occurred during Holocene time, and produced a [[dacite|dacitic]] lava flow ({{convert|2.5|km3|cumi|0}} in volume) that extends for {{convert|30|km|mi|0}}.&lt;ref name=SUM/&gt; Cerro Colorado, with an elevation of {{convert|2928|m|ft|0}}, forms another cone in the complex.&lt;ref name=syn/&gt;

Towards the center of the caldera, [[hot spring]]s including Cajon Los Calabozos and Baños de Llolli&lt;ref name=syn/&gt; are present.&lt;ref name=SUM/&gt; The springs are as old as 0.3 [[mya (unit)|mya]], and may have formed directly after Calabozos's second eruption&lt;ref name=Get/&gt; as a result of [[Tectonic uplift|uplift]] caused by re-occurring activity in the caldera.&lt;ref name=SUM/&gt; The vents occur in two clusters, Colorado and Puesto Calabozos, and are located along the margin of a fault at the southwestern edge of the caldera.&lt;ref name=Get&gt;Grunder ''et al''. (1987), p. 289.&lt;/ref&gt;  Hildreth ''et al''. (1983) evaluated that Calabozos could potentially be useful for the harvesting of [[geothermal energy]].&lt;ref&gt;Hildreth ''et al.'' (1984), p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Geology==
[[File:South American plates.png|thumb|left|The [[subduction]] of the [[Nazca Plate]] resulted in the formation of the Andean Volcanic Belt and the Peru–Chile Trench.]]
[[Subduction]] of the eastern edge of the [[Nazca Plate]] under the western edge of the [[South American Plate]] occurs about {{convert|160|km|mi|0|sp=us}} west of Peru and Chile, at a rate of 9 to {{convert|11|cm|in|0}} per year at [[30th parallel south|30 degrees south]] latitude.&lt;ref name=HEA45/&gt; This subduction process has resulted in the formation of the [[Peru–Chile Trench]], an [[oceanic trench]] in the [[Pacific Ocean]].&lt;ref name=HEA45/&gt; It also produced the [[Andean Volcanic Belt]] and the rest of the Andes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.volcano.si.edu/world/region.cfm?rnum=15&amp;rpage=highlights|title=Volcanoes of South America: Highlights|publisher=Smithsonian Institution|work=Global Volcanism Program|accessdate=January 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Calabozos is one of 44 Holocene [[Geologic time scale|epoch]] volcanoes located in central Chile and Argentina.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.volcano.si.edu/world/region.cfm?rnum=1507|title=Volcanoes of South America: Central Chile and Argentina|publisher=Smithsonian Institution|work=Global Volcanism Program|accessdate=January 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is included within the Southern Volcanic Zone, the most active section of the Chilean Andes.&lt;ref name=Stern154/&gt; The date of its last known eruption is not known with precision, though it took place during the Holocene.&lt;ref name=SUM/&gt;

Through [[K-Ar dating]], geologist Robert Edward Drake established the age of 66 events in central Chile, and divided them into groups based on the time of their origin. In a paper published in 1976, he described the location of each group and the west-east-trending movement of volcanism in the range. 
To the west of the Chilean Andes are an early group of eruptions, dated from the [[Oligocene]] and the Early [[Miocene]] (33.3–20.2&amp;nbsp;[[mya (unit)|mya]]). The scale of the eruptive events that produced these features remains unclear. Further east, in the actual range, are huge numbers of eruptions. Between 15.3 and 6.4&amp;nbsp;mya, widespread volcanism took place, followed by extensive [[fold (geology)|folding]]; this process then repeated itself from 18.4 to 13.7 mya during the Miocene. Beginning 6.4 mya the Chilean Andes were quiet, though whether or not this quiet period took place throughout all of the Andes remains unknown. Central Chilean volcanoes became active once again around 2.5&amp;nbsp;mya, and have erupted almost continuously since.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Potassium-argon dating of igneous activity in the central Chilean Andes – latitude 33°S|author1=Drake, Robert E. |author2=Curtis, Garniss |author3= Vergara, Mario |date=November 1976|journal=Journal of Volcanology and Geothermal Research|volume=1|issue=3|pages=285–295 | doi = 10.1016/0377-0273(76)90012-3|bibcode = 1976JVGR....1..285D }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Local ===

Calabozos lies in an area between thick and thin continental crust, and its eruptions are probably fed from a pool of [[andesite|andesitic]] and rhyolitic magma that sits just under its caldera.&lt;ref&gt;Grunder (1988), p. 71.&lt;/ref&gt; The caldera is underlain by a layer of [[volcaniclastic]] [[sedimentary rock]] from the [[Mesozoic]] era coalesced with [[Intrusive rock|intrusive]] and volcanic rocks of [[Tertiary]] age, over a layer of [[Precambrian]]-[[Triassic]] sedimentary and metamorphic rock formed from later [[pluton]]s (magma intrusions).&lt;ref name=G72&gt;Grunder (1987), p. 72.&lt;/ref&gt; Under its northeast edge, Calabozos is cut by a north-south trending segment of sedimentary rock that includes gypsiferous and [[carbonate rock|carbonates]].&lt;ref name=&quot;HEA47&quot;/&gt;

Calabozos is similar in age to [[Cerro Azul (Chile volcano)|Cerro Azul]] and [[Descabezado Grande]], and its eruptions may correspond to past activity at both volcanoes. Eruption products of very similar composition (including [[mafic]] [[andesite]], agglutinates, and [[dacite]]) make up the volcanoes. There is also a similarity in size (all are between 40 and 70 cubic kilometers in volume).&lt;ref name=HEA51&gt;Hildreth ''et al.'' (1984), p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt;

The volcano appears to be part of a north-south trending group of rhyolitic, [[silicic]] Quaternary volcanoes (including Puelche Volcanic Field, [[Laguna del Maule (volcano)|Laguna del Maule]], and Volcán Domuyo) that veers off the north-northeast direction of the rest of the Andes. The directional formation of this belt corresponds to the [[fault (geology)|fold-and-thrust]] movement of the nearby Malargüe fault, which formed in the [[Tertiary]] and remained active until the early Pliocene or late Miocene. This may suggest that Calabozos' activity is more dependent on local processes than subduction of the Nazca Plate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.scielo.cl/scielo.php?pid=S0716-02081999000200008&amp;script=sci_arttext|title=The Puelche Volcanic Field: extensive Pleistocene rhyolite lava flows in the Andes of central Chile|journal=Revista geológica de Chile|volume=26|issue=2|doi=10.4067/S0716-02081999000200008|author1=Hildreth, Wes |author2=Fierstein, Judy |author3=Godoy, Estanislao |author4=Drake, Robert E. |author5= Singer, Brad |date=December 1999|accessdate=February 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Geologic record ===
In comparison to the well-preserved rocks of the dry, central part of the Andes, the record that defines the southern sector is poorly preserved. Remnants of Miocene and Quaternary eruptions within the central part are clearly preserved in the rock record. Ash flow sheets constitute as much as 40&amp;nbsp;percent of the area's total erupted material, suggesting that pyroclastic eruptions were rather important during this time. By examining the eruption rate of individual volcanoes, Hildreth ''et al.'' concluded that similar amounts of ash-flow volcanism took place in the southern sector as well. Their study established that in particular [[silicic]] ash was missing from the record, and concluded that erosion had probably disrupted [[Deposition (geology)|deposition]] of volcaniclastic rock.&lt;ref name=HEA45/&gt;

While the volcanic history of the area extends back far further, the earliest fully recognizable events in the region are recorded in the [[Pyroclastic rock|pyroclastic]] Campanario Formation. This sequence appears to begin at Laguna de la Invernada and ranges from 15 to 6&amp;nbsp;mya. Remnants of magma intrusions as young as 7&amp;nbsp;mya can be found at the lake (Laguna de la Invernada).&lt;ref name=HEA48&gt;Hildreth ''et al.'' (1984), p. 48.&lt;/ref&gt;

The most recent volcanic phase began about 4&amp;nbsp;mya, producing largely andesitic eruptions. A series of eruptions built up a broad [[plateau]] of lava, and extended over the area where Calabozos now lies. Locally, this plateau was composed of mafic andesite with [[olivine]], which over time gathered to form {{convert|300|m|ft|-2|adj=on}} to {{convert|500|m|ft|-2|adj=on}} thick layers. Nearby volcanoes sit on top of two mya lavas that formed during this period, while the Loma Seca Tuff lies atop andesitic deposits from Descabezado Grande.&lt;ref name=HEA48/&gt;

===Composition===
Calabozos lies between two different types of volcanism—to its north, [[andesite]] and [[rhyolite]] are the primary constituents of [[lava]] while its southern neighbors are composed of more [[mafic]] andesite and [[basalt]]. It is mainly [[basaltic andesite]] and [[rhyodacite]] that make up Calabozos, forming a [[Calc-alkaline|calcalkilic]] suite rich with [[potassium]]. Its lavas are dotted with [[phenocryst]]s, which vary from 2 to 25&amp;nbsp;percent of their mass.&lt;ref&gt;Grunder and Mahood (1988), p. 831.&lt;/ref&gt; These phenocrysts are typically made of [[plagioclase]], but also contain [[clinopyroxene]], [[orthopyroxene]], [[ilmenite]], [[apatite]], and [[titanomagnetite]].&lt;ref name=G72/&gt;

== Climate and vegetation ==
The area's rainfall averages {{convert|134|cm|in|0}} annually, varying from {{convert|50|cm|in|0}} at its lowest to {{convert|225|cm|in|0}} at its highest. Precipitation between May and August (primarily snow) is normally 20 to 35 centimetres, dropping to below one centimetre during summer. Temperature is also variable, typically registering 25 degrees Celsius during the summer, but dropping below freezing at high elevations (above {{convert|2500|m|ft|-2}}).&lt;ref name=HEA47/&gt;

Vegetation is rare in the area. The 1932 eruption of [[Cerro Azul (Chile volcano)|Cerro Azul]]'s Quizapu Crater reduced much of the land to a pumice desert. Above {{convert|1200|m|ft|-2}}, vegetation becomes even more sparse.&lt;ref name=HEA47/&gt;

==Eruptive history==
[[File:Mineraly.sk - ryodacit.jpg|thumb|right|Calabozos' tuff eruptions were mostly [[rhyodacite|rhyodacitic]] and [[dacite|dacitic]] in origin.]]
During the late [[Pleistocene]], Calabozos erupted [[tuff]] composed primarily of [[rhyodacite]] and [[dacite]]. Three distinct eruptions have taken place within the last million years. The sheets of remaining [[volcanic ash|ash]] left over from all of the eruptions together range from {{convert|200|km3|cumi|0}} to {{convert|500|km3|cumi|0}} in volume and are known as the Loma Seca Tuff.&lt;ref name=SUM/&gt;

The first eruption, which took place 0.8&amp;nbsp;[[mya (unit)|mya]], was distinct from later eruptions in that its product lacks flattened lenticles (lens-shaped layers of mineral or rock embedded in rock). The tuff is dotted with predominantly [[plagioclase]] [[phenocrysts]], which make up between less than 5 to approximately 15&amp;nbsp;percent of each particle's mass. After being erupted, the material settled in canyons, where it underwent glaciation. This carved cliffs which drop as much as {{convert|100|m|ft|0}}. The tuff is limited to just a few kilometers around the complex.&lt;ref name=HEA49&gt;Hildreth ''et al.'' (1984), p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt;

Taking place 0.3&amp;nbsp;mya, the second eruption was the most extensive. It was probably between {{convert|250|km3|cumi|0}} and {{convert|300|km3|cumi|0}} in volume and extended past the reaches of the caldera, down the adjacent [[foothill]]s. Beyond the caldera, the eruptive products are poor in phenocrysts (unlike those of the first eruption). They are instead rich in lithic material, which makes up as much as 10&amp;nbsp;percent of the rock in parts (50&amp;nbsp;percent at the base of the caldera). As the first of the ash was deposited, it accumulated in layers that formed quickly and resisted erosion, but only partially melded together. However, except for these basal layers and thin zones where the ash was devitrified (loses the properties of a glass and becomes brittle), the entire sheet is melded together. Inside Calabozos, the ash resisted welding and contains more phenocrysts. Instead, erosion ate away at it, in the form of acid leaching, and broke down much of its [[pumice]] content. Still, the rock layer here contains five to 30&amp;nbsp;percent phenocrysts, and has high levels of [[devitrification]] and lithic content.&lt;ref name=HEA49/&gt;

The differences between these two deposits can be accounted for by a few factors, including time of eruption and placement. The material inside the caldera must be younger and erupted from a pool of magma that had larger crystals. Its extensive erosion can be explained by the presence of hydrothermal vents, and its high levels of lithics probably originate from either being exposed to the rocks after they were erupted, lying adjacent to them while they underwent [[subsidence]], or is a result of long, slow formation. Any of these reasons would also effectively account for the poor mixing of the lavas.&lt;ref name=HEA49/&gt;
[[File:BishopTuff.jpg|thumb|left|The third eruption was high in [[fiamme]] (on the right), and erupted material with large phenocrysts.]]
Activity continued for approximately 150,000 years in the form of quiet andesitic eruptions, as glaciation took place. About 0.15&amp;nbsp;mya (150,000 years ago), a third and final ash flow was erupted. With a volume of {{convert|175|km3|cumi|0|sp=us}} to {{convert|250|km3|cumi|0}}, it was smaller than the second eruption, but acted similarly, and had much more densely welded tuff. The ash was thickest at {{convert|300|m|ft|0}}, at Loma Seca, and the top of the deposit has undergone erosion. It is densely welded in crevasses, but not at thin {{convert|50|m|ft|0}} layers, where much of the material is barely welded or not welded at all.&lt;ref name=HEA49/&gt;

The first layers of the last deposit were alternating belts of light and dark-colored material, and were densely welded. They appear to have been erupted in pulses, and continue for hundreds of meters. Deposition was continuous except for one interruption, which can be seen at proximity to the caldera, where the layers are replaced by thin, nonwelded sheets of lava. Another zone of nonwelded material, about {{convert|20|m|ft|0}} and near Cajon Los Calabozos, underwent no erosion, suggesting that activity stopped, then began again.&lt;ref name=HEA49/&gt;

High in [[fiamme]], the third tuff layer differs from the second in that it has even higher phenocryst content, but poor lithics. In the fiamme, phenocrysts constitute between 5 and 15 percent of the rock, increasing to 25 to 30&amp;nbsp;percent near the caldera. In the younger emplacements, clinopyroxene is evident along with an increase in [[mafic]] content.&lt;ref name=HEA50&gt;Hildreth ''et al.'' (1984), p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{clear}}

== Threats and preparedness ==
Calabozos is in the South Volcanic Zone, which contains potentially deadly and active volcanoes such as [[Mount Hudson]], Llaima, and Villarrica.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://vulcan.wr.usgs.gov/Volcanoes/Chile/description_chile_volcanoes.html|publisher=[[United States Geological Survey]]|title=Description: Chile Volcanoes and Volcanics|author=Topinka, Lyn|date=March 4, 2002|accessdate=February 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Villarrica and Llaima together have more than 80&amp;nbsp;reported episodes of volcanism since 1558, and at least 40&amp;nbsp;South Volcanic Zone volcanoes have had Holocene-age eruptions.&lt;ref name=Stern154/&gt;

Its remoteness means that Calabozos poses little threat to humans, but if necessary relief efforts could be orchestrated. The Volcanic Disaster Assistance Program (VDAP) formed in response to the [[Armero tragedy|famous eruption]] of [[Nevado del Ruiz]] in [[Colombia]] and saved lives following the 1991 eruption of [[Mount Hudson]] in Chile by organizing evacuations. The team's stated aim is to &quot;reduce eruption-caused fatalities and economic losses in developing countries&quot;. Made up of various USGS offices such as the [[Cascades Volcano Observatory]] (CVO), responsible for monitoring [[Mount St. Helens]], the team has equipment to monitor any volcano, allowing the timely prediction of volcanic eruptions and the evacuation of nearby homes.&lt;ref name=VDAP&gt;{{cite web|author=Topinka, Lyn|url=http://vulcan.wr.usgs.gov/Vdap/description_vdap.html|title=The USGS/OFDA Volcano Disaster Assistance Program |publisher=[[United States Geological Survey]]|date=March 21, 2001|accessdate=February 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Geology of Chile]]
* [[List of volcanoes in Chile]]

==References==
{{reflist|27em}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite journal|last=Grunder, Anita L.|title=Low δ&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O Silicic Volcanic Rocks At the Calabozos Caldera Complex, Southern Andes|year=1987|volume=95|issue=1|pages=71–81|doi=10.1007/BF00518031|journal=Contributions to Mineralology and Petrology|first1=Anita L.|bibcode = 1987CoMP...95...71G }}
* {{cite journal|last=Grunder |title=The Hydrothermal System of the Calabozos Caldera, Central Chilean Andes|year=1987|publisher=[[Elsevier]]|journal=[[Journal of Volcanology and Geothermal Research]]|volume=32|pages=287–298|doi=10.1016/0377-0273(87)90080-1|first1=A|last2=Thompson|first2=J|last3=Hildreth|first3=W|issue=4|bibcode = 1987JVGR...32..287G }}
* {{cite journal|last=Grunder |title=Physical and Chemical Models of Zoned Silicic Magmas: the Loma Seca Tuff and Calabozos Caldera, Southern Andes|year=1988|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|journal=Journal of Petrology|volume=29|issue=4|pages=831–867 | doi = 10.1093/petrology/29.4.831|first1=A. L.|last2=Mahood|first2=G. A.}}
*{{cite journal|last=Hildreth |title=The Loma Seca Tuff and the Calabozos Caldera: A Major Ash-flow and Caldera Complex In The Southern Andes of Chile|journal=Geological Society of America Bulletin|publisher=[[Geological Society of America]]|volume=95|pages=45–54|doi=10.1130/0016-7606(1984)95&lt;45:TLSTAT&gt;2.0.CO;2|date=January 1984|issn=0016-7606|first1=WES|last2=Grunder|first2=Anita L.|last3=Drake|first3=Robert E.|bibcode = 1984GSAB...95...45H }}
*{{cite book| title = Geology of Chile| last = Stern, Charles R. |author2=Moreno, Hugo |author3=[[Leopoldo López Escobar|López-Escobar, Leopoldo]] |others=Clavero, Jorge E., Lara, Luis E., Naranjo, Jose A., Parada, Miguel A., and Skewes, M. Alexandra | editors = Moreno, Teresa, and Gibbons, Wes| chapter = 5. Chilean Volcanoes| year = 2007| publisher = Geological Society of London|isbn=1-86239-220-X|place=London}}

===Further reading===
* {{cite book|last=González-Ferrán|first=Oscar|title=Volcanes de Chile|language=Spanish|publisher=Instituto Geográfico Militar|location=Santiago, Chile|year=1995|isbn=956-202-054-1}}
* {{cite book|author1=Simkin, T. |author2=Siebert, L.|title=Volcanoes of the World|edition=2nd|publisher=Geoscience Press (in association with the Smithsonian Institution Global Volcanism Program)|location=Tucson Arizona|year=1994|isbn=0-945005-12-1}}
{{Andean volcanoes}}
{{featured article}}

[[Category:Volcanoes of Maule Region]]
[[Category:Volcanic calderas of Chile]]
[[Category:South Volcanic Zone]]
[[Category:Stratovolcanoes of Chile]]
[[Category:Subduction volcanoes]]
[[Category:Mountains of Chile]]</text>
      <sha1>4qq7t901h55iwd13g0sdnt0p8zsct43</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
