<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Changeling (film)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>10825132</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750387097</id>
      <parentid>749955074</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-19T11:55:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 6 sources and tagging 0 as dead. #IABot (v1.2.7.1)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="124131">{{about|the 2008 film directed by Clint Eastwood|the 1980 film|The Changeling (1980 film)}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2015}}
{{Infobox film
| name = Changeling
| image = Changeling poster.jpg
| border = yes
| caption = Theatrical release poster
| alt = On a white background, the top left of the poster is dominated by a woman's head looking down on a much smaller silhouette of a child in the bottom right corner. The woman is pale with prominent red lips and is wearing a brown cloche hat. Across the top of the poster are the names &quot;Angelina Jolie&quot; and &quot;John Malkovich&quot; in uppercase white. Adjacent to the child is the title, &quot;Changeling&quot; in uppercase black. Above are the words, &quot;A true story&quot; in uppercase red. Underneath is the tagline, in uppercase black: &quot;To find her son, she did what no-one else dared.&quot;
| director = [[Clint Eastwood]]
| producer = {{unbulleted list |Clint Eastwood |[[Brian Grazer]] |[[Ron Howard]] |[[Robert Lorenz]]}}
| writer = [[J. Michael Straczynski]]
| starring = {{unbulleted list |[[Angelina Jolie]] |[[John Malkovich]] |}}
| music = Clint Eastwood
| cinematography = [[Tom Stern (cinematographer)|Tom Stern]]
| editing = {{unbulleted list |[[Joel Cox]] |[[Gary D. Roach]]}}
| production companies = {{unbulleted list |[[Imagine Entertainment]] |[[Malpaso Productions]] |[[Relativity Media]]}}
| distributor = [[Universal Studios|Universal Pictures]]
| released = {{film date|2008|10|24}}
| runtime = 141 minutes
| country = United States
| language = English
| budget = $55 million
| gross = $113 million
}}

'''''Changeling''''' is a 2008 American [[Psychological drama|psychological drama film]] directed, co-produced and scored by [[Clint Eastwood]] and written by [[J. Michael Straczynski]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Changeling&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tcm.com/tcmdb/title/676834/Changeling/full-credits.html|title=Changeling|work=[[Turner Classic Movies]]|publisher=[[Turner Broadcasting System]] ([[Time Warner]])|location=[[Atlanta]]|accessdate=November 16, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; that explores child endangerment, female disempowerment, political corruption, mistreatment of mental health patients, and the repercussions of violence. Based partly on real-life events –&amp;nbsp;the 1928 [[Wineville Chicken Coop Murders|&quot;Wineville Chicken Coop&quot; kidnapping and murder case]] in present day [[Mira Loma, California]]&amp;nbsp;– the film stars [[Angelina Jolie]] as a woman supposedly reunited with a boy she immediately realizes is not her missing son. When, however, she tries to demonstrate this to the police and city authorities, she is vilified as delusional and an unfit mother.

Straczynski spent a year researching the story after hearing about the Wineville Chicken Coop case from a contact at Los Angeles City Hall. Almost all&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;Straczynski described 95% of the script as being drawn from around 6,000 pages of documentation.&lt;/ref&gt; of the film's script was drawn from thousands of pages of documentation. His first draft became the [[shooting script]] and his first film [[screenplay]] to be produced. [[Ron Howard]] had meant to direct the film, but scheduling conflicts led to his replacement by Eastwood. Instead, Howard and his [[Imagine Entertainment]] partner [[Brian Grazer]] produced ''Changeling'' alongside [[Malpaso Productions]]' [[Robert Lorenz]] and Eastwood. [[Universal Pictures]] financed and distributed the film.

Several actors campaigned for the leading role; ultimately, the key factor in Eastwood's decision to cast Jolie was his feeling that her face would suit the 1920s period setting. The film also stars [[Jeffrey Donovan]], [[Jason Butler Harner]], [[John Malkovich]], [[Michael Kelly (American actor)|Michael Kelly]] and [[Amy Ryan]]. While some characters are [[Composite character|composites]], most are based on actual people. [[Principal photography]], which began on October 15, 2007 and concluded a few weeks later in December, took place in Los Angeles and other locations in [[southern California]]. Eastwood's low-key direction led actors and crew to note the calmness of the set and the short working days. In [[post-production]], scenes were supplemented with computer-generated skylines, backgrounds, vehicles and people.

''Changeling'' premiered to critical acclaim at the [[2008 Cannes Film Festival|61st Cannes Film Festival]] on May 20, 2008. Further festival appearances preceded a limited release in the United States on October 24, 2008, followed by a general release in North America on October 31, 2008; in the United Kingdom on November 26, 2008; and in Australia on February 5, 2009. Critical reaction was more mixed than at Cannes. While the acting and story were generally praised, the film's &quot;conventional staging&quot; and &quot;lack of nuance&quot; were criticized. ''Changeling'' earned $113&amp;nbsp;million in box-office revenue worldwide{{spaced ndash}}of which $35.7&amp;nbsp;million came from the United States and Canada{{spaced ndash}}and received nominations in three [[Academy Award]] and eight [[British Academy Film Awards|BAFTA Award]] categories.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0824747/awards?ref_=tt_awd |title=Changeling- Awards |publisher=[[IMDb]] |accessdate=June 6, 2016 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131128024304/http://www.imdb.com:80/title/tt0824747/awards?ref_=tt_awd |archivedate=November 28, 2013 |deadurl=yes |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=changeling08.htm |title=Changeling |publisher=BoxOfficeMojo.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Plot ==

In [[Los Angeles]] in 1928, single mother [[Christine Collins]] ([[Angelina Jolie|Jolie]]) returns home to discover her nine-year-old son, Walter ([[Gattlin Griffith]]), is missing. Reverend Gustav Briegleb ([[John Malkovich|Malkovich]]) publicizes Christine's plight and rails against the [[Los Angeles Police Department]] (LAPD) for its incompetence, corruption and the [[extrajudicial punishment]] meted out by its &quot;Gun Squad&quot; led by [[James E. Davis (police)|Chief James E. Davis]] (Feore). Several months after Walter's disappearance, the LAPD tells Christine that he has been found alive. Believing the positive publicity will negate recent criticism of the department, the LAPD organizes a public reunion. Although &quot;Walter&quot; (Devon Conti) claims he is Christine's son, she says he is not. Captain J. J. Jones (Donovan), the head of the LAPD's Juvenile Division, insists the boy is Walter and pressures Christine into taking him home &quot;on a trial basis&quot;.

After Christine confronts Jones with physical discrepancies between &quot;Walter&quot; and her son, Jones arranges for a medical doctor to visit her. He tells Christine that &quot;Walter&quot; is three inches shorter than before his disappearance because trauma has shrunk his spine, and that the man who took Walter had him [[Circumcision|circumcised]]. A newspaper prints a story that implies Christine is an unfit mother; Briegleb tells Christine it was planted by police to discredit her. Walter's teacher and dentist give Christine signed letters confirming &quot;Walter&quot; is an impostor. Christine tells her story to the press; as a result, Jones sends her to [[Los Angeles County-USC Medical Center|Los Angeles County Hospital]]'s &quot;[[Psychiatric ward|psychopathic ward]]&quot;. She befriends inmate Carol Dexter (Ryan), who tells Christine she is one of several women who were sent there for challenging police authority. Dr. Steele (O'Hare) deems Christine delusional and forces her to take mood-regulating pills. Steele says he will release Christine if she admits she was mistaken about &quot;Walter&quot;; she refuses.

Detective Ybarra (Kelly) travels to a ranch in [[Mira Loma, California|Wineville]], [[Riverside County, California|Riverside County]], to arrange the deportation of 15-year-old Sanford Clark ([[Eddie Alderson]]) to Canada. The boy's uncle, Gordon Northcott (Harner), has fled after a chance encounter with Ybarra, who mentions his business there being a juvenile matter. Clark tells Ybarra that Northcott forced him to help kidnap and murder around twenty children, and identifies Walter as one of them. Jones tells Briegleb that Christine is in protective custody following a mental breakdown. Jones orders Clark's deportation, but Ybarra takes Clark to the murder site and tells him to dig where the bodies are buried. Clark hesitates, but soon uncovers body parts. Briegleb secures Christine's release by showing Steele a newspaper story about the Wineville killings that names Walter as a possible victim. Under interrogation by Ybarra, Walter's impostor reveals his motive was to secure transport to Los Angeles to see his favorite actor, [[Tom Mix]], and says the police told him to lie about being Christine's son. The police capture Northcott in [[Vancouver]], Canada. Christine's attorney (Pierson) secures a court order for the release of other unjustly imprisoned women who the police wanted to silence.

On the day of the city council's hearing into the case, Christine and Briegleb arrive at Los Angeles City Hall, where they encounter thousands of protesters who are demanding answers from the city. The hearing is intercut with scenes from Northcott's trial. The council concludes that Jones and Davis should be removed from duty, and that extrajudicial internments by police must be stopped. Northcott's jury finds him guilty of murder and the judge sentences him to death by hanging.

Two years later, Christine has not given up her search for Walter. Northcott sends her a message saying he is willing to admit to killing Walter on condition that Christine meets him before his execution. She visits Northcott, but he refuses to tell her if he killed her son. Northcott is executed the next day.

In 1935, David Clay, one of the boys assumed to have been killed, is found alive in [[Hesperia, California]]. He reveals that one of the boys with whom he was imprisoned was Walter. David, Walter, and another boy escaped, but were separated. David does not know whether Walter was recaptured, but he says Walter helped him escape, giving Christine hope he is alive.

In the epilogue, it states that after the hearing, Captain Jones was suspended, Chief Davis was demoted, and Los Angeles Mayor George Cryer chose not to run for reelection. California's [[state legislature]] made it illegal to forcibly commit people to psychiatric facilities by mere words alone of authorities, and Rev. Briegleb continued to use his radio show to expose police misconduct and political corruption. Wineville is said to have changed its name to Mira Loma, and Christine Collins reportedly never stopped searching for her son.

==Cast==
* [[Angelina Jolie]] as [[Christine Collins]]
* [[John Malkovich]] as Rev. Gustav Briegleb
* [[Jeffrey Donovan]] as J.J. Jones
* [[Michael Kelly (American actor)|Michael Kelly]] as Det. Lester Ybarra
* [[Colm Feore]] as [[James E. Davis (police officer)|Chief James E. Davis]]
* [[Jason Butler Harner]] as [[Gordon Stewart Northcott]]
* [[Amy Ryan]] as Carol Dexter
* [[Geoff Pierson]] as Sammy &quot;S.S.&quot; Hahn
* [[Denis O'Hare]] as Dr. Jonathan Steel
* [[Frank Wood (actor)|Frank Wood]] as Ben Harris
* Peter Geretty as Dr. Earl W. Tarr
* Reed Birney as Mayor Cryer
* [[Gattlin Griffith]] as [[Walter Collins]]

==Historical context==

{{Main|Wineville Chicken Coop Murders}}
In 1926, 13-year-old Sanford Clark was taken from his home in [[Saskatchewan]] (with the permission of his mother and reluctant father) by his uncle, 19-year-old Gordon Stewart Northcott.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Flacco|first=Anthony|others=Clark, Jerry|title=The Road Out of Hell: Sanford Clark and the True Story of the Wineville Murders|publisher=Union Square Press|isbn=978-1-4027-6869-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; Northcott took Clark to a ranch in Wineville, California, where he regularly beat and sexually abused the boy — until {{Nowrap|August 1928}}, when the police took Clark into custody after his sister, 19-year-old Jessie Clark, informed them of the situation.&lt;ref name=&quot;stokley&quot;/&gt; Clark revealed that he was forced to help Northcott and his mother, Sarah Louise Northcott, in killing three young boys after Northcott had kidnapped and molested them.&lt;ref name=&quot;stokley&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;howells&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.film.com/movies/spoilers-changeling-the-real-story-behind-eastwoods-movie | title=Spoilers: Changeling - The Real Story Behind Eastwood's Movie | author=Sacha Howells | work=film.com | publisher=[[RealNetworks]] | date=November 7, 2008 | accessdate=November 10, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The police found no bodies at the ranch — Clark said they were dumped in the desert — but discovered body parts, blood-stained axes, and personal effects belonging to missing children. The Northcotts fled to Canada, but were arrested and extradited to the United States. Sarah Louise initially confessed to murdering Walter Collins, she later retracted her statement; Gordon, who had confessed to killing five boys, did likewise.&lt;ref name=&quot;howells&quot;/&gt;

Christine Collins was placed in Los Angeles County Hospital by Captain Jones. After her release, she sued the police department twice, winning the second lawsuit. Although Captain Jones was ordered to pay Collins $10,800, he never did.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/1999/feb/07/local/me-5769|title=The Boy Who Vanished—and His Impostor|author=Cecilia Rasmussen|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=February 7, 1999|accessdate=February 23, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; A city council welfare hearing recommended that Jones and Chief of Police [[James E. Davis (police)|James E. Davis]] leave their posts, but both were later reinstated. The [[California State Legislature]] later made it illegal for the police to commit someone to a psychiatric facility without a warrant.&lt;ref name=&quot;revisits&quot;/&gt; Northcott was convicted of the murders of Lewis Winslow (12), Nelson Winslow (10) and an unidentified Mexican boy;&lt;ref name=&quot;stokley&quot;/&gt; after his conviction, Northcott was reported to have admitted to up to 20 murders, though he later denied the claim.&lt;ref name=&quot;stokley&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;revisits&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/la-ca-changeling19-2008oct19,0,7763296.story | title='Changeling' revisits a crime that riveted L.A. | author=Rachel Abramowitz | work=[[Los Angeles Times]] | date=October 18, 2008 | accessdate=October 19, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Northcott was executed by hanging in 1930 at the age of 23. Sarah Louise was convicted of Walter Collins' murder and served almost 12 years in prison.&lt;ref name=&quot;stokley&quot;/&gt; In 1930, the residents of Wineville changed the town's name to [[Mira Loma]] to escape the notoriety brought by the case.&lt;ref name=&quot;howells&quot;/&gt;

==Production==

===Development===
Several years before writing ''Changeling'', television screenwriter and former journalist [[J. Michael Straczynski]] was contacted by a source at [[Los Angeles City Hall]]. The source told him that officials were planning to burn numerous archive documents,&lt;ref name=&quot;united&quot;/&gt; among them &quot;something [Straczynski] should see&quot;. The source had discovered a transcript of the city council welfare hearings concerning Collins and the aftermath of her son's disappearance.&lt;ref name=&quot;amc&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blogs.amctv.com/movie-news/2008/05/cannes-film-festival-changeling.php|title=Cannes Film Festival - Interview With Changeling Screenwriter J. Michael Straczynski|author=Clayton Neuman|work=[[AMC (TV network)|American Movie Classics]]|publisher=[[Rainbow Media]]|date=May 20, 2008|accessdate=May 23, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Straczynski became fascinated with the case;&lt;ref name=&quot;post-gazette&quot;/&gt; he carried out some research,&lt;ref name=&quot;wga&quot;/&gt; and wrote a [[spec script]] titled ''The Strange Case of Christine Collins''. Several studios and independent producers [[option (filmmaking)|optioned]] the script, but it never found a buyer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=[[J. Michael Straczynski]]|title=The Complete Book of Scriptwriting|edition=Revised|year=1996|publisher=[[Writer's Digest|Writer's Digest Books]]|page=165|isbn=0-89879-512-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; Straczynski felt he lacked the time to devote to making the story work and only returned to the project following the cancellation of his television show ''[[Jeremiah (TV series)|Jeremiah]]'' in 2004.&lt;ref name=&quot;wga&quot;/&gt; After 20 years as a screenwriter and producer for television, Straczynski felt he needed a break from the medium,&lt;ref name=&quot;post-gazette&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/07221/808007-217.stm|title=Busy writer is drawn back to 23rd century|author=Sharon Eberson|work=[[Pittsburgh Post-Gazette]]|publisher=[[Block Communications]]|date=August 9, 2007|accessdate=January 30, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; so he spent a year researching the Collins case through archived criminal, county courthouse, city hall and city morgue records.&lt;ref name=&quot;gnerre&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.moviemaker.com/articles/print/j_michael_straczynski_changeling_clint_eastwood_angelina_jolie_20081023/|title=Times Are Changing for J. Michael Straczynski|author=Andrew Gnerre|journal=[[MovieMaker]]|publisher=MovieMaker Publishing Co.|date=October 24, 2008|accessdate=October 24, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; He said he collected around 6,000 pages of documentation on Collins and the Wineville murders,&lt;ref name=&quot;united&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/united-changeling-123327|title=United for 'Changeling'|author=Todd Longwell|journal=[[The Hollywood Reporter]]|date=November 20, 2008|accessdate=November 21, 2008}} (registration required for online access)&lt;/ref&gt; before learning enough to &quot;figure out how to tell it&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;post-gazette&quot;/&gt; He wrote the first draft of the new script in 11 days.&lt;ref name=&quot;wga&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wga.org/content/default.aspx?id=3360|title=The Phenom|author=Shira Gotshalk|work=wga.org|publisher=[[Writers Guild of America, west|Writers Guild of America West]]|accessdate=November 5, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Straczynski's agent passed the script to producer [[Jim Whitaker (producer)|Jim Whitaker]]. He forwarded it to [[Ron Howard]],&lt;ref name=&quot;gnerre&quot;/&gt; who optioned it immediately.&lt;ref name=&quot;post-gazette&quot;/&gt;

In June 2006, Universal Studios and Howard's Imagine Entertainment bought the script for Howard to direct. The film was on a shortlist of projects for Howard after coming off the commercial success of ''[[The Da Vinci Code (film)|The Da Vinci Code]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Gabriel Snyder|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117946051.html|title=U picks up 'Changeling'|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=June 27, 2006|accessdate=January 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; In {{Nowrap|March 2007}}, Universal fast-tracked the production. When Howard chose ''[[Frost/Nixon (film)|Frost/Nixon]]'' and ''[[Angels &amp; Demons (film)|Angels &amp; Demons]]'' as his next two directing projects, it became clear he could not direct ''Changeling'' until 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;variety2&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Garrett|first1=Diane|last2=Fleming|first2=Michael|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117960798.html|title=Eastwood, Jolie catch 'Changeling'|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=March 8, 2007|accessdate=January 1, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; After Howard stepped down, it looked as if the film would not be made, despite admiration for the script in the industry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/1143501161.html?dids=1143501161:1143501161&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT|title=The Big Name Gets Distracted|author=Jay Fernandez|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=October 11, 2006|accessdate=January 30, 2008}} (registration required for online access)&lt;/ref&gt; Howard and Imagine partner [[Brian Grazer]] began looking for a new director to helm the project;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite newsgroup|title=Re: Ron Howard's Changeling project falls through?|author=[[J. Michael Straczynski]]|date=October 11, 2006|newsgroup=rec.arts.sf.tv.babylon5.moderated|message-id=1160616893.068094.9610@i42g2000cwa.googlegroups.com|url=https://groups.google.com/forum/#!original/rec.arts.sf.tv.babylon5.moderated/G40Bb2QMKWg/eLTf3ZTedN0J}} Retrieved on January 28, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; they pitched the film to Eastwood in {{Nowrap|February 2007}},&lt;ref name=&quot;united&quot;/&gt; and he agreed to direct immediately after reading the script.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video|people=[[Clint Eastwood]]|title=Partners In Crime: Clint Eastwood and Angelina Jolie|medium=DVD featurette|publisher=[[Universal Studios]]|date=February 17, 2009|time=1:15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood said his memories of growing up during the [[Great Depression]] meant that whenever a project dealing with the era landed in his hands, he &quot;redoubled his attention&quot; upon it.&lt;ref name=&quot;le monde&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.lemonde.fr/cgi-bin/ACHATS/acheter.cgi?offre=ARCHIVES&amp;type_item=ART_ARCH_30J&amp;objet_id=1036282&amp;clef=ARC-TRK-NC_01|title=Clint Eastwood, dans les ténèbres de Los Angeles|author=Samuel Blumenfeld|work=[[Le Monde]]|language=French|date=May 16, 2008|accessdate=June 12, 2008}} (registration required for online access)&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood also cited the script's focus on Collins—rather than the &quot;[[Freddy Krueger]]&quot; story of Northcott's crimes—as a factor in deciding to make the film.&lt;ref name=&quot;united&quot;/&gt;

===Writing===
Straczynski viewed &quot;sitting down and ferreting out [the] story&quot; as a return to his journalistic roots. He also drew on his experience writing crime drama for the [[Police procedural|procedural]] elements of the plot.&lt;ref name=&quot;wga&quot;/&gt; Straczynski said he had gathered so much information about the case that it was difficult to work out how to tell it. To let the story develop at its own pace, he put the project aside to allow himself to forget the less essential elements and bring into focus the parts he wanted to tell. He described what he saw as two overlaid triangles: &quot;the first triangle, with the point up, is Collins' story. You start with her, and her story gets broader and broader and begins having impact from all kinds of places. The overlay on that was an upside down triangle with the base on top, which is the panorama of Los Angeles at that time—1928. And it begins getting narrower and narrower toward the bottom, bearing down on her.&quot; Once Straczynski saw this structure, he felt he could write the story.&lt;ref name=&quot;creative&quot;/&gt; He chose to avoid focusing on the atrocities of the Wineville murders in favor of telling the story from Collins' perspective;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=95935010|title=Behind 'Changeling,' A Tale Too Strange For Fiction|author=Elizabeth Blair|work=[[National Public Radio]]|date=October 24, 2008|accessdate=October 24, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Straczynski said she was the only person in the story without a hidden agenda,&lt;ref name=&quot;creative&quot;/&gt; and it was her tenacity—as well as the legacy the case left throughout California's legal system—that had attracted him to the project. He said, &quot;My intention was very simple: to honor what Christine Collins did.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title='Changeling' production notes|work=universalpicturesawards.com|publisher=[[Universal Pictures]]|url=http://www.universalpicturesawards.com/docs/prodNotes/Changeling_Notes.doc|accessdate=October 18, 2008|format=[[Microsoft Word]] document}}{{dead link|date=September 2016|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote box|width=35%|align=right|quote=&quot;The story is just so bizarre that you need something to remind you that I'm not making this stuff up. So it seemed important to me to put in those clippings because you reach the part of the story where you go, 'Come on he's got to have gone off the rails with this.' Turn the page and there is indeed an article confirming it, which is why, in terms of writing the script, I [hewed] very close to the facts. The story is already extraordinary enough.&quot;|source=—Screenwriter J. Michael Straczynski placed newspaper clippings into physical copies of the script to remind people it was a true story.&lt;ref name=&quot;amc&quot;/&gt;}}
With Collins as the inspiration, Straczynski said he was left with a strong desire &quot;to get it right&quot;; he approached it more like &quot;an article for cinema&quot; than a regular film.&lt;ref name=&quot;wga&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;creative&quot;/&gt; He stuck close to the historical record because he felt the story was bizarre enough that adding too many fictional elements would call into question its integrity.&lt;ref name=&quot;creative&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|title=How Changeling Changed J. Michael Straczynski|author=Jason Davis|journal=Creative Screenwriting Magazine|publisher=Creative Screenwriters Group|issn=1084-8665|volume=15|issue=5|pages=18–21|date=September–October 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Straczynski claimed that 95% of the script's content came from the historical record;&lt;ref name=&quot;gnerre&quot;/&gt; he said there were only two moments at which he had to &quot;figure out what happened&quot;, due to the lack of information in the records. One was the sequence set in the psychopathic ward, for which there was only limited after-the-fact testimony.&lt;ref name=&quot;amc&quot;/&gt; Straczynski originally wrote a shorter account of Collins' incarceration. His agent suggested the sequence needed development, so Straczynski extrapolated events based on standard practice in such institutions at the time. It was at this stage he created composite character Carol Dexter, who was intended to symbolize the women of the era who had been unjustly committed.&lt;ref name=&quot;creative&quot;/&gt; Straczynski cited his academic background, including [[Academic major|majors]] in psychology and sociology, as beneficial to writing the scenes, specifically one in which Steele distorts Collins' words to make her appear delusional.&lt;ref name=&quot;wga&quot;/&gt; Straczynski worked at making the dialogue authentic, while avoiding an archaic tone. He cited his experience imagining alien psyches when writing ''[[Babylon 5]]'' as good practice for putting himself in the cultural mindset of the 1920s.&lt;ref name=&quot;creative&quot;/&gt;

Straczynski described specific visual cues in the screenplay, such as in Sanford Clark's confession scene. Clark's flashback to a falling axe is juxtaposed with the crumbling ash from Detective Ybarra's cigarette. The image served two purposes: it was an aesthetic correlation between the axe and the cigarette, and it suggested that Ybarra was so shocked by Clark's confession that he had not moved or even smoked in the 10 minutes Clark took to tell his story. As with most of the cues, Eastwood shot the scene as written.&lt;ref name=&quot;creative&quot;/&gt; To ensure the veracity of the story, Straczynski incorporated quotes from the historical record, including court testimony, into the dialogue. He also included photocopies of news clippings every 15–20 pages in the script to remind people the story was a true one.&lt;ref name=&quot;notes&quot;/&gt; So the credits could present the film as &quot;a true story&quot; rather than as &quot;based on&quot; one, Straczynski went through the script with Universal's legal department, providing attribution for every scene.&lt;ref name=&quot;cruz&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1852963,00.html|title=Q&amp;A: Changeling Writer J. Michael Straczynski|author=Gilbert Cruz|journal=[[Time (magazine)|Time]]|date=October 23, 2008|accessdate=October 23, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Straczynski believed the only research error he made was in a scene that referenced ''[[Scrabble]]'', pre-dating its appearance on the market by two years. He changed the reference to a crossword puzzle.&lt;ref name=&quot;wga&quot;/&gt; He did not alter the [[shooting script]] any further from his first draft;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.comicbookresources.com/?page=article&amp;id=12669|title=Wondercon: Spotlight on Straczynski|work=[[Comic Book Resources]]|publisher=Boiling Point Productions|author=Erik Amaya|date=February 24, 2008|accessdate=March 3, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; though Straczynski had written two more drafts for Howard, Eastwood insisted the first draft be filmed as he felt it had the clearest voice of the three.&lt;ref name=&quot;creative&quot;/&gt; Straczynski said, &quot;Clint's funny—if he likes it, he'll do it, that's the end of the discussion. When I met with him to ask, 'Do you want any changes, do you want any things cut, added to, subtracted from, whatever', he said, 'No. The draft is fine. Let's shoot the draft.{{' &quot;}}&lt;ref name=&quot;amc&quot;/&gt;

Among the changes Straczynski made from the historical record was to omit Northcott's mother—who participated in the murders—from the story. He also depicted Northcott's trial as taking place in Los Angeles, though it was held in [[Riverside, California|Riverside]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.pe.com/localnews/inland/stories/PE_News_Local_W_whist08.46b9c03.html|title=Hal Durian's Riverside Recollections|author=Hal Durian|work=[[The Press-Enterprise (California)|The Press-Enterprise]]|publisher=[[A. H. Belo Corporation]]|date=February 7, 2009|accessdate=February 25, 2009}}{{dead link|date=September 2016|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt; The title is derived from Western European [[folklore]] and refers to a creature—a &quot;[[changeling]]&quot;—left by [[fairie]]s in place of a human child.&lt;ref name=&quot;newsblaze&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://newsblaze.com/story/20081011134900mill.nb/topstory.html|title=Changeling Movie Review: Angelina On Fire|author=Prairie Miller|work=NewsBlaze|date=October 11, 2008|accessdate=October 10, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to the word's association with the supernatural, Straczynski  intended it only as a temporary title, believing he would be able to change it later on.&lt;ref name=&quot;cruz&quot;/&gt;

===Casting===
[[File:Angelina Jolie on the set of Changeling by Monique Autrey (cropped).jpg|200px|thumb|alt=From waist–up, a pale skinned, red-lipped slender woman in a cloche hat and fastened fur-trimmed coat, both brown|Angelina Jolie was cast partly because Eastwood believed her face evoked the period.&lt;ref name=&quot;mtv&quot;/&gt;]]
The filmmakers retained the names of the real-life protagonists, though several supporting characters were [[composite character|composites]] of people and types of people from the era.&lt;ref name=&quot;notes&quot;/&gt; [[Angelina Jolie]] plays Christine Collins; five actresses campaigned for the role,&lt;ref name=&quot;revisits&quot;/&gt; including [[Reese Witherspoon]] and [[Hilary Swank]].&lt;ref name=&quot;horn&quot;/&gt; Howard and Grazer suggested Jolie; Eastwood agreed, believing that her face fit the period setting.&lt;ref name=&quot;mtv&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mtv.com/movies/news/articles/1589851/story.jhtml|title=Clint Eastwood On 'Changeling' With Angelina Jolie, 'Gran Torino' And Reuniting With Morgan Freeman|author=Josh Horowitz|work=mtv.com|publisher=[[MTV Networks]]|date=June 24, 2008|accessdate=July 1, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Eliot|first=Marc|title=American Rebel: The Life of Clint Eastwood|publisher=[[Harmony Books]]|year=2009|page=327|isbn=978-0-307-33688-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jolie joined the production in {{Nowrap|March 2007}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Michael Fleming, Diane Garrett|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117961436.html|title=Jolie 'Wanted' for Universal film|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=March 19, 2007|accessdate=January 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; She was initially reluctant because, as a mother, she found the subject matter distressing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090614042719/http://dallasnews.com/sharedcontent/dws/ent/stories/DN-peo_0205gd.ART.State.Edition1.4c756ea.html|archivedate=June 14, 2009|deadurl=yes|url=http://www.dallasnews.com/sharedcontent/dws/ent/stories/DN-peo_0205gd.ART.State.Edition1.4c756ea.html|title=People: Penelope Cruz, Ellen DeGeneres, Angelina Jolie|author=Staff|work=[[The Dallas Morning News]]|publisher=[[A. H. Belo Corporation]]|date=February 5, 2009|accessdate=March 4, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; She said she was persuaded by Eastwood's involvement,&lt;ref name=&quot;united&quot;/&gt; and the screenplay's depiction of Collins as someone who recovered from adversity and had the strength to fight the odds.&lt;ref name=&quot;notes&quot;/&gt; Jolie found playing Collins very emotional. She said the most difficult part was relating to the character, because Collins was relatively passive. Jolie ultimately based her performance on her own mother, who died in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/7739707.stm|title=Emotional Jolie takes no prisoners|author=Liam Allen|work=[[BBC News Online]]|date=November 21, 2008|accessdate=November 21, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; For scenes at the telephone exchange, Jolie learned to roller skate in high heels, a documented practice of the period.&lt;ref name=&quot;notes&quot;/&gt;

[[Jeffrey Donovan]] portrays Captain J. J. Jones, a character Donovan became fascinated with because of the power Jones wielded in the city. The character quotes the real Jones' public statements throughout the film, including the scene in which he has Collins committed.&lt;ref name=&quot;notes&quot;/&gt; Donovan's decision to play Jones with a slight Irish accent was his own.&lt;ref name=&quot;united&quot;/&gt; [[John Malkovich]] joined the production in {{Nowrap|October 2007}} as Reverend Gustav Briegleb.&lt;ref name=&quot;hr1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/3-join-jolie-changeling-152663|title=3 join Jolie for 'Changeling'|author=Borys Kit|date=October 16, 2007|journal=[[The Hollywood Reporter]]|accessdate=November 25, 2007}} (registration required for online access)&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood cast Malkovich against [[typecasting (acting)|type]] as he felt this would bring &quot;a different shading&quot; to the character.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Susan Chenery|url=http://www.theaustralian.news.com.au/story/0,25197,24206976-16947,00.html|title=Master of Reinvention|work=[[The Australian]]|date=August 23, 2008|accessdate=August 22, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jason Butler Harner]] plays Gordon Stewart Northcott, whom Harner described as &quot;a horrible, horrible, wonderful person&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.playbill.com/news/article/111681.html|title=Playbill on Opening Night: Mauritius—A Threepenny Opera|author=Harry Haun|journal=[[Playbill]]|date=October 5, 2007|accessdate=January 30, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; He said Northcott believes he shares a connection with Collins due to their both being in the headlines: &quot;In his eyes, they're kindred spirits.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;notes&quot;/&gt; Harner landed the role after one taped audition. Casting director [[Ellen Chenoweth]] explained that Eastwood chose Harner over more well-known actors who wanted the part because Harner displayed &quot;more depth and variety&quot; and was able to project &quot;a slight craziness&quot; without evoking [[Charles Manson]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Elisa Lipsky-Karasz|title=Jason Butler Harner: The New York Theater Veteran Takes to the Big Screen with a Frightening Star Turn|work=[[W Magazine]]|publisher=[[Condé Nast Publications]]|date=October 2008|url=http://www.wmagazine.com/celebrities/2008/10/jason_butler_harner?currentPage=1|accessdate=September 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood was surprised by the resemblance between Northcott and Harner, saying they looked &quot;very much&quot; alike when Harner was in makeup.&lt;ref name=&quot;notes&quot;/&gt;

As Harner did for the Northcott role, [[Amy Ryan]] auditioned via tape for the role of Carol Dexter.&lt;ref name=&quot;ventura&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=Brett Johnson|url=http://www.venturacountystar.com/news/2008/jan/27/amy-ryan-rides-roller-coaster-of-a-career/|title=Amy Ryan rides roller coaster of a career|work=Ventura County Star|publisher=[[E. W. Scripps Company]]|date=January 27, 2008|accessdate=January 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; She cited the filming of a fight scene during which Eastwood showed her &quot;how to throw a movie punch&quot; as her favorite moment of the production.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1703101-2,00.html|title=Q&amp;A: Amy Ryan|author=Lina Lofaro|journal=[[Time (magazine)|Time]]|date=January 12, 2008|accessdate=January 30, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Michael Kelly (American actor)|Michael Kelly]] portrays Detective Lester Ybarra, who is a composite of several people from the historical record.&lt;ref name=&quot;notes&quot;/&gt; Kelly was chosen based on a taped audition; he worked around scheduling conflicts with the television series ''[[Generation Kill (TV series)|Generation Kill]]'', which he was filming in Africa at the same time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Susan King|title='Changeling' actor reveres his boss: Clint Eastwood|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=September 7, 2008|url=http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/movies/la-ca-changeling7-2008sep07,0,3529964.story|accessdate=September 5, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Geoff Pierson]] plays Sammy Hahn, a [[Attorney at law (United States)|defense attorney]] known for taking high-profile cases. He represents Collins and in doing so plants the seeds for overturning &quot;Code 12&quot; internments, used by police to jail or commit those deemed difficult or an inconvenience. Code 12 was often used to commit women without [[due process]]. [[Colm Feore]] portrays [[chief of police#United States|Chief of Police]] James E. Davis, whose backstory was changed from that of his historical counterpart. Reed Birney plays Mayor [[George Edward Cryer|George E. Cryer]]; [[Denis O'Hare]] plays composite character Doctor Jonathan Steele; [[Gattlin Griffith]] plays Walter Collins; and Devon Conti plays his supplanter, Arthur Hutchins. [[Eddie Alderson]] plays Northcott's nephew and accomplice, Sanford Clark.&lt;ref name=&quot;notes&quot;/&gt;

===Filming===

====Locations and design====
[[File:Pacific Electric Railway 1299.JPG|200px|thumb|alt=A 1930s streetcar, bright red, showing its front and right side|The production used two functioning replica [[Pacific Electric Railway]] streetcars for some scenes.&lt;ref name=&quot;partners&quot;&gt;{{cite video|people=[[Clint Eastwood]]|title=Partners In Crime: Clint Eastwood and Angelina Jolie|medium=DVD featurette|publisher=[[Universal Studios]]|date=February 17, 2009|time=12:17}}&lt;/ref&gt; The visual effects team added further streetcars to background shots.&lt;ref name=&quot;notes&quot;/&gt;]]
[[James J. Murakami]] supervised the production design. [[Location scouting]] revealed that many of the older buildings in Los Angeles had been torn down, including the entire neighborhood where Collins lived. Suburban areas in [[San Dimas, California|San Dimas]], [[San Bernardino, California|San Bernardino]] and [[Pasadena, California|Pasadena]] doubled for 1920s Los Angeles instead. The Old Town district of San Dimas stood in for Collins' neighborhood and some adjacent locales. Murakami said Old Town was chosen because very little had changed since the 1920s. It was used for interiors and exteriors; the crew decorated the area with a subdued color palette to evoke feelings of comfort.&lt;ref name=&quot;notes&quot;/&gt; For some exterior shots they renovated derelict properties in neighborhoods of Los Angeles that still possessed 1920s architecture.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video|people=[[Clint Eastwood]], [[Jon Stewart]]|date=October 2, 2008|title=The Daily Show with Jon Stewart|url=http://www.thedailyshow.com/video/index.jhtml?videoId=186778&amp;title=Clint-Eastwood|medium=Television production|publisher=[[Comedy Central]]|location=[[New York City]]|accessdate=October 5, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The crew staged the third floor of the Park Plaza Hotel in Los Angeles into a replica of the 1920s [[Los Angeles City Council]] chambers.&lt;ref name=&quot;asc&quot;/&gt;

The 1918 Santa Fe Depot in San Bernardino doubled for the site of Collins' reunion with &quot;Walter&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.pe.com/localnews/inland/stories/PE_News_Local_E_ntrain10.4644400.html|title=Enthusiasts mark National Train Day|author=Jerry Soifer|work=[[The Press-Enterprise (California)|The Press-Enterprise]]|publisher=[[A. H. Belo Corporation]]|date=May 9, 2009|accessdate=May 10, 2009}}{{dead link|date=September 2016|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt; The production filmed scenes set at [[San Quentin, California|San Quentin]] in the community.&lt;ref name=&quot;united&quot;/&gt; A small farm on the outskirts of [[Lancaster, California]], stood in for the Wineville chicken ranch. The crew recreated the entire ranch, referencing archive newspaper photographs and visits to the original ranch to get a feel for the topography and layout.&lt;ref name=&quot;notes&quot;/&gt; Steve Lech, president of the Riverside Historical Society, was employed as a consultant and accompanied the crew on its visits.&lt;ref name=&quot;stokley&quot;&gt;{{cite news|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090123111352/http://www.pe.com/localnews/riverside/stories/PE_News_Local_S_chicken31.38a6836.html|archivedate=January 23, 2009|deadurl=yes|url=http://www.pe.com/localnews/riverside/stories/PE_News_Local_S_chicken31.38a6836.html|title=Riverside County 'chicken coop murders' inspire Clint Eastwood movie, new book|author=Sandra Stokley|work=[[The Press-Enterprise (California)|The Press-Enterprise]]|publisher=[[A. H. Belo Corporation]]|date=October 30, 2008|accessdate=November 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The production sourced around 150 vintage motor cars, dating from 1918 to 1928, from collectors throughout Southern California. In some cases the cars were in too good a condition, so the crew modified them to make the cars appear like they were in everyday use; they sprayed dust and water onto the bodywork, and to &quot;age&quot; some of the cars they applied a coating that simulated rust and scratches.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/entertainmentnewsbuzz/2008/11/scene-stealer-c.html|title=Scene Stealer: 'Changeling's' vintage autos|author=Patrick Kevin Day|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=November 5, 2008|accessdate=November 6, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The visual effects team retouched shots of Los Angeles City Hall—on which construction was completed in 1928—to remove weathering and newer surrounding architecture.&lt;ref name=&quot;notes&quot;/&gt; Costume designer [[Deborah Hopper]] researched old [[Sears, Roebuck and Company|Sears department store]] catalogs, back issues of [[Life (magazine)|''Life'' magazine]], and high-school yearbooks to ensure the costumes were historically accurate.&lt;ref name=&quot;brisbane&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.brisbanetimes.com.au/news/life-and-style/changeling-your-wardrobe/2009/02/02/1233423111748.html|title=Changeling your wardrobe|author=Rachel Wells|work=[[Brisbane Times]]|publisher=[[Fairfax Media]]|date=February 2, 2009|accessdate=February 2, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hopper sourced 1920s clothing for up to 1,000 people; this was difficult because the fabrics of the period were not resilient. She found sharp wool suits for the police officers. The style for women of all classes was to dress to create a boyish silhouette, using [[waistline (clothing)|dropped waist]] dresses, [[cloche hat]]s that complemented [[bob cut]] hairstyles, fur-trimmed coats and knitted gloves.&lt;ref name=&quot;notes&quot;/&gt; Jolie said the costumes her Collins character wore formed an integral part of her approach to the character. Hopper consulted historians and researched archive footage of Collins to replicate her look. Hopper dressed Jolie in austere grays and browns with knitted gloves, wool [[serge (fabric)|serge]] skirts accompanying cotton blouses, [[Mary Jane (shoe)|Mary Jane shoes]], crocheted [[corsage (bodice)|corsages]] and [[Art Deco]] jewelry.&lt;ref name=&quot;brisbane&quot;/&gt; In the 1930s sequences at the end of the film, Jolie's costumes become more shapely and feminine, with a decorative stitching around the waistline that was popular to the era.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video|people=[[Deborah Hopper]]|title=The Common Thread: Angelina Jolie Becomes Christine Collins|medium=DVD featurette|publisher=[[Universal Studios]]|date=February 17, 2009|time=4:03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Principal photography====
[[Principal photography]] began on October 15, 2007,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Army Archerd|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117972374.html|title=Eastwood plots schedule|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=September 20, 2007|accessdate=January 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; finishing two days ahead of its 45-day schedule on December 14, 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;united&quot;/&gt; Universal Pictures provided a budget of $55&amp;nbsp;million.&lt;ref name=&quot;mojo&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hughes|first=Howard|title=Aim for the Heart|publisher=[[I.B. Tauris]]
|page=209|year=2009|isbn=978-1-84511-902-7|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film was Eastwood's first for a studio other than [[Warner Bros.]] since ''[[Absolute Power (film)|Absolute Power]]''&amp;nbsp;(1997).&lt;ref name=&quot;la weekly&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.laweekly.com/2007-12-20/film-tv/clint-eastwood-the-set-whisperer/|author=Scott Foundas|title=Clint Eastwood: The Set Whisperer|work=[[LA Weekly]]|publisher=[[Village Voice Media]]|date=December 19, 2007|accessdate=October 8, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Filming mainly took place on the Universal Studios [[backlot]] in Los Angeles.&lt;ref name=&quot;vfx&quot;/&gt; The backlot's New York Street and Tenement Street depicted [[downtown]] Los Angeles. Tenement Street also stood in for the exterior of Northcott's sister's Vancouver apartment; visual effects added the city to the background.&lt;ref name=&quot;united&quot;/&gt; The production also used the Warner Bros. backlot in [[Burbank, California|Burbank]], California.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Film Details: l' échange (The Exchange)|work=festival-cannes.com|publisher=[[Cannes Film Festival]]|url=http://www.festival-cannes.com/en/archives/ficheFilm/id/10803061/year/2008.html|accessdate=May 12, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood had clear childhood memories of 1930s Los Angeles and attempted to recreate several details in the film: the town hall, at the time one of the tallest buildings in the city; the city center, which was one of the busiest in the world; and the &quot;perfectly functioning&quot; [[Pacific Electric Railway]], the distinctive red [[streetcars]] of which feature closely in two scenes.&lt;ref name=&quot;le monde&quot;/&gt; The production used two functioning replica streetcars for these shots,&lt;ref name=&quot;partners&quot;/&gt; with visual effects employed for streetcars in the background.&lt;ref name=&quot;notes&quot;/&gt;

{{quote box|width=35%|align=right|quote=&quot;One day we were shooting a scene where [Collins and Briegleb] talk about her case&amp;nbsp;... We started shooting at {{Nowrap|9:30 a.m.}} and it was seven or eight pages, which is usually an 18-hour day. Around 2:30, [Eastwood] goes, 'That's lunch and that's a wrap.'&amp;nbsp;... I've made close to 100 films now and that's certainly a phrase I've never heard in my entire life.&quot;|source=—John Malkovich discusses Eastwood's famously economical directing style, which extended to ''Changeling''{{'}}s set.&lt;ref name=&quot;ew&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20219070_20219072_20218934,00.html|author=Tony Rivetti Jr.|title=Movie Preview: Changeling|journal=[[Entertainment Weekly]]|issue=1007–1008|date=August 22, 2008|accessdate=October 7, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
Eastwood is known for his economical film shoots;&lt;ref name=&quot;ew&quot;/&gt; his regular camera operator, Steve Campanelli, indicated the rapid pace at which Eastwood films—and his intimate, near-wordless direction—also featured during ''Changeling''{{'}}s shoot.&lt;ref name=&quot;canada&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.canada.com/theprovince/news/etoday/story.html?id=b33a4893-c3b4-4fab-a363-0e8d7f67faff&amp;k=92924|title=He makes Clint's day|author=Glen Schaefer|work=[[The Province]]|publisher=Pacific Newspaper Group|date=April 13, 2008|accessdate=April 23, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood limited rehearsals and [[takes]] to garner more authentic performances.&lt;ref name=&quot;notes&quot;/&gt; Jolie said, &quot;You've got to get your stuff together and get ready because he doesn't linger&amp;nbsp;... He expects people to come prepared and get on with their work.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://moviesblog.mtv.com/2007/06/18/angelina-jolie-cant-wait-to-go-toe-to-toe-with-eastwood/|title=Angelina Jolie Can’t Wait To Go Toe-To-Toe with Clint Eastwood|author=Josh Horowitz|work=mtv.com|publisher=[[MTV Networks]]|date=June 18, 2007|accessdate=January 30, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Campanelli sometimes had to tell Jolie what Eastwood wanted from a scene, as Eastwood talked too softly.&lt;ref name=&quot;canada&quot;/&gt; To provide [[verisimilitude]] to certain scenes, Eastwood sometimes asked Jolie to play them quietly, as if just for him. At the same time he would ask his camera operator to start filming discreetly, without Jolie's seeing it.&lt;ref name=&quot;le monde&quot;/&gt; Malkovich noted Eastwood's direction as &quot;redefining economical&quot;, saying Eastwood was quiet and did not use the phrases &quot;action&quot; and &quot;cut&quot;. He said, &quot;Some [directors]—like Clint Eastwood or Woody Allen—don't really like to be tortured by a million questions. They hire you, and they figure you know what to do, and you should do it&amp;nbsp;... And that's fine by me.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://moviesblog.mtv.com/2007/11/09/malkovich-makes-a-changeling/|title=Malkovich Makes A 'Changeling'|author=Jessica Goebel, Larry Carroll|work=mtv.com|publisher=[[MTV Networks]]|date=November 9, 2007|accessdate=January 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ryan also noted the calmness of the set,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://moviesblog.mtv.com/2007/11/27/amy-ryan-loves-spare-changeling/|title=Amy Ryan Loves Spare 'Changeling'|author=Larry Carroll|work=mtv.com|publisher=[[MTV Networks]]|date=November 27, 2007|accessdate=January 30, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; observing that her experiences working with director [[Sidney Lumet]] on ''[[100&amp;nbsp;Centre Street]]'' and ''[[Before the Devil Knows You're Dead]]'' were useful due to his sharing Eastwood's preference for filming a small number of takes.&lt;ref name=&quot;ventura&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20162677_20164082_20167336,00.html|title=Amy Ryan Checks In|author=Missy Schwartz|work=[[Entertainment Weekly]]|date=November 2007|accessdate=January 30, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Donovan said Eastwood seldom gave him direction other than to &quot;go ahead&quot;, and that Eastwood did not even comment on his decision to play Jones with a slight Irish accent: &quot;Actors are insecure and they want praise, but he's not there to praise you or make you feel better&amp;nbsp;... All he's there to do is tell the story, and he hired actors to tell their story.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;united&quot;/&gt; [[Gaffer (filmmaking)|Gaffer]] Ross Dunkerley said he often had to work on a scene without having seen a rehearsal: &quot;Chances are we'll talk about it for a minute or two, and then we're executing it.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;asc&quot;/&gt;

The original edit was almost three hours long; to hone it to 141 minutes, Eastwood cut material from the first part of the film to get to Collins' story sooner. To improve the pacing he also cut scenes that focused on Reverend Briegleb.&lt;ref name=&quot;creative&quot;/&gt; Eastwood deliberately left the ending of the film ambiguous to reflect the uncertain fates of several characters in the history. He said that while some stories aimed to finish at the end of a film, he preferred to leave it open-ended.&lt;ref name=&quot;le monde&quot;/&gt;

====Cinematography====
''Changeling'' was director of photography [[Tom Stern (cinematographer)|Tom Stern]]'s sixth film with Eastwood.&lt;ref name=&quot;asc&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Heuring|first=David|title=Lost and Seemingly Found|journal=[[American Cinematographer]]|publisher=[[American Society of Cinematographers]]|date=November 2008|volume=89|issue=11|pages=18–20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the muted palette, the film is more colorful than some previous Stern–Eastwood collaborations. Stern referenced a large book of period images. He attempted to evoke [[Conrad Hall]]'s work on [[Great Depression|Depression]]-set film ''[[The Day of the Locust (film)|The Day of the Locust]]'', as well as match what he called the &quot;leanness&quot; of ''[[Mystic River (film)|Mystic River]]''{{'}}s look. Stern said the challenge was to make ''Changeling'' as simple as possible to shoot. To focus more on Jolie's performance, he tended to avoid the use of [[fill light]]ing.&lt;ref name=&quot;asc&quot;/&gt; Eastwood did not want the flashbacks to Northcott's ranch to be too much like a horror film—he said the focus of the scene was the effect of the crimes on Sanford Clark—so he avoided graphic imagery in favour of casting the murders in shadow.&lt;ref name=&quot;andrew&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | title=Changeling Man | author=Geoff Andrew | journal=[[Sight &amp; Sound]] | issn= 0037-4806 | page=17 | volume=18 | issue=9 | date=September 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Stern shot ''Changeling'' in [[anamorphic format]] on [[35 mm film|35mm film]] using [[List of motion picture film stocks#VISION color negative (ECN-2 process 1996–2002)|Kodak Vision 500T 5279]] film stock. The film was shot on [[Panavision]] cameras and C-Series lenses. Due to the large number of sets, the lighting rigs were more extensive than on other Eastwood productions. The crew made several ceilings from bleached [[muslin]] tiles. Stern lit the tiles from above to produce a soft, warm light that was intended to evoke the period through tones close to antique and [[Sepia (color)|sepia]]. The crew segregated the tiles using fire safety fabric Duvatyn to prevent light spilling onto neighboring clusters. The [[key light]] was generally softer to match the warm tones given off by the toplights. Stern used stronger [[skypan]]s—more intense than is commonly used for key lighting—to reduce contrasts when applying daytime rain effects, as a single light source tended to produce harder shadows.&lt;ref name=&quot;asc&quot;/&gt;

Stern lit scenes filmed at the Park Plaza Hotel using dimmable [[hydrargyrum medium-arc iodide lamp|HMI]] and tungsten lights rigged within [[balloon light]]s. This setup allowed him to &quot;dial in&quot; the color he wanted, as the blend of tones from the tungsten fixtures, wooden walls and natural daylight made it difficult to illuminate the scenes using HMIs or daylight exclusively. Stern said the period setting had little effect overall on his lighting choices because the look was mostly applied in the production design and during [[digital intermediate]] (DI), the post-production digital manipulation of color and lighting. [[Thomson SA|Technicolor Digital Intermediates]] carried out the DI. Stern supervised most of the work via e-mailed reference images as he was in Russia shooting another film at the time. He was present at the laboratory for the application of the finishing touches.&lt;ref name=&quot;asc&quot;/&gt;

===Visual effects===

====Overview====
[[File:Los Angeles City Hall (color) edit2.jpg|thumb|200px|upright|alt=A tall, white, stone building set against a cloudless blue sky. The base is thicker than the top and is surrounded by smaller buildings of a similar material|Scenes set outside [[Los Angeles City Hall]] were retouched by the effects team to make the building appear new.&lt;ref name=&quot;notes&quot;/&gt;]]
[[Rainmaker Digital Effects|CIS Vancouver]] and Pac Title created most of the visual effects, under the overall supervision of Michael Owens. CIS' work was headed by Geoff Hancock and Pac Title's by Mark Freund. Each studio created around 90 shots. Pac Title focused primarily on 2D imagery;&lt;ref name=&quot;vfx&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.vfxworld.com/?atype=articles&amp;id=3807|title=Changeling: VFX as 'Peripheral Imagery'|author=Thomas J. McLean|journal=VFXWorld|publisher=[[Animation World Network]]|date=October 27, 2008|accessdate=November 6, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; VICON House of Moves handled the [[motion capture]].&lt;ref name=&quot;vfx2&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.vfxworld.com/?sa=adv&amp;code=3631a5a1&amp;atype=news&amp;id=25498|title=VICON House of Moves Provides Mo-Cap for Changeling|author=Thomas J. McLean|journal=VFXWorld|publisher=[[Animation World Network]]|date=November 20, 2008|accessdate=November 21, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The effects work consisted mainly of peripheral additions: architecture, vehicles, crowds and furniture.&lt;ref name=&quot;vfx&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;cg&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://features.cgsociety.org/story_custom.php?story_id=4767|title=Guiding the eye to the Invisible Digital Effects for Changeling|author=Renee Dunlop|work=The CG Society|publisher=Ballistic Media|date=November 6, 2008|accessdate=November 6, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; CIS used 3D modeling package [[Maya (software)|Maya]] to animate city scenes before [[Rendering (computer graphics)|rendering]] them in [[mental ray]]; they generated [[matte painting]]s in [[Softimage XSI]] and Maya, and used [[Eyeon Fusion|Digital Fusion]] for some 2D shots. The team's work began with research into 1928 Los Angeles; they referenced historical photographs and data on the urban core's population density.&lt;ref name=&quot;vfx&quot;/&gt; CIS had to generate mostly new computer models, textures and motion capture because the company's existing effects catalog consisted primarily of modern era elements.&lt;ref name=&quot;cg&quot;/&gt; CIS supplemented exteriors with skylines and detailed backdrops.&lt;ref name=&quot;notes&quot;/&gt; They created set extensions digitally and with matte paintings.&lt;ref name=&quot;cg&quot;/&gt; CIS created city blocks by using shared elements of period architecture that could be combined, rearranged and restacked to make buildings of different widths and heights; that way, the city could look diverse with a minimum of textural variation. CIS referenced vintage aerial photographs of downtown Los Angeles so shots would better reflect the geography of the city, as Hancock felt it important to have a consistency that would allow audiences to understand and become immersed in the environment.&lt;ref name=&quot;vfx&quot;/&gt;

To maintain the rapid shooting pace Eastwood demanded, Owens chose to mostly avoid using [[Chroma key|bluescreen]] technology, as the process can be time-consuming and difficult to light. He instead used [[rotoscoping]], the process whereby effects are drawn directly onto live action shots.&lt;ref name=&quot;cg&quot;/&gt; Rotoscoping is more expensive than bluescreen, but the technique had proved reliable for Eastwood when he made extensive use of it on ''[[Flags of Our Fathers (film)|Flags of Our Fathers]]''&amp;nbsp;(2006) to avoid shooting against bluescreen on a mountaintop. For Owens, the lighting was better, and he considered rotoscoping to be &quot;faster, easier and more natural&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;vfx&quot;/&gt; Owens used bluescreen in only a few locations, such as at the ends of backlot streets where it would not impact the lighting.&lt;ref name=&quot;cg&quot;/&gt; The Universal Studios backlot had been used for so many films that Owens thought it important to disguise familiar architecture as much as possible, so some foreground and middle distance buildings were swapped. One of his favorite effects shots was a scene in which Collins exits a taxi in front of the police station. The scene was filmed almost entirely against bluescreen; only Jolie, the [[sidewalk]], the taxi cab and an extra were real. The completed shot features the full range of effects techniques used in the film: digital extras in the foreground, set extensions, and computer-generated vehicles.&lt;ref name=&quot;vfx&quot;/&gt;

====Digital extras====
For crowd scenes, CIS supplemented the live-action extras with digital pedestrians created using motion capture.&lt;ref name=&quot;vfx&quot;/&gt; House of Moves captured the movements of five men and four women during a two-day shoot supervised by Hancock.&lt;ref name=&quot;vfx2&quot;/&gt; The motion capture performers were coached to make the &quot;small, formal and refined&quot; movements that Owens said reflected the general public's conduct at the time.&lt;ref name=&quot;vfx&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;cg&quot;/&gt; CIS combined the motion data with the [[Massive (software)|Massive]] software package to generate the interactions of the digital pedestrians. The use of Massive presented a challenge when it came to blending digital pedestrians with live-action extras who had to move from the foreground into the digital crowd.&lt;ref name=&quot;cg&quot;/&gt; Massive worked well until this stage, when the effects team had to move the digital pedestrians to avoid taking the live-action extras out of the shot.&lt;ref name=&quot;vfx&quot;/&gt; To allow close-ups of individual Massive extras, the effects team focused on their faces and walking characteristics. Hancock explained, &quot;We wanted to be able to push Massive right up to the camera and see how well it held up. In a couple of shots the characters might be 40 feet away from the camera, about 1/5 screen height. The bigger the screen is, the bigger the character. He could be 10 feet tall, so everything, even his hair, better look good!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;cg&quot;/&gt; Typically, a limited number of motion performances are captured and Massive is used to create further variety, such as in height and walking speed. Because the digital extras were required to be close to the foreground,&lt;ref name=&quot;vfx2&quot;/&gt; and to integrate them properly with the live action extras, House of Moves captured twice as much motion data than CIS had used on any other project.&lt;ref name=&quot;vfx&quot;/&gt; CIS created nine distinct digital characters. To eliminate inaccuracies that develop when creating a digital extra of different proportions to the motion capture performer, CIS sent nine skeleton rigs to House of Moves before work began. This gave House of Moves time to properly adapt the rigs to its performers, resulting in motion capture data that required very little editing in Massive.&lt;ref name=&quot;vfx2&quot;/&gt; CIS wrote [[shader]]s for their clothing; [[displacement mapping|displacement maps]] in the air shader were linked with the motion capture to animate wrinkles in trousers and jackets.&lt;ref name=&quot;vfx&quot;/&gt;

====Closing sequence====
[[File:Changeling closing sequence.png|300px|thumb|alt=Elevated daytime view of a busy city crossroads, looking down one street along which a series of tall buildings recede into the distance. Pedestrians line the sidewalks, cars litter the streets; a bright red electric streetcar features in the foreground|In the final shot, the perspective slowly lifts to take in the city scene. The sequence was introduced to give the audience room for emotional reflection after previous versions of the film ended with a [[Fade (lighting)|cut to black]].&lt;ref name=&quot;cg&quot;/&gt; The streetcars, tracks, power lines and most of the extras were computer generated.&lt;ref name=&quot;vfx&quot;/&gt; The buildings in the distance were created digitally with [[matte painting]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;cg&quot;/&gt;]]
Forgoing the [[Closure (psychology)|closure]] favored by its contemporaries, ''Changeling''{{'}}s final sequence reflects Collins' renewed hope that Walter is alive.&lt;ref name=&quot;cg&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;hanks&quot;/&gt; The shot is a two and a half minute sequence showing Collins' walking off to become lost in a crowd.&lt;ref name=&quot;cg&quot;/&gt; The sequence is representative of the range of effects that feature throughout the film; Los Angeles is presented as major character,&lt;ref name=vfx/&gt; brought to life by unobtrusive peripheral imagery that allows the viewer to focus on the story and the emotional cues. The &quot;hustle and bustle&quot; of the sequence was required to convey that downtown Los Angeles in 1935 was a congested urban center. In the closing shot, the camera tilts up to reveal miles of city blocks,&lt;ref name=&quot;cg&quot;/&gt; pedestrians on the streets, cars going by and streetcars running along their tracks.&lt;ref name=&quot;vfx&quot;/&gt; The version of the film that screened at [[Cannes Film Festival|Cannes]] did not include this sequence; the scene faded to black as Collins walked away. The new 4,000-frame shot was Owens' idea. He felt the abrupt cut to black pulled the viewer out of the film too quickly, and that it left no room for emotional reflection. Owens said, &quot;There is a legend at the end before the credits. The legend speaks to what happened after the fact, and I think you need to just swallow that for a few moments with the visual still with you.&quot; Owens told Eastwood the film should end like ''[[Chinatown (1974 film)|Chinatown]]''&amp;nbsp;(1974), in which the camera lifts to take in the scene: &quot;The camera booms up and she walks away from us from a very emotional, poignant scene at the end, walks away into this mass of people and traffic. It's very hopeful and sad at the same time.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;cg&quot;/&gt;

Owens did not have time to complete the shot before the Cannes screenings, but afterwards he used [[cineSync]] to conduct most of the work from home. The shot includes two blocks of computer-generated buildings that recede into the distance of a downtown set extension. As Collins disappears into the crowd about a minute into the shot, the live footage is gradually joined with more digital work.&lt;ref name=&quot;cg&quot;/&gt; The streetcars, tracks and power lines were all computer generated. Live-action extras appear for the first minute of the shot before being replaced by digital ones. The shot was made more complicated by the need to add [[Massive (software)|Massive]] extras.&lt;ref name=&quot;vfx&quot;/&gt; Owens constructed the scene by first building the digital foreground around the live action footage. He then added the background before filling the scene with vehicles and people.&lt;ref name=&quot;cg&quot;/&gt;

===Music===
{{main|Changeling (soundtrack)}}
Eastwood composed ''Changeling''{{'}}s [[jazz]]-influenced score. Featuring lilting guitars and strings, it remains largely low-key throughout. The introduction of [[brass instrument]]s evokes film noir, playing to the film's setting in a city controlled by corrupt police. The theme shifts from piano to a full orchestra, and as the story develops, the strings become more imposing, with an increasing number of [[sustain]]s and [[Melodic motion|rises]]. Eastwood introduces voices reminiscent of those in a horror film score during the child murder flashbacks.&lt;ref name=&quot;musicmag&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.filmmusicmag.com/?p=2110|title=CD Review: Changeling—Original Soundtrack|author=Daniel Schweiger|work=Film Music Magazine|publisher=Global Media Online|date=November 25, 2008|accessdate=November 26, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=95990500|title='Changeling' Another Step In Eastwood's Evolution|author=Elizabeth Blair|work=[[National Public Radio]]|date=October 24, 2008|accessdate=April 23, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The score was orchestrated and conducted by [[Lennie Niehaus]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite AV media notes|title=[[Changeling (soundtrack)|Changeling Soundtrack]]|others=[[Clint Eastwood]]|date=2008|type=CD liner|publisher=[[Varèse Sarabande]]|id=3020669342}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was released on CD in North America on {{Nowrap|November 4}}, 2008, through record label [[Varèse Sarabande]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.varesesarabande.com/servlet/the-251/Changeling/Detail|title=Changeling: Product Details|work=varesesarabande.com|publisher=[[Varèse Sarabande]]|accessdate=November 26, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Themes==

===Disempowerment of women===
''Changeling'' begins with an abduction, but largely avoids framing the story as a family drama to concentrate on a portrait of a woman whose desire for independence is seen as a threat to male-dominated society.&lt;ref name=&quot;le monde&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;liberation&quot;/&gt; The film depicts 1920s Los Angeles as a city in which the judgment of men takes precedence; women are labeled &quot;hysterical and unreliable&quot; if they dare to question it.&lt;ref name=&quot;honeycutt&quot;/&gt; Film critic Prairie Miller said that in its portrayal of female courage the film was &quot;about as feminist as Hollywood can get&quot;, and that because of this it had been the subject of sexist disdain. She compared this with the sexism shown to the women in ''Changeling'' and those who vied for high political office in 2008. Miller surmised that attitudes to independent, career-minded women had not changed significantly in the intervening years: Collins defies male-generated cultural expectations that women are not suited for professional careers and are punished for it.&lt;ref name=&quot;newsblaze&quot;/&gt; Rather than &quot;an expression of feminist awareness&quot;, [[David Denby (film critic)|David Denby]] argues, the film—like Eastwood's ''[[Million Dollar Baby]]''—is &quot;a case of awed respect for a woman who was strong and enduring&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.newyorker.com/reporting/2010/03/08/100308fa_fact_denby?currentPage=all#ixzz0hnyNNTgl|title=Out of the West|author=David Denby|work=[[The New Yorker]]|date=March 8, 2010|accessdate=March 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The portrait of a vulnerable woman whose mental state is manipulated by the authorities was likened to the treatment of [[Ingrid Bergman]]'s character in ''[[Gaslight (1944 film)|Gaslight]]''&amp;nbsp;(1944), who also wondered if she might be insane;&lt;ref name=&quot;le monde&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090216215113/http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/files/2008/10/why-i-disagree.html|archivedate=February 16, 2009|deadurl=yes|url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/files/2008/10/why-i-disagree.html|author=Scott Feinberg|title='Changeling' and Angelina Jolie: Awards are not won on paper|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=October 7, 2008|accessdate=October 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood cited photographs that show Collins smiling with the child she knows is not hers.&lt;ref name=&quot;le monde&quot;/&gt; Like many other women of the period who were deemed disruptive, Collins is forced into the secret custody of a mental institution. The film shows that psychiatry became a tool in the gender politics of the era, only a few years after [[History of women's suffrage in the United States|women's suffrage in the United States]] was guaranteed by the ratification of the [[Nineteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Nineteenth Amendment]]. As women ceased to be second-class citizens and began to assert their independence, the male establishment used mental institutions in an effort to disempower them; in common with other unmanageable women, Collins is subjected to medical treatment designed to break her spirit and compel obedience, though some of the treatments, specifically the [[electroconvulsive therapy]] depicted in the film, did not exist ca. 1928-1930.&lt;ref name=&quot;newsblaze&quot;/&gt; The film quotes the testimony of the psychiatrist who treated Collins. Eastwood said the testimony evidenced how women were prejudged, and that the behavior of the police reflected how women were seen at the time. He quoted the words of the officer who sent Collins to the mental facility: {{&quot; '}}Something is wrong with you. You're an independent woman.{{' &quot;}} Clint Eastwood said, &quot;The period could not accept [it]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;le monde&quot;/&gt;

===Corruption in political hierarchies===
Romantic notions of the 1920s as a more innocent period are put aside in favor of depicting Los Angeles as ruled by a despotic political infrastructure, steeped in sadistic, systematic corruption throughout the city government, police force and medical establishment.&lt;ref name=&quot;notes&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;honeycutt&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;time&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1807949,00.html|author=Richard Corliss|title=Clint and Angelina Bring a Changeling Child to Cannes|journal=[[Time (magazine)|Time]]|date=May 20, 2008|accessdate=October 10, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to being a [[Kafkaesque]] drama about the search for a missing child,&lt;ref name=&quot;hanks&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/films/reviews/film-of-the-week-changeling-15-1038392.html | title=Film of the week: Changeling|author=Robert Hanks|work=[[The Independent]]|date=November 28, 2008|accessdate=April 16, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;new man&quot;/&gt; the film also focuses on issues relevant to the modern era.&lt;ref name=&quot;yahoo&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://au.news.yahoo.com/a/-/technology/5356827/eastwood-given-special-honour-cannes/|author=Staff|title=Eastwood given special honour by Cannes|work=[[Yahoo News]]/[[Australian Associated Press]]|date=February 27, 2009|accessdate=March 2, 2009}}{{dead link|date=September 2016|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood noted a correlation between the corruption of 1920s Los Angeles and that of the modern era, manifesting in the egos of a police force that thinks it cannot be wrong and the way in which powerful organizations justify the use of corruption.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/brad-balfour/clint-eastwood-as-a-emcha_b_143287.html|title=Clint Eastwood As a Changeling|author=Brad Balfour|work=[[The Huffington Post]]|date=November 12, 2008|accessdate=December 12, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;[The] Los Angeles police department every so often seems to go into a period of corruption,&quot; he said, &quot;It's happened even in recent years&amp;nbsp;... so it was nice to comment [on that] by going back to real events in 1928.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;yahoo&quot;/&gt; Eastwood said that Los Angeles had always been seen as &quot;glamorous&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;andrew&quot;/&gt; but he believed there had never been a &quot;golden age&quot; in the city.&lt;ref name=&quot;le monde&quot;/&gt; In ''Changeling'', this dissonance manifests in the actions of Arthur Hutchins, who travels to the city in the hope of meeting his favorite actor. Eastwood said that given the corruption that the story covers, Hutchins' naïvete seemed &quot;bizarre&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;andrew&quot;/&gt; As a lesson in democratic activism, the film shows what it takes to provoke people to speak against unchecked authority, no matter the consequences. [[Richard Brody]] of ''[[The New Yorker]]'' said this rang as true for 1928 Los Angeles as it did for [[Gdańsk Agreement|Poland in 1980]] or [[Pakistani general election, 2008|Pakistan in 2008]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.newyorker.com/arts/events/revivals/2009/03/09/090309gomo_GOAT_movies_brody|title=Eastwood Ho!|author=[[Richard Brody]]|journal=[[The New Yorker]]|date=March 9, 2009|accessdate=March 2, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film directly quotes Chief of police James E. Davis: &quot;We will hold trial on gunmen in the streets of Los Angeles. I want them brought in dead, not alive, and I will reprimand any officer who shows the least bit of mercy to a criminal.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;notes&quot;/&gt; It compares police excess to the [[vigilante|vigilantism]] of the [[Ku Klux Klan]] of the 1920s, as the department's &quot;Gun Squad&quot; carries out illegal executions of criminals—&quot;not to stamp out crime&amp;nbsp;... but 'competition{{'&quot;}}. The pressure from the police hierarchy was a motivator for officers to quickly solve Walter Collins' disappearance, and a potential reason why they ignored the fact they had returned the wrong child.&lt;ref name=&quot;newsblaze&quot;/&gt;

===Children and violence===
''Changeling'' sits with other late-period Eastwood films in which parenting—and, the search for family—is a theme. It makes literal the parental struggle to communicate with children. It can also be seen as a variation of the Eastwood &quot;revenge movie&quot; ethic; in this case, the &quot;avenging grunt&quot; transforms into a courteous woman who only once makes a foul-mouthed outburst.&lt;ref name=&quot;new man&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://entertainment.timesonline.co.uk/tol/arts_and_entertainment/film/article5814534.ece|title=How Clint Eastwood became a New Man|author=Andrew Billen|work=[[The Times]]|date=February 28, 2009|accessdate=March 2, 2009 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood dealt with themes of child endangerment in ''[[A Perfect World]]''&amp;nbsp;(1993) and ''[[Mystic River (film)|Mystic River]]''&amp;nbsp;(2003).&lt;ref name=&quot;herald&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=David Germain|title=Eastwood takes on mother's story; Jolie plays single mom whose child goes missing|work=[[The Chronicle Herald]]|agency=Associated Press|date=May 21, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Changeling'' is a thematic companion piece to ''Mystic River'',&lt;ref name=&quot;le monde&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;mccarthy&quot;/&gt; which also depicted a community contaminated by an isolated, violent act against a child—a comparison with which Eastwood agreed.&lt;ref name=&quot;le monde&quot;/&gt; He said that showing a child in danger was &quot;about the highest form of drama you can have&quot;, as crimes against them were to him the most horrible.&lt;ref name=&quot;herald&quot;/&gt; Eastwood explained that crimes against children represented a theft of lives and innocence.&lt;ref name=&quot;andrew&quot;/&gt; He said, &quot;When [a crime] comes along quite as big as this one, you question humanity. It never ceases to surprise me how cruel humanity can be.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;herald&quot;/&gt; Samuel Blumenfeld of ''[[Le Monde]]'' said the scene featuring Northcott's execution by hanging was &quot;unbearable&quot; due to its attention to detail; he believed it one of the most convincing pleas against the death penalty imaginable. Eastwood noted that for a supporter of capital punishment, Northcott was an ideal candidate, and that in a perfect world the death penalty might be an appropriate punishment for such a crime.&lt;ref name=&quot;le monde&quot;/&gt; He said that crimes against children would be at the top of his list for justifications of capital punishment,&lt;ref name=&quot;revisits&quot;/&gt; but that whether one were pro- or anti-capital punishment, the barbarism of public executions must be recognized. Eastwood argued that in putting the guilty party before his victims' families, justice may be done, but after such a spectacle the family would find it hard to find peace. The scene's realism was deliberate: the audience hears Northcott's neck breaking, his body swings, and his feet shake. It was Eastwood's intention to make it unbearable to watch.&lt;ref name=&quot;le monde&quot;/&gt;

==Release==

===Strategy===
[[File:ClintEastwoodCannesMay08.jpg|thumb|150px|right|alt=An older man is at the center of the image smiling and looking off to the right of the image. He is wearing a white jacket, and a tan shirt and tie. The number 61 can be seen behind him on a background wall.|Eastwood at a panel for the film at the [[2008 Cannes Film Festival|61st Cannes Film Festival]]]]
''Changeling'' premiered in competition at the [[2008 Cannes Film Festival|61st Cannes Film Festival]] on May 20, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.festival-cannes.com/assets/Pdf/General/pdf-9141.pdf|format=PDF|title=Screenings Guide|work=festivale-cannes.com|publisher=[[Cannes Film Festival]]|accessdate=May 8, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film was Eastwood's fifth to enter competition at the festival.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117984494.html|title=Clint's 'Changeling' set for Cannes|author=Todd McCarthy|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=April 22, 2008|accessdate=April 23, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its appearance was not part of the original release plan. Universal executives had been looking forward to the festival without the worry associated with screening a film, until Eastwood made arrangements for ''Changeling''{{'}}s appearance.&lt;ref name=&quot;masters&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/cannes-late-lineup-headaches-111572|title=Cannes' late lineup causes headaches|author=Charles Masters, Scott Roxborough|journal=[[The Hollywood Reporter]]|date=May 13, 2008|accessdate=May 15, 2008}} (registration required for online access)&lt;/ref&gt; He was pleased with the critical and commercial success that followed ''[[Mystic River (film)|Mystic River]]''{{'}}s appearance at the festival in 2003 and wanted to generate the same &quot;positive buzz&quot; for ''Changeling''.&lt;ref name=&quot;horn&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2008/oct/23/entertainment/et-word23|title='Changeling' banks on the Eastwood effect|author=John Horn|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=October 23, 2008|accessdate=March 26, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film was still in [[post-production]] one week before the start of the festival.&lt;ref name=&quot;masters&quot;/&gt; It appeared at the 34th [[Deauville American Film Festival]], held September 5&amp;ndash;14, 2008,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=John Hopewell|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117989258.html|title='Mamma Mia!' opens Deauville: Musical to kick off festival on Sept. 5|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=July 21, 2008|accessdate=August 13, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and had its North American premiere on October 4, 2008 as the centerpiece of the 46th [[New York Film Festival]], screening at the [[Ziegfeld Theatre (1969)|Ziegfeld Theatre]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Gregg Goldstein|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/filmNews/idUSN1244530820080813|title=New York film fest stocked with Cannes titles|work=[[Reuters]]|date=August 13, 2008|accessdate=August 20, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The producers and Universal considered opening ''Changeling'' wide in its first weekend to capitalize on Jolie's perceived [[box office]] appeal, but they ultimately modeled the release plan after those of other Eastwood-directed films, ''Mystic River'' in particular. While the usual strategy is to open films by notable directors in every major city in the United States to ensure a large opening gross, in what the industry calls a &quot;platform release&quot;, Eastwood's films generally open in a small number of theaters before opening wide a week later.&lt;ref name=&quot;horn&quot;/&gt; ''Changeling'' was released in 15 theaters&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;The theater count refers to individual [[movie theater]]s that may include multiple auditoriums. The screen count refers to individual auditoriums.&lt;/ref&gt; in nine markets in the United States on October 24, 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;limited&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117994680.html|title='HSM 3' makes box office honor roll|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|author=Dade Hayes|date=October 26, 2008|accessdate=October 26, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The marketing strategy involved trailers that promoted Eastwood's involvement and the more commercial mystery thriller elements of the story. Universal hoped the limited release would capitalize on good word-of-mouth support from &quot;serious movie fans&quot; rather than those in the 18&amp;ndash;25-year-old [[demographic profile|demographic]].&lt;ref name=&quot;horn&quot;/&gt; The film was released across North America on October 31, 2008, playing at 1,850 theaters,&lt;ref name=&quot;wide&quot;/&gt; expanding to 1,896 theaters by its fourth week.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117995955.html|title='Quantum' posts Bond's best opening|author=Pamela McClintock|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=November 16, 2008|accessdate=November 25, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Changeling'' was released in the United Kingdom on November 26, 2008,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/7734948.stm|title=Jolie's tears for her late mother|author=Staff|work=[[BBC News Online]]|date=November 18, 2008|accessdate=March 3, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; in Ireland on November 28, 2008,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.rte.ie/ten/2008/1007/eastwood_jolie_palin.html|author=Staff|title=Eastwood jokes about VP offer|work=rte.ie|publisher=[[Raidió Teilifís Éireann|Radio Telefís Éireann]]|date=October 7, 2008|accessdate=October 27, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in Australia on February 5, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.theage.com.au/news/entertainment/film/modern-morality-tales/2008/12/23/1229998532682.html|title=Modern morality tales|author=Jim Schembri|work=[[The Age]]|publisher=[[Fairfax Media]]|date=December 24, 2008|accessdate=December 24, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Box office===
[[File:Cinema projecting differents movies in Edinburgh.jpg|thumb|200px|right|alt=|The Cameo Cinema in [[Edinburgh]] screening the film]]
''Changeling'' performed modestly at the box office,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Geoffrey Macnab|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/films/features/julia-roberts--has-cinemas-queen-lost-her-crown-1643714.html|title=Julia Roberts - Has cinema's queen lost her crown?|work=[[The Independent]]|date=March 13, 2009|accessdate=April 3, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; grossing more internationally than in North America.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Pamela McClintock|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1118001196.html|title='Watchmen' battle superhero bias|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=March 13, 2009|accessdate=March 26, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Pamela McClintock|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1118001053.html|title=Clint mints overseas box office|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=March 10, 2009|accessdate=March 26, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The worldwide gross revenue was $113&amp;nbsp;million.&lt;ref name=&quot;mojo&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=changeling08.htm|title=Changeling (2008)|work=[[Box Office Mojo]]|publisher=[[Amazon.com]]|accessdate=June 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film's limited American release saw it take $502,000—$33,441 per theater—in its first two days.&lt;ref name=&quot;limited&quot;/&gt; Exit polling showed strong commercial potential across a range of audiences.&lt;ref name=&quot;finke&quot;/&gt; [[CinemaScore]] polls conducted during the opening weekend revealed the average grade cinemagoers gave ''Changeling'' was A− on an A+ to F scale.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Joshua Rich|title='High School Musical 3' Scares up Another Win|url=http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20237423,00.html|journal=[[Entertainment Weekly]]|date=November 2, 2008|accessdate=November 2, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Audiences were mostly older; 68% were over 30 and 61% were women.&lt;ref name=&quot;var-weekend&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117995130.html|title='School' still rules box office|author=Pamela McClintock|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=November 2, 2008|accessdate=November 3, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Audience evaluations of &quot;excellent&quot; and &quot;definitely recommended&quot; were above average. The main reasons given for seeing the film were its story (65%), Jolie (53%), Eastwood (43%), and that it was based on fact (42%).&lt;ref name=&quot;finke&quot;/&gt; The film made $2.3M in its first day of wide release,&lt;ref name=&quot;wide&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117995123.html|title='Saw&amp;nbsp;V' scares off B.O. competition|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|author=Anthony D'Alessandro|date=November 1, 2008|accessdate=November 1, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; going on to take fourth place in the weekend box office chart with $9.4M—a per-theater average of $5,085.&lt;ref name=&quot;var-weekend&quot;/&gt; This return surpassed Universal's expectations for the weekend.&lt;ref name=&quot;finke&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.deadline.com/2008/11/box-office-report-coming/|title=Halloween Scared Weekend Filmgoers|author=[[Nikki Finke]]|work=Deadline Hollywood Daily|date=November 1, 2008|accessdate=November 25, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Changeling''{{'}}s link to the [[Inland Empire (California)|Inland Empire]]—the locale of the Wineville killings—generated additional local interest, causing it to outperform the national box office by 45% in its opening weekend.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.pe.com/localnews/inland/stories/PE_News_Local_S_boxoffice04.37cb1b6.html|title=Local ties help make 'Changeling' an Inland box-office hit|author=Fielding Buck|work=[[The Press-Enterprise (California)|The Press-Enterprise]]|publisher=[[A. H. Belo Corporation]]|date=November 3, 2008|accessdate=November 4, 2008}}{{dead link|date=September 2016|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;''Changeling'' took $117,862 in 16 Inland Empire theaters, for an average of $7,366 per location.&lt;/ref&gt; The film surpassed expectations in its second weekend of wide release,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.the-numbers.com/interactive/newsStory.php?newsID=3817|title=Box Office Goes Wild|author=Staff|work=The Numbers|publisher=Nash Information Services|date=November 11, 2008|accessdate=December 22, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; declining 22% to take $7.3M.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117995549.html|title=Audiences wild about 'Madagascar'|author=Pamela McClintock|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=November 9, 2008|accessdate=November 25, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the fourth week, ''Changeling'' had dropped to fifth place at the box office, having taken $27.6M overall.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.the-numbers.com/interactive/newsStory.php?newsID=3830|title=Nothing Small About Quantum|author=Staff|work=The Numbers|publisher=Nash Information Services|date=November 18, 2008|accessdate=December 22, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; In its sixth week the number of theaters narrowed to 1,010,&lt;ref name=&quot;numbers&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.the-numbers.com/movies/2008/CHNGL.php|title=The Changeling|work=The Numbers|publisher=Nash Information Services|accessdate=February 11, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''Changeling'' dropped out of the national top ten, though it remained in ninth place on the Inland chart.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.pe.com/localnews/inland/stories/PE_News_Local_S_boxoffice02.1dcd2e2.html|title=It's very merry at box office for 'Four Christmases'|author=Fielding Buck|work=[[The Press-Enterprise (California)|The Press-Enterprise]]|publisher=[[A. H. Belo Corporation]]|date=December 1, 2008|accessdate=December 22, 2008}}{{dead link|date=September 2016|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;In the film's sixth week of release in the Inland Empire, it earned $20,540 on 14 screens.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Changeling'' completed its theatrical run in North America on January 8, 2009, having earned $35.7M overall.&lt;ref name=&quot;mojo&quot;/&gt;

''Changeling'' made its international debut in four European markets on November&amp;nbsp;12–14, 2008,&lt;ref name=&quot;int&quot;/&gt; opening in 727 theaters to strong results.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117995954.html|title='Solace' continues world domination|author=Dave McNary|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=December 16, 2008|accessdate=November 25, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Aided by a positive critical reaction, the film took $1.6M in Italy from 299 theaters (a per-location average of $5,402),&lt;ref name=&quot;europe&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117996322.html|title='Burn After Reading' on fire overseas|author=Pamela McClintock, Archie Thomas|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=November 21, 2008|accessdate=November 25, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and $209,000 from 33 screens in Belgium.&lt;ref name=&quot;school&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.the-numbers.com/interactive/newsStory.php?newsID=3844|title=School Climbing Higher|author=Staff|work=The Numbers|publisher=Nash Information Services|date=November 23, 2008|accessdate=December 23, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Changeling'' had a slower start in France, but improved to post $2.8M from 417 theaters in its first five days,&lt;ref name=&quot;europe&quot;/&gt; and finished the weekend in second place at the box office.&lt;ref name=&quot;school&quot;/&gt; The second week in France saw the box office drop by just 27%, for a total gross of $5.4M.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117996452.html|title=Bond still boss in Europe|author=Archie Thomas|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=November 25, 2008|accessdate=December 23, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; By November 23, 2008, the film had taken $8.6M outside North America.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/solace-still-going-strong-overseas-123422|title='Solace' still going strong overseas|author=Frank Segers|journal=[[The Hollywood Reporter]]|date=November 23, 2008|accessdate=November 25, 2008}} (registration required for online access)&lt;/ref&gt; The weekend of November&amp;nbsp;28–30 saw ''Changeling'' take $4.4M from 1,040 theaters internationally;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117996589.html|title='Quantum' still rules overseas|author=Dave McNary|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=November 30, 2008|accessdate=December 23, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; this included its expansion into the United Kingdom, where it opened in third place at the box office, taking $1.9M from 349 theaters.&lt;ref name=&quot;segers&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/quantum-takes-intl-bo-fifth-123636|title='Quantum' takes int'l b.o. for fifth week|author=Frank Segers|journal=[[The Hollywood Reporter]]|date=November 30, 2008|accessdate=November 30, 2008}} (registration required for online access)&lt;/ref&gt; It took $1.5M from the three-day weekend, but the total was boosted by the film's opening two days earlier to avoid competition from previews of ''[[Madagascar: Escape 2 Africa]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/film/filmblog/2008/dec/02/uk-box-office|title=Santa smashes Bond for UK box-office crown|author=Charles Gant|work=[[The Guardian]]|date=December 2, 2008|accessdate=December 2, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The return marked the best opening of any Eastwood-directed film in the United Kingdom to that point.&lt;ref name=&quot;segers&quot;/&gt; Its second week of release in the United Kingdom saw a drop of 27% to $1.1M.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117997076.html|title='Escape 2 Africa' heats up Europe|author=Archie Thomas|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=December 9, 2008|accessdate=December 23, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Changeling'' earned $7.6M in Ireland and the United Kingdom.&lt;ref name=&quot;int&quot;/&gt;

''Changeling''{{'}}s release in other European markets continued throughout {{Nowrap|December 2008}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117996868.html|title='Punisher' to hit box office zone|author=Ben Fritz, Dave McNary|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=December 4, 2008|accessdate=December 23, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;hy&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/madagascar-sequel-marks-territory-124064|title=Madagascar' sequel marks its territory|author=[[Hy Hollinger]]|journal=[[The Hollywood Reporter]]|date=December 8, 2008|accessdate=December 23, 2008}} (registration required for online access)&lt;/ref&gt; By December 8, the film had opened in 1,167 theaters in nine markets for an international gross of $19.1M.&lt;ref name=&quot;hy&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;enthralling&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.the-numbers.com/interactive/newsStory.php?newsID=3891|title=International Releases are Enthralling|author=Staff|work=The Numbers|publisher=Nash Information Services|date=December 14, 2008|accessdate=December 23, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Changeling''{{'}}s next significant international release came in Spain on December 19, 2008,&lt;ref name=&quot;enthralling&quot;/&gt; where it opened in first place at the box office with $2.0M from 326 theaters. This figure marked the best opening for an Eastwood-directed film in the country to that point;&lt;ref name=&quot;screen1&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.screendaily.com/ScreenDailyArticle.aspx?intStoryID=42458|title=Madagascar 2 soars past $200m after $33.5m weekend for PPI|author=Jeremy Kay|work=[[Screen International|Screen Daily]]|publisher=[[EMAP|East Midland Allied Press]]|date=December 22, 2008|accessdate=December 23, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; after six weeks it had earned $11.0M. In {{Nowrap|January 2009}}, major markets in which the film opened included Germany, South Korea and Russia. In Germany, it opened in ninth place at the box office with $675,000 from 194 theaters. South Korea saw a &quot;solid&quot; opening of $450,000 from 155 theaters.&lt;ref name=&quot;screen2&quot;/&gt; In Russia, it opened in eighth place with $292,000 from 95 theaters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.the-numbers.com/interactive/newsStory.php?newsID=3981|title=International Details - Escaping the Top Five|author=Staff|work=The Numbers|publisher=Nash Information Services|date=January 25, 2009|accessdate=February 12, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; By January 26, 2009, the film had taken $47.2M from 1,352 international theaters.&lt;ref name=&quot;screen2&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.screendaily.com/ScreenDailyArticle.aspx?intStoryID=42833|title=Valkyrie leads international box office with $13.2m in 13 markets|author=Jeremy Kay|work=[[Screen International|Screen Daily]]|publisher=[[EMAP|East Midland Allied Press]]|date=January 26, 2009|accessdate=February 12, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Aided by strong word-of-mouth support, ''Changeling''{{'}}s Australian release yielded $3.8M from 74 screens after eight weeks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://blogs.theage.com.au/schembri/archives/2009/03/post_16.html|title='Knowing' hits while 'Two Fists' tanks|author=Jim Schembri|work=[[The Age]]|publisher=[[Fairfax Media]]|date=March 31, 2009|accessdate=April 2, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film opened in Japan on February 20, 2009,&lt;ref name=&quot;int&quot;/&gt; where it topped the chart in its first week with $2.4M from 301 screens.&lt;ref name=&quot;numbers-conf&quot;/&gt; After six weeks, it had earned $12.8M in the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.screendaily.com/ScreenDailyArticle.aspx?intStoryID=43828|title=Summit's Knowing takes international crown with $9.8m from 10 markets|author=Jeremy Kay|work=[[Screen International|Screen Daily]]|publisher=[[EMAP|East Midland Allied Press]]|date=March 29, 2009|accessdate=March 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film's last major market release was in Mexico on February 27, 2009,&lt;ref name=&quot;numbers-conf&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.the-numbers.com/interactive/newsStory.php?newsID=4066|title=Confessions of the International Box Office|author=Staff|work=The Numbers|publisher=Nash Information Services|date=March 1, 2009|accessdate=March 4, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; where it earned $1.4M. The international gross was $77.3M.&lt;ref name=&quot;int&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?page=intl&amp;id=changeling08.htm|title=Changeling (2008) International Box Office Results|work=[[Box Office Mojo]]|publisher=[[Amazon.com]]|accessdate=June 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Home media===
''Changeling'' was released on [[Blu-ray Disc]], [[DVD]], and [[Video on demand|Video on Demand]] in North America on February 17, 2009,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.highdefdigest.com/news/show/Universal/Disc_Announcements/Universal_to_Bring_Changeling_to_Blu-ray/2330|author=Staff|title=Universal to Bring 'Changeling' to Blu-ray|work=High-Def Digest|publisher=[[Internet Brands]]|date=December 15, 2008|accessdate=December 22, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;dvdsales&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.the-numbers.com/movies/2008/CHNGL-DVD.php|title=The Changeling - DVD Sales|work=The Numbers|publisher=Nash Information Services|accessdate=March 27, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in the United Kingdom on March 30, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.play.com/DVD/DVD/4-/5830681/Changeling/Product.html|title=Changeling (2008)|work=[[Play.com]]|accessdate=March 4, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; After its first week of release, ''Changeling'' placed fourth in the DVD sales chart with 281,000 units sold for $4.6&amp;nbsp;million;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.the-numbers.com/interactive/newsStory.php?newsID=4072|title=High School Graduates Top of Its Class|author=Staff|work=The Numbers|publisher=Nash Information Services|date=March 3, 2009|accessdate=March 4, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; by its fourth week of release, the film had dropped out of the top 10, having earned $10.1&amp;nbsp;million.&lt;ref name=&quot;dvdsales&quot;/&gt; As of the latest figures, 762,000 units have been sold, translating to $12,638,223 in revenue.&lt;ref name=&quot;dvdsales&quot;/&gt; The DVD release included two [[featurette]]s: ''Partners in Crime: Clint Eastwood and Angelina Jolie'' and ''The Common Thread: Angelina Jolie Becomes Christine Collins''. The Blu-ray Disc release included two additional features: ''Archives'' and ''Los Angeles: Then and Now''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://bluray.highdefdigest.com/news/show/Universal/Exclusive_HD_Content/Universal_Outlines_Changeling_Blu-ray_Specs,_Exclusives/2380|author=Staff|title=Universal Outlines 'Changeling' Blu-ray Specs, Exclusives|work=High-Def Digest|publisher=[[Internet Brands]]|date=January 7, 2009|accessdate=March 4, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reception==

===Critical response===
The film's screening at Cannes met with critical acclaim, prompting speculation it could be awarded the [[Palme d'Or]].&lt;ref name=&quot;creative&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://goldderby.latimes.com/awards_goldderby/2008/05/clint-eastwood.html|title=Clint Eastwood could win the Palme d'Or for his Angelina Jolie pic (whatever the title is)|author=Tom O'Neil|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=May 21, 2008|accessdate=May 21, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The award eventually went to ''[[Entre les murs]]'' (''The Class'').&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Kenneth Turan|url=http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/movies/la-et-cannes26-2008may26,0,7548309.story|title=Palme d'Or goes to France's 'Entre les Murs'|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=May 28, 2008|accessdate=October 7, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Straczynski claimed that ''Changeling''{{'}}s loss by two votes was due to the judges' not believing the story was based on fact. He said they did not believe the police would treat someone as they had Collins. The loss led to Universal's request that Straczynski annotate the script with sources.&lt;ref name=&quot;creative&quot;/&gt; Although the positive critical notices from Cannes generated speculation that the film would be a serious contender at the 2009 Academy Awards, the North American theatrical release met with a more mixed response.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.variety.com/awardcentral_article/VR1117995793.html|title=Changeling: Eastwood continues success with Jolie drama|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|author=Justin Chang|date=November 14, 2008|accessdate=November 14, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.variety.com/awardcentral_article/VR1118000050.html|title=Quest for Oscar leaves some films out|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|author=Glenn Whipp|date=February 11, 2009|accessdate=March 30, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Critics generally judged ''Changeling'' well-acted and beautifully shot, but considered the compelling story to have been told too conventionally.&lt;ref name=&quot;rotten&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/1191742_changeling/|title=Changeling Movie Reviews|work=[[Rotten Tomatoes]]|publisher=IGN Entertainment, Inc|accessdate=April 6, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Metacritic]], which assigns a [[standard score|normalized]] rating out of 100 to reviews from mainstream critics, reported that reviews were &quot;generally favorable,&quot; with an [[weighted mean|average]] score of 63 based on 38 reviews.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.metacritic.com/film/titles/changeling2008|title=Changeling (2008): Reviews|work=[[Metacritic]]|publisher=CNET Networks, Inc|accessdate=November 27, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of June 10, 2014, 63% of 197 critics listed by review aggregator [[Rotten Tomatoes]] had given the film a positive review, with an average rating of 6.3/10.&lt;ref name=&quot;rotten&quot;/&gt; The film's reception in several European countries was more favorable,&lt;ref name=&quot;europe&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117997653.html|title=Europe gets in festive mood|author=Nick Vivarelli|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=December 19, 2008|accessdate=December 20, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in the United Kingdom 83% of critics listed by Rotten Tomatoes gave ''Changeling'' a positive review.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/1191742_changeling/news/1783626/uk_critics_consensus_local_critics_warm_to_changeling_de_niro_delights_but_what_just_happened_doesnt|title=UK Critics Consensus: Local Critics Warm To Changeling; De Niro Delights But What Just Happened Doesn't|author=Tom Butler|date=November 28, 2008|work=[[Rotten Tomatoes]]|publisher=IGN Entertainment, Inc|accessdate=November 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote box|width=35%|quote=&quot;Jolie puts on a powerful emotional display as a tenacious woman who gathers strength from the forces that oppose her. She reminds us that there is nothing so fierce as a mother protecting her cub.&quot;|source=—Kirk Honeycutt of ''The Hollywood Reporter''&lt;ref name=&quot;honeycutt&quot;/&gt;}}
Todd McCarthy of ''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]'' said Jolie was more affecting than in ''[[A Mighty Heart (film)|A Mighty Heart]]''&amp;nbsp;(2007) because she relied less on artifice. He also noted a surfeit of good supporting performances, Michael Kelly's in particular.&lt;ref name=&quot;mccarthy&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=awardcentral&amp;jump=review&amp;id=film&amp;reviewid=VE1117937210|title='Changeling' review|author=Todd McCarthy|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=May 20, 2008|accessdate=May 21, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Oliver Séguret of ''[[Libération]]'' said the cast was the film's best feature. He praised the supporting actors and said Jolie's performance was forceful yet understated.&lt;ref name=&quot;liberation&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.liberation.fr/cinema/010181328-l-echange-bon-procede|title=L'Echange: bon procédé|author=Oliver Séguret|work=[[Libération]]|language=French|date=May 21, 2008|accessdate=February 25, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kirk Honeycutt of ''[[The Hollywood Reporter]]'' said Jolie shunned her &quot;movie star&quot; persona to appear vulnerable and resolute. He perceived the supporting characters—Amy Ryan's excepted—as having few shades of gray.&lt;ref name=&quot;honeycutt&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/review/changeling-126241|title=Film Review: Changeling|author=Kirk Honeycutt|journal=[[The Hollywood Reporter]]|date=May 20, 2008|accessdate=May 21, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; David Ansen, writing in ''[[Newsweek]]'', echoed the sentiment, but said that &quot;some stories really are about the good guys and the bad&quot;. He said that with the distractions of Jolie's celebrity and beauty put aside, she carried the role with restraint and intensity.&lt;ref name=&quot;ansen&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.newsweek.com/id/164500|title=The Horror Of It All|author=David Ansen|journal=[[Newsweek]]|date=October 18, 2008|accessdate=October 21, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Manohla Dargis]] of ''[[The New York Times]]'' felt that Jolie's celebrity was distracting enough to render her unconvincing,&lt;ref name=&quot;dargis&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/05/21/movies/21dargis.html|title=A California of Noir Shadows and Blood|author=[[Manohla Dargis]]|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=May 21, 2008|accessdate=November 11, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[David Denby (film critic)|David Denby]] of ''The New Yorker'' said that while Jolie showed skill and selflessness, the performance and character were uninteresting. He said Collins was one-dimensional, lacking desires or temperament. He cited similar problems with Malkovich's Briegleb, concluding, &quot;The two of them make a very proper and dull pair of collaborators.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;denby&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/cinema/2008/10/27/081027crci_cinema_denby?currentPage=all|title=Troubled Sons|author=David Denby|journal=[[The New Yorker]]|date=October 27, 2008|accessdate=October 20, 2008|authorlink=David Denby (film critic)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

McCarthy admired the &quot;outstanding&quot; script, calling it ambitious and deceptively simple. He said Eastwood respected the script by not playing to the melodramatic aspects and not telegraphing the story's scope from the start.&lt;ref name=&quot;mccarthy&quot;/&gt; Honeycutt wrote that due to its close adherence to the history the drama sagged at one point, but that the film did not feel as long as its 141 minutes because the filmmakers were &quot;good at cutting to the chase&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;honeycutt&quot;/&gt; Ansen said Straczynski's dialogue tended to the obvious, but that while the film lacked the moral nuance of Eastwood's others, the well-researched screenplay was &quot;a model of sturdy architecture&quot;, each layer of which built audience disgust into a &quot;fine fury&quot;. He said, &quot;when the tale is this gripping, why resist the moral outrage?&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ansen&quot;/&gt;

{{quote box|width=35%|align=left|quote=&quot;J. Michael Straczynski's disjointed script manages to ring false at almost every significant turn&amp;nbsp;... and Clint Eastwood's ponderous direction—a disheartening departure from his sure touch in {{'}}''Letters From Iwo Jima''{{'}} and {{'}}''The Bridges of Madison County''{{'}}—magnifies the flaws.&quot;|source=—[[Joe Morgenstern]], writing for ''[[The Wall Street Journal]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB122479914867964509.html | title='Changeling,' Impostor Tale, Itself Feels False | author=[[Joe Morgenstern]] | work=[[The Wall Street Journal]] | date=October 24, 2008 | accessdate=April 4, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
Séguret said the film presented a solid recreation of the era, but that Eastwood did not seem inspired by the challenge. Séguret noted that Eastwood kept the embers of the story alight, but that it seldom burst into flames. He likened the experience to being in a luxury car: comfortable yet boring.&lt;ref name=&quot;liberation&quot;/&gt; Denby and Ansen commented that Eastwood left the worst atrocities to audiences' imaginations. Ansen said this was because Eastwood was less interested in the lurid aspects of the case.&lt;ref name=&quot;ansen&quot;/&gt; McCarthy praised the thoughtful, unsensationalized treatment,&lt;ref name=&quot;mccarthy&quot;/&gt; while Denby cited problems with the austere approach, saying it left the film &quot;both impressive and monotonous&quot;. He said Eastwood was presented with the problem of not wanting to exploit the &quot;gruesome&quot; material because this would contrast poorly with the delicate emotions of a woman's longing for her missing son. Denby said Eastwood and Straczynski should have explored more deeply the story's perverse aspects. Instead, he said, the narrative methodically settled the emotional and dramatic issues—&quot;reverently chronicling Christine's apotheosis&quot;—before &quot;[ambling] on for another forty minutes&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;denby&quot;/&gt; Ansen said the classical approach lifted the story to another level, and that it embraced horror film conventions only in the process of transcending them.&lt;ref name=&quot;ansen&quot;/&gt; McCarthy said ''Changeling'' was one of Eastwood's most vividly realized films, noting Stern's cinematography, the set and costume design, and CGI landscapes that merged seamlessly with location shots.&lt;ref name=&quot;mccarthy&quot;/&gt; Dargis was not impressed by the production design; she cited the loss of Eastwood's regular collaborator [[Henry Bumstead]]—who died in 2006—as a factor in ''Changeling''{{'}}s &quot;overly pristine&quot; look.&lt;ref name=&quot;dargis&quot;/&gt;

Damon Wise of ''[[Empire (magazine)|Empire]]'' called ''Changeling'' &quot;flawless&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.empireonline.com/features/cannes2008/Post.asp?id=145|title=Clint Eastwood's Changeling Is The Best Of The Festival So Far|author=Damon Wise|journal=[[Empire (magazine)|Empire]]|date=May 20, 2008|accessdate=May 21, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and McCarthy said it was &quot;emotionally powerful and stylistically sure-handed&quot;. He stated that ''Changeling'' was a more complex and wide-ranging work than Eastwood's ''Mystic River'', saying the characters and social commentary were brought into the story with an &quot;almost breathtaking deliberation&quot;. He said that as &quot;a sorrowful critique of the city's political culture&quot;, ''Changeling'' sat in the company of films such as ''Chinatown'' and ''[[L.A. Confidential (film)|L.A. Confidential]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;mccarthy&quot;/&gt; Honeycutt said the film added a &quot;forgotten chapter to the L.A. noir&quot; of those films, and that Eastwood's melodic score contributed to an evocation of a city and a period &quot;undergoing galvanic changes&quot;. Honeycutt said, &quot;[the] small-town feel to the street and sets&amp;nbsp;... captures a society resistant to seeing what is really going on&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;honeycutt&quot;/&gt; Séguret said that while ''Changeling'' had few defects, it was mystifying that other critics had such effusive praise for it.&lt;ref name=&quot;liberation&quot;/&gt; Denby said it was beautifully made, but that it shared the chief fault of other &quot;righteously indignant&quot; films in congratulating the audience for feeling contempt for the &quot;long-discredited&quot; attitudes depicted.&lt;ref name=&quot;denby&quot;/&gt; Ansen concluded that the story was told in such a sure manner that only a hardened cynic would be left unmoved by the &quot;haunting, sorrowful saga&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ansen&quot;/&gt;

===Awards and honors===
In addition to the following list of awards and nominations, the [[National Board of Review of Motion Pictures]] named ''Changeling'' one of the 10 best films of 2008,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.variety.com/VR1117996815.html|title=NBR names 'Slumdog' best of year|author=Staff|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=December 4, 2008|accessdate=December 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; as did the [[International Press Academy]], which presents the annual [[Satellite Award]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Gregg Kilday|title=Int'l Press Academy announces nominations|journal=[[The Hollywood Reporter]]|date=November 30, 2008|url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/intl-press-academy-announces-nominations-123650|accessdate=December 3, 2008}} (registration required for online access)&lt;/ref&gt; Several critics included the film on their lists of the top 10 best films of 2008. [[Anthony Lane]] of ''[[The New Yorker]]'' named it second best, ''[[Empire (magazine)|Empire]]'' magazine named it fourth best, and Rene Rodriguez of ''[[The Miami Herald]]'' named it joint fourth best with Eastwood's ''[[Gran Torino (film)|Gran Torino]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://apps.metacritic.com/film/awards/2008/toptens.shtml|title=Metacritic: 2008 Film Critic Top Ten Lists|work=[[Metacritic]]|publisher=CNET Networks, Inc|accessdate=February 4, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Japanese film critic [[Shigehiko Hasumi]] listed the film as one of the best films of 2000-2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Aoyama |first1=Shinji |authorlink1=Shinji Aoyama |last2=Hasumi |first2=Shigehiko |authorlink2=Shigehiko Hasumi |last3=Kurosawa |first3=Kiyoshi |authorlink3=Kiyoshi Kurosawa |title=Eiga Nagabanashi |year=2011 |language=Japanese |publisher=Little More |page=271 |isbn=978-4-89815-313-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|- 
! Award
! Category
! Nominee
! Result
|-
|rowspan=3|[[81st Academy Awards]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1118000452.html|title=2009 Oscar winners list|author=Staff|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=February 22, 2009|accessdate=February 23, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|[[Academy Award for Best Actress|Best Actress in a Leading Role]]
|Angelina Jolie
|{{nom}}
|-
|[[Academy Award for Best Art Direction|Best Art Direction]]
|James Murakami, Gary Fettis
|{{nom}}
|-
|[[Academy Award for Best Cinematography|Best Cinematography]]
|Tom Stern
|{{nom}}
|-
|2008 [[African American Film Critics Association]] Awards&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aafca.org/index2.php?option=com_content&amp;do_pdf=1&amp;id=64|format=PDF|title=AAFCA Top 10 - 2008|work=aafca.com|publisher=[[African-American Film Critics Association]]|date=December 30, 2008|accessdate=March 3, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Best Actress
|Angelina Jolie
|{{won}}
|-
|2009 [[Casting Society of America|Artios Award Nominations for Outstanding Achievement in Casting]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last = Kilday|first = Gregg|title = Artios nominees unveiled|work = [[Hollywood Reporter]]| date = September 17, 2009|url = http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/artios-nominees-unveiled-89012|accessdate = September 18, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last = Lehman|first = Dan|title = Casting Directors Feted at Artios Awards|work = [[Backstage (magazine)|Backstage]]| date = November 3, 2009|url = http://www.backstage.com/bso/content_display/news-and-features/e3i4eef19a7bf70315db6f2aad35a0321df|accessdate = December 18, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Big Budget Feature – Drama 
|Ellen Chenoweth
|{{nom}}
|-
|[[Art Directors Guild Awards 2008|2008 Art Directors Guild Awards]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117998295.html|title=Art Directors Guild unveils nominees 'Button,' 'Doubt,' 'Torino' among contenders|author=Justin Kroll|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=January 9, 2009|accessdate=January 9, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Excellence in Production Design – Period Film
|James Murakami
|{{nom}}
|-
|rowspan=8|[[62nd British Academy Film Awards]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Film Winners in 2009|work=bafta.org|publisher=[[British Academy of Film and Television Arts]]|url=http://www.bafta.org/awards/film/film-nominations-in-2009,657,BA.html|accessdate=February 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|[[BAFTA Award for Best Actress in a Leading Role|Best Actress in a Leading Role]]
|Angelina Jolie
|{{nom}}
|-
|[[BAFTA Award for Best Cinematography|Best Cinematography]]
|Tom Stern
|{{nom}}
|-
|[[BAFTA Award for Best Costume Design|Best Costume Design]]
|Deborah Hopper
|{{nom}}
|-
|[[BAFTA Award for Best Direction|Best Direction]]
|Clint Eastwood
|{{nom}}
|-
|[[BAFTA Award for Best Editing|Best Editing]]
|Joel Cox, Gary D. Roach
|{{nom}}
|-
|[[BAFTA Award for Best Screenplay|Best Screenplay]]
|J. Michael Straczynski
|{{nom}}
|-
|[[BAFTA Award for Best Production Design|Best Production Design]]
|James Murakami, Gary Fettis
|{{nom}}
|-
|[[BAFTA Award for Best Sound|Best Sound]]
|Walt Martin, Alan Robert Murray, John Reitz, Gregg Rudloff
|{{nom}}
|-
|2008 [[Chicago Film Critics Association]] Awards&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chicagofilmcritics.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=62&amp;Itemid=60 |title=Chicago Film Critics Awards - 2008 |work=chicagofilmcritics.org |publisher=[[Chicago Film Critics Association]] |accessdate=January 16, 2009 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100224070822/http://www.chicagofilmcritics.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=62&amp;Itemid=60 |archivedate=February 24, 2010 |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|[[Chicago Film Critics Association Award for Best Actress|Best Actress]]
|Angelina Jolie
|{{nom}}
|-
|60th [[Christopher Award]]s&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Christopher Award Winners Found Inspiration Around the Globe and Throughout History|work=christophers.org|publisher=[[Christopher Award]]s|url=http://www.christophers.org/Page.aspx?pid=956|date=April 14, 2009|accessdate=April 18, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Feature Films
|
|{{won}}
|-
|[[Costume Designers Guild Awards 2008|2008 Costume Designers Guild Awards]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117998450.html|title=Costume designers unveil nominees|author=Andrew Stewart|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=January 13, 2009|accessdate=January 16, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Excellence in Costume Design – Period Film
|Deborah Hopper
|{{nom}}
|-
|rowspan=3|[[14th Critics' Choice Awards]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.variety.com/VR1117997072.html|title=Broadcast critics favor 'Milk,' 'Button'|author=Dade Hayes|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=December 9, 2008|accessdate=December 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Best Actress
|Angelina Jolie
|{{nom}}
|-
|Best Film
|
|{{nom}}
|-
|Best Score
|Clint Eastwood
|{{nom}}
|-
|[[Empire Awards 2009|2009 Empire Awards]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bauermedia.co.uk/Press-Office/News/Jameson-Empire-Awards-2009---Nominations/ |title=Jameson Empire Awards 2009 - Nominations |work=bauermedia.co.uk |publisher=[[Bauer Media Group]] |accessdate=April 3, 2009 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090508031015/http://www.bauermedia.co.uk/Press-Office/News/Jameson-Empire-Awards-2009---Nominations |archivedate=May 8, 2009 |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|[[Empire Awards 2009#Best Actress|Best Actress]]
|Angelina Jolie
|{{nom}}
|-
|rowspan=2|[[66th Golden Globe Awards]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.variety.com/VR1117997209.html|title=Golden Globe nominations list|author=Staff|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=December 11, 2008|accessdate=December 11, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|[[Golden Globe Award for Best Actress – Motion Picture Drama|Best Actress – Motion Picture Drama]]
|Angelina Jolie
|{{nom}}
|-
|[[Golden Globe Award for Best Original Score|Best Original Score]]
|Eastwood
|{{nom}}
|-
|[[The 6th Annual Irish Film &amp; Television Awards 2009|6th Irish Film and Television Academy Awards]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ifta.ie/winners2009/index.htm|title=Winners of the 6th Annual Irish Film &amp; Television Awards|work=ifta.ie|publisher=[[Irish Film and Television Awards]]|accessdate=March 14, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Best International Actress
|Angelina Jolie
|{{nom}}
|-
|[[Japan Academy Prize (film)|2009 Japan Academy Prize]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last = Young|first = Irene|title = 2009 Japanese Academy Award Nominations|work = Alt Film Guide| date = December 23, 2009|url = http://www.altfg.com/blog/awards/japanese-academy-award-nominations-2009-894/|accessdate = December 24, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title = 33rd Japan Academy Awards: Results!|work = Wildgrounds: Treasures of Asian Cinema| date = March 5, 2010|url = http://wildgrounds.com/index.php/2010/03/05/33rd-japan-academy-awards-results/|accessdate = March 5, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|[[Japan Academy Prize for Outstanding Foreign Language Film]]
|
|{{nom}}
|-
|rowspan=2|2008 [[London Film Critics' Circle]] Awards&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.variety.com/VR1117997595.html|title='Slumdog' tops with London critics|author=Archie Thomas|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=December 18, 2008|accessdate=December 18, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Actress of the Year
|Angelina Jolie
|{{nom}}
|-
|Director of the Year
|Clint Eastwood
|{{nom}}
|-
|2009 [[:nl:Rembrandt Award|Rembrandt Award]]s&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.brabantsdagblad.nl/algemeen/kunst/film/4630875/Filmwereld-bijeen-voor-Rembrandt-Awards.ece|title=Filmwereld bijeen voor Rembrandt Awards|author=Staff|work=[[:nl:Brabants Dagblad|Brabants Dagblad]]|publisher=[[:nl:Wegener (media)|Wegener NieuwsMedia]]|date=March 9, 2009|accessdate=March 14, 2009|language=Dutch}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Best International Actress
|Angelina Jolie
|{{nom}}
|-
|rowspan=2|[[Satellite Awards 2008|2008 Satellite Awards]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pressacademy.com/satawards/awards2008.shtml |title=2008 13th Annual Satellite Awards |work=pressacademy.com |publisher=[[International Press Academy]] |accessdate=January 16, 2009 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081202035312/http://www.pressacademy.com/satawards/awards2008.shtml |archivedate=December 2, 2008 |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|[[Satellite Award for Best Actress – Motion Picture Drama|Best Actress – Motion Picture Drama]]
|Angelina Jolie
|{{won}}
|-
|[[Satellite Award for Best Cinematography|Best Cinematography]]
|Tom Stern
|{{nom}}
|-
|rowspan=6|35th [[Saturn Award]]s&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.saturnawards.org/nominations.html |title=Nominations for the 35th Annual Saturn Awards |work=saturnawards.org |publisher=[[Saturn Award|Academy of Science Fiction, Fantasy &amp; Horror Films]] |accessdate=March 10, 2009 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/65olbBrXC?url=http://www.saturnawards.org/nominations.html |archivedate=February 29, 2012 |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.saturnawards.org/index.html |title=The Winners of the 35th Annual Saturn Awards |work=saturnawards.org |publisher=[[Saturn Award|Academy of Science Fiction, Fantasy &amp; Horror Films]] |accessdate=June 25, 2009 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080509062056/http://www.saturnawards.org/index.html |archivedate=May 9, 2008 |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Best Action/Adventure/Thriller Film
|
|{{nom}}
|-
|Best Actress
|Angelina Jolie
|{{won}}
|-
|Best Costumes
|Deborah Hopper
|{{nom}}
|-
|Best Director
|Clint Eastwood
|{{nom}}
|-
|Best Music
|Clint Eastwood
|{{nom}}
|-
|Best Writing
|J. Michael Straczynski
|{{nom}}
|-
|[[15th Screen Actors Guild Awards]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.variety.com/VR1117997589.html|title='Doubt' leads SAG awards race|author=Dave McNary|journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=December 18, 2008|accessdate=December 18, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|[[Screen Actors Guild Award for Outstanding Performance by a Female Actor in a Leading Role|Best Actress in a Leading Role – Motion Picture]]
|Angelina Jolie
|{{nom}}
|-
|rowspan=2|2008 [[Visual Effects Society#VES Awards|Visual Effects Society Awards]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/awards/2009/02/the-curious-cas.html|title=Benjamin Button' and 'Dark Knight' win VES Awards|author=Susan King|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=February 21, 2009|accessdate=February 23, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Outstanding Matte Paintings in a Feature Motion Picture
|Romain Bayle, Abel Milanes, Allan Lee, Debora Dunphy
|{{won}}
|-
|Outstanding Supporting Visual Effects in a Motion Picture
|Michael Owens, Geoffrey Hancock, Jinnie Pak, Dennis Hoffman
|{{won}}
|-
|rowspan=2|2008 [[Women Film Critics Circle|Women Film Critics' Circle Awards]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.upi.com/Entertainment_News/2008/12/15/UPI_NewsTrack_Entertainment_News/UPI-66551229367600/|author=Staff|title=WFCC: 'Changeling' best movie about women|work=[[United Press International]]|date=December 15, 2008|accessdate=December 22, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|[[Adrienne Shelly Award]]
|
|{{won}}
|-
|Best Film About Women
|
|{{won}}
|}

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=&quot;Note&quot;}}

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Commons category|Changeling (2008 film)|Changeling}}
* {{Official website|http://www.changelingmovie.net}}
* {{IMDb title|0824747|Changeling}}
* {{Rotten-tomatoes|1191742_changeling|title=Changeling}}
* {{AllMovie title|391262|Changeling}}
* [http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/thedailymirror/changeling/index.html Original ''Los Angeles Times'' stories and photos on Walter Collins' disappearance]

{{Clint Eastwood}}
{{J. Michael Straczynski}}
{{Brian Grazer}}
{{featured article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Changeling}}
[[Category:2008 films]]
[[Category:2000s drama films]]
[[Category:2000s thriller films]]
[[Category:American drama films]]
[[Category:American films]]
[[Category:American thriller drama films]]
[[Category:Crime films based on actual events]]
[[Category:Drama films based on actual events]]
[[Category:English-language films]]
[[Category:Films about abduction]]
[[Category:Films about capital punishment]]
[[Category:Films about children]]
[[Category:Films about death]]
[[Category:Films about missing people]]
[[Category:Films about pedophilia]]
[[Category:Films about child sexual abuse]]
[[Category:Films directed by Clint Eastwood]]
[[Category:Films produced by Clint Eastwood]]
[[Category:Films set in 1928]]
[[Category:Films set in 1935]]
[[Category:Films set in Los Angeles]]
[[Category:Films set in psychiatric hospitals]]
[[Category:Films produced by Brian Grazer]]
[[Category:Imagine Entertainment films]]
[[Category:Malpaso Productions films]]
[[Category:Relativity Media films]]
[[Category:Universal Pictures films]]
[[Category:Works by J. Michael Straczynski]]
[[Category:Film scores by Clint Eastwood]]</text>
      <sha1>e1ibtdgmtx2d5re5e1145vbi9it4q1n</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
