<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Double Seven Day scuffle</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>12748526</id>
    <revision>
      <id>698646020</id>
      <parentid>697129287</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-01-07T11:20:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SSTflyer</username>
        <id>25530780</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>replace deprecated reflist columns, replaced: {{Reflist|2}} → {{Reflist|30em}} using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14731">[[File:Arnett nose.jpg|thumb|The aftermath of the altercation. [[David Halberstam]] ''(center, wearing sunglasses)'' repels plainclothes policemen after their attack on [[Peter Arnett]] ''(far left)''. |alt=A crowded and narrow street with a lot of people in the vicinity. A tall, Caucasian man with brown hair and sunglasses stands in front of a smaller Asian man with black hair, shielding a shorter man in light shirt with a bloodied face. The smaller Asian man puts an open palm in the air to acknowledge the taller man. A steel-helmeted policeman is in the foreground and others in white caps are in the background.]]
The '''Double Seven Day scuffle''' was a physical altercation on July 7 (7/7), 1963, in [[Saigon]], [[South Vietnam]]. The secret police of [[Ngô Đình Nhu]]&amp;mdash;the brother of [[President of South Vietnam|President]] [[Ngô Đình Diệm]]&amp;mdash;attacked a group of journalists from the United States who were covering protests held by [[Buddhism in Vietnam|Buddhists]] on the ninth anniversary of Diệm's rise to power. [[Peter Arnett]] of the [[Associated Press]] (AP) was punched on the nose, and the quarrel quickly ended after [[David Halberstam]] of ''[[The New York Times]]'', being  much taller than Nhu's men, counterattacked and caused the secret police to retreat. Arnett and his colleague, the [[Pulitzer Prize]]-winning journalist and photographer [[Malcolm Browne]], were later accosted by police at their office and taken away for questioning on suspicion of attacking police officers.

After their release, the journalists went to the [[Embassy of the United States, Saigon|US embassy in Saigon]] to complain about their treatment at the hands of Diệm's officials and asked for US government protection. Their appeals were dismissed, as was a direct appeal to the [[White House]]. Through the efforts of [[United States Ambassador to South Vietnam|US Ambassador]] [[Frederick Nolting]], the assault charges laid against the journalists were subsequently dropped. Vietnamese Buddhists reacted to the incident by contending that Diệm's men were planning to assassinate monks, while [[Madame Nhu]] repeated earlier claims that the US government had been trying to overthrow her brother-in-law.

Browne took photographs of Arnett's bloodied face, which were published in newspapers worldwide. This drew further negative attention to the behaviour of the Diệm régime amidst the backdrop of the [[Buddhist crisis]].

==Background==
{{Main|Huế Phật Đản shootings}}
[[File:Ngo_Dinh_Diem_-_Thumbnail_-_ARC_542189.png|thumb|right|Ngo Dinh Diem|alt=A portrait of a middle-aged man, looking to the left in a half-portrait/profile. He has chubby cheeks, parts his hair to the side and wears a suit and tie.]]
The incident occurred during a period of popular unrest by the Buddhist majority against the Roman Catholic rule of Diệm. Buddhist discontent had grown since the [[Huế Phật Đản shootings]] on May 8, 1963.&lt;ref name=&quot;j247&quot;&gt;Jones, p. 247.&lt;/ref&gt; The government decided to selectively invoke a law, prohibiting the display of religious flags, by banning the use of the [[Buddhist flag]] on [[Vesak]], the birthday of [[Gautama Buddha]].&lt;ref name=&quot;j247&quot;/&gt; One week earlier, the [[Holy See|Vatican]] flag had been flown at a celebration for Archbishop [[Ngô Đình Thục]], Diệm's brother. The Buddhists defied the ban, flying their flags on Vesak and holding a demonstration, which was ended with government gunfire and eight deaths.&lt;ref name=&quot;j247&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jacobs, pp. 141&amp;ndash;143.&lt;/ref&gt; The killings sparked nationwide protests by South Vietnam's Buddhist majority against the policies of Diệm's regime. The Buddhists demanded that Diệm give them religious equality, but with their demands unfulfilled, the protests increased in magnitude.&lt;ref&gt;Jones, pp. 248&amp;ndash;262.&lt;/ref&gt; The most notable of these was the self-immolation of [[Thích Quảng Đức]] on June 11, which was iconically photographed by the media and became a negative symbol of the Diệm régime.&lt;ref name = &quot;h157&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;j285&quot;/&gt;

Known as Double Seven Day, July 7 was the ninth anniversary of Diệm's 1954 ascension to Prime Minister of the [[State of Vietnam]].&lt;ref name=&quot;j286&quot;/&gt; In October 1955, following a [[State of Vietnam referendum, 1955|fraudulent referendum]], Diệm established the Republic of Vietnam, generally known as [[South Vietnam]], and declared himself [[Leaders of South Vietnam|President]].&lt;ref&gt;Jacobs, p. 95.&lt;/ref&gt; The night of July 6, 1963, had started in a festive mood as Diệm awarded decorations to military officers at a ceremony.&lt;ref name=&quot;h157&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;j285&quot;/&gt; Among those in the audience were Generals [[Trần Văn Đôn]] and [[Dương Văn Minh]], the Chief of Staff of the [[Army of the Republic of Vietnam]] and the Presidential Military Advisor, respectively.&lt;ref&gt;Hammer, p. 147.&lt;/ref&gt; They had returned from observing [[SEATO]] military exercises in [[Thailand]],&lt;ref name=&quot;j286&quot;&gt;Jones, p. 286.&lt;/ref&gt; where they had been informed about the regional disquiet over Diem's policies towards the Buddhists.&lt;ref name=&quot;j247&quot;/&gt;

==Incident==
American pressmen had been alerted to an upcoming Buddhist demonstration to coincide with Double Seven Day at Chanatareansey Pagoda in the north of Saigon.&lt;ref name=&quot;j286&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;l219&quot;/&gt; The group, which included Arnett, Browne, [[David Halberstam]], [[Neil Sheehan]] of ''[[United Press International]]'', and [[CBS]]'s [[Peter Kalischer]] waited outside the building with their equipment. After an hour-long religious ceremony, the Buddhists filed out of the [[pagoda]] into a narrow alley along a side street, where they were blocked and ordered to stop by plain-clothed policemen. The Buddhists did not resist, but Arnett and Browne began taking photos of the confrontation. The police, who were loyal to [[Ngô Đình Nhu]],&lt;ref name=&quot;l219&quot;&gt;Langguth, p. 219.&lt;/ref&gt; thereupon punched Arnett in the nose, knocked him to the ground, kicked him with their pointed-toe shoes, and broke his camera.&lt;ref&gt;Prochnau, p. 328.&lt;/ref&gt; Halberstam, who won a Pulitzer Prize for his coverage of the Buddhist crisis, was a tall man, standing around {{convert|20|cm|0|in}} taller than the average Vietnamese policeman.&lt;ref name=&quot;j285&quot;/&gt; He waded into the fracas swinging his arms, reportedly saying &quot;Get back, get back, you sons of bitches, or I'll beat the shit out of you!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;j285&quot;/&gt; Nhu's men ran away without waiting for a Vietnamese translation,&lt;ref name=&quot;l219&quot;/&gt; but not before Browne had clambered up a power pole and taken photos of Arnett's bloodied face. The police smashed Browne's camera, but his [[photographic film]] survived the impact. The other journalists were jostled and rocks were thrown at them. Photos of Arnett's bloodied face were circulated in US newspapers and caused further ill-feeling towards Diệm's regime, with the images of the burning Thích Quảng Đức on the front pages still fresh in the minds of the public.&lt;ref name=&quot;h157&quot;&gt;Hammer, p. 157.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;j285&quot;&gt;Jones, p. 285.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:LBJ nhu.jpg|right|thumb|Ngô Đình Nhu ''(pictured right)'' controlled South Vietnam's secret police.|alt=Tall Caucasian man standing in profile at left in a white suit and tie shakes hands with a smaller black-haired Asian man in a white shirt, dark suit and tie.]]
Diệm's address on Double Seven Day worsened the mood of Vietnamese society. He stated that the &quot;problems raised by the [[General Association of Buddhists]] have just been settled.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;h78&quot;/&gt; He reinforced perceptions that he was out of touch by attributing any lingering problems to the &quot;underground intervention of international red agents and Communist fellow travelers who in collusion with fascist ideologues disguised as democrats were surreptitiously seeking to revive and rekindle disunity at home while arousing public opinions against us abroad&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;h78&quot;/&gt; The remark about fascists was seen as a reference to the conspiratorial [[Đại Việt Quốc dân đảng]] who had long been enemies of Diem, but his address attacked all those who had criticised him in the past. He no longer trusted anyone outside his family and considered himself to be a martyr.&lt;!--Why did he consider himself a martyr?--&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;j285&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;h78&quot;&gt;Hammer, pp. 157&amp;ndash;158.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reaction==
The indignant reporters stridently accused the Diệm regime of causing the altercation,&lt;ref name=&quot;j285&quot;/&gt; whereas the police claimed that the journalists threw the first punch.&lt;ref name=&quot;l219&quot;/&gt; Embassy official [[John Mecklin]] noted that even Diem's media officials were privately skeptical about the veracity of the testimony of Nhu's men.&lt;ref name=&quot;p329&quot;/&gt; In a heated meeting at the embassy, the press corps demanded that [[William Trueheart]], the acting [[United States Ambassador to South Vietnam|US Ambassador to South Vietnam]] in the absence of the vacationing [[Frederick Nolting]], deliver a formal protest to Diệm on behalf of the American government. Trueheart angered them by refusing to do so and blaming both sides for the confrontation.&lt;ref name=&quot;j285&quot;/&gt; In his report to [[White House|Washington]], Trueheart asserted that the uniformed policemen had tacitly helped their plainclothed counterparts, but he also had &quot;no doubt that [the] reporters, at least once [the] fracas had started, acted in [a] belligerent manner towards [the] police&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;j285&quot;/&gt; Trueheart contended that since the journalists had a long history of bad blood with the Diem regime, their word could not be taken over that of the Vietnamese police.&lt;ref name=&quot;l219&quot;/&gt;

Since the embassy was unwilling to provide government protection against police aggression, the journalists appealed directly to the White House.&lt;ref name=&quot;j285&quot;/&gt; Browne, Halberstam, Sheehan and Kalischer wrote a letter to US President [[John F. Kennedy]], asserting that the regime had begun a full-scale campaign of &quot;open physical intimidation to prevent the covering of news which we feel Americans have a right to know&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;h157&quot;/&gt;
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Hammo1.jpg|thumb|[[David Halberstam]], [[Malcolm Browne]], and [[Neil Sheehan]] {{Deletable image-caption|date=May 2012}}]] --&gt;
The protests did not garner any Presidential sympathy for the journalists, but instead resulted in trouble from their media employers. UPI's Tokyo office criticised Sheehan for trying to &quot;make Unipress policy&quot; on his own when &quot;Unipress must be neutral, neither pro-Diem, pro-Communist or pro-anybody else&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;p330&quot;/&gt; [[Emanuel Freedman]], the foreign editor of ''[[The New York Times]]'' reprimanded Halberstam, writing: &quot;We still feel that our correspondents should not be firing off cables to the President of the United States without authorization.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;p330&quot;/&gt;

The incident provoked reactions from both the Buddhists and the Diệm regime. A monk called on the US embassy to send a military unit from the American advisors already present in Vietnam to [[Xá Lợi Pagoda]], the main Buddhist temple in Saigon and the organisational hub of the Buddhist movement. The monk claimed that the attack on Arnett indicated that Xá Lợi's monks were targets of assassination by Nhu's men, something that Trueheart rejected, turning down the protection request.&lt;ref name=l219/&gt; Xá Lợi and other Buddhist centers across the country were [[Xá Lợi Pagoda raids|raided a month later]] by [[Army of the Republic of Vietnam Special Forces|Special Forces]] under the direct control of the Ngo family. On the part of the South Vietnamese government,  the ''de facto'' first lady [[Madame Nhu]] used her English-language mouthpiece newspaper, the ''[[Times of Vietnam]]'', to accuse the United States of supporting the [[1960 South Vietnamese coup attempt|failed coup attempt against Diem in 1960]].&lt;ref name=&quot;l219&quot;/&gt;

==Arrest and interrogation==
Later on during the day of the altercation, the police collected Browne and Arnett from the AP [[news bureau|bureau]] in Saigon and took the pair to what they described as a &quot;[[safe house]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;p329&quot;/&gt; The police interrogators said that they would be arrested but were unspecific about the charges. One charge was that of [[assault]]ing two police officers, but the interrogators hinted that more serious offences such as organising illegal demonstrations were being considered. The officers conversed among themselves in French, a language which the reporters did not speak, but Arnett thought that they mentioned the word ''[[espionage]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;p329&quot;/&gt;  After four hours of questioning, the pair were charged with assault. Browne and Arnett in turn filed charges against the police over the altercation, and demanded compensation for the damage to their photographic equipment.&lt;ref name=&quot;l219&quot;/&gt; Arnett and Browne were temporarily released in the evening, after which the whole Saigon press corps stormed the US embassy.&lt;ref name=&quot;p329&quot;&gt;Prochnau, p. 329.&lt;/ref&gt;

Browne and Arnett were called in for five hours of questioning on the following day. Arnett was accompanied by a British embassy official who, reflecting Arnett's New Zealand citizenship, provided consular assistance on behalf of [[New Zealand|Wellington]].&lt;ref name=&quot;p330&quot;&gt;Prochnau, p. 330.&lt;/ref&gt; In the end, Diem agreed to have the charges against Browne and Arnett dropped after hours of heated argument with US Ambassador [[Frederick Nolting]], who had returned from his vacation.&lt;ref name=&quot;l219&quot;/&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
*{{Cite book| title=A Death in November: America in Vietnam, 1963| authorlink=Ellen Hammer |first=Ellen J.|last=Hammer| year=1987 |publisher=E. P. Dutton|isbn=0-525-24210-4 |location=New York City}}
*{{Cite book| first=Seth |last=Jacobs| year=2006| title=Cold War Mandarin: Ngo Dinh Diem and the Origins of America's War in Vietnam, 1950&amp;ndash;1963| publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield| isbn=0-7425-4447-8|location=Lanham, Maryland}}
*{{Cite book| first=Howard |last=Jones| year=2003| title= Death of a Generation: how the assassinations of Diem and JFK prolonged the Vietnam War | publisher=Oxford University Press| isbn=0-19-505286-2|location=New York City}}
*{{Cite book| title=Our Vietnam: the war, 1954&amp;ndash;1975 | author=[[A. J. Langguth|Langguth, A. J.]] |year=2000 |publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster | isbn=0-684-81202-9 |location=New York City}}
*{{Cite book| first=William|last= Prochnau | authorlink=William Prochnau| title=Once Upon a Distant War| year=1995 |publisher=Times Books|isbn=0-8129-2633-1|location=New York City}}

{{Buddhist crisis}}

{{Featured article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Double Seven Day Scuffle}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1963]]
[[Category:Buddhist crisis]]
[[Category:History of South Vietnam]]
[[Category:1963 in Vietnam]]</text>
      <sha1>bm27ms8mej77ge3rhreppkio8290itr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
