<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ecclesiastical heraldry</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5549981</id>
    <revision>
      <id>740511405</id>
      <parentid>738296191</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-21T14:36:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JMK</username>
        <id>938515</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>change link</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="47919">[[File:Stemma di Agostino Bausa, palazzo arcivescovile di Firenze.JPG|thumb|right|Coat of arms of Cardinal [[Agostino Bausa]] in the courtyard of the archiepiscopal palace of [[Florence]]]]
'''Ecclesiastical heraldry''' refers to the use of [[heraldry]] within the Christian Church for dioceses and [[Christianity|Christian]] [[clergy]]. Initially used to mark documents, [[ecclesiology|ecclesiastical]] heraldry evolved as a system for identifying people and [[diocese]]s. It is most formalized within the [[Catholic Church]], where most [[bishop]]s, including the [[Pope]], have a personal [[coat of arms]]. Clergy in [[Anglicanism|Anglican]], [[Lutheranism|Lutheran]], [[Eastern Catholic Churches|Eastern Catholic]], and [[Eastern Christianity|Orthodox churches]] follow similar customs, as do institutions such as schools and dioceses.

Ecclesiastical heraldry differs notably from other heraldry in the use of special insignia around the [[Escutcheon (heraldry)|shield]] to indicate rank in a church or [[religious denomination|denomination]]. The most prominent of these insignia is the low crowned, wide brimmed ecclesiastical hat, commonly the Roman [[galero]]. The color and ornamentation of this hat indicate rank. [[Cardinal (Catholicism)|Cardinals]] are famous for the &quot;red hat&quot;, but other offices and other churches have distinctive hat colors, such as black for ordinary clergy and green for bishops, customarily with a number of [[tassel]]s increasing with rank.

Other insignia include the processional [[Christian cross|cross]], the [[mitre]] and the [[crosier]]. Eastern traditions favor the use of their own style of head gear and crosier, and the use of the [[Mantle (vesture)|mantle]] or cloak rather than the ecclesiastical hat. The [[motto]] and certain shapes of shields are more common in ecclesiastical heraldry, while [[supporters]] and [[crest (heraldry)|crests]] are less common. The [[papal coats of arms]] have their own heraldic customs, primarily the [[Papal Tiara]] (or mitre), the keys of [[Saint Peter]], and the [[ombrellino]] (umbrella). Pope Benedict XVI replaced the use of the Papal Tiara in his coat of arms with a mitre. He was the first pope to do so, despite the fact that [[Pope Paul VI]] was the last pope to be [[Papal coronation|crowned with the tiara]].  The arms of institutions have slightly different traditions, using the mitre and crozier more often than is found in personal arms, though there is a wide variation in uses by different churches.  The arms used by organizations are called impersonal or corporate arms.

==History==
[[File:Archbishop Stefan Insignia.png|thumb|right|120px|12th-century [[seal (device)|seal]] of [[Stefan (archbishop of Uppsala)|Stefan]] of [[Archbishop of Uppsala|Uppsala]]]]
[[File:Siegel Tempelritter (Cropped).png|thumb|right|120px|Reproduction of a medieval [[Knights Templar Seal]]]]
[[File:LutherRose.jpg|thumb|right|120px|[[Luther rose|personal seal]] of [[Martin Luther]] from 1530, now a symbol of Lutheranism]]
[[Heraldry]] developed in [[Middle Ages|medieval Europe]] from the late 11th century, originally as a system of personal badges of the warrior classes, which served, among other purposes, as identification on the battlefield. The same insignia were used on [[seal (device)|seals]] to identify documents. The earliest seals bore a likeness of the owner of the seal, with the shield and heraldic insignia included.&lt;ref&gt;Williamson, ''Debrett's Guide'', p.14.&lt;/ref&gt; Over time, the seals were reduced to just the shield.

The Church likewise identified the origin and ownership of documents and buildings with seals, which were typically a pointed oval called a vesica to distinguish from round seals in non-religious use.&lt;ref&gt;{{CathEncy | wstitle=Ecclesiastical Heraldry | short=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Edward I of England]] decreed in 1307 that all legal documents required a seal.{{sfn|Rogers|1956|p=134}} These seals initially depicted a person, but as secular seals began to depict only a shield, clergy likewise used seals with heraldic insignia.{{sfn|Boutell|Brooke-Little|1978|pp=223-224}} Personal seals of bishops and [[abbot]]s continued to be used after their deaths, gradually becoming an impersonal seal.{{sfn|Rogers|1956|p=134}} Clergy tended to replace military devices with clerical devices. The shield was retained, but ecclesiastical hats often replaced helmets and [[coronet]]s. In some religious arms a [[Human skull|skull]] replaces the helmet.&lt;ref&gt;Neubecker, ''Heraldry'', p.237.&lt;/ref&gt;

The structure of Church heraldry developed significantly in the 17th century when a system for ecclesiastical hats attributed to Pierre Palliot came into use.&lt;ref&gt;Selvester, [http://www.guyselvester.50megs.com/custom4.html Aspects of Heraldry].&lt;/ref&gt; The full system of emblems around the shield was regulated in the Catholic Church by the letter of [[Pope Pius X]] ''Inter multiplices curas'' of February 21, 1905, while the composition of the shield itself was regulated through the Heraldry Commission of the [[Roman Curia]] until this office was abolished by [[Pope John XXIII]] in 1960.&lt;ref&gt;Noonan, ''The Church Visible'', p.188.&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[Annuario Pontificio]]'' ceased publishing the arms of Cardinals and previous Popes after 1969. International custom and national law govern limited aspects of Church heraldry, but shield composition is now largely guided by expert advice. Archbishop [[Bruno Heim]], a noted ecclesiastical [[armory (heraldry)|armorist]] (designer of arms), said

{{quote|Ecclesiastical heraldry is not determined by heraldic considerations alone, but also by [[doctrine|doctrinal]], [[liturgy|liturgical]] and [[canon law|canonical]] factors. It not only produces arms denoting members of the ecclesiastical state but shows the rank of the bearer.... In the eyes of the Church it is sufficient to determine who has a right to bear an ecclesiastical coat of arms and under what conditions the different insignia are acquired or lost... The design of [[prelate|prelatial]] arms is often a disastrous defiance of the rules of heraldry, if only as a breach of good taste.{{sfn|Heim|1978|pp=43-45}}}}

A similar system for the [[Church of England]] was approved in 1976.{{sfn|Boutell|Brooke-Little|1978|pp=225-226}} The traditions of [[Eastern Christianity|Eastern Christian]] heraldry have less developed regulation. Eastern secular coats of arms often display a shield before a mantle topped with a crown. Eastern clergy often display coats of arms according to this style, replacing the crown with an appropriate hat drawn from liturgical use.

Marking documents is the most common use of arms in the Church today. A Roman Catholic bishop's coat of arms was formerly painted on miniature wine barrels and presented during the ordination ceremony.{{sfn|Rogers|1956|p=133}}{{sfn|Heim|1978|p=115}} Cardinals may place their coat of arms outside the church of their title in Rome.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fiu.edu/~mirandas/instruction69.htm &quot;Instruction&quot;], 1969, n.28–29.&lt;/ref&gt; Impersonal arms are often used as the banner of a school or religious community.

==Shield==
[[File:COAabbess.png|thumb|right|100px|Arms of an abbess displayed on a [[lozenge (heraldry)|lozenge]] with [[crosier]] turned left]]
The [[Escutcheon (heraldry)|shield]] is the normal device for displaying a coat of arms. Clergy have used less-military shapes such as the oval [[cartouche]], but the shield has always been a clerical option. Clergy in [[Italy]] often use a shield shaped like a horse's face-armor. Clergy in [[South Africa]] sometimes follow the national style using a [[Nguni shield]].&lt;ref&gt;von Volborth, ''Heraldry of the World'', p.176.; See the [[coat of arms of Botswana]], of [http://www.civicheraldry.com/page/11666 Guateng], or the [http://www.kwazulunatal.gov.za/ KwaZulu-Natal Provincial Government].&lt;/ref&gt; Women traditionally display their coats of arms on a diamond-shaped [[lozenge (heraldry)|lozenge]]; [[abbess]]es follow this tradition or use the cartouche.

===Personal design===
In the Roman Catholic Church, unless a new bishop has a family coat of arms, he typically adopts within his shield symbols that indicate his interests or past service. Devotion to a particular [[saint]] is represented by symbols established in [[iconography]] and heraldic tradition. In the Church of England, new bishops typically choose a coat that looks entirely non-clerical, not least because their descendants may seek reassignment of the arms, and few of them are likely to be clerics.

The first rule of heraldry is the [[rule of tincture]]: &quot;Colour must not appear upon colour, nor metal upon metal.&quot;{{sfn|Heim|1978|p=9}} The heraldic metals are [[or (heraldry)|gold]] and [[argent|silver]], usually represented as yellow and white, while red, green, blue, purple and black normally comprise the colors. Heraldic bearings are intended for recognition at a distance (in battle), and a contrast of light metal against dark color is desirable. The same principle can be seen in the choice of colors for most [[vehicle registration plate|license plates]].

This rule of tincture is often broken in clerical arms: the flag and arms of [[Vatican City]] notably have yellow (gold) and white (silver) placed together. In [[Byzantine Rite|Byzantine]] tradition, colors have a mystical interpretation. Because gold and silver express sublimity and solemnity, combinations of the two are often used regardless of the rule of tincture.{{sfn|Heim|1978|p=102}}

===Marshalling===
[[File:COAanglicanmarried.gif|thumb|left|120px|Arms of an Anglican bishop marshalled with those of the diocese (left shield) and spouse (right shield)]]
If a bishop is a diocesan bishop, it is customary for him to combine his arms with the arms of the diocese following normal heraldic rules.{{sfn|Rogers|1956|p=134}} This combining is termed [[Heraldry#Marshalling|marshalling]], and is normally accomplished by [[impalement (heraldry)|impalement]], placing the arms of the diocese to the viewer's left (''dexter'' in heraldry) and the personal arms to the viewer's right. The arms of [[Thomas Arundel]] are found impaled with those of the [[See of Canterbury]] in a document from 1411.&lt;ref&gt;Woodcock, ''The Oxford Guide to Heraldry'', p.119.&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Germany]] and [[Switzerland]], [[quartering (heraldry)|quartering]] is the norm rather than impalement. [[Guy Selvester]], an American ecclesiastical heraldist, says if arms are not designed with care, marshalling can lead to &quot;busy&quot;, crowded shields. Crowding can be reduced by placing a smaller shield overlapping the larger shield, known as an [[inescutcheon]] or an escutcheon surtout. In the arms of [[Heinrich Mussinghoff]], [[Bishop of Aachen]], the personal arms are placed in front of the diocesan arms, but the opposite arrangement is found in front on the arms of [[Paul Gregory Bootkoski]], Bishop of [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Metuchen|Metuchen]].&lt;ref&gt;See arms of [[:File:Heinrich Mussinghoff Aachen CoA.svg|Heinrich Mussinghoff]] and [http://www.diometuchen.org/mainweb/coat.htm Paul Bootkoski]&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Heim|1978|pp=56-57}} [[Cardinal (Catholicism)|Cardinals]] sometimes combine their personal arms with the arms of the Pope who named them a cardinal. As [[Prefecture of the Pontifical Household|Prefect of the Pontifical Household]], Jacques Martin impaled his personal arms with those of three successive pontiffs.&lt;ref&gt;Martin, ''Heraldry in the Vatican'', p.32.&lt;/ref&gt; A married Church of England bishop combines his arms with those of his wife and the diocese on two separate shields placed ''accollé'', or side-by-side.&lt;ref&gt;Woodcock, ''Oxford Guide to Heraldry'', p.119.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Roman Catholicism in Great Britain|Roman Catholic bishops in England]] historically used only their personal arms, as dioceses established by the [[Holy See|See of Rome]] are not part of the official state [[Church of England]] and cannot be recognized in law,&lt;ref&gt;Fox-Davies, ''A Complete Guide to Heraldry'', p.465&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Rogers|1956|p=133}} though in Scotland the legal situation has been different and many Roman Catholic dioceses have arms. If a [[suffragan bishop|suffragan]] or [[auxiliary bishop]] has a personal coat of arms, he does not combine it with the arms of the diocese he serves.&lt;ref&gt;{{CathEncy | wstitle=Ecclesiastical Heraldry | short=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Around the shield==
[[File:Coat of arms of Arthur Richard Dillon.svg|thumb|right|Arms of eighteenth-century [[Archbishop]] [[Arthur-Richard Dillon]] with a green [[galero]] (hat) and [[Patriarchal cross]] above the shield, and the [[Order of the Holy Spirit]] below, and showing fifteen tassels before ten became standard]]
The shield is the core of heraldry, but other elements are placed above, below, and around the shield, and are usually collectively called external ornaments.&lt;ref&gt;{{CathEncy | wstitle=Ecclesiastical Heraldry | short=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; The entire composition is called the achievement of arms or the armorial bearings. Some of these accessories are unique to Church armory or differ notably from those which normally accompany a shield.

===Ecclesiastical hat===
The ecclesiastical hat is a distinctive part of the achievement of arms of a Roman Catholic cleric. This hat, called a [[galero]] (or gallero), was originally a pilgrim's hat like a sombrero. It was granted in red to cardinals by [[Pope Innocent IV]] at the [[First Council of Lyon]] in the 13th century, and was adopted by heraldry almost immediately. The galero in various colors and forms was used in heraldic achievements starting with its adoption in the arms of bishops in the 16th century. In the 19th century the galero was viewed heraldically as specifically &quot;Catholic&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Selvester, [http://www.guyselvester.50megs.com/custom4.html Aspects of Heraldry].&lt;/ref&gt; but the Public Register of Arms in Scotland show Roman Catholic, presbyterian Church of Scotland and Anglican Episcopalian clergy all using the wide brimmed, low crowned hat. The galero is ornamented with tassels (also called ''houppes'' or ''fiocchi'') indicating the cleric's current place in the hierarchy; the number became significant beginning in the 16th century, and the meaning was fixed, for Catholic clergy, in 1832.{{sfn|Boutell|Brooke-Little|1978|pp=226-227}} A bishop's galero is green with six tassels on each side; the color originated in [[Roman Catholicism in Spain|Spain]] where formerly a green hat was actually worn by bishops.{{sfn|Heim|1978|p=69}} A [[territorial abbot]] was equivalent to a bishop and used a green galero. An [[archbishop]]'s galero is green but has ten tassels. [[Roman Catholicism in Switzerland|Bishops in Switzerland]] formerly used ten tassels like an archbishop because they were under the immediate jurisdiction of the Holy See and not part of an archiepiscopal [[ecclesiastical province|province]].{{sfn|Heim|1978|p=95}} Both [[patriarch]]s and cardinals have hats with fifteen tassels. A cardinal's hat is red or scarlet while a patriarch who is not also a cardinal uses a green hat; the patriarch's tassels are interwoven with gold.&lt;ref&gt;{{CathEncy | wstitle=Ecclesiastical Heraldry | short=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[primate (bishop)|Primates]] may use the same external ornaments as patriarchs.{{sfn|Heim|1978|p=107}}&lt;ref&gt;Lartigue, ''Dictionnaire &amp; Armorial'', contains examples of 19th-century archiepiscopal arms with 30 tassels, e.g. Lyonnet (p.236b), De Breil (p.134b), Forcade (p.150b), Fruchaud (p.172a).&lt;/ref&gt;

The depiction of the galero in arms can vary greatly depending on the artist's style. The top of the hat may be shown flat or round. Sometimes the brim is shown much narrower; with a domed top it can look like a [[cappello romano]] with tassels, but in heraldry it is still called a galero. The tassels may be represented as knotted cords.
[[File:Zen motto.jpg|thumb|left|150px|Arms of Bishop [[Joseph Cardinal Zen|Joseph Zen]] of [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Hong Kong|Hong Kong]] with the simple [[Christian cross#Forms of the Cross|Latin cross]], and a violet galero (prior to his elevation to cardinal priest)]]
An exception is made for [[Roman Catholicism in China|Chinese bishops]], who often avoid using green hat in their arms since &quot;wearing a green hat&quot; is the Chinese idiom for [[cuckold]].&lt;ref&gt;The title of the film ''The Green Hat'' comes from this idiom, according to reviews by the [http://2005.adelaidefilmfestival.org/films/greenhat.html Adelaide] and [http://www.tribecafilmfestival.org/tixSYS/archive/eventnote.php?EventNumber=20042866 Tribeca] film festivals. Accessed 2007-12-10.&lt;/ref&gt; Rather than green, these bishops use a variety of colors from violet and black to blue, or scarlet if a cardinal. A cross behind the shield denotes a bishop.

Lesser Roman Catholic prelates use a variety of colors. Violet hats were once actually worn by certain [[monsignor]]s,{{sfn|Heim|1978|pp=69–70, 118–119}} and so in heraldry they have used a violet hat with red or violet tassels in varying numbers, currently fixed at six on each side. The lowest grade of monsignor, a [[Chaplain of His Holiness]], uses a black hat with violet tassels.{{sfn|Heim|1978|pp=119-121}} The [[superior general]] of an order displays a black galero with six tassels on each side, while provincial superiors and abbots use a black galero with six or three tassels on each side, although [[Premonstratensian|Norbertines]] (White Canons) use a white galero. Although a [[priesthood (Catholic Church)|priest]] would rarely assume arms unless he had an ancestral right to arms independent of his clerical state, a priest would use a simple black ecclesiastical hat with a single tassel on each side. Priests who hold an office such as [[Rector (ecclesiastical)|rector]] would have two tassels on each side.{{sfn|Heim|1978|pp=124-125}}

Clergy of the [[Church of England]] who were not bishops historically bore arms identical to a [[laity|layman]], with a shield, helm and crest, and no ecclesiastical hat. In England in 1976 a system for [[dean (religion)|deans]], [[archdeacon]]s and [[canon (priest)|canons]] was authorized by the [[College of Arms]], allowing a black ecclesiastical hat, black or violet cords, and three violet or red tassels on each side.{{sfn|Heim|1978|pp=135,139–142}}&lt;ref&gt;von Volborth, ''The Art of Heraldry'', p.71.&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Boutell|Brooke-Little|1978|pp=225-226}} A priest uses a black and white cord with a single tassel on each side, and a [[deacon]] a hat without tassels. A [[Doctor of Divinity]] may have cords interwoven with red and a hat appropriate to the degree, and members of the [[Ecclesiastical Household]] add a [[Tudor rose]] on the front of the hat. According to ''Boutell's Heraldry'', this system represents the practice of the Church in England in the 16th century.{{sfn|Boutell|Brooke-Little|1978|p=226}}

Within [[Presbyterianism|Presbyterian]] Church heraldry, a minister's hat is represented as black with a single tassel on each side, sometimes blue, though a doctoral bonnet or Geneva cap may replace the brimmed hat.&lt;ref&gt;Fox-Davies, ''A Complete Guide to Heraldry'', p.470; See [http://heraldry-scotland.com/HSSforum/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=83&amp;sid=7a7ba8957d9a4b28e0b855aceb887f9f arms of Rev. Denis Towner]. As can be seen in the Scots Public Register the term 'ecclesiastical hat' can be shown as a Geneva bonnet but this is done only rarely.&lt;/ref&gt; Clergy of the [[Chapel Royal]] display red tassels. The office of [[presbyterian polity|moderator]] does not have corporate arms,&lt;ref&gt;Innes of Learney, ''Scots Heraldry'', p.143.&lt;/ref&gt; but for official occasions, a moderator may add tassels to his personal arms to indicate parity with offices of other churches: three for a moderator of a presbytery, and six for a moderator of a regional synod.&lt;ref&gt;Innes of Learney, ''Scots Heraldry'', p.35–37; [http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9031885 &quot;Ecclesiastical Heraldry&quot;], ''Encyclopædia Britannica''.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[moderator of the General Assembly]] of the Church of Scotland now uses a differenced version of the General Assembly's arms, with a hat having a blue cord and ten tassels on each side, and may also show the moderator's staff, a gold Celtic crosier, behind the shield as can be seen in vol 41, p 152 of the Scots Public Register.

===Cross===
[[File:Brasão de Dom Antônio de Castro Mayer.jpg|thumb|right|120px|Coat of arms of the Bishop [[Antônio de Castro Mayer]], carved in a wooden door in a Church.]]

In the Catholic Church, display of a cross behind the shield is restricted to bishops as a mark of their dignity.{{sfn|Rogers|1956|p=139}} The cross of an ordinary bishop has a single horizontal bar or traverse, also known as a [[Christian cross#Forms of the Cross|Latin cross]]. A [[patriarch]] uses the [[patriarchal cross]] with two traverses, also called the [[cross of Lorraine]]. The papal cross has three traverses, but this is never displayed behind the papal arms.

Beginning in the 15th century, the cross with a double traverse is seen on the arms of archbishops, and relates to their processional cross and the jurisdiction it symbolizes.{{sfn|Boutell|Brooke-Little|1978|p=227}}&lt;ref&gt;{{CathEncy | wstitle=Processional Cross | short=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; Except for cardinals of the [[Roman Curia]], most cardinals head an archdiocese and use an [[archiepiscopal cross]] on their arms. Other cardinals use a simple Latin cross,&lt;ref&gt;Noonan, ''The Church Visible'', p.191–192,194.&lt;/ref&gt; as is found in the arms of Cardinal [[Joseph Zen]], [[Catholic Diocese of Hong Kong|bishop emeritus of Hong Kong]], because Hong Kong is not an archdiocese.

Today all cardinals are required to be bishops, but priests named cardinal at an advanced age often petition the Pope for an exception to this rule. [[Bruno Heim]] says that since the cross is one heraldic emblem that only bishops have the right to bear, cardinals who are not bishops do not use it.{{sfn|Heim|1978|p=74}}&lt;ref&gt;Selvester, [http://www.guyselvester.50megs.com/custom4.html Aspects of Heraldry].&lt;/ref&gt; Notable examples are Cardinals [[Albert Vanhoye]] and [[Avery Dulles]]; the latter's arms do display a cross.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fordham.edu/dulles Avery Cardinal Dulles, S.J.] at [[Fordham University]].&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mitre and pallium===
[[File:Soemblem.JPG|thumb|right|Emblem of [[Syriac Orthodox Church]]: and Eastern crozier crossed with a [[blessing cross]] beneath a Syriac bishop's turban]]
[[File:CoA Francis de Sales.svg|thumb|left|150px|Coat of arms of [[Francis de Sales]], [[Diocese of Lausanne, Geneva and Fribourg#Geneva|bishop of Geneva]] displayed on an oval shield with both mitre and galero above, and motto below]]
[[File:COADUCATRAD.svg|thumbnail|left|What a Bishop's Coat of Arms would have looked like before the rules were changed in 1969. This is not an official version.]]
In the western churches, the [[mitre]] was placed above the shield of all persons who were entitled to wear the mitre, including abbots. It substituted for the [[helmet]] of military arms, but also appeared as a [[crest (heraldry)|crest]] placed atop a helmet, as was common in German heraldry.&lt;ref&gt;{{CathEncy | wstitle=Ecclesiastical Heraldry | short=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the Anglican Churches, the mitre is still placed above the arms of bishops and not an ecclesiastical hat. In the Roman Catholic Church, the use of the mitre above the shield on the personal arms of clergy was suppressed in 1969,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fiu.edu/~mirandas/instruction69.htm &quot;Instruction&quot;], 1969, n.28.&lt;/ref&gt; and is now found only on some corporate arms, like those of dioceses. Previously, the mitre was often included under the hat,&lt;ref&gt;Lartigue, ''Dictionnaire''.&lt;/ref&gt; and even in the arms of a cardinal, the mitre was not entirely displaced.&lt;ref&gt;von Volborth, ''Heraldry of the World'', p.171, shows the arms of Cardinal [[Francis Spellman]] with mitre in 1967, just two years before the 1969 [http://www.fiu.edu/~mirandas/instruction69.htm ''Instruction''.]&lt;/ref&gt;

The mitre may be shown in all sorts of colours. It may be represented either gold or jewelled, the former more common in English heraldry.{{sfn|Boutell|Brooke-Little|1978|p=224}} A form of mitre with [[coronet]] is proper to the [[Bishop of Durham]] because of his role as [[Prince-Bishop]] of the [[County palatine|palatinate]] of Durham.&lt;ref&gt;Fox-Davies, ''A Complete Guide to Heraldry'', p.467,469. The use of coronet by all archbishops is &quot;mistaken&quot; and &quot;inaccurate&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; For similar reasons the Bishop of Durham and some other bishops display a [[sword]] behind the shield, pointed downward to signify a former civil jurisdiction.{{sfn|Boutell|Brooke-Little|1978|p=225}}{{sfn|Rogers|1956|pp=142–143}}

The [[pallium]] is a distinctive vestment of [[metropolitan archbishop]]s, and may be found in their bearings as well as the corporate arms of archdioceses, displayed either above or below the shield. The pallium is sometimes seen within the shield itself. With the exception of [[Archbishop of York|York]], the archiepiscopal dioceses in England and [[Ireland]] include the pallium within the shield.&lt;ref&gt;Fox-Davies, ''A Complete Guide to Heraldry'', p.466–467. The arms of the [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Westminster]] and older versions of the arms of York also have the pallium.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Crosier===
[[File:Franz Christoph von Hutten Wappen.jpg|thumb|right|[[:de:Franz Christoph von Hutten|Franz Christoph von Hutten's]] coat of arms from the 18th century with mitre, staff, and sword]]
The [[crosier]] was displayed as a symbol of pastoral jurisdiction by bishops, abbots, abbesses, and cardinals even if they were not bishops. The crosier of a bishop is turned outward or to the right. Frequently the crosier of an abbot or abbess is turned inward, either toward the mitre or to the left, but this distinction is disputed and is not an absolute rule.&lt;ref&gt;Fox-Davies, ''A Complete Guide to Heraldry'', p.466&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Heim|1978|p=67}} [[Pope Alexander VII]] decreed in 1659 that the crosiers of abbots include a ''sudarium'' or veil, but this is not customary in English heraldry.{{sfn|Boutell|Brooke-Little|1978|p=228}} The veil may have arisen because abbots, unlike bishops, did not wear gloves when carrying an actual crosier.&lt;ref&gt;Selvester, [http://www.guyselvester.50megs.com/custom4.html Aspects of Heraldry].&lt;/ref&gt; Because the cross has similar symbolism,{{sfn|Boutell|Brooke-Little|1978|p=226}} the crosier was suppressed for cardinals and bishops by the Catholic Church in 1969, and is now used only on some corporate arms, and the personal arms of abbots and some abbesses.&lt;ref&gt;Noonan, ''The Church Visible'', p.191.&lt;/ref&gt; In English custom and in the Anglican Churches, two crosiers are often found crossed ''in saltire'' behind the shield.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9031885 &quot;Ecclesiastical Heraldry&quot;], ''Encyclopædia Britannica''; Fox-Davies, ''A Complete Guide to Heraldry'', p.468.&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Boutell|Brooke-Little|1978|p=224}} In the Lutheran [[Church of Sweden]], the crosier is displayed in the arms of bishops in office but is removed when a bishop retires.
[[File:Coat of arms of the Diocese of Cubao - Based on 10th Anniversary.svg|thumbnail|A rendition of the coat of arms of the [[Diocese of Cubao]], showing the [[mitre]], [[crozier]], and [[cross]].]]
A ''bourdon'' or knobbed staff is shown behind the arms of some priors and prioresses as a symbol of office analogous to the crosier.{{sfn|Heim|1978|pp=74-75}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catholic-forum.com/saints/ncd03889.htm &quot;Ecclesiastical Heraldry&quot;] ''New Catholic Dictionary'' (1910).&lt;/ref&gt; Arms of [[prior]]s from the 15th century had a banner surrounding the shield,&lt;ref&gt;von Volborth, ''Heraldry of the World'', p.169.&lt;/ref&gt; but today this is often a [[rosary]].&lt;ref&gt;von Volborth, ''Heraldry of the World'', p.175.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mantle===
[[File:Slipyj herb.jpg|thumb|left|Arms of Cardinal [[Josyf Slipyj]], [[major archbishop]] of the [[Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church]], with [[mantling]]]]
[[Mantling]] was originally a piece of material attached to a helmet and covering the shoulders, possibly to protect from the sun. In secular heraldry the mantling was depicted shredded, as if from battle. In the 17th and 18th centuries, another form of mantling called a &quot;robe of estate&quot; became prominent.&lt;ref&gt;von Volborth, ''The Art of Heraldry'', p.64; von Volborth, ''Heraldry of the World'', p.21,174.&lt;/ref&gt; This form is used especially in the [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Orthodox Churches]], where bishops display a mantle tied with cords and tassels above the shield. The heraldic mantle is similar to the [[Mantle (vesture)|mantiya]], and represents the bishop's authority. It can also be found in the arms of the Grand Master of the [[Sovereign Military Order of Malta]].&lt;ref&gt;Williamson, ''Debrett's Guide'', p.49; Noonan, ''The Church Visible'', p.195.&lt;/ref&gt;

The outside of the mantle may be any color, typically red, while the inside is white or sometimes yellow to distinguish it from a secular mantle.{{sfn|Heim|1978|p=133}} David Johnson suggested that the mantle of all bishops should be white inside, excepting only patriarchs who use [[ermine (heraldry)|ermine]], to indicate that all bishops are equally bishops.&lt;ref&gt;Johnson, [http://www.americancollegeofheraldry.org/ORTHODOX.htm Orthodox Ecclesiastical Heraldry].&lt;/ref&gt; Above the mantle is a mitre (of the Eastern style) between a processional cross and a crosier. The earliest examples of the arms of Orthodox hierarchs have the cross to the dexter of the mitre and the bishop's staff to sinister, but opposite examples exist. An abbot ([[archimandrite]] or [[hegumen]]) should display a veiled abbot's staff to distinguish it from the bishop's staff.

[[File:Biskup Ljavinec Ivan CoA.jpg|thumb|Coat of arms of an [[Eastern Catholic]] prelate, combining elements of both Eastern and Western ecclesiastical heraldry]]
[[Archpriest]]s and priests would use a less ornate mantle in their arms, and an ecclesiastical hat of the style they wear liturgically. Although an [[Monk#Eastern Christianity|Orthodox monk]] (not an abbot) displaying personal arms is rare, a [[hieromonk]] (monk who has been [[ordained]] a priest) would appropriately display a monastic hat (''[[klobuk]]'') and a black cloak or veil suggestive of his [[monastic habit|attire]], and a [[hierodeacon]] (monastic deacon) would display an [[orarion]] behind the shield.

A shield in front of a mantle or cloak may be found among bishops of the [[Eastern Catholic Churches]].&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.archeparchy.org/page/metropolitan/metropolitan.htm Byzantine Catholic Archeparchy, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania] and [http://eparchy-of-van-nuys.org Byzantine Catholic Eparchy of Van Nuys].&lt;/ref&gt; However, some Eastern ecclesiastical variations omit the mantle but retain the mitre, cross and staff.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ukrarcheparchy.us/index.php?categoryid=9&amp;s=&amp; Ukrainian Catholic Archdiocese of Philadelphia].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Maronite Church|Maronite]] bishops traditionally display a pastoral staff behind the shield, topped with a globe and cross or a cross within a globe.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stmaron.org/coat_arms.html Arms of the bishop of the Eparchy of St. Maron of Brooklyn].&lt;/ref&gt; Eastern Catholic bishops may follow the Roman style with a low crowned, wide brimmed ecclesiastical hat, although the shield itself is often rendered in a Byzantine artistic style, and a mitre if present would be in the appropriate liturgical style.&lt;ref&gt;See examples from the [http://www.ucet.ca/ Ukrainian Catholic Eparchy of Toronto and East Canada], [http://procyk.tripod.com/ Ukrainian Catholic Eparchy of Stamford], and [http://members.aol.com/DioceseofChicago/index.html Syro-Malabar Catholic Diocese of Chicago]; the [[Syro-Malabar Church]] uses the western-style mitre in the liturgy.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Motto===
A [[motto]] is a short phrase usually appearing below the shield as a statement of belief. Catholic bishops and Presbyterian churches use a motto in their arms,&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.gg.ca/heraldry/pub-reg/project.asp?lang=e&amp;ProjectID=346 St. James] and [http://www.gg.ca/heraldry/pub-reg/project.asp?lang=e&amp;ProjectID=546 St. Matthew's] Presbyterian Churches.&lt;/ref&gt; though it is rare among Anglican bishops.{{sfn|Boutell|Brooke-Little|1978|p=224}}&lt;ref&gt;{{CathEncy | wstitle=Ecclesiastical Heraldry | short=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; A notable exception is the motto on the coat of arms of [[Rowan Williams]], former [[Archbishop of Canterbury]].

[[Gustavo Testa]], created cardinal in December 1959, quickly selected as his arms a shield with the words ''sola gratia tua'' and the motto ''et patria et cor'' in order to meet a publishing deadline. Literally these phrases mean &quot;only by your favor&quot; and &quot;both fatherland and heart&quot;. Testa explained to [[Pope John XXIII]] that the shield meant &quot;I am a cardinal because of you alone&quot;, and the motto meant &quot;because I am from Bergamo and a friend&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Martin, ''Heraldry in the Vatican'', p.242.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Papal insignia==
{{Main article|Papal regalia and insignia}}
[[File:Medici Leo XI.jpg|thumb|right|[[Pope Leo XI]]'s coat of arms, the family arms of the [[Medici]]]]
[[Saint Peter]] was represented holding keys as early as the fifth century. As the Roman Catholic Church considers him the first pope and bishop of Rome, the keys were adopted as a papal emblem; they first appear with papal arms in the 13th century.&lt;ref&gt;Noonan, ''The Church Visible'', p.189.&lt;/ref&gt; Two keys perpendicular were often used on coins, but beginning in the 15th century were used to represent [[St. Peter's Basilica]]. Perpendicular keys last appeared in the shield of the papacy in 1555, after which the crossed keys are used exclusively.&lt;ref&gt;Galbreath, ''Papal Heraldry'', p.6–7.&lt;/ref&gt; The keys are gold and silver, with the gold key placed to dexter (viewer's left) on the personal arms of the Pope, although two silver keys or two gold keys were used late into the 16th century.&lt;ref&gt;Galbreath, ''Papal Heraldry'', p.12–13.&lt;/ref&gt; The keys as a symbol of Saint Peter may be found within many coats of arms; the coat of arms of the [[Prince-Archbishopric of Bremen]] displayed two [[Argent|argent (silver)]] crossed keys as Saint Peter is the patron saint of the [[Bremen Cathedral|Bremian archiepiscopal cathedral]].

The [[Papal Tiara]] or ''triregnum'' is the three-tiered crown used by the Pope as a sovereign power. It is first found as an independent emblem in the 13th century, though at that time with only one coronet.&lt;ref&gt;Galbreath, ''Papal Heraldry'', p.22.&lt;/ref&gt; In the 15th century, the tiara was combined with the keys above the papal shield. The tiara and keys together within a shield form the arms of Vatican City. In heraldry, the white tiara is depicted with a bulbous shape and with two attached red strips called [[lappet]]s or infulae.&lt;ref&gt;Noonan, ''The Church Visible'', p.195.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[coat of arms of Pope Benedict XVI]] sparked controversy by displaying a mitre and pallium instead of the customary tiara.

Besides the Holy See, another Catholic see has the right to bear the triple tiara in its coat of arms: the [[Patriarchate of Lisbon]].{{sfn|Heim|1978|pp=52, 94}} The title of Patriarch of Lisbon was created in 1716 and is held by the [[archbishop of Lisbon]] since 1740. While the coat of arms of the Holy See combines the tiara with the crossed keys of St. Peter, that of the Lisbon Patriarchate combines it with a processional cross and a pastoral staff.

[[File:COAppiusix.png|thumb|150px|left|Rendition of [[Pope Pius IX]]'s coat of arms with tiara, keys and supporters]]
The red and gold striped [[ombrellino]] or pavilion was originally a processional canopy or sunshade and can be found so depicted as early as the 12th century.&lt;ref&gt;Galbreath, ''Papal Heraldry'', p.27.&lt;/ref&gt; The earliest use of the ombrellino in heraldry is in the 1420s when it was placed above the shield of [[Pope Martin V]]. It is more commonly used together with the keys, a combination first found under [[Pope Alexander VI]].&lt;ref&gt;Galbreath, ''Papal Heraldry'', p.31.&lt;/ref&gt; This combined badge represents the temporal power of Vatican City between Papal reigns, when the acting head of state is the cardinal [[Camerlengo of the Holy Roman Church|Camerlengo]]. The badge first appeared with a cardinal's personal arms on coins minted by order of the Camerlengo, Cardinal Armellini, during the inter-regnum of 1521. During the 17th and 18th centuries, it appeared on coins minted ''[[sede vacante]]'' by papal legates, and on coins minted in 1746 and 1771 while a pope reigned.&lt;ref&gt;Galbreath, ''Papal Heraldry'', p.34.&lt;/ref&gt; The ombrellino appears in the arms of [[basilica]]s since the 16th century, with ornamentation for major basilicas. If found in a family's coat of arms, it indicates that a relative had been pope.&lt;ref&gt;von Volborth, ''Heraldry of the World'', p.172.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Wappen Hagen im Bremischen.png|thumb|130px|right|Emblem of Bremen's archbishop (red shield) within the emblem of ''Hagen i.B.'']]
The [[papal coats of arms]] are often depicted with [[angel]]s as [[supporters]].&lt;ref&gt;[[:Commons:Category:Dizionario araldico ufficiale italiano|''Vocabolario Araldico Ufficiale della Consulta Araldica'']] (1907), images [[:File:Araldiz Manno 384.png|384]] and [[:File:Araldiz Manno 420.png|420]].&lt;/ref&gt; Other Catholic or Anglican clergy do not use supporters unless they were awarded as a personal honor, or were inherited with family arms.{{sfn|Boutell|Brooke-Little|1978|p=224}}&lt;ref&gt;{{CathEncy | wstitle=Ecclesiastical Heraldry | short=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some cathedral arms use a single chair ([[cathedra]]) as a supporter.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.gg.ca/heraldry/pub-reg/project-pic.asp?lang=e&amp;ProjectID=582&amp;ProjectElementID=2051 St. Paul's Cathedral].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Chivalric insignia==
Roman Catholic clergy may not display insignia of [[knight]]hood in their arms, except awards received in the [[Order of the Holy Sepulchre]] or the [[Sovereign Military Order of Malta]]. If entitled, Roman Catholic clergy may display the red [[Cross#In heraldry|Jerusalem Cross]] for the former or the [[Maltese cross]] for the latter behind the shield, or may display the ribbon of their rank in the order.&lt;ref&gt;Noonan, ''The Church Visible'', p.195–196.&lt;/ref&gt; This restriction does not apply to laymen who have been knighted in any royal or [[Papal Orders|Papal order]], who may display the insignia of their rank, either a ribbon at the base of the shield or a chain surrounding the shield.

Church of England clergy may display chivalric insignia. The [[List of Deans of Westminster Abbey|Dean of Westminster]] is also the Dean of the Most Honourable [[Order of the Bath]], and displays the civil badge of that order.{{sfn|Heim|1978|p=136}}

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
;Works cited
* {{cite book|ref=harv|last1=Boutell|first1=Charles |authorlink1=Charles Boutell|last2=Brooke-Little|first2=John Philip |authorlink2=John Brooke-Little|title=Boutell's heraldry|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=UTUOAQAAMAAJ|year=1978|publisher=F. Warne|isbn=978-0-7232-2096-1}} &lt;!-- 1973 edition, ISBN 0-7232-1708-4 --&gt;
* {{cite book | last=Fox-Davies | first=A.C. | authorlink=Arthur Charles Fox-Davies | title=A Complete Guide to Heraldry | year=1969 | publisher=Nelson | editor-last=Brooke-Little|editor-first=J. P.|editor-link=John Brooke-Little|isbn=978-1-60239-001-0}}
* {{cite book | last=Galbreath | first=Donald Lindsay | title=Papal Heraldry | year=1972 | publisher=Heraldry Today | isbn=0-900455-22-5}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|last=Heim|first=Bruno Bernhard |authorlink=Bruno Heim|title=Heraldry in the Catholic Church: its origin, customs, and laws|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6dwZAAAAYAAJ|year=1978|publisher=Humanities Press|isbn=0-391-00873-0}} &lt;!-- Also published by Gerrard's Cross: id=ISBN 0-905715-05-5 --&gt;
* {{cite book | last=Heim | first=Bruno | title=Or and Argent | year=1994 | publisher=Van Duren | isbn=0-905715-24-1}}
* {{cite book | last=Innes of Learney | first=Sir Thomas | authorlink=Thomas Innes of Learney | title=Scots Heraldry | publisher=Oliver and Boyd | year=1956}}
* {{cite web | title=Instruction on the dress, titles and coat-of-arms of cardinals, bishops and lesser prelates. | publisher=''[[L'Osservatore Romano]]'', English ed. (17 April 1969) | pages=vol.4 | url=http://www.fiu.edu/~mirandas/instruction69.htm | accessdate=2006-09-01}}
* {{cite web | last=Johnson | first=David Pittman, D.S.W | url=http://www.americancollegeofheraldry.org/ORTHODOX.htm | title=Orthodox Ecclesiastical Heraldry | publisher= [[American College of Heraldry]] | accessdate=2006-09-01}}
* {{cite book | last=Lartigue | first=Jean-Jacques | title=Dictionnarie &amp; Armorial de L'Épiscopat Français (1200–2000) | year=2000 | publisher=L'Intermédiare des Chercheurs et Curieux | isbn=2-908003-19-8}}
* {{cite book | last=Martin | first=Jacques | title=Heraldry in the Vatican | year=1987 | publisher=Van Duren | isbn=0-905715-25-X}}
* {{cite book | last=Neubecker | first=Ottfried | title=Heraldry: Sources, Symbols and Meaning | year=1976 | publisher=McGraw-Hill | isbn=0-07-046308-5}}
* {{cite book | last=Noonan, Jr. | first=James-Charles | title=The Church Visible: The Ceremonial Life and Protocol of the Roman Catholic Church | year=1996 | publisher=Viking | isbn=0-670-86745-4}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|last=Rogers|first=H. C. B. |title=The Pageant of Heraldry. An Explanation of Its Principles &amp; Its Uses To-day, Etc.|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=DFMJMwEACAAJ|year=1956|publisher=Pitman|location=London}}
* {{cite web | last=Selvester | first=Guy | authorlink=Guy Selvester | url=http://www.guyselvester.50megs.com/custom4.html | title=Aspects of Heraldry in the Catholic Church | publisher=Personal website |accessdate=2006-09-01 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20060827045955/http://www.guyselvester.50megs.com/custom4.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-08-27}}
* {{cite book | last=von Volborth | first=Carl Alexander | authorlink=Carl-Alexander von Volborth | title=The Art of Heraldry | year=1987 | publisher=Tiger Books | isbn=1-85501-154-9}}
* {{cite book | last=von Volborth | first=Carl Alexander | title=Heraldry of the World | year=1973 | publisher=MacMillan}}
* {{cite book | last=Williamson | first=David | title=Debrett's Guide to Heraldry and Regalia | year=1992 | publisher=Headline | isbn=0-7472-0609-0}}
* {{cite book | last=Woodcock | first=Thomas | authorlink=Thomas Woodcock (officer of arms) | title=The Oxford Guide to Heraldry | year=1988 | publisher=Oxford University Press | isbn=0-19-211658-4}}

;Encyclopedia articles
* {{cite encyclopedia | url=http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9031885 | title=Ecclesiastical Heraldry | encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Britannica | year = 2006 | accessdate=2006-09-01}}
* {{cite encyclopedia | url=http://www.catholic-forum.com/saints/ncd03889.htm | title=Ecclesiastical Heraldry | encyclopedia=New Catholic Dictionary | year=1910 | accessdate=2006-09-01}}
* {{CathEncy | last=Fox-Davies | first=A.C | wstitle=Ecclesiastical Heraldry}}
* {{CathEncy | last=Thurston | first=Herbert | wstitle=Processional Cross}}

;Online examples in order of mention
* {{cite web | url=http://www.civicheraldry.com/page/11666 | title=Gauteng province (South Africa) coat of arms | work=civicheraldry.com | accessdate=2009-06-02}}
* {{cite web | url=http://www.kwazulunatal.gov.za/ | title=Provincial Government Kwazulu-Natal | work=kwazulunatal.gov.za | accessdate=2007-12-29}}
* {{cite web | url=http://www.diometuchen.org/mainweb/coat.htm | title=Bishop Bootkoski Coat of Arms | work=diometuchen.org | accessdate=2007-12-29| archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070928154405/http://www.diometuchen.org/mainweb/coat.htm| archivedate = September 28, 2007}}
* {{cite web | url=http://2005.adelaidefilmfestival.org/films/greenhat.html | title=The Green Hat (Lü Mao Tze)| work=Adelaide Film Festival | accessdate=2007-12-29| archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20071218033811/http://2005.adelaidefilmfestival.org/films/greenhat.html| archivedate = December 18, 2007}}
* {{cite web | url=http://heraldry-scotland.com/HSSforum/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=83&amp;sid=7a7ba8957d9a4b28e0b855aceb887f9f | title=Denis Towner | work=heraldry-scotland.com | accessdate=2007-12-29| archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070928180026/http://heraldry-scotland.com/HSSforum/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=83&amp;sid=7a7ba8957d9a4b28e0b855aceb887f9f| archivedate = September 28, 2007}}
* {{cite web | url=http://www.fordham.edu/dulles/ | title=Avery Cardinal Dulles, S.J. | work=fordham.edu | accessdate=2007-12-29}}
* {{cite web | url=http://eparchy-of-van-nuys.org/ | title=Most Rev. William Charles Skurla, Bishop | work=Byzantine Catholic Eparchy of Van Nuys | accessdate=2007-12-29}}
* {{cite web | url=http://www.archeparchy.org/page/metropolitan/metropolitan.htm | title=Metropolitan Archbishop Basil Schott | work=Catholic Archeparchy - Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania | accessdate=2007-12-29}}
* {{cite web | url=http://www.ukrarcheparchy.us/index.php?categoryid=9&amp;s=&amp; | title=The Coat of Arms of Metropolitan Stefan Soroka | work=Ukrainian Catholic Archdiocese of Philadelphia | accessdate=2007-12-29 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070928080916/http://www.ukrarcheparchy.us/index.php?categoryid=9&amp;s=&amp; &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-09-28}}
* {{cite web | url=http://www.stmaron.org/coat_arms.html | title= The Coat of Arms of His Excellency Gregory John Mansour, S.T.L. | work=Eparchy of Saint Maron of Brooklyn | accessdate=2007-12-29}}
* {{cite web | url=http://www.ucet.ca/ | title=Ukrainian Catholic Eparchy of Toronto and Eastern Canada | accessdate=2007-12-29}}
* {{cite web | url=http://procyk.tripod.com/ | title=Eparchy of Stamford | accessdate=2007-12-29}}
* {{cite web | url=http://members.aol.com/DioceseofChicago/index.html | title=Mar Jacob Angadiath Bishop | work=St. Thomas Syro-Malabar Catholic Diocese of Chicago | accessdate=2007-12-29}}
* {{cite web | url=http://reg.gg.ca/heraldry/pub-reg/project.asp?lang=e&amp;ProjectID=346 | title=St. James Presbyterian Church | work=Public Register of Arms, Flags and Badges of Canada | accessdate=2007-12-29}}
* {{cite web | url=http://reg.gg.ca/heraldry/pub-reg/project.asp?lang=e&amp;ProjectID=546 | title=St. Matthew's Presbyterian Church | work=Public Register of Arms, Flags and Badges of Canada | accessdate=2007-12-29}}
* [[:File:Araldiz Manno 384.png]] and [[:File:Araldiz Manno 420.png]], [[:Commons:Category:Dizionario araldico ufficiale italiano|''Vocabolario Araldico Ufficiale della Consulta Araldica'']] (1907)
* {{cite web | url=http://reg.gg.ca/heraldry/pub-reg/project.asp?lang=e&amp;ProjectID=582 | title=St. Paul's Cathedral | work=Public Register of Arms, Flags and Badges of Canada | accessdate=2007-12-29}}

;Further reading
* {{cite book | last=Dennys | first=Rodney | authorlink=Rodney Dennys | title=The Heraldic Imagination | publisher=Barrie &amp; Jenkins | year=1975 | isbn=0-919974-01-5}}
* {{cite book | last=Galbreath | first=Donald Lindsay | title=A Treatise on Ecclesiastical Heraldry | year=1930 | publisher=W. Heffer}}
* {{cite book | last=McCarthy | first=Michael Francis | title=A Manual of Ecclesiastical Heraldry | publisher=Thylacine | year=2005 | isbn=0-9577947-7-0}}
* {{cite book | last=Woodward | first=John | title=A Treatise on Ecclesiastical Heraldry | publisher=W. &amp; A.K. Johnston | year=1894 | url=https://books.google.com/books?vid=OCLC04349158 | accessdate=2007-01-26}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Heraldry}}
{{Commons category|Ecclesiastical heraldry}}
* [http://www.heraldica.org/topics/catholic.htm Catholic Heraldry] at heraldica.org
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20091027032159/http://uk.geocities.com/kruisstaf/ArmsChurch.html  Armoria ecclesiastica] - Church arms in South Africa

{{heraldry}}
{{Featured article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ecclesiastical Heraldry}}
[[Category:Ecclesiastical heraldry| ]]
[[Category:Heraldry]]
[[Category:Coats of arms]]
[[Category:Episcopacy in Roman Catholicism]]
[[Category:Bishops|*]]</text>
      <sha1>8kajy6ch100s8wvye3oqji7idcmsqp5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
