<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Monroe Edwards</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>44925295</id>
    <revision>
      <id>713922549</id>
      <parentid>713922541</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-04-06T15:33:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contribs/ScratchClubYoutube|ScratchClubYoutube]] to version by Ealdgyth. [[WP:CBFP|Report False Positive?]] Thanks, [[WP:CBNG|ClueBot NG]]. (2611789) (Bot)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20829">{{featured article}}
{{Infobox person
|name             = Monroe Edwards
|image            = File:Engraving of Monroe Edwards from the frontispiece of Life and Adventures of the Accomplished Forger and Swindler, Colonel Monroe Edwards.jpg
|image_size       = 220px
|caption          = A portrait engraving of Edwards from ''Life and Adventures of the Accomplished Forger and Swindler, Colonel Monroe Edwards'', published a year after his death
|birth_date       = 1808
|birth_place      = [[Danville, Kentucky]]
|death_date       = January 27, 1847
|death_place      = [[Sing Sing]] Prison, New York
|death_cause      = [[tuberculosis|Consumption]]
|nationality      = American
|other_names      = 
|occupation       = Slave trader
|known_for        = Forgery
|criminal_charge  = Multiple counts of forgery and fraud
|criminal_penalty = 10 years in prison
}}

'''Monroe Edwards''' (1808&amp;nbsp;– January 27, 1847) was an American slave trader, forger and convicted criminal who was the subject of a well-publicized trial and conviction in 1842. Originally from [[Kentucky]], Edwards moved to [[New Orleans]] then settled in [[Texas]]. He smuggled slaves into Brazil in 1832, and used the proceeds to purchase land in Texas. In 1836 he was again smuggling slaves, this time into Texas. After attempting to swindle his partner out of the profits of the venture, partly with forged documents, Edwards was forced to flee the [[Republic of Texas]] to the United States. He then tried to scam money out of various abolitionists in the United States and the United Kingdom, partly with forged letters of introduction. He traveled to the United Kingdom, but his schemes were mainly unsuccessful and he returned to the United States in mid-1841.

Edwards' largest swindle involved forged letters from cotton brokers in New Orleans, which he used to secure bank drafts for large sums that he then cashed. His fabrications caught up with him and he was arrested and tried for the forgeries in June 1842. Convicted partly because his distinctive good looks made him memorable and easily recognizable, and partly from making the same spelling errors in his fakes, Edwards was sentenced to 10 years in prison and died in 1847 while incarcerated. Several sensational accounts of his offenses and trial were published after his death, and he was mentioned in [[Herman Melville]]'s 1853 short story &quot;[[Bartleby, the Scrivener]]&quot;.

==Early life==
Edwards was born in 1808 in [[Danville, Kentucky]]. His father was reported to be Amos Edwards&lt;ref name=ADNB/&gt; or Moses Edwards,&lt;ref name=Handbook/&gt; but the name of his mother is unknown.&lt;ref name=ADNB/&gt; His brother was Amos Edwards, and his uncle was Haden Edwards who lived in [[Nacogdoches, Texas|Nacogdoches]].&lt;ref name=Muir265&gt;Muir &quot;Union Company in Anahuac&quot; ''Southwestern Historical Quarterly'' p. 265&lt;/ref&gt; Nothing is known with certainty of his childhood. As a grown man, he was considered very handsome, and usually dressed fashionably.&lt;ref name=ADNB&gt;Thompson &quot;Edwards, Monroe&quot; ''American National Biography Online''&lt;/ref&gt; Some accounts give him the title &quot;Colonel&quot;.&lt;ref name=Barrows21&gt;Barrows ''William M. Evarts'' pp. 21–23&lt;/ref&gt;

Around 1822, Edwards was sent to [[New Orleans]] to learn business from a merchant named Mr. Morgan. By the late 1820s Morgan had established a trading post on [[San Jacinto Bay]] near [[Galveston]] in what was then [[Mexican Texas]]. Some time after, Edwards met a slave trader and joined his new acquaintance on a smuggling trip to acquire slaves in Africa. This first effort ended when they were shipwrecked, but a second attempt in 1832 successfully smuggled slaves into Brazil.&lt;ref name=ADNB/&gt; Edwards invested the profits from this venture into land in Texas, where in late 1833 he established a plantation on the [[San Bernard River]] in present-day [[Brazoria County, Texas]];&lt;ref name=Robbins158&gt;Robbins &quot;Origin and Development of the African Slave Trade&quot; ''East Texas Historical Journal'' p. 158&lt;/ref&gt; he named his new home &quot;[[Chenango, Texas|Chenango]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=ADNB/&gt;{{efn|Edwards may have been the only American citizen in Texas to have gone to Africa to acquire slaves.&lt;ref name=Robbins158/&gt;}} Unconnected with his slave trading, Edwards was arrested in 1832 as part of the [[Anahuac Disturbances]], and was briefly imprisoned during the uprising against the Mexican government which ruled Texas.&lt;ref name=Handbook/&gt;&lt;ref name=Rowe280&gt;Rowe &quot;Disturbances at Anahuac&quot; ''Quarterly'' p. 280&lt;/ref&gt;

==Slave trading and forgery==
Edwards' next efforts in smuggling involved a new partner, [[Christopher Dart]],&lt;ref name=ADNB/&gt; a lawyer from [[Natchez, Mississippi|Natchez]], Mississippi. In 1835 Dart invested $40,000&lt;ref name=Kelley410/&gt; to buy the contracts of [[indentured servant|indentured blacks]] in Cuba and smuggle them into Texas as slaves.&lt;ref name=ADNB/&gt; Instead providing money for the partnership, Edwards' contribution was [[land certificate]]s.&lt;ref name=Kelley410/&gt; At the time, Texas was a [[Mexican Texas|Mexican border province]].&lt;ref name=Lack4/&gt; In 1829, Mexico had abolished slavery&lt;ref name=Valdes194&gt;Valdes &quot;Decline of Slavery in Mexico&quot; ''Americas'' p. 194&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the importation of slaves, but gave Texas an exemption from emancipating slaves who were already in the territory.  To circumvent the ban on importing slaves, traders instead reclassified them as indentured servants with 99-year contracts. The Mexican government cracked down on this practice in 1832, limiting terms of indenture to a maximum of 10 years.&lt;ref name=Lack4&gt;Lack &quot;Texas Revolutionary Experience&quot; p. 4&lt;/ref&gt; Edwards secured further financing from a New Orleans company named George Knight and Company and then went to Cuba where he purchased slaves.&lt;ref name=Kelley410/&gt;

In February 1836 Edwards landed 170 black people in Texas, taking advantage of the confusion surrounding the end of the [[Texas Revolution]] and the establishment of the independent [[Republic of Texas]], which had not yet outlawed the importation of slaves.&lt;ref name=Robbins158/&gt; William Fisher, the customs collector on the Brazos River, wrote to the Texas Constitutional Convention that Edwards did not report the importation to the authorities, and Fisher went to Edwards' plantation to confront Edwards. Because of uncertainty about the legality of importing slaves, Fisher did not seize the slaves but referred the issue to the newly formed Texas Government after securing a [[Surety bond|monetary bond]] from Edwards. Although the new Texas Republic eventually outlawed the importation of slaves from anywhere but the United States, Edwards' landing of slaves from Cuba in early 1836 was never prosecuted.&lt;ref name=Kelley410/&gt;  After this, Edwards also established a slave market on [[Galveston Bay]], near present-day [[San Leon, Texas|San Leon]].&lt;ref name=Robbins158/&gt; In 1837, he was sued by Robert Peebles for fraud involving the sale of a slave with [[tuberculosis]] to Peebles. Peebles won the case.&lt;ref name=Kelley418&gt;Kelley &quot;Blackbirders&quot; ''Civil War History'' p. 418&lt;/ref&gt;

Edwards then tried to change the deal with Dart. Instead of dividing the smuggled slaves between the two men, Edwards tried to keep all the slaves and instead repay the money Dart had advanced him, with some interest.&lt;ref name=ADNB/&gt; Dart sued, and at the trial in March 1839 Edwards offered two forged documents claiming that Dart had sold his interest in the slaves to Edwards.&lt;ref name=ADNB/&gt; In forging the documents, Edwards originally secured Dart's signature on a document written in a type of ink that could later be chemically removed. After Dart signed the document, Edwards then removed the original wording of the document and substituted a deed selling Dart's interest in the land and slaves.&lt;ref name=Kelley410/&gt; The documents were determined to be forgeries and on April 2, 1840, Dart was awarded $89,000.&lt;ref name=Handbook/&gt; Edwards fled the Republic of Texas to the United States.&lt;ref name=ADNB/&gt;

As part of a plot to discredit both Dart and the government of Texas, Edwards persuaded some abolitionists in [[Cincinnati]] to give him money with which he would supposedly liberate the slaves on his plantation in Texas, which he no longer owned. Edwards also tried to get money from the [[American and Foreign Anti-Slavery Society]] in New York, but its leader, [[Lewis Tappan]], did not trust him and no money was forthcoming from that source. Edwards then went to England, bearing forged letters of introduction from, among others, [[Daniel Webster]]&lt;ref name=ADNB/&gt; and the American [[Secretary of State]], [[John Forsyth (Georgia)|John Forsyth]].&lt;ref name=Denham13&gt;Denham &quot;Peerless Wind Cloud&quot; ''East Texas Historical Journal'' p. 13&lt;/ref&gt; One of these letters was to [[John Spencer, Viscount Althorp|Lord Spencer]], who was so impressed he gave Edwards [[pound (currency)|£]]250&lt;ref name=Dillingham51/&gt; as a loan. While in England, Edwards defrauded a company in [[Liverpool]] of about $20,000,&lt;ref name=Dillingham51/&gt; and then used part of the funds to repay Lord Spencer.&lt;ref name=Dillingham51/&gt; The Republic of Texas ambassador in London warned the English government against Edwards. Tappan also sent warnings, so Edwards was unable to acquire more money in England and had returned to the United States by June 1841.&lt;ref name=ADNB/&gt;

==Final scheme==
Edwards' next fraudulent scheme involved forging letters to cotton brokers in New Orleans, and using the signatures obtained from their replies to forge letters to brokers in New York City, saying that the fake John Caldwell&amp;nbsp;– Edwards' alias&amp;nbsp;– had a large amount of cotton on deposit with the New Orleans brokers. Edwards used those letters to secure fraudulent loans from brokers on the security of the non-existent cotton. Two New York brokers&amp;nbsp;– [[Brown Bros. &amp; Co.]] and [[Jacob Little]]&amp;nbsp;– gave Edwards [[bank draft]]s for $25,000&lt;ref name=ADNB/&gt; each. Edwards then cashed the drafts pretending to be Caldwell, but without attempting to disguise his appearance.&lt;ref name=ADNB/&gt; Unluckily for Edwards, in September 1841 Brown Brothers was informed by the New Orleans brokers that there was no cotton on account for Caldwell,&lt;ref name=Brown77&gt;Kouwenhoven ''Partners in Banking'' p. 77&lt;/ref&gt; and this prompted the bankers to offer a reward for information on the forger.&lt;ref name=Barrows21/&gt; The police began to search for the forger of the letters, but were unsuccessful until Edwards attempted to distract their attention to an acquaintance, Alexander Powell, who happened to look much like him. Edwards sent an anonymous letter to the New York police, stating that the forger they were hunting was sailing to England, as Powell was about to do. Edwards assumed that by the time the police  acted, Powell's ship would already have sailed. The ship was delayed and the police were able to catch Powell, who told them that Edwards was their forger.&lt;ref name=ADNB/&gt;

After his arrest, Edwards was imprisoned in [[the Tombs]], New York City's jail. When he was arrested, he had more than $44,000&lt;ref name=Dillingham51/&gt; in a trunk in his room.&lt;ref name=Dillingham51&gt;Dillingham ''Melville's Short Fiction'' pp. 51–52&lt;/ref&gt; While in jail awaiting trial, Edwards forged a letter alleging he had funds in New Orleans, and then showed the letter to one of his lawyers in order to reassure the lawyer about Edwards' ability to pay for legal counsel. In an attempt to delay his trial, Edwards also forged a letter from a supposed witness, Charles Johnson, stating that he was in Cuba and would not be able to come and testify for Edwards for a while; this gained Edwards a three-month delay.&lt;ref name=Barrows24&gt;Barrows ''William M. Evarts'' pp. 24–27&lt;/ref&gt;

==Trial==
[[File:Trial of Monroe Edwards.jpg|thumb|Depiction of Edward's trial, from ''Life and Adventures of the Accomplished Forger and Swindler, Colonel Monroe Edwards'']]
Edwards' trial was in June 1842 and was a media sensation. He secured a defense team of six lawyers, including [[John J. Crittenden]], a sitting [[United States Senate|U. S. Senator]], and [[Thomas F. Marshall]], a sitting [[U. S. Representative]]. Both Crittenden and Marshall absented themselves from their legislative duties during the trial.&lt;ref name=ADNB/&gt; One of the junior lawyers was [[William M. Evarts]],{{efn|Evarts went on to be the first president of the [[New York Bar Association]], [[United States Secretary of State]], and a U. S. Senator.&lt;ref name=Evarts&gt;Hoogenboom &quot;Evarts, William Maxwell&quot; ''American National Biography''&lt;/ref&gt;}} who presented the opening remarks for the defense.&lt;ref name=Dyer12&gt;Dyer ''Public Career of William M. Evarts'' p. 12&lt;/ref&gt; Another defense lawyer was [[John Worth Edmonds]], who Edwards paid with a forged check.&lt;ref name=Wilson25&gt;Wilson &quot;Sympathy for the Lawyer&quot; ''ANQ'' pp. 25–26&lt;/ref&gt; Edwards' handsome appearance worked against him, when one of the bankers who had cashed the drafts identified him in court and remarked that he remembered Edwards because of his striking good looks. Edwards had also neglected to dispose of a marked [[bank bag]] from one of the banks that cashed the fraudulently obtained draft. A final tie-in was the commonality of misspellings between letters from Edwards and the forged letters. The trial ended with Edwards being convicted and given a 10-year prison sentence.&lt;ref name=ADNB/&gt;{{efn|Documents produced in the trial showed that Edwards was attempting to finance another slaving trip from [[Martinique]] into Texas by use of land he claimed to hold in Texas, although at the time the documents were written it was not clear if Edwards still owned any land there.&lt;ref name=Kelley410&gt;Kelley &quot;Blackbirders&quot; ''Civil War History'' pp. 410–412&lt;/ref&gt;}} The trial's proceedings were published by a New York newspaper, ''[[New York Herald|The Herald]]'', and ran to 50,000 copies. None of Edwards' lawyers were ever paid for their services.&lt;ref name=Barrows24/&gt; He was sent to [[Sing Sing]] prison, where he attempted to use forged letters to escape. Edwards died in prison on January 27, 1847,&lt;ref name=ADNB/&gt; of [[tuberculosis|consumption]].&lt;ref name=Dillingham51/&gt; He was insane at the time of his death.&lt;ref name=Barrows24/&gt;{{efn|Another account of his death states he died after a beating by prison guards.&lt;ref name=Handbook&gt;Jones &quot;[https://tshaonline.org/handbook/online/articles/fed07 Edwards, Monroe]&quot; ''Handbook of Texas Online''&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Legacy==
Edwards earned a mention in [[Herman Melville]]'s story &quot;[[Bartleby, the Scrivener]]&quot;, who used the names of contemporary events and people to give a modern feel to his short stories.&lt;ref name=Dillingham14&gt;Dillingham ''Melville's Short Fiction'' pp. 14–15&lt;/ref&gt; One of Melville's characters asks Bartleby, when imprisoned in the Tombs, if he is a &quot;gentleman forger&quot; like Edwards.&lt;ref name=Dillingham51/&gt; The career of Melville's narrator in &quot;Bartleby&quot; parallels that of Edmonds, who defended Edwards then went on to be the prison inspector at Sing Sing during Edwards' prison term, and was known for his attempts to improve the treatment of the prisoners. Melville's narrator also tries to secure better treatment for Bartleby. The narrator's description of Bartleby just prior to death, in the words of Robert Wilson, &quot;eerily echoed&quot; the state of Edwards just prior to his death.&lt;ref name=Wilson25/&gt;{{efn|Melville's short story appears to be set in the mid-1840s, but his mention of Edwards' death by consumption while still at Sing-Sing in 1847 is at odds with the rest of the historical events depicted as contemporary in the story.&lt;ref name=Swann&gt;Swann &quot;Dating&quot; ''Notes and Queries'' pp. 357–358&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Edwards was known during and after his trial as the &quot;Great Forger&quot;.&lt;ref name=Dillingham14/&gt; The main account of his life and trial is ''Life and Adventures of the Accomplished Forger and Swindler, Colonel Monroe Edwards'', which was written by an editor of the ''[[National Police Gazette]]'' in 1848. The account, which was probably written by [[George Wilkes]], is the fullest account of Edwards' life, but mingles fact with fiction to the extent that it has been listed in bibliographies of American fiction. Wilkes' account is the source for the story of Kitty Clover, supposedly a slave who loved Edwards, rescued him, and followed him throughout his life. There are other accounts, including two anonymous narratives published in 1842.&lt;ref name=ADNB/&gt;

==Notes==
{{notelist|60em}}

==Citations==
{{reflist|40em}}

==References==
{{refbegin|60em}}
* {{cite book |author=Barrows, Chester L. |title=William M. Evarts: Lawyer, Diplomat, Statesman |publisher=University of North Carolina Press |location=Chapel Hill, NC |year=1941 |oclc= 2746630}}
* {{cite journal |author=Denham, James M. |title = The Peerless Wind Cloud: Thomas Jefferson Green and the Tallahassee Land Company |journal=East Texas Historical Journal |url=http://scholarworks.sfasu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2067&amp;context=ethj |volume=29 |issue=2 |date=1991 |pages=3–14}}
* {{cite book |author=Dillingham, Wiliam B. |title=Melville's Short Fiction 1853–1856 |publisher=University of Georgia Press |location=Athens, GA |year=1977 |oclc= 2632482}}
* {{cite book |author=Dyer, Brainerd |title=The Public Career of William M. Evarts |publisher=University of California Press |location=Berkeley, CA |year=1933 |oclc = 479207}}
* {{cite encyclopedia |author= Hoogenboom, Ari |title=Evarts, William Maxwell |url=  http://www.anb.org/articles/05/05-00225.html |encyclopedia = American National Biography Online |publisher= Oxford University Press |date=February 2000 |accessdate=  February 15, 2016 }}
* {{cite web |author= Jones, Mary Beth |title=Edwards, Monroe |website=Handbook of Texas Online |url=http://www.tshaonline.org/handbook/online/articles/fed07 |accessdate= March 30, 2015 |date= June 12, 2010 |publisher= Texas State Historical Association}}
* {{cite journal |author = Kelley, Sean |title = Blackbirders and Bozales: African-Born Slaves on the Lower Brazos River of Texas in the Nineteenth Century |journal = Civil War History |volume = 54 |issue= 4 |date= December 2008 |pages = 406–423 |doi = 10.1353/cwh.0.0031}}
* {{cite book |author=Kouwenhoven, John A. |title=Partners in Banking: An Historical Portrait of a Great Private Bank Brown Brothers Harriman &amp; Co. 1818–1968 |publisher=Doubleday &amp; Company |location=Garden City, NY |year=1968 |oclc= 249770 }}
* {{cite book |author=Lack, Paul D. |title=The Texas Revolutionary Experience: A Political and Social History 1835–1836 |publisher=Texas A&amp;M University Press |location=College Station, TX |date=1992 |isbn=0-89096-497-1 }}
* {{cite journal |author=Muir, Andrew Forest |title=The Union Company in Anahuac 1831–1833 |journal=Southwestern Historical Quarterly |volume=70 |issue=2 |date=October 1966 |pages=256–268 |jstor= 30236390 }}
* {{cite journal |author=Robbins, Fred |title=The Origin and Development of the African Slave Trade in Galveston, Texas, and Surrounding Areas from 1816 to 1836 |journal = East Texas Historical Journal |date= 1971 |volume=9 |issue=2 |url=http://scholarworks.sfasu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1231&amp;context=ethj |pages= 153–161}}
* {{cite journal |author=Rowe, Edna |title=The Disturbances at Anahuac in 1832 |journal = The Quarterly of the Texas State Historical Association |volume= 6 |issue=4 |date=April 1903 |jstor= 27784935 |pages= 265–299}}
* {{cite journal |author= Swann, Charles |title=Dating the Action of 'Bartleby' |journal=Notes and Queries |date=September 1985 |pages=357–358 |volume=32 |issue=2 |doi=10.1093/notesj/32.3.357-a }}
* {{cite encyclopedia |author=Thompson, George A. |title=Edwards, Monroe |encyclopedia =American National Biography Online |url= http://www.anb.org/articles/20/20-01708.html |year=2000 |accessdate= January 2, 2015 }}
* {{cite journal |author=Valdes, Dennis N. |title=The Decline of Slavery in Mexico |journal=The Americas |volume=44 |issue=2 |date=October 1987 |pages=167–194 |jstor= 1007289}}
* {{cite journal |author= Wilson, Robert Andrew |title= Sympathy for the Lawyer: A Source for 'Bartleby' and Nineteenth-Century Prison Reform |journal = [[American Notes and Queries|ANQ: A Quarterly Journal of Short Articles, Notes and Reviews]] |volume=21 |number=4 |pages=24–30 |date=Fall 2008 | doi = 10.3200/ANQQ.21.4.24-30 }}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |author=[[George Wilkes|Wilkes, George]], attrib. |title=Life and Adventures of the Accomplished Forger and Swindler, Colonel Monroe Edwards |publisher=H. Long &amp; Brother |location=New York, NY |year=1848}}
{{refend}}

{{Authority control}}


{{DEFAULTSORT:Edwards, Monroe}}
[[Category:1808 births]]
[[Category:1847 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Danville, Kentucky]]
[[Category:American slave traders]]
[[Category:American fraudsters]]
[[Category:Forgers]]</text>
      <sha1>ee81h9s02j1vs6eeeuvl2lrn4mawmmu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
