<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.28.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2600" case="first-letter">Topic</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>National emblem of Belarus</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>457096</id>
    <revision>
      <id>724334181</id>
      <parentid>707885458</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-06-08T15:33:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>86.58.36.235</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Emblem of the Byelorussian SSR */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17342">{{Featured article}}
{{Infobox coat of arms
|name             = National Emblem of Belarus
|image            = Official_coat_of_arms_of_the_Republic_of_Belarus_(v).svg
|image_width      = 200
|middle           = 
|middle_width     = 
|middle_caption   = 
|lesser           = 
|lesser_width     = 
|lesser_caption   = 
|armiger          = [[Republic of Belarus]]
|year_adopted     = June 7, 1995
|crest            = [[Red star]]
|torse            = 
|shield           = [[Globe]], rising sun and an outline of Belarus in green
|supporters       = 
|compartment      = 
|motto            = 
|orders           = 
|other_elements   = 
|earlier_versions = 
|use              = 
}}

The '''national emblem of [[Belarus]]''', which replaced the historic [[Pahonia]] arms in a [[1995 Belarus Referendum|1995 referendum]], features a ribbon in the colours of the [[Flag of Belarus|national flag]], a map of [[Belarus]], wheat ears and a [[red star]]. It is sometimes referred to as the [[coat of arms]] of Belarus, although this is incorrect due to the lack of several [[heraldry|heraldic]] elements. The emblem is an allusion to one that was used by the [[Byelorussian SSR]], designed by [[Ivan Dubasov]] in 1950, with the biggest change being a replacement of the hammer and sickle with an outline map of Belarus. [[Socialist heraldry|Emblems reminiscent of the times of the Soviet Union]] are also used in [[Coat of arms of the Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]], [[Emblem of Tajikistan|Tajikistan]], [[Emblem of Uzbekistan|Uzbekistan]] and the region of [[Coat of arms of Transnistria|Transnistria]].

The Belarusian name is Дзяржаўны герб Рэспублікі Беларусь, ''Dziaržaŭny herb Respubliki Biełaruś'', and the name in Russian is Государственный герб Республики Беларусь, ''Gosudarstvennyĭ gerb Respubliki Belarusʹ''.

In 2012 the emblem has been modified.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ctv.by/%D0%BD%D0%BE%D0%B2%D0%BE%D1%81%D1%82%D0%B8/%D1%84%D0%BB%D0%B0%D0%B3-%D0%B8-%D0%B3%D0%B5%D1%80%D0%B1-%D0%B1%D0%B5%D0%BB%D0%B0%D1%80%D1%83%D1%81%D0%B8-%D0%BA%D0%B0%D0%BA%D0%B8%D0%B5-%D0%B8%D0%B7%D0%BC%D0%B5%D0%BD%D0%B5%D0%BD%D0%B8%D1%8F-%D0%BF%D1%80%D0%BE%D0%B8%D0%B7%D0%BE%D1%88%D0%BB%D0%B8-%D0%B2-2012-%D0%B3%D0%BE%D0%B4%D1%83-%D0%B8-%D0%BA%D0%B0%D0%BA-%D1%81%D0%BE%D0%B7%D0%B4%D0%B0%D1%8E%D1%82%D1%81%D1%8F-%D1%81%D0%B8%D0%BC%D0%B2%D0%BE%D0%BB%D1%8B|title=The Flag and the Coat of Arms of Belarus: what changes has been in 2012 and how makes symbols of belarussian country|accessdate=|language=russian|publisher=СТВ}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.belarus.by/rel_image/893 The emblem in the redaction of 2012]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Description==
[[File:Belarus-Minsk-Coat of Arms of Belarus.jpg|thumb|The emblem on a building in Minsk]]

===Design===
In the center of the emblem sits a green outline of Belarus, superimposed over the rays of a golden sun. The sun is partially covered by a globe, with the landmass (part of [[Eurasia]]) in purple and waters in blue. Lining the left and right sides of the emblem are stalks of wheat, superimposed with flowers. [[Clover]]s adorn the left wheat stalks; [[flax]] flowers adorn the right. Wrapped around the wheat stalks is a red and green ribbon bearing the colours of the [[flag of Belarus]]; the ribbon meets at the base of the emblem, where the name ''Republic of Belarus'' (''Рэспублiка Беларусь'') is inscribed in gold in the [[Belarusian language]]. At the top of the emblem there is a five-pointed [[red star]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ByArms&quot;&gt;President of the Republic of Belarus [http://president.gov.by/en/press10664.html Description of the National emblem]. Retrieved March 1, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Symbolism===
The elements that comprise the state emblem are not tied to any &quot;official&quot; symbolism. The design of the emblem of the [[Byelorussian SSR]] was used as the basis for the current Belarusian emblem; the primary difference between the two is that the Byelorussian SSR emblem contains more references to [[Communism]], such as the Communist symbol of [[hammer and sickle]] and pure red ribbon, which the modern emblem does not, replaced with the outline and the flag of Belarus, respectively, however it still retains the communist red star, the globe and the wheat bundles, which are also typical of Soviet emblems and still is very Soviet in nature.

===Legislation===
[[File:Пашпарт. Рэспубліка Беларусь. 2009. 1.jpg|thumb|[[Belarusian passport]] bearing the state emblem on the left. 2009]]
The current law regulating the design and use of the Belarusian emblem was passed on July 5, 2004. Article 9 of Chapter 3 of Law No. 301-3 begins by describing the official drawing of the Belarusian arms and regulates on its proper design. Officially, the arms can be drawn in full colour, [[monochrome]] or using two colors. Article 10 states that the national emblem must be displayed at specified locations on a continual basis, such as the residences of the [[President of Belarus|Belarusian leader]], the chamber of the [[National Assembly of the Republic of Belarus|National Assembly]] and at governmental offices of national and regional levels. The emblem can also be used on documents issued by the government, including money, [[Belarusian passport|passport]]s and official [[letterhead]]s.&lt;ref name = &quot;law&quot;/&gt;

The law also restricts the use of the emblem in other contexts—e.g. cities, towns or oblasts may not adopt a coat of arms or emblem using the national emblem either completely or in part. Furthermore, organizations not listed in the Law on State Symbols may only use the emblem by permission. The emblem can be used by both foreigners and citizens of Belarus, as long as the symbol is displayed with respect, although citizens may not use the state emblem on letterheads or [[business card]]s if they are not agents of the government.&lt;ref name=&quot;law&quot;&gt;{{ru icon}} Republic of Belarus Law No. 301-3 [http://www.pravo.by/webnpa/text.asp?RN=H10400301 Law of the National Symbols of the Republic of Belarus]. Retrieved March 1, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Belarus jersey.jpg|thumb|right|100px|Emblem of Belarus on the jersey of its national ice hockey team]]

In addition to standard usages listed in the law, the emblem has been used in various other circumstances. The emblem is displayed, along with the national flag, at the beginning and the end of a video clip with the Belarusian anthem ''[[My Belarusy]]'', regularly played on Belarusian [[television]]. Another use of the emblem is on ballot boxes and campaign mailings used during national and local elections. The emblem also appears on Belarus's border posts.&lt;ref name=&quot;border&quot;&gt;{{ru icon}} State Border Troops Committee of the Republic of Belarus [http://gpk.gov.by/ru-border_patrol-history-heraldry/ Symbols of the Border Guard]. Retrieved 21 November 2006. {{wayback|url=http://gpk.gov.by/ru-border_patrol-history-heraldry/ |date=20090107060449 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

===Pahonia===
{{Main|Pahonia}}
The Pahonia was used as an official coat of the [[Grand Duchy of Lithuania]] since 1366 after being first used as the personal arms of [[Algirdas]], the Grand Duke of Lithuania. The arms continued to be used until [[Grand Duchy of Lithuania]] were annexed by the [[Russian Empire]] in 1795, though the arms was incorporated into the Imperial coat of arms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www3.lrs.lt/home/w5_viewer/statiniai/seimu_istorija/w5_show-p_r=4056&amp;p_d=49325&amp;p_k=2.html |title=The Coat of Arms of Lithuania |accessdate=2008-10-29 |date=2006-01-10 |publisher=Seimas of the Republic of Lithuania }}&lt;/ref&gt; The idea of return to the historic national symbol was pursued by Belarusian poet [[Maksim Bahdanovič]] in his poem &quot;Pahonia&quot;. The arms was again used in 1918 when the short-lived [[Belarusian People's Republic]] used the Pahonia as part of their emblem.

More recently, the Pahonia was the official coat of arms starting in 1991, when Belarus declared itself independent of the [[Soviet Union]]. It was replaced by the current emblem following a controversial [[Belarusian referendum, 1995|referendum]] held in 1995.

Since it was dropped as the official emblem of Belarus, opposition groups such as the [[Belarusian People's Front]] have used the Pahonia as part of their own party symbols or used them as a form of protest against Belarusian leader [[Alexander Lukashenko]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pbnf&quot;&gt;{{be icon}} [http://pbnf.org/symvol.html Symbols of the Belarusian People's Front]. Retrieved 7 March 2006. {{wayback|url=http://pbnf.org/symvol.html |date=20081228130854 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Pahonia - Пагоня, Grand Duchy of Lithuania COA (1575) cut.png|Coat of arms of the [[Grand Duchy of Lithuania]] since the 16th century
File:Lob Rech Pospolita.svg|The Pahonia as part of the [[Coat of arms of the Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth]]
File:Vitebsk gub coa.png|The Pahonia on the coat of arms of the [[Vitebsk Governorate]] of the [[Russian empire]] (from 1856)
File:Vilna Governorate COA.gif|The Pahonia on the coat of arms of the [[Vilna Governorate]] of the Russian empire
File:Герб Княжества и области белорусские и литовские 1882.svg|The united coat of arms of the White Russia's and Lithuanian Provinces from Coat of arms of the Russian Empire (1882)
File:Postcard BNR.jpg|The Pahonia as the symbol of the [[Belarusian Democratic Republic]] (from 1918, no unified design of the coat of arms was approved)
File:Герб БНР 1918.svg|The Pahonia as the symbol of the [[Belarusian Democratic Republic]] 
File:Печать Белорусской Центральной Рады 1943.jpg|Seal of [[Belarusian Central Rada]] in 1943–1944
File:Coat of Arms of Belarus (1991).svg|Coat of arms of Belarus in 1991-1995
File:Coat_of_Arms_of_Lithuania.svg|Current [[coat of arms of Lithuania]] (from 1992)
&lt;/gallery&gt;

===Emblem of the Byelorussian SSR===
{{Main|Emblem of the Byelorussian Soviet Socialist Republic}}
From 1920 until [[dissolution of the Soviet Union|the fall of the Soviet Union in 1991]], the [[Byelorussian SSR]] used an emblem instead of a coat of arms. The first emblem used by Soviet Byelorussia was adopted in 1919 and is similar to the contemporary insignia of the Russian and Ukrainian republics. The central part of the emblem is a stylized red shield, showing a golden sun rising from the base. Above the sun is a crossed golden [[hammer and sickle]], symbolizing unity between workers and peasants. Above the hammer and sickle, the letters ''Б.С.С.Р'' are shown in black, denoting the name of the republic. БССР (BSSR) is an abbreviation for the full name of the republic; &quot;Беларуская Савецкая Сацыялістычная Рэспубліка&quot;, the ''Byelorussian Soviet Socialist Republic''. The shield is framed by ears of wheat meeting at the its base and featuring a red ribbon inscribed in black with the state motto of the Soviet Union, &quot;Workers of the World, Unite!&quot; The text is written in the Belarusian language.&lt;ref name=&quot;sb1919&quot;&gt;Heraldicum [http://www.hrono.ru/heraldicum/belarus/sovet.htm History of the Soviet Byelorussian emblem]. Retrieved November 3, 2006. {{ru icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1937, this emblem was replaced by a new one, removing the shield and including more text. The right side of the emblem features [[oak]] leaves and the left features wheat ears with clovers placed on top. In the center of the emblem, a sun is rising behind a profile of Earth. A hammer, sickle and red star appears over the sun. Around the ears of wheat and leaves of oak is a red ribbon, featuring the phrase &quot;Workers of the World, Unite!&quot; written (from left to right) in Belarusian, [[Yiddish]], [[Polish language|Polish]] and [[Russian language|Russian]]. The initials ''Б.С.С.Р'' are shown at its base denoting the name of the republic. Ten years before in 1927, the arms was the same except for the wording on the bottom ribbon. Instead of the letters reading БССР, the letters read &quot;С.С.Р.Б&quot;, which stood for the Soviet Socialist Republic of Byelorussia.&lt;ref name=&quot;bssr&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.heraldicum.ru/belarus/index.htm |script-title=ru:Гербы БССР |accessdate=2010-04-28 |date=2003-12-16 |work=Геральдикум |publisher=Русский Центр флаговедения и геральдики |language=Russian }}&lt;/ref&gt;

This emblem was in turn replaced by a new one in 1950. The central feature of this symbol is a crossed [[hammer and sickle]], a universal Communist symbol symbolizing the unity of workers and peasants. Below this symbol, a sun is shown rising behind a globe. The insignia is framed by ears of wheat, each ear ending in flowers; [[clover]] on the left and [[flax]] on the right. A red ribbon is wrapped around the ears of wheat, reminiscent of the [[Red flag (politics)|red flag]] used by the Communist movement. The base of the emblem shows the letters ''БССР''. The ribbon features the phrase ''[[Workers of the world, unite!|Workers of the World, Unite!]]'' The left side inscribed in Belarusian, the right side in [[Russian language|Russian]]. The red star of Communism is featured above the hammer and sickle. The 1950 version was designed by [[Ivan Dubasov]], a [[People's Artist of the USSR]].&lt;ref name=&quot;bssr&quot;/&gt; Article 119 of the [[Constitution of the Byelorussian SSR]] defines the design of the emblem.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Anon | first = | authorlink = | coauthors = | title = Флаг и Герб СССР | publisher = | year = 1972 | location = Moscow | pages = 26 | url = | doi = | id = | isbn = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Emblem of the Byelorussian SSR (1919).svg|1920 coat of arms
File:Emblem of the Byelorussian SSR (1927).svg|1927–1937 coat of arms with the inscription ''Workers of the World, Unite!'' (from left to right) in [[Belarusian language|Belarusian]], [[Yiddish]], [[Russian language|Russian]] and [[Polish language|Polish]]
File:Emblem of the Byelorussian SSR (1926-1937).svg|1937–1938 coat of arms
File:Emblem of the Byelorussian SSR (1938-1949).svg|1938–1949 coat of arms
File:Emblem of the Byelorussian SSR.svg|1958–1981 coat of arms
File:Emblem of the Byelorussian SSR (1981-1991).svg|modification from 1981 until 1991
&lt;/gallery&gt;

===1995 referendum===
{{Main|Belarusian referendum, 1995}}
On May 14, 1995, a referendum was conducted in all regions of Belarus. Out of four questions, one was the following: &quot;Do you support the introduction of the new [[national symbols]]?&quot; With a voter turnout of 64.7%, the new state symbols were approved by a ratio of 3:1 (75.1% to 24.9%). The way the referendum was carried out was heavily criticized by the opposition, including the exact wording of the question about the national insignia.&lt;ref name=&quot;byguide&quot;&gt;Belarus Guide - National Symbols in Belarus: The Past and Present. Retrieved 5 August 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Supporters of the Pahonia also criticize that the Pahonia and [[white-red-white flag|the former white-red-white flag]] were compared to ones, used by [[Belarusian collaborationism with the Axis powers|collaboration forces]], in propaganda that was published during the run-up to the vote.&lt;ref name=&quot;nazi&quot;&gt;[http://www.belarusguide.com/as/history/pahonia.html#4 Belarus Guide - Pahonia]. Retrieved 7 March 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; The comparison was made due to the white, red, white flag and Pahonia being used on the patches and symbols of the [[Belarusian Central Rada]], the Belarusian government under the control of Nazi Germany. Alexander Lukashenko claimed the selection of the Soviet-inspired symbols as a victory, especially to his [[Great Patriotic War]] veteran base, by saying &quot;we have returned to you the flag of the country for which you fought. We have returned to you both memory and a sense of human pride.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;luka&quot;&gt;Belarus News and Analysis [http://www.data.minsk.by/belarusnews/052005/30.html Vitali Silitski - A Partisan Reality Show]. May 11, 2005. Retrieved 7 March 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{commons category|Coats of arms of Belarus|National emblem of Belarus}}
*[[Belarusian heraldry]]
*[[List of Belarusian coats of arms]]
*[[Coat of arms of Lithuania]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*President of the Republic of Belarus [http://president.gov.by/en/press10664.html Official description of the National Emblem of Belarus]
*{{ru icon}} [http://pravo.by/webnpa/text_txt.asp?RN=H10400301 2004 Law on the National Symbols of Belarus]
*{{ru icon}} [http://geraldika.ru/symbols/2727 1995 Law on the National Emblem of the Republic of Belarus]
*{{ru icon}} [http://www.statesymbol.ru/abroad/cis/20050804/39598414.html Brief history of Belarusian symbols]
*{{ru icon}} [http://www.heraldicum.narod.ru/belarus/rb.htm Heraldicum - Emblems of the Republic of Belarus]

{{Symbols of Belarus}}
{{Coats of arms of Europe}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:National Emblem Of Belarus}}
[[Category:Belarusian coats of arms| ]]
[[Category:National symbols of Belarus]]
[[Category:National emblems|Belarus]]
[[Category:Coats of arms with suns|Belarus]]
[[Category:Coats of arms with sunrays|Belarus]]
[[Category:Coats of arms with wheat|Belarus]]
[[Category:Coats of arms with stars|Belarus]]
[[Category:Coats of arms with globes|Belarus]]
[[Category:Coats of arms with flax|Belarus]]
[[Category:Coats of arms with clover|Belarus]]
[[Category:Coats of arms with maps|Belarus]]</text>
      <sha1>8se5m90w4vpol9h0xiy1grh04p9p3va</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
